Daniel Friedman: Hello, it's June 23rd, 2023.
We're in ActInf GuestStream Number 46.1
with Denise Holt.
So Denise, thank you very much for
joining.
We'll have your presentation first, any
length of time you want,
and then we'll have a discussion about
some of the topics you're bringing up,
and I'll read some comments from the live
chat too.
So thanks again, Denise, looking forward
to your presentation.
Denise Holt: Hi, Daniel. Thank you so much for
having me today.
Yeah, so let's just dive right in.
Today I'm going to be talking about
Active Inference AI and the Spatial Web.
And for those who are not familiar, there
is a company called Verses AI,
and they're basically delivering the next
generation of AI.
This is beyond the current machine
learning, deep learning models
that we're all so familiar with that are
incredible tools,
but really those are tools.
They are great at creating content,
performing tasks, things like that,
but they operate in a way that is pattern
matching,
and they're all siloed in their ability
for what they can do.
They're trained on enormous amounts of
data to increase the pattern recognition
and hopefully increase accurate outputs,
but that's really what they do.
What Verses has created is something
completely different,
and it's based on Active Inference.
And so Active Inference AI is entirely
new,
and this is the AI that will be able to
get us to AGI,
leading to synthetic self-evolving
intelligence.
So today what I'm going to be talking
about in this deck is Active Inference
AI
and the Spatial Web and how these
technologies are going to affect
and change the world.
We'll talk about how Active Inference
works with artificial intelligence,
how the Spatial Web protocol enables the
perception
and the belief updating of the AI,
and how these technologies together
enable the only AI in the world
that can run critical operations for
systems or infrastructure,
smart cities, the planet.
So when you're talking about airports,
hospitals, things like that.
So, yeah, so let's dive right in.
So the Spatial Web, what is that?
So the Spatial Web is being called the
network of everything.
Basically, it's the next evolution of the
internet,
and it's powered by AI.
So this is taking us from a library of
pages and documents
that we have in the World Wide Web.
And oh, my gosh, my dog is wanting out.
I'm so sorry.
I have to let him out of the park.
Sorry about that.
So the next evolution of the internet.
Now, you know, as I said, World Wide Web,
a library of pages, documents,
you know, everything is static.
The Spatial Web protocol, HSTP,
hyperspace transaction protocol,
and the programming language for the
protocol called HSML,
which is hyperspace modeling language.
This new protocol takes us into a library
of spaces where, you know,
we have spatial domains, and everything
within any space can be locatable
and programmable within this new network.
.
And it's just extending the protocol that
we have now, right?
So same internet, just more capabilities.
.
Now, Dr. Carl J. Friston and the Verses
AI white paper,
and I'm sure a lot of you are familiar
with him,
the father of Active Inference and the
Free Energy Principle.
Now, so Verses with Dr. Friston has
developed a new type of AI
that mimics the self-organized systems of
nested intelligence found in nature.
And it's based on his methodologies of
Active Inference
and the Free Energy Principle and the
Spatial Web protocols,
which I just mentioned, which were
developed by Verses AI.
In December, they put out a white paper
called
Designing Ecosystems of Intelligence from
First Principles.
And just to back up a second, you know,
Verses created the protocol,
the HSTP and the HSML, but donated it to
the public
because nobody can own the internet.
But they needed that in place for what
they wanted to do as a company.
So that framework needed to be there.
So then they also donated the protocol
and the IP to the IEEE,
which is one of the largest core
standards bodies
that develops everything with, you know,
electronics and engineering.
You know, they're responsible for the
core standards around things
like Bluetooth and Wi-Fi and things like
that.
So the core standards have been being
developed around the protocol
for the last almost three years.
And yeah, Verses in that time has been
building, you know,
what they've been building, which I'll be
talking about.
So what is this white paper about?
It's basically about shared intelligence.
.
So in the white paper, they proposed
cyber-physical nested ecosystems
of distributed intelligence, joining
humans, machines,
and AI agents on a common network.
So we're talking about humans as integral
participants, adaptive behavior,
self-evidencing, self-organization,
belief updating over several scales,
belief sharing over ensembles of agents.
So we're talking about a network of
intelligent agents
and collective intelligence.
And then, of course, the protocols, HSTP
and HSML.
So the knowledge graph and digital twins.
.
Digital twins of our planet and all
nested systems and entities within them.
So nested ecosystems, intelligent agents,
both human and synthetic,
sensing and perceiving continuously
evolving environments,
making sense of changes, updating their
mental model
and what they know to be true, and then
acting on the new information
they receive.
And in the white paper, it's also
discussing a network
of distributed intelligence.
So this enables a cognitive architecture
made up of the collective
intelligence of multiple agents that
continuously communicate,
coordinate, and collaborate with each
other.
Individual and specialized intelligences
are all coming together
on a common network.
They're speaking a common language, HSML
and HSTP.
It's efficient, powerful cross-
-communication to perform tasks,
regulate systems, and address problems in
real time.
And it scales up and grows in tandem with
humans.
So Active Inference and the Free Energy
Principle.
So what exactly is Active Inference?
Active Inference is a biologically
inspired approach to AI systems
as a method for understanding behavior
incorporating the brain,
cognition, and behavior, modeled after
the design principles
from nature and from how the brain,
nervous system,
and the body act and react.
One of the questions that Dr. Fristin
asks in this paper
that is an important question in
reference to Active Inference
is, you know, with AI systems, you need
to be able to understand
what is it that intelligence must be,
given that intelligent systems
exist in a universe like ours.
So Active Inference is a theoretical
framework that describes how agents
like people, animals, robots, or
artificial systems can maintain
their internal states and behavior in
unison with their objectives or goals.
So what is the Free Energy Principle?
The Free Energy Principle is the
theoretical foundation of Active
Inference.
It proposes that organisms or agents
maintain their internal states
and behavior by acting in a way that
minimizes the difference
between their current beliefs about the
world and what they expect to be true.
So in other words, the agents try to make
things more predictable
by mitigating the difference between what
they expect to happen
and what actually ends up happening.
And they do this by way of a continuous
cycle of improving their perception
by acting on the environment.
So basically, it helps to extract the
signal from the noise
and extract the regularities from the
irregularities.
So extracting the prediction error,
minimizing the prediction error.
And there are two parts to this inference
cycle.
There's the perceptual inference part,
which minimizes the free energy
by improving the internal model to better
match the sensory input.
Making Bayesian inferences about the
world, the brain minimizes free energy
by optimizing perception, so through
hypothesizing and observation.
In other words, the brain models the
environment better,
improving the perception.
Now, the Active Inference part minimizes
the free energy
by acting on the environment.
So acting on the environment to reduce
the surprises,
the disorder or the unpredictability,
and action can indirectly influence the
observation.
So Active Inference, the Active Inference
part of free energy minimization
is equal to lowering the surprise in the
sensory observations
by acting on the environment.
Actions can't directly change
observations,
but they can indirectly change them by
acting on the environmental states.
So then we get to Active Inference AI.
So in the context of artificial
intelligence,
Active Inference and the Free Energy
Principle explain how agents can learn
and adapt to new situations and how they
can generate predictions
and plan actions based on their goals or
objectives,
which leads to more accurate predictions
and results,
which is the real goal of AI.
Active Inference AI enables us to
overcome current limitations
with machine learning and deep learning
AI models,
providing a realistic path towards
artificial general intelligence.
So, you know, the idea is that an agent
can use Active Inference
to minimize the free energy and optimize
its behavior
in a way that's consistent with its
objectives,
which leads to more accurate AI.
So the action perception loop,
the perceptual inference and Active
Inference unfold continuously
and simultaneously, underlying deep
continuity between perception and action.
.
They're both sides of the same coin,
performing the same free energy
minimization algorithm.
So the free energy can be minimized by
improving the perception
and then acting on the environment in
this loop that just keeps narrowing down
the focus.
And then also by learning the generative
model,
you know, how the brain codes the
environment.
So, you know, that's the side that the
Spatial Web protocol actually helps with
because it bakes context into every
person, place or thing in any space.
So that context informs the AI.
So then it's optimizing the expected
precision and regulating the learning.
So thus we update the model over and over
to improve our understanding of the world.
.
And that is what the AI does as well.
So how does it do this?
So self-optimization and self-evolution.
So Active Inference AI and the Free
Energy Principle through the Bayesian
inference
allows a neural network to self-optimize
through intake
and continuous updating of new real-time
sensory data
while simultaneously considering
previously established outputs and
determinations.
So past decisions plus the new input lead
to future outcomes.
And that cycle is a self-optimization and
self-evolution cycle.
So a self-evolving system evolves over
time.
Current systems, current AI systems are
more like a machine.
They're just neural nets that are trained
to do a specific task.
But a self-evolving system is learning
from moment to moment and upgrading its
world model.
And thus it mimics biology while also
enabling general intelligence.
So within the Free Energy Principle,
neural networks self-optimize
through a set of mathematical rules
enabling next generation artificial
intelligence
to efficiently learn, predict, plan, and
make decisions.
Spatial Web protocol. Let's talk about
this.
So what is the Spatial Web protocol?
HSTP, hyperspace transaction protocol.
It gives browsers the ability to link
spaces with an ID for every person, place,
, or thing,
both digital and physical, so virtual or
real.
But it's much more than a location
identifier.
HSTP is also a gatekeeper.
It allows various parties the ability to
agree on who, what, and where anything is
in space,
who owns it, has access to it, and what
can be done with it.
So HSTP gives browsers the ability to
link the spaces with an ID.
Oh, did I get this in here?
So HSTP is multidimensional query.
So it allows for query over multiple
dimensions, identifying, localizing,
and updating the attributes, conditions,
contingencies,
and interrelationships of objects in
space and over time.
So if it can be defined and calculated in
the sphere of natural or digital science,
,
it can be searchable through HSTP.
So HSML, this is the programming language
that informs the protocol.
And I like to call it the smartest
contract around because it's the
foundational contract now
for every person, place, or thing in any
space in any reality.
So the only way to create a truly
technologically augmented existence is to
be able to consider
and measure the contextual elements that
affect the expression of shared
information
by and between all objects in space.
This is known as computable context.
And this is what HSML, hyperspace
modeling language, was made for.
And what are some of the contextual
elements that can be programmed?
Location, the where, the when of anything
in any space.
And you're talking about reality, the
different realities, spaces, time, and
channels as well.
And then activities, so the what and the
how.
And this is in regards to things like
rights and credentials or claims or
activities.
And then when you're talking about
identities, the who and the what of
anything in any space,
you're talking about authority or domains
or users or assets.
So all of these contextual elements can
affect the expression of the shared
information by and between anything.
So belief updating through context and
sensors.
So HSML is a cipher for context.
The Spatial Web, which is web 3.0, the
next evolution of the internet,
is a library of spaces that contain
objects, people, places, and things.
These objects do things and change over
time.
The context or circumstances that govern
these shifts and changes is the most
important factor to consider
if we're to understand how objects relate
to each other, to people, and to their
environments.
So the Free Energy Principle and HSML.
The Free Energy Principle is perfectly
suited to the programming language of the
Spatial Web.
HSML, the hyperspace modeling language,
which enables computable context based on
defining, recording, and tracing
the changing details in physical and
digital dimensions, social dimensions,
meanings, culture, conditions,
circumstances, situations,
whether geometrical, geopolitical, or
geosocial by nature.
Self-evidencing and belief updating.
So HSML computes context, enabling the AI'
's perception to understand the real-time
changing state of anything in the world,
accumulating evidence for a generative
model of one's sensed world, also known
as self-evidencing.
So we're talking about multiple agents,
so individual intelligences,
and based on each agent's generative
world model, unique perspective, frame of
reference,
and nested ecosystems of these
intelligences, and different levels of
self-organization.
So all of this results in a collective
shared intelligence.
So, call on architecture and markup
blankets.
So the Spatial Web is a holonic structure.
.
So Active Inference, well, Active
Inference AI within the Spatial Web on
the versus CosmOS platform
operates with a holonic structure of
nested spatial domains.
So if you're not familiar with what a
holon is, a holon is where, you know,
something can be a whole in and of itself,
,
and yet also be a part of something
greater.
So the human heart is a great example.
The human heart's made up of cells.
Each one of those cells, they're whole
cells in and of themselves, yet they're
also part of the heart.
And then the heart is a whole heart, but
yet it's part of the human body.
So you have this nested structure of
whole parts that are governed by the
outside part,
but still have this intrinsic governing
going on within itself as well.
So each component is a whole element,
part of the entire organism.
They're nested entities and they're
governed by the rules of the greater
influencing organism.
And then they have inherited, they
inherit the governing and it's passed to
the internal parts that are nested within
it.
And each part has its own governmental
considerations for its specific intrinsic
requirements as well.
So this is how the Spatial Web is set up
to work as well.
So when you're talking about spatial
domains, you're talking about, for
instance,
you can have a restaurant that's inside
of a skyscraper building that's inside of
a city,
and that city is inside of a state, these
nested domains.
And then the Active Inference AI also
includes the principle of Markov blankets
at each level of analysis.
So the Markov blankets define boundaries
acting as partitions to mediate the
interactions between the internal and
external states of the spatial domains,
such as like a single unit or a region or
entire complex network.
And this results in a self-organizing
system.
And a Markov blanket is just a mediator
between how things are attuned to each
other through the Free Energy Principle.
So nested domains in the Spatial Web.
So one good example of how this may work
is, you know, if you take a factory,
right?
So, you know, a factory is a part of the
supply chain and has raw materials
feeding into it from various locations.
Like mines or, you know, anywhere.
And then the factory produces finished
goods that may ship to another
destination, like a warehouse, right?
Like a distribution warehouse.
So just as that factory is an object
within a larger ecosystem of the supply
chain,
every object within the factory belongs
to its internal ecosystem, right?
So with a factory, you've got all the
internal ecosystem of what's going on in
that factory.
But yet it's still part of this global
supply chain with, you know, raw
materials being fed into it.
And then when it's done with what it's
doing, it's feeding out to other like
distribution, you know, pathways.
So you have an internal and an external
ecosystem,
and they simultaneously operate according
to the individual internal and external
standards.
The interdependencies, the
interrelationships.
So, you know, this is how you can see
things working within the Spatial Web.
So every object within the entire Spatial
Web network is part of an interrelated
ecosystem
that feeds a continuous stream of real-
-time context between all points in space
and time.
This continual interaction and
communication stream takes note of all
the nuances and changes within the
relationships
between all objects and the parameters
that govern them,
which leads to adaptive collective
intelligence automation.
So you have programmable spaces.
And, you know, within these spaces,
everything within these spaces have a
digital ID.
And the way the Spatial Web is set up is
it enables zero knowledge proofs between
all of these entities.
So anything inside of any space is
uniquely identifiable and programmable
with a digital twin of the earth,
producing a model for data normalization.
.
So by programming context into everything
in any space, it creates this digital
twin of the space.
So the Spatial Web becomes a digital twin
of everything from the planet to every
single system,
every single object within it that's on
the network.
So.
The contingencies and changing details,
inherent qualities, circumstances for all
objects and situations can now be
measured and computed,
providing a basis for the AI perception
affecting all entities and their
interrelationships to each other.
So you're talking about adaptive
intelligence automation, security through
geo encoded governance,
multi network interoperability, and it
enables all smart technologies to
function together on a unified system.
So, you know, when you consider all of
the Web3 technologies, all of the
extended reality technologies, you know,
AR, VR,
distributed ledger technologies. So you
have all of these technologies that are
siloed and disparate.
This brings all of those technologies
onto a common unified network now with a
common language between them.
So it makes all of these all of these
technologies then become interoperable.
And when you're talking about smart
technologies, when you're talking about
like the Internet of Things,
there's been no common language for these
Internet of Things to talk to each other
and communicate.
So the Spatial Web brings all of the
Internet of Things onto the common
network now where they become baked into
this?
this network and informing the AI, so all
of the data being gathered by all of
these sensors or cameras or, you know,
the context that's baked into the
protocol. This is all the data that is
now coming together that is continually
updating in real time and informing the
AI.
So you have ecosystems of nested
intelligence. The design of intelligent
systems must begin from the physicality
of information and its processing at
every scale or level of organization.
So within the Spatial Web, you have AI
that scales up the way nature does,
aggregating locally contextualized
knowledge bases and acting across
ecosystems.
And this maximizes efficiency. So this is
the complete opposite of the way the
machine learning models work because they'
're top down.
It's just massive amounts of data. And,
you know, that's what's training the
machine model AI.
But there's a cutoff date. So then that
model now can only reference this
historical data that it's been trained on.
.
And, you know, again, it's just a it's it'
's a pattern recognition machine.
The algorithms are just to make sense of
the data that it's been fed and how to
recognize patterns within it.
Every time those models have to compute
and try to perform an output, it requires
massive amounts of energy because it
still has to pull from its library, this
massive library to try to make sense of
things.
Now, the way that the Spatial Web works
with the Active Inference AI is you have
any amount of data.
You know, small amounts of data can now
be made smart because you have context
informing the AI and you have sensors
that are giving it real time data inputs
to let it kind of look outward and see
what's happening in the world now.
Not, you know, referencing historical
data.
So this leads to minimizing complexity.
So when you're talking about the machine
learning versus the Active Inference for
efficiency and accuracy.
The more complex a system is, the more
energy it consumes.
So that's what I was just referring to
with all this big data approach on these
machine models.
Active Inference in the Free Energy
Principle naturally minimize the
complexity.
That's the whole idea with the Free
Energy Principle is to minimize the
prediction error and use the information
that it can sense.
Right. So it's taking in the senses from
sensors, like the Internet of Things and
cameras and things like that.
But it's also taking in what it knows
about.
It's, you know, the data at hand. Right.
And it's informed to the call, the
Spatial Web protocol with all of the
context, all of the attributes around
everything in any space or any data set.
So, you know, sensor data is noisy and
ambiguous, but HSML provides clarity with
specific and precise contextual data to
narrow the complexity and close the gap
on the free energy.
So more certainty means less noise, and
that that equals free energy is reduced
faster and lower.
So it's a it's a faster way to operate,
more efficient.
And, you know, another point to this,
which is really interesting, too, is that,
, you know, most of the data that exists
exists behind.
Password walls right behind gated it
within gated password areas, right,
whether it's, you know, on the Internet
and it's all the data that people have
behind a password or whether you're
talking about like an enterprise
organization that has all their
proprietary data that's in time.
Internal, you know, so the awesome thing
about the Spatial Web is that an Active
Inference is that you can be within this
network and still have all of your
proprietary data gated off because the
protocol allows for that security.
You know, it's a it's gated at every
touch point.
So you can put boundaries around your
particular data, but still be able to
access the the the power of the network
and the power of the Active Inference.
AI now for your proprietary data because
it can take that small amount of data and
make it smart.
So this is a game changer for, you know,
access to AI for any systems in any
databases.
So embodied AI.
Active Inference is mimics biological
design.
And it's so it's like embodied AI with
the ability to take action.
And this is the core engine of the
Spatial Web.
So what makes Active Inference so
accurate?
Active Inference is so accurate because
it continually looks outward into the
world, measuring the world in real time
through a global network of sensors, IoT
devices, cameras, robots, drones,
anything that's connected within the
Spatial Web, the digital twin network of
the world.
H.S.M.L. informs the AI with precise data,
, extracts the signal from the noise,
minimizing the prediction error.
And this mimics the way humans and
animals make decisions.
So the perception of the world in the
Spatial Web, Active Inference, AI, you
know, create this creates a cybernetic
feedback loop of perception of the world
and it updates the model of the world
with the belief of what it knows to be
true, gaining the understanding of the
intricacies and inner workings of the
world.
So that it can make decisions and take
action.
And it provides ever, ever evolving
intelligence.
So the more this feedback loop plays out,
the AI learns more about the world and
the results of the actions taken just as
a child learns about the world as it
grows and interacts with it.
And the more accurate this AI becomes by
further updating its understanding of the
world.
So it's been described to me that, you
know, when versus launches their COSM
operating system, and then, you know,
which is going to be later this year, it'
's going to enable everybody to be able
to build these intelligent agents on top
of the network, right?
They're they have a intelligent app store,
, that's going to be launching with the
operating system.
So then everybody can make these
intelligent agents.
The difference is these agents.
So when you build an app on say, like the
Apple App Store, or Google Play, you're
building a siloed piece of software,
right?
Those apps are not aware of each other,
they just do whatever their function is
to do.
The difference is these intelligent
agents that you're building on COSM are
going to be aware of each other and aware
of the network.
So they're going to be empowered with the
AI and be able to act as an agent within
the network.
Now, it's been described to me that, you
know, when people are first building
these, you know, intelligent agent apps,
it's not going to be like this stark
difference of like, the power of what it
can do versus the power of what these
machine models can do, because they're
all pretty, it's all pretty impressive
right now.
But the difference is, is if you take
like, the comparison of like a chimpanzee
and a toddler, at first they seem about
the same intellectually.
But the difference is that toddler is
going to grow, it's going to grow into a
full fledged adult, it's going to
continue learning, whereas that
chimpanzee has maxed out.
So that's going to be really interesting
to watch over the next, you know, year or
two is that we're going to see this
Active Inference AI really modeling the
same way that humans learn and it's going
to grow in intelligence with this, you
know, scores of these intelligent agents
now all working together within the
network.
So now one of the really awesome things
about this too, is that the Active
Inference AI is explainable, auditable
and governable.
So versus AI just published a
groundbreaking industry report about a
week, week and a half ago, called
designing explainable artificial
intelligence with Active Inference, a
framework for transparent introspection
and decision making.
So Active Inference is explainable AI.
Now, how, how can this be? Well, Active
Inference can self report. So machine
learning models, they're black boxes, you
know, and and therefore they can't
quantify their uncertainty.
They're unobservable, unalterable and
unknowable. Basically, the the way the
algorithm is processing the data and
coming up with its output, you can't see
what's happening, you can't know how it's
coming to its decision.
It's just this black box that's happening.
. And there's no way to really know what
it's doing just how you know, the input
and the output. So you can't explain that.
.
Now, one of the interesting things, you
know, with this call for, you know,
putting governance around AI is that if
you have these black boxes that are not
controllable, and not explainable, how do
you govern that?
So, you know, the only options have been
to, you know, either, you know, regulate
the the companies that are developing
these, you know, these tools, or to just
let the free market reign. Now, letting
free market reign is a little bit tricky
with AI, because that can really lead to
like this AI arms race kind of a thing,
you know, for AI domination.
And that, that that has some risks to,
you know, like the human nature, right.
So, and then the other problem with
regulating the companies that are
developing these tools is that you're
asking them, you're basing those
regulations off them being able to do
things like, you know, explain how the
results are coming, you know, to fruition
through their tools, or holding them
accountable for, you know,
for outputs that are, you know, false, or,
, you know, causing harm to anybody, or,
you know, different things like that,
which you really can't do that either.
Because what's happening within these
tools is not controllable. It's not
auditable, it's not controllable. So
there's a real issue with governance
around these machine model AIs.
Now, with Active Inference AI, it is
completely explainable, auditable,
transparent. And when you're talking
about the the self report, you know,
Active Inference AI is capable of
introspection.
So this enables the intelligent agents to
access and analyze their own internal
states and decision making processes. So
we get better understanding of their
decision making process. And they have
the ability to report on themselves to
basically report on how they arrived at
their decisions.
Beliefs and belief updating are known. So
this, this dissolves the explainability
problem of the conventional AI.
And then you also have programmable
intelligence. So versus refers to this as
code as law.
So the act of correcting a machine occurs
within the code within the computational
architecture of versus AI system, human
law can now be transformed into
computable law that AI can comprehend,
abide by, and then act accordingly within
its decision making process.
This is a process which is fully
auditable, knowable, and it updates in
real time. And versus has been proving
this concept in a program called Flying
Forward 2020.
And this is a European drone project.
The conducted with the European Union.
And, you know, there's eight or 12
different countries involved. I'm, I'm
not sure. But basically, what they've
proven is that they can take the the
Spatial Web protocol, the HSTP and HML.
And they can translate human laws, all
the laws around like the airspace laws,
and you know, laws, how how they shift
crossing country boundaries, different
things like that.
They can take those laws, put them in a
programmable, you know, code through the
protocol that the AI within the drone can
understand, and then abide by.
So they've, they've met with great
success through this project. And they've,
, they've proven that, you know, these
drones can deliver medical supplies, you
know, to a hospital crossing borders into
various air state airspaces, you know,
understanding no fly zones versus fly
zones, all of these things.
So basically, human law computable that
the AI can understand and abide by. So
when you're talking about AI governance,
you know, this, the protocol
allows you to actually program law that
the AI can understand. So then the other
aspect of this too, is, you know, humans
with AI, because, you know, there's a lot
of
there's a lot of fear baked into people,
especially in regard to all these sci fi
scenarios that have played out in, you
know, fictional books and movies and
things like that. But one of the great
things about the Active Inference AI
within the Spatial Web is that the AI
grows in tandem with the humans, you know,
, because you can take programmable laws
and
make it to where the AI understands and
you've got this symbiotic relationship
between the AI and the human, it's a
network system that operates in tandem
with humans. And then the AI is growing
its intelligence in sync with the growth
of humans and the world, right? So it
makes a controllable AI.
So in versus white paper, you know, one
of their opening statements was that the
the purpose of the white paper, its
denouement is a cyber-physical ecosystem
of natural and synthetic sensemaking in
which humans are an integral are integral
participants, what we call shared
intelligence.
So versus AI and the Spatial Web
foundation offer us the framework in
which we can build an ethical and
cooperative path forward for AI and human
civilization. And one thing I want to
read to you from the white paper that's,
you know, specific about this is, is this,
, so quote, we believe that developing a
cyber-physical network of emerging
intelligence in the manner described by
the white paper is a
necessary and appropriate process. And
the process described above not only
ought to, but for architectural reasons
must be pursued in a way that positively
values and safeguards the individuality
of people, as well as potentially non
human persons.
So, in the late 1990s, before the
widespread adoption of the internet, as a
communication technology, a future state
of society had been hypothesized in which
the intrinsic value of individuals is
acknowledged in part because knowledge is
valuable and knowledge and life are
inseparable.
That is, each person has a distinct and
unique life experience, and as such knows
something that no one else does.
This resonates deeply with our idea that
every intelligence implements a
generative model of its own existence.
The form of collective intelligence that
we envision can emerge only from a
network of essentially unique
epistemically and experientially diverse
agents.
This useful diversity of perspectives is
a special case of functional
specialization across the components of a
complex system.
So, you know, within the versus white
paper for this Active Inference, AI, you
know, they're very clear about the
importance of the human experience and
the various human experiences in tandem
with the growth of the AI within the
Spatial Web.
So I just thought that was really
important to to kind of let people know.
So then you have accurate world models.
Collective intelligence trained on real
time data evolves, making decisions and
updating its interior model based on what
is happening now, not on historical data
sets.
Active Inference AI is not a language
model generating words about the world
based on outdated knowledge it's been fed
regarding the world.
Active Inference is like a biological
organism that perceives and acts on our
world by generating more accurate models,
understandings and beliefs about our
world.
These ever more accurate world models
enable better decisions, a smarter world.
.
And this is the true measure of
intelligence.
So Active Inference AI as the operator,
this is the final section.
So you have the Internet of everything.
The days of training AI on big data will
give way to an interconnected Internet of
everything that deploys Active Inference
AI throughout the network.
Inherently secure and accurate because it
takes any point of real time data and
makes it smart through an empowered
ecosystem of interconnected AI apps that
act as intelligent agents.
Active Inference, QASM and the Spatial
Web.
Active Inference AI inside of the versus
AI QASM operating system has access to
the entire Spatial Web with IoT sensors
and cameras and all context markers
attached to all objects within all spaces
within the network, tracking and
identifying changes over time.
This AI becomes an ecosystem of
intelligent agents that are all
interoperable over HSTP.
So what does this mean for the planet?
Active Inference AI can run the planet.
Dan Mapes, who's one of the co-founders
of versus, he describes the Spatial Web
with Active Inference AI as a nervous
system for the planet.
Together, these technologies enable the
only AI in the world that can run
critical operations for systems,
infrastructures, smart cities and the
planet.
So when you're thinking of climate or
traffic control or smart cities or
advanced education or hospitals or
airports, all of these are critical
systems that need accurate functioning of
the AI.
You cannot rely on machine models who
give you plausible answers, plausible
outputs that sound accurate, but aren't
necessarily accurate because they're just
trained to make it sound appropriate.
Appropriate and accurate are very
different things.
So because the Active Inference AI is
based on real time data, actual data,
context that's baked into everything, it'
's an accurate form of AI and it can be
trusted to run these critical systems.
So it can be the operator.
And then we come to sentient intelligence.
.
So this is the missing piece of the data
puzzle that gets us to artificial general
intelligence.
We now have the world model and we now
possess the ability for continuous and
adaptive context markers, enabling a
cognitive world, a cognitive model of
this world and the ability to compute
awareness.
So this is taking us from the artificial
narrow intelligence, which is what these
machine models are, to potentially
artificial general intelligence and then
artificial super intelligence.
Because the more the Active Inference AI
learns about the world, it can start to
question and become curious about the
world.
And it's the difference between asking
the AI agent something and then having
the AI agent ask you something to clarify
what you want or what your needs are.
It's that curiosity back on you that'll
take us to the artificial super
intelligence.
So I'm just going to close by letting you
know that versus AI, their CosmOS is
going to be launching at the end of the
year.
And the idea is let's create a new world
together.
They've created the tools for anybody to
create the AIs on top of.
So, you know, it's a huge opportunity.
They're going to be launching the beta at
the end of this year.
If you go to my website, DeniseHolt.us,
there's a menu item where you can sign up
for the beta if you'd like.
So if you'd like to be considered, feel
free to sign up there.
And then, of course, I have a podcast and
it's on YouTube or Spotify, Apple,
anywhere you find a podcast.
But if you'd like to learn more about
this, you know, that's really my role is
I've just been educating on the Spatial
Web protocol and this Active Inference AI.
.
So there's a lot of information on my
website.
There's a lot of articles on the podcast.
.
There's just a lot of information so that
you can learn more.
So I think that's it.
Daniel: Awesome. Thank you.
Denise: Thank you, Daniel.
Daniel: All right. I'm going to come back
on video and then?
All right.
Well, thank you for the amazing
presentation.
There's many places to begin, many ways
to do it.
But again, thank you again for sharing
this information. So?
Denise: My pleasure!
Daniel: I'll start by just asking the
live stream viewers if they want to ask
anything, just put it in a live chat.
And then perhaps? just there were so many
topics that you brought up that perhaps I
can just reflect on a few of the topics
and just kind of
summarize it as as I heard it, especially
where it's different from what we've
heard in terms of framings on other
streams where we go way more into the
technical.
But but there are just so many great ways
that you had of framing what was
happening.
OK, so good?
Denise: Yeah, sounds great.
Daniel: All right. So you described
Active Inference as biologically based;
and one way that... biologically INSPIRED,
, perhaps exactly, but based upon
biological systems.
And it made me think about the way of
viewing the world in terms of its spatial
connectivity and then thinking about the
world in terms of its statistical or
causal connectivity.
And so when people think about what would
biologically inspired AI look like, they
might think about the actual connections
amongst the neurons in the brain or the
actual connections amongst ants in the
colony.
But that connectivity allows solving that
problem.
So if you want to solve some different
problem or some thing else, you need to
learn from those structures, but not copy
them verbatim.
And so that level of learning that we
have to pull back to and the level of
thinking is about the agent in their
engagement with the environment and the
minimization of surprise instead of the
maximization of reward.
And that's a really clear path, I think,
from what we can generalize from natural
intelligence towards how we can think
about what kinds of imperatives we should
design and what design principles should
be for synthetic intelligent agents.
Denise: Absolutely. Yeah.
Daniel: Okay.
What brought you to this presentation?
Like what was your way into the Spatial
Web or how did this even come to be?
Denise: Well, so Dan Mapes, who's one of
the co-founders, he's a longtime friend
of mine.
And, you know, so I knew when he and his
co-founder, Gabriel Ren?, who's the CEO
of Verses, when they were starting Verses
back in 2016, 2017 -
so, you know, I knew what I knew what was
coming.
And I've been kind of watching it unfold
over the last, like, you know, handful of
years.
And so then last summer, you know, it
became really clear to me that, you know,
Verses was getting close to launching to
the public.
You know, they've been working over the
past, you know, couple of years with like
Fortune 500 companies, with, you know,
governments and smart city development
all over the globe.
They've been involved in this Flying
Forward project.
You know, they've been deep into the
supply chain -
one of the first apps they created was an
app called Wayfinder, which is
specifically built for, you know, the
supply chain.
And so, you know, watching all of that,
but then knowing it's coming to later
this year, I was like, okay, there's a
transition.
And, you know, people need to understand
what's coming, because, you know, I've
been involved in like, you know,
blockchain and Web3 for the last, you
know, handful of years.
And so you see all these amazing
technologies being built and all these
awesome projects.
But one of the biggest problems is that
they're all siloed and the
interoperability is the biggest struggle.
.
So, you know, to me, it's like, okay, you
know, these people need to know that this
is coming.
And, you know, the interoperability is
going to be there for, you know, not just
within the Web3 or the blockchain space,
but really all technology.
Really, you know, anybody who has a
business that is present on the World
Wide Web is going to want to evolve that
presence into the Spatial Web, just for
the empowerment of what this AI and this
interoperability is going to do for their
business.
So I knew there was a learning curve.
So that's really what I set out to do,
was to kind of break down that learning
curve and really start to educate people
about the protocol, about the AI and
about what to expect.
Daniel: All right. Great. Um, few more
questions. Again, we're just starting to
explore this.
And so whatever you do or don't know is
all good. How will the open source nature
of the web and the ecosystem around
Active Inference related technologies be
secured?
Denise: Well, so, so basically, you know,
you have to think of the COSM operating
system as that's, that's literally the
operating system that is going to enable
people to easily build with build these
intelligent agents within the Spatial Web
network, right?
So, you know, that allows anybody to come
on this network and build these, build
these intelligent agents, these
intelligent apps, right?
So the beauty of it is that the protocol
itself for the Spatial Web, it bakes in
security at every touch point, right?
So you can program in access permissions,
different things like that into whatever
you're building.
So it really becomes individualized,
right? You can, you can gate off to where,
, you know, you have data that's
proprietary.
And then you have data that's allowed to
be accessed by the world.
You can, you can make it look however you
want for whatever you're building,
whatever your project is.
And what these intelligent apps then
become is, it's your opportunity to share
your knowledge with the world, right?
And you can share it to whatever extent
that you, that you want to, you know.
Daniel: Thanks.
When talking about just a few terms, I
wrote down - culture, ownership,
authority -
How do differences amongst locations and
peoples play out when there are such
different concepts of those mentioned
terms and many other terms that arose?
It might not just be something like, well,
, the drone can go a hundred feet here
and 10 feet here.
What about when there's different
concepts of authority and ownership and
justice and culture?
Denise: Right. So, well, so that's, that'
's one of the, it's one of the beauties
of the world is that, you know, we all
have our own unique understandings, our
own unique beliefs, our own unique
cultural traditions.
And the differing governing bodies and
types of government, right?
So the protocol needed to be built to be
able to preserve all of that?
"You know, you don't want there to be
this next evolution of technology that
includes AI that becomes this
dictatorship of, you know, ""This is the
way the world's going to be,"
"and this is how everybody has to
operate!"""
This preserves the uniqueness and the
individuality of everybody in any area.
So really the way this plays out, it's
going to be able to be customized for
region, for, you know, cultures, belief
systems, you know.
So it's like this socio-technical ability
to, you know, safeguard and preserve
traditions and different things and
mindsets.
So, you know, really it's, it's, it's,
you know, it's not going to be a
hindrance as much as it is going to be
something that, you know, kind of
preserves the beauty of individuality.
And so when you're talking about systems
like that, like you were talking about,
you know, it's pretty much going to be
similar to where it is today.
You know, like, you know, people have the
right to? the right of refusal, right?
[Laughs]
"You know, even in a restaurant, you know,
, ""no shirt, no shirt, shoes, no service,
,"" you know!"
So, you know, there's not going to be a
lot of difference with that, you know.
And then, so when you're talking about
things like drone delivery and things
like that, then you're going to have
other standards bodies that are making
those decisions to, you know, make things
more inclusive rather than, you know,
kind of silliness of, you know, denying
people for whatever reason.
Daniel: Wow! All right.
I'll ask a question from the live chat.
"Bert asks, ""Thank you for the
presentation."
What is the limitation of implementing
this vision?
"Is it getting people to use the
hyperspatial language or getting Active
Inference working right?"""
Or I'll add a secret third thing.
Denise: "Well, so, so, you know, I've had
people say that, you know, ask that with
me saying, you know, ""Well, what's the
guarantee that anybody's going to, you
know, you know, take part in this new
Spatial Web?"""
And it's you have to think of the way the
Internet has evolved, right?
This isn't just like this whole separate
network that you're going to try to bring
everybody on to.
It's the same network we're already on,
and it's just evolving the capabilities
within that network.
So, you know, when you think of the way
the Internet started, you know, when you
had like TCP/IP and the killer app was
email.
And then Sir Tim Berners-Lee created HTTP
and HTML.
And then you had the World Wide Web,
right?
So it didn't get rid of email!
It just enabled this whole other
capability that now people could build
websites.
Now, instead of just sending, you know,
digital messages from computer to
computer, you could actually bring an
audience to your web page and engage that
way on the Internet.
And you could do it that way on like a
property within the network.
So that's all that's happening right now,
is that we're just taking the capability
from this Web 2 environment that really
lacks security;
and it lacks protection for people and
their data;
and it opens up a lot of vulnerabilities,
because you have to all of the
transactions are taking place,
the data is transacting on a website,
which is the property of a centralized
organization, right?
So what this is doing is, it's
decentralizing it;
now, everything in any space becomes
programmable and becomes a spatial domain,
, right?
So now you have self-sovereign identity;
you have zero-trust architecture;
you have this ability to program 3D
spaces.
So it's going to be a natural progression
for people to come, you know, tp take
advantage of this new programming
language to, you know, be able to empower
and expand what they can do within the
network we already are on.
So, you know, the World Wide Web is like
40 billion computers!
Now we're evolving from just computers to
spaces and objects and everything within
there.
So, you know, it's not going to be a
matter of people? getting people to do
that.
"It's, you know, people are going to go, "
""Wow, I can do that!"""
And, you know, it's going to be a natural
progression.
As far as the Active Inference AI, it's
going to start working within the network,
, and it's just going to grow.
So the more people are engaging on, you
know, within the Spatial Web network, and
the more people that are building these
AI apps?
And I think, if we look at what's
happened just in the first six months of
this year since ChatGPT came out, with
all of the, you know, all of the open
source and everything that's been
available as soon as it got available to
the public -
And now we can tinker with it.
Now we can build things.
You've had an explosion of development!
So, you know, with the ability to build
these intelligent agents within the
network and do it very easily and have
this interoperability within the network,
I just see it as, we're going to have
this explosion of development.
So that's, of course, that's my opinion,
but that's what I see happening.
Daniel: You stake your claim!
That's a beautiful thing.
I'll ask another question.
Your answer led perfectly to it.
Bert asked again in the chat:
"""Also, is there a resource where we can
learn more about how to build a
hyperSpatial Website?"""
Denise: So, I don't think there? I don't
think those resources are out yet.
And, you know, and it's not going to be a
website.
So, you know, it's as soon as the COSM
operating system launches, the AI is
going to become a tool for building
anything.
So the other side of this app store where
you can build an intelligent agent is the
interface.
The public interface is an intelligent
agent called GIA, and it stands for
General Intelligent Agent.
So GIA then becomes the interface for the
public of the network, of the Spatial Web.
.
So GIA is going to become your personal
assistant -
everybody's personal assistant.
GIA will be able to act on your behalf
within the network.
So, you know, just like with ChatGPT-4
and how the AIs are starting to be able
to program.
So within the Spatial Web, the AI is
going to play an integral part in
creating your own intelligent agents and,
you know, doing your own?
establishing your own presences and, you
know, spatial domains and things like
that.
So I don't have a lot of detail on how
that's going to look or work, but that's
my general understanding of it.
So I don't think there's going to be a
huge learning curve when it comes to that.
.
Daniel: Wow. All right! I'll go to
another question. Dave asked in the chat,
,
"""Does Verses plan eventually to expand
the inventory of Element types (beyond
the 12 mentioned in today's
presentation)?"
"People negotiate concerns that don't
seem to fit easily in this framework."""
Denise: Yeah. So I don't know. I don't
know if I can really answer that.
And the reason why is because I don't?
I don't? my technical knowledge of what's
happening behind the scenes is very
limited.
So the answer could be yes; it could be
it's already there.
I mean, the reality is, is those those 12
aspects are just, you know, kind of a
generalized idea of what you can program.
.
But when you're talking about, you know,
HSTP being multidimensional, you know,
and you can program in everything from
like, you know, temperature to, you know,
pressure to, you know, you can... you can.
... you can?
If it's programmable and definable, you
know, in a computational form, you can?
you can bake it into, you know, the
context around whatever you're
programming.
So, you know, in that respect, it's it's
pretty unlimited, except for that
limitation, as long as it's measurable
and definable in a computational way.
Daniel: I'll try to restate that, just
how I heard it, because I think it's a
really important point.
The 12 (again, this can be totally off
base if I don't have any information),
but the 12 components shown are kind of
like fully? one way of fully showing your
work.
But when you really get down to the last
mile and the shoes on the ground, you're
in the realm of the particulars and the
specific measurements, at which point
complex cultural topics will be playing
out through the minute particulars, not
necessarily inheriting some stringency
from a top-down ontology.
If that's fair, I just want to kind of
say it that way.
Denise: Yeah.
Daniel: OK! You mentioned, I think, a few
times in the presentation, the idea of
realities.
So, yeah, we have our beloved cyber-
-physical reality.
And what other are the plural realities?
Denise: So basically, when you think of
being able to, you know, program the
context into the spaces, right, then that
provides you with a digital twin, which
automatically is giving you this mixed
reality ability.
Right? Because, you know, digital twin
and then physical reality, this is going
to open us up to this augmented existence,
, this augmented reality existence that
we all kind of envision.
But the foundation hasn't been there.
The framework hasn't really been there.
This is providing that framework.
So we're going to? we're going to see
this kind of augmented reality future for
us, you know, where we're able to cross,
you know, cross through mixed realities.
You're going to have the virtual reality,
you're going to have the augmented
reality, and then you're going to have
the physical reality.
And there's going to be an unlimited way
of mixing that.
And then the other aspect of this, too,
is when you talk about like virtual
reality and you talk about the metaverses
and different, you know, metaverse
experiences, you know, I think one of the
reasons why the metaverse experience has
been so lackluster is because they're
siloed right now!
When you consider the Spatial Web, that's
going to be able to make it to where you
can jump in and out of these virtual
reality spaces.
You can actually take your assets from
one space to another space, because all
of it then becomes interoperable over the
network.
So this is going to really open up -
everything that we've been wanting to do
is going to now be possible within this
Spatial Web network.
Daniel: Great. All right. As we kind of
begin to land the plane, I'll just
reflect on two or so positive aspects
that I think are part of the vision,
which we will, of course, await future
sensory observations to confirm, reduce
our surprise.
But in Active Inference, what we expect
is what we prefer.
So if we think it's the most likely path
forward, then c'est la vie.
So the first positive thing is that it
starts from the actual and the
measurements, defining things at some
defined cyber-physical layer; and
(potentially extrapolating here, but)
earlier this week, we had a GuestStream
with Mahault [Albarracin] and Maxwell
[Ramstead].
And in the quantum Free Energy Principle
approach to the brain, there is a top
level decision maker within that blanket
where the buck stops.
So that doesn't mean like that the brain
is not composed of, you know, as a
component of part of larger compositions;
but within the given blanket, there's a
highest stop.
So instead of handing our self-
-sovereigntizing ability and intelligence
to the black box, here we can start from
the actual, maybe even pick up and
stabilize or change what we already have.
.
So rather than proposing just a totally
different future that some scaling law is
going to help us get to, maybe or maybe
not, we start with like what we already
measure and the decisions we already make.
.
So I very much appreciate the pragmatism.
What else might you reflect on that
point?
Denise: I think you said it well. Yeah.
Daniel: OK! Then the second piece was
that everyone's knowledge is adding
something.
It might be a close sample or a distant
sample on some dimension in some setting;
but everyone, every cognitive agent is
adding non-zero information.
And there's a lot of technical details
underneath why that is.
The amount of information added might be
very small for a given question; but
because of differences, we literally get
more perspectives.
So we always see better with more
perspectives if we have the right
integration approach.
So that's also very powerful. And it's
something that is formally true with the
math and the statistics.
And I think we want it to be true for our
ecosystems.
Denise: Right. Yeah, absolutely.
And it's interesting because, yeah, you
want to preserve that, the diversity of
information and opinion and have that
accessible.
For sure.
Daniel: Awesome. Well, it will be quite
the coming days, probably, or at least as
expected or preferred.
But we'll very much look forward to you
coming back on the ActInf Streams, as
well as some technical presentations that
might help our community and our
Institute learn, more about the details,
or more philosophical discussions.
The whole spectrum of learning and
applying and implementing these
technologies will be really important to
characterize.
But for sure, it's been incredible to
have you share this first bit.
Is there any last words you'd like?
Denise: No, just thank you so much for
having me.
It's been a pleasure.
And I will throw this out there.
I know there's not a lot of information
available out there regarding the Spatial
Web and the Active Inference AI.
So if anybody has any questions, feel
free to reach out to me.
You can reach me on Twitter or LinkedIn
or my blog, deniseholt.us.
There's plenty of ways on there to reach
me.
So I'm happy to answer any questions
anybody might have.
Daniel: All right. Thank you, Denise.
Till next time.
Denise: Thanks a lot. Bye bye.