Hey, everyone, thanks for tuning in.
And today it is March 30, 2022.
We're here in the ActInf Lab Quarterly,
roundtable number one for 2022. Welcome
to the ActInf lab. We're a participatory
online lab that is communicating,
learning, and practicing applied active
inference. You can find us at some of
the links here on this slide. This is
recorded in an archived Livestream, so
please provide us with feedback so that
we can improve our work. All backgrounds
and perspectives are welcome here, and
we'll be following video etiquette for
live streams today in
the ActInf Lab Quarterly, roundtable
number one for 22. We're going to have a
first section after our intros on lab
scale updates and then we'll talk about
project scale updates which are nested
within the lab scale and just close with
some preferences and expectation and
through and through. We hope that you'll
see many affordance for participation,
many active cue signals in your
epistemic niche that elicit action that
make you curious about something that
connect with your preexisting
preferences or update them so that you
get involved with active inference or
possibly even the lab. So whenever you
do see this or listen to it or some
other combination, feel free to go to
Active Inference.org or email us,
Active Inference Lab@gmail.com, and
we'll be in touch from there. So we can
begin with just some introduction and
warm ups. And it feels so different to
do this without a paper that we've read
before. So for these intros, we can just
say hi and anyone can reflect on just
like, how is your generative models
updated this quarter? What did you
perceive or learn? How did you change?
And what might be something that you're
looking forward to as we Parr on the
latter of 75% of 2022?
So, I'm Daniel And, a researcher in
California. I think my generative model
updated and fragmented into a thousand
little pieces with Coda and the way that
we used formal documents this quarter as
opposed to previous quarters, but it's
coherent in a way that is actually
helpful. I hope so.
I'll pass to Alex.
Yes. Hi, rule one. I'm Alex Zotkin. I'm
one of the founders of the lab and also
Researcher Assistance Management School.
And from latest time, I feel like
we're sharing our generative models more
and more, and hopefully it will bring us
to new developments. And they
paste it to Bleu.
Hi, everyone. I'm Bleu. I am an
independent research consultant in New
Mexico. I think this quarter was
pretty special. Like, the Coda
restructuring was pretty awesome and
just contributing to building, like,
lab infrastructure in Coda and in
YouTube with videos and timestamps and
podcasts and I don't know, it was fun.
I think probably the biggest update was
the quantum paper because that was
pretty epic, the one that we just have
discussed over the last couple of weeks.
And in the next quarter, I'm looking
forward to having some more quiet
time, less talking more doing. That's
what I'm looking forward to in Q. Two
of, and I will pass it to
Yvonne.
Thanks. Good. Yeah, that is very nice.
We finally run System
Thinking Study Group this
border, and I hope Web participants
enjoy it and I see that they do.
And I hope we run next another
study group and it will be.
So. That is.
A lot going on. I'm becoming a
little less guilty about skipping at
least half of the activities, but I get
to hear at least to read the papers and
listen to the live streams. And there's
lots of work going on with the
transcript, which is very gratifying.
Even if Daniel no longer believes
himself about how valuable it is to do
the print transcripts and put them in
service, I still am sticking with the
10,000 times more value from a
transcribe talk than just a YouTube
audio with pictures. So who haven't we
heard from? Stephen?
Hello? Yeah, we're still here. We're
still standing, sort of. So that's
great. I'm here in Toronto. For me,
I'm appreciative for certain of the
capacity the labs offered, the
connections, the conversation, the
ability to bounce the ideas.
And that's been really, really helpful.
And particularly with Mark's
songs and a lot of these ideas with
Quantum, which at first I thought some
might be quite abstract, we're starting
to synthesize and find ways to pull
them together, and so I'm hoping that
can be used. Now I'm working with some
embodied workshops and taking that into
communities and letting this work inform
how I coach, how I facilitate,
how I try and explain.
That's the hard bit, but Parr.
And it could but shouldn't go without
saying, just massive appreciation to
everybody who does and continues to show
up for Active Lab. You see the tip of
the iceberg on the live streams, but
there are many others. So as we continue
to formalize and determine and reduce
our uncertainty about what kind of thing
we are here, we'll hopefully have
clearer and clearer ways to force
attribution and to show recognition for
all the people who contribute in just
the million ways that are possible from
beginner to very familiar. So we will
just provide a brief overview of ActInf
Lab from a narrative perspective before
we jump into our strategy discussion.
So in 2020, towards the middle and in
the end, some of us wrote a paper in
September was when it was published,
active Inference Lab and Behavior
Engineering for Teams, which was
addressing a gap that we perceived in
the literature, which was the
relationship between active inference
framework and remote teams and
communication. At the end of that year,
after thinking about what our next steps
would be after that paper, we thought
that something like an active lab would
be cool. So we sent out an initial call
for collaboration. During all of 2021
was our first year of ActInf Lab project
operation. And the projects were in the
three organizational units of education,
communication and tools this year in
2022, which is what we're going to be
talking about today. A lot has
happened at both the Lab scale and the
project scale. So we're going to first
talk about the lab scale and the two
pieces under. Lab scale updates are
going to be the initial release of the
lab strategy document. And we'll also
discuss the initial advisory board
cohort. And then we'll go into the
project scale and discuss some of the
ongoing projects that have
resulted in all kinds of deliverables
and outputs. So first to the Lab scale.
Alex, would you like to talk a little
bit about just from a high level
strategy? Yeah,
thanks. I think
everything in our lab we are trying to
do things in some new
ways that was not using before
and also trying to put it on some
StateoftheART errors and approaches. So
as for strategy, we consider strategy
not as a concrete document,
but as and ongoing process which
will have quarterly reviews
and updates. And on high level we
are following open address approach.
So who is interested? It now
can be approached from developments
of Stanley and we are trying to avoid
using classic objective missions,
goals and other corporate stuff. So we
are trying to see in the future,
we are trying to see some endstopping
stones that we can make next
steps. And also for sure,
as from the beginning we use active
inference not only as a research field,
but also trying to implement and
use concepts from there such as
preferences and expectation. And also we
consider that all our activities are
on different scales. So we need to
follow and understand how it's applied
on different scales.
Thank you. So we will now go
through the current state of the
strategy document and just anyone here,
feel free to raise your hands and of
course anyone watching along, feel free
to write questions and we'll get to
them. So pause
the video or check it out to read the
full text here. But just to summarize,
our strategic document preamble in
ActInf Lab, we're directing our
attention to different phenomena across
multiple scales. And the scales that
we're most interested in, or the ones
that we are heuristically using are the
personal, the individual human scale,
the Lab scale, that's active Lab scale
and then the Community or the Niche or
the Environment scale which is the
epistemic surroundings of the Lab.
And what's special about the Lab scale
is that is where the lab can implement
policy, we can least action that are
perceived as sense states by individual
people or by the external community.
And that may or may not chance their
policy selection. But the Lab scale is
where strategy happens because that's
where we can actually implement policy
selection. And we're taking this
multiscale nested systems
perspective to five exafferent aspects
of act in Flap. And those five aspects
that we're going to talk about in the
next few slides are education,
research, outreach and engagement
methods and open endedness.
Any general comments before we
continue? Brea so act and Clark
is an educational nonprofit.
This plays out at all scales, as all
things do. But we're especially
interested here in the personal scale,
in educating individuals, in having
individuals that learn and update their
generative models, and also respecting
just the tremendous diversity of active
inference journeys that different
individuals are coming in and through
relationship with the active inference
lab. And at the more community scale,
our educational efforts are oriented
towards reducing research debt and
increasing the applicability and the
comprehensibility and the rigor and
accessibility of active inference and
related ideas. Any concepts on
education?
Okay, the second aspects
of the lab is the research aspect,
and here it also plays out at the
personal and at the community scale. At
the personal scale, we hope to provide a
niche that scaffolds and catalyzes the
research projects by participants,
which is something we'll come back to
later. But we both do research
in the lab as well as on the interface
and just hope to motivate and create a
space for people to share their
individual research updates. And at the
community scale, we're recognizing that
research is carried out alongside
ongoing discussions about responsibility
and ownership and many, many other
terms. So there we hope to
learn practices and improve and give our
own twist on what the future of
science, open science, decentralized
science, DSI, just science with no
adjectives, and education. What will
research and education be in our future?
Esteves. Thanks, Daniel. Yeah,
this is really helpful to read and also
the fact that we've got lots of people
from different backgrounds coming
together. The research
that's happening is quite
transdisciplinary, and it's
been informed by lots of different
ideas. So there's a kind of a mixture of
those processes. So it's helpful to have
the systems engineering work that
probably comes through later. But that's
helpful in letting us get a feel for
how the research doesn't get siloed as
purely a paper. But okay,
how could that be bounced off to maybe
make a difference in the world in ways
that maybe people who don't even know
active inference find that they're using
something differently because active
coherence has helped the way that their
practice is shaped. So I like that.
Awesome. The third
aspect is outreach and engagement and
active inference lab lab is working on a
Global scale with a participatory model.
So at the personal scale, we welcome all
participation and engagement, and that
means all time zones and spoken
languages and preferences and what
people want to do and where they're at.
With active coherence. Participation,
in a sense, begins with where the
participant is. And there is
of course, more that everybody can say
and add and show, not tell or show and
tell if they've brought enough for the
class in the coming years. And then at
the community scale, we also seek to
be part of a emergence landscape of high
quality science, communication and
participation, and inclusion in research
and projects around topics like active
inference, which is what we're most
attuned to in our regime of attention.
But that doesn't mean we only talk
active inference lab people. So we hope
that our outreach and engagement is
meaningful and sustained and impactful
any comments on outreach and agreement.
Okay, methods.
The Active Inference Lab applies
StateoftheART methods across domain
that refers to the methodology of active
inference and the emergence tools and
ways that we have of working with active
coherence, as well as other
methodologies like for project
management, for education, for
communication, etc. So at the personal
scale, we're educating participants so
that they can grow their expertise in
different disciplines and also develop
as a person holistically like keeping it
balanced, you're not going to stay up
and finish reading every single active
paper. So staying balanced and having
methodologies that help us be affordance
but also balanced are quite important.
And then at the lab scale, we hope to
implement the cutting edge,
the Pareto optimal, the Bayesian optimal
methodology, which includes our
switching strategies, and we
fix typos on the fly. That's what
editable documents allow. Our
affordances as an organization are the
methodologies that we scaffold
in projects. So especially at the lab
scale, we hope that we use methodology
that's powerful and facilitates
collective intelligence and also
clarifies the distinction or the
inclination of partition, perhaps even
between those who are following along
and listening ActInf Livestream,
reading the papers in the game. That's
awesome. And then those who actually on
board into the lab and eventually have a
role in a project will be able
to increasingly be clear about what that
means through the uses of different
systems, ideas like practices, cases,
responsibilities and concerns. Yes.
Elon?
Yeah, thank you. I would like to add
that if we compile methods and outreach
so the lab provides a lot of
opportunities for the understanding of
active in. For instance, we provide a
lot of tools and for
those who already participate
in the lab and for those who just start
to deep inside the active coherence.
Awesome. And the
lab. Last, but not really the last
aspect is openendedness. As Alex
mentioned earlier and has been bringing
and reminding us all of since the
beginning, that ActInf lab is on the
path of openendedness. It doesn't mean
that we sit and wait where the road
forks or when we have uncertainty about
the future. Those are fundamentals. And
in fact, openendedness is action amidst
uncertainty. So at the personal scale,
we recognize and support the
openendedness of the personal journey of
individuals who are learning and
applying active inference. So even if
you don't know exactly where you're
headed or what your finish line or your
milestones, your checkpoint looks like,
if you don't even know what your
preferences are, or you're unsure about
some other parameter in your generative
models. That's all good. At the lab
scale, our strategy is
to say it is a work in progress, would
be to almost assume that there would be
a final strategy, but rather our
strategy is and encoding process that
will always be updating in response to
changes in the niche and the effect that
our action have over multiple active
states. So we do recognize
and utilize approaches to active
shortterm success and realizing products
and deliverables over short term. But
also there's a time and a space and a
place for thinking about active
coherence and the active inference lab
in deeper time. And that is especially
where diverse participation and our lab
advisory board come into play, which
we'll talk about in a second. And then
just lastly, at the community scale,
it's true in principle that active lab
can participate in various kinds of
activities that might be beyond
education, research and outreach and
agreement. We will always be considering
those opportunities in a case by case
way and assessing whether it's something
that fits best within the Markov blanket
and the kind of thing that ActInf lab is
or maybe some thing else could exist
that could play that role in the
ecosystem. Yes, Dave?
Okay, Stephen, I'm interested
by the way that the ecosystem,
this question of what's in the Markov
blanket and the nonequilibrium steady
state and what's in the niche and those
three things are kind of dynamic. So I
think over time, looking at the way the
world is and without getting too
evangelical, there's lots of big
claims made about active coherence and
its potential. And as we've
been having conversations, we've seen a
lot of things at scale come up, which is
quite exciting conversations around
that, but often maybe a little bit
fuzzy, a little bit conceptual. So I
think some of the stuff that's going to
come out there, the lab is going to be
spinning off as much as it might be
holding on to.
Excellent. Thank you. So that concludes
the discussion on the strategy update.
The second lab scale update is to
mention our advisory board. So this
information can be found at our website
Active Inference. And on the top right
head over to where it says Advisory
Board. The advisory board is and
insight and guidance board. It's not a
managerial board and it exists to help
the lab make better strategic decisions.
So we engage our advisory board
participants in terms of their
expertise, different recommendations and
questions they have for the lab and we
recognize and hope to draw on and
synergize with their experience in many,
many different areas. We have and image
here from Kirchhoff Ant All 2018 about
nested systems and about the way
that as systems develop, for example,
as potentially and overdevelopmental
time, a zygote goes from being a single
cell enclosed by a lipid bilayer towards
increasingly ramified levels
of embryonic complexity or similar
transitions could be happening over
evolutionary time. Something like that
is occurring as we elaborate and build
the ActInf lab. We have an awesome
initial Conor of the advisory board,
and it includes Bradley, Alicia, john
Boyke, matt Brain, john Kippinger,
scott David Jeff, Emmett, Chris Fields,
karl Friston, raphael Kaufman,
anatole Levinschuk, roslyn Morin, elvis
Arano, cheryl Benhoof tim Rebellion,
swan Webb and Michael Zargam. And we
have already received really important
and meaningful feedback from them and
really appreciate it. And for those who
are interested in the kinds of work that
we're up to and might have experience in
a certain domain that could be helpful,
for example, related to educational
nonprofits, then perhaps get in touch
with us. But this is a major change to
the Lab scale to introduce and advisory
board and we're off to a fun start with
them so far. So we look forward to just
seeing how that continues.
Any other comments on Active at the Lab
scale or we can head to the projects.
Okay, so as we head through these
projects, feel free to raise your hand
ant any point if you want to add a
comment or a question. And as a
participatory lab, those who are
listening and you've made it this far,
recognize that all of these reflect the
contributions of participants and
reflect affordances for you to
contribute further, even if only to
reduce your uncertainty about the
documentation or the way that something
is occurring. So hopefully if you're
listening to this string of symbols,
know that you can participate and
perhaps you even should. We're going to
talk about a few different projects
today, in fact eleven different of them.
And you can see loosely on the left that
these are in three organizational
units.edu, comma and tools.
But the project scale is really where
the team and the roles and the practices
occur. So we're highlighting the project
scale and the project is also the unit
of Granularity where you can really get
involved and make a contribution. So
showing up for our synchronous
organizational unit meetings is an
awesome way to kind of paint a first
Costa and to be exposed to many of the
projects. But by and large, the
contributions happen at the project
scale and asynchronously so, all
backgrounds, all time zones, all levels
of commitment, everyone is welcome to
get involved with these projects, which
we're going to go through now. They're
going to be the active coherence
ontology the active inference course,
internal educational initiatives like
the systems thinking, reading,
discussion group and ontology working
group active inference journal research
updates, live streams, podcasts,
social media, active blockerents
robotics and embodied and active lab
meta modeling. On we go to the ontology.
We've just recently pushed an update
to the Active Coherence ontology and
it's available at this Coda link here.
The goal of the Active Inference
Ontology is to increase the
accessibility and impact of active
inference by increasing clarity and
interoperability and expressivity and
all these other good things about terms
and ideas. And when you go to this site,
you'll find that there's and explanatory
preamble. And what this ontology
release contains primarily are two
different kinds of things, proposed
definitions and translations. So first,
the proposed definitions. This is what
the proposed definitions look like for
the core terms. The terms are
on the left column here and then
everywhere there's an app and a Bleu is
like a clickable link to another term.
So it's kind of like how dictionaries
use other words in that language and it
will say A is kind of like B, except
it's different than C. And so that's
what the definitions are. Their natural
language answers to the question what is
X? And so these proposed definitions are
currently in natural language, but there
are other ways to develop them. More
formally, the proposed definitions are
there for those who just say, well,
what does this term mean? It also helps
with computationally aided sense making.
And then the second piece that is in
this current release of the ontology is
the translations. And so here's the
current view of the top of the
translations table. So we have the term
in the English on the left side and then
we have so far complete translations of
the core ontology terms into Spanish,
Portuguese, French, Italian,
Czech, Russian and Hebrew, and some
German and some others that are sort of
beginning. So especially if you have
fluency or friends with fluency in some
of these languages, but especially new
and different languages, this is a
really awesome opportunity to translate
some terms, which are mostly normal
natural language terms, into another
human natural language. And that will
facilitate the ability to, for example,
deploy educational information or
transcripts and their translations do it
in a way that's rigorous and accessible
and meets people where they are in terms
of their language fluency. Yes. Dave
okay, so that's the Active Ontology
project where we're developing
participatory biology for active
inference terms. Stephen, can I just
ask, not putting you on the spot, but if
I was to ask you what areas have been
the most challenging or the most
difficult to overcome? And what
are the sort of questions that are still
being grappled with on the ontology?
And which ones have we overcome already?
And which ones are still sitting there
in the background? I'm just curious if
you got any thoughts on that. Yeah,
good question. I'll give a thought and
then anyone else is welcome to if they
want. One interesting thing is
these definitions, although many papers
do sometimes define their terms either
in the text or in a box or in a
glossary, that doesn't mean that the way
that the terms are defined are coherent
or compatible or consistent.
And a lot of times it's like a yes and
someone defines it one way and someone
else just kind of takes a different spin
on it. But other times we have come
across several situations altogether,
all of us, at least here, where there
were incompatible seeming uses of
terms. And perhaps that happens with all
kinds of linguistic elements. So that
was one interesting thing, was that it's
not just like we're looking through
papers and copying sentences. There's
actually a really powerful process of
the discussion that we had focusing week
by week on just a few terms or one term
where we were seeing all the different
ways that different terms are being used
inside and outside of active inference
and just trying to work towards some
kind of grip on that. Bleu.
So one of the biggest challenges that I
think we face is dirty and incomplete
data, which is like pervasive across
field and disciplines everywhere. So I
mean, trying to be the bridge to fill
the gaps, to make the data, to complete
the data. There's always opportunities
if people want to get involved, like in
filling out the data, like helping us to
have a complete picture of which to
metamodel. Awesome. And there are
other columns and features of the
ontology that we're working on in the
lab for anybody who wants to get
involved, like correct examples,
just simple declarative, concise
positive examples of terms being used
correctly, that's awesome.
Incorrect examples, people who are using
sentences. It doesn't have to be caught
in the wild, but it could be but just
generative sentences that are like
counterexamples can be very helpful
for both humans and computers in their
learning. And so we have examples,
counter examples, formalisms connecting
Jorge terms and other terms to equations
and papers and connecting it with
literature corpus. So there's so many
angles. Those with curiosity and
expertise in active inference and or
ontology should absolutely get involved
with this, which will be a long term
project of the lab and we hope to find
new ways of deploying it. And just to
give one little contextualizing slide
here, this entire continuum
can be considered to be different types
or grades or like a taxonomy of
ontologies. And so ontologies in their
most informal can be as simple as a list
of terms or glossaries the sources or
what we have right now with the current
release, which is like a principled,
informal, hierarchical and some
relationships amongst terms. And that's
what we have right now with the proposed
definitions and translations. We're also
working with the Ontology working group
which we'll talk about in a few minutes
on foraging that ontology, for example,
using Sumo and cue Kev and thinking
about how do we integrate the ontology
with course development, with knowledge
engineering and literature integration.
So some of the many things that people
can look forward to.
Okay, on to the second project,
which is the Active Course. So in
the active Course project we are seeking
to create a learning platform that
embodies the principles of active
inference and facilitates the learning
of its principles and concepts to
learners of many different backgrounds.
And this is something that we are not
too far down the road on but are eagerly
looking forward to especially in light
of some recent epistemic changes in our
niche which we'll talk about soon but
there's a massive potential for active
inference education and we hope to have
course offerings and educational
experiences that meet that opportunity.
Alex? Yes, just a quick
note to avoid possible misunderstanding
that action platform here is not
like for some It platform but more about
set of educational services which will
be supported to improve learning
affordance. Yes,
good call, thanks for clarifying that.
So if you're interested or
curious about course design education,
education in a participatory way
nonprofits, those are all excellent cues
for people who'd like to come on board
and help in a serious way for this
course as we start to think about what
it can be.
Okay,
third project we have several internal
educational initiatives in active lab
and so on the left we see the Systems
thinking reading discussion group and on
the right ontology working group the
OWG. Alex or anyone? Would you like
to describe or give a note on either of
these sides?
I just want to say that from the very
beginning we consider that we should not
only learn and educate
active coherence but also to learn.
As you mentioned before, state of our
practices and systems was one of the
main discipline from the beginning what
we think is very useful for collective
work especially in remote mode. So it's
great right now more and more people
start learning and it definitely will
improve our communication and speed up
our activity on the projects.
Thank you. Yes, Ivanne has been
facilitating the Systems Thinking
Reading discussion group strdg and we
have an intrepid group of participants
who are working their way through this
online course and having regular
discussions and asynchronous
conversation as well around it. And as
Alex said, this is really important for
the ways that we work together and
communication. And on the right side we
have the Ontology Working Group. So
previously we were discussing the active
ontology as a project where we're
talking about active inference terms and
how they're related in the ontology
working group. We are increasing our
competency in computational ontology and
what that chaos looked like primarily
has been working with the Sumo suggested
upper merged ontology system in Suo Kif
and working through the textbook of
Adam Tie. And this has been an awesome
experience. Dave has made a massive
amount of contributions and ontological
limericks of different formats. And that
has also been a great learning
experience that hopefully will fold back
in towards improving the active
inference ontology. But it's also just a
learning initiative. And that brings us
to an ongoing learning
initiative which is the release,
literally, in the last several DAGs of
the textbook by thomas Parr, Giovanni
Pezzulo, and karl Friston, it's the
active inference textbook. And we asked,
well, what can the ActInf lab do for
slash with? Around the
textbook. Do you want to join a textbook
group? Not just a reading group, just a
textbook group, because we are going to
be organizing cohorts of textbook groups
and you can email us for the form if you
don't already have access to it, but you
will fill out a form that asks whether
you'd like to join an upcoming textbook
group cohort and it will be done in
groups and cohorts. Yes, you're ready or
no, you'd like to perhaps hear about
that affordance in a few months?
We ask for name, email address and
country, whether you have a textbook or
not, and then just for you to provide
several sentences or more on your level
of familiarity and your interest in
active inference and all backgrounds and
familiarities, as with all activities,
are welcome. This is going to be a
really awesome experience, I think, to
work through this textbook and see
it as just one pebble on the ant hill or
the tip of the iceberg or any other
metaphor that people use. For the way in
which this textbook will both be a
visible and centralizing artifact as
well as something that is really only a
few hundred pages long. And it's a
relatively small physical book. So it's
just the beginning, it's not the end of
active inference and those in the
textbook groups will realize that and
enact it. Any comments on internal
educational initiatives?
All right.
Number four, the active inference
journal. So in this project we are
publishing knowledge artifacts so that
they are searchable, indexable and
citable. Most recently, in the active
inference journal, we uploaded a second
improved version of the transcript of
the Karl Friston symposium applied
active inference symposium. That was in
June 2021. And from that
we are improving our methodology that we
learnt and learnt by doing in that first
symposium transcript process and
applying that to other event recordings.
For example, Gas stream 16 with Mark
Solms and Livestream number 40 with a
quantum free free energy principle.
The journal is going to be a great place
where we continue to build a
participatory pipeline for improving
spoken and written dissemination.
Anything that anyone wants to add on
this? Yes, Dave.
Yeah, I sent the original
paper and the three video
segments to Sean Carroll along with a
summary of the three big points.
In the summary he says this is cool,
I will check it out, which I'm sure
incentivizes the gentleman who
volunteered to go through our transcript
and make it more presentable to get
through that. And then we can send that
to the very busy Dr. Carol who just has
a new appointment. He is something like
the chair of the Philosophy of Science
at Johns Hopkins. So all his
pain of being denied tenure is paying
off and he may
pay off. He already, I think, gets along
very well with Professor Friston. He
says, I have never had to work so hard
in an interview with somebody who is so
knowledgeable and well spoken and
anxious to communicate. Awesome.
And it's a great example of a project
that increases accessibility.
For example, by taking two or 6
hours of YouTube discussions and making
them searchable and translatable and
then also reduces reachers research debt
because we can have somebody spend three
or 7 hours improving and foraging a
manuscript and finding when somebody
mentioned this paper here's that
specific citation that multiplied by
thousands of people searching for that
paper. Maybe they have access, maybe
they don't, maybe they misheard the
name. There's so much that we can be
proactive about in terms of making our
knowledge corpus really accessible and
meaningful and woven according to Modern
practices. Okay, awesome work though.
Dave and others on the journal Maria and
others as well. Okay,
on five we have research
updates. So this is not a project that
we actively steward per se in the lab,
but this is just capturing research
that's in progress and finished by lab
participants. So just to highlight a few
papers and products that have been
released by active inference lab
participants, but not necessarily as an
active lab project in the last few
months. So by Avel, Gwen and Carlos,
aka Serval, aka Icarus, the paper
cognitive agency in sociocultural
evolution, and then and awesome
collaborative paper that we wrote with
myself, Sean, Arhan, RJ, Shadi,
Avel, Bleu, Yvonne, Sid,
Amit, Jacob, Caleb and Alex,
where we talked about decentralized
science DSI. We integrated some of the
more technological perspectives on DSI,
for example, related to Web Three, and
Blockchain and juxtapose that with some
of the bottom up, the view from the
bottom participatory sense making and
epistemic, commons and produced.
An active entity ontology for science
AOS that we hope will allow us to have a
way to model some of these complex
epidemic ecosystems in the encoding
months. So that's just some of the
research and there's other awesome
research. Seth in progress.
Okay, on to yes, Steven, go for it.
Yeah, I'd be curious. I think this work
with situated sense making the
decentralized science is really
interesting and I think there'd be ways
that the other areas of sense making
which this can be helpful to bridge that
active coherence generative model
modeling approach with other ways. So
I'm really glad that you did this work,
actually, as a group, and I think it's
going to help tell another story, which
might have been a bit too hard to tell
from the ground up, but now you've got a
bridge. So. Thanks, Conor.
Okay, on to six. So we
had awesome live streams as usual in
this quarter at the Coda IO
Slash ActInf Lab, active lab, you can
find the past and upcoming live streams.
We had several guest streams and other
kinds of streams, but most of our
streams in the last few months were the
paper discussions. So in Livestream
number 35, one and two. So, as with all
of these there was a dot zero, a
background and contextualizing video
that was prepared in the weeks leading
up to the dot one, dot two discussions
which are participatory group
discussions. So if you ever see a paper
where you want to be in the dot one or
the dot two and be part of a group and
you don't need to say a ton, no one's
going to call on you, you can ask
anything you want, provide any
perspectives. You're always welcome to
join that way. And then something that's
incredibly helpful for the lab is to
commit assuredly ahead of time and
contribute to the dot zero making the
slides and helping contextualize the
paper ahead of the dot one and the dot
two. So we in the last few months have
talked about in number 35 we talked
about a tail of two architectures, free
energy, its models and modularity.
Check out the live streams to learn
more. I won't even attempt to summarize
the papers other than just to state
their titles. In 36 we discussed
modeling ourselves what the free energy
principle reveals about our implicit
notions of representation. We then dove
a bit into the technical in 37 with Free
Energy a user's guide in 38
discussed the evolution of brain
architecture's for predictive coding.
Active inference lab in 39 discussed
Morphogenesis as Bayesian Coherence, a
variational approach to pattern
formation and control in complex
biological systems. And then in 40 we
discussed a free energy principle for
generic quantum systems which was, as
anybody who was there before or during
or after it happened, can attest, was
quite a special and interesting
experience. And just to show what that
Coda a page looks like, if you head over
there, you'll see the encoding streams.
Here we are in the end of March. It's
not in the live stream section, it's in
the roundtable
section. Here we are right now. But in
live streams you'll see the papers that
we're going to be discussing in the
coming months. So if you're interested
in any of these upcoming papers, please
get involved in the dot zero zero or the
dot one and two. If you're interested in
inviting anybody or yourself, being a
guest on a guest stream, that's always
an affordance. These are like one off or
small series that can be on active
inference research or related topics.
And we've had some great discussions in
the last few weeks on guest streams. We
have model streams and math streams that
are for presenting some of the formal
and model based components of active
inference, and streams where we talk
about organizational principles and
organizational design. So those are just
some of the live streams that we've had
and it's been fun. So especially
if you want to give a guest stream, or
if you can connect to somebody who does
want to or encourage or recommend
somebody, or you want to be a
facilitator for someone else to present
or any other combination of affordances.
Let's make it happen because we can get
a lot of awesome modifications in our
niche. I think what they used to call
making content back in the web. Two
days. So that's all for Live Streams
podcast Bleu, do you want to give an
update? Sure. So we are moving through
the podcast, really revisits a lot of
the early livestreams. So like if you're
playing catch up, like if you caught a
live stream you're like, I should go
through the back catalog. Like maybe now
you're on live stream 20 something.
Like the podcast starts with the early
episodes and I think we're through
episode nine Livestream number nine now.
So yeah, check it out. It's fun. Also a
great chance to get involved if you have
like AV expertise. Would love to get
some pointers. Also like, I know some
stuff. I've been clipping the podcast
for a little bit. So if you'd like to
learn like the basic things that I know
and want to get involved in making the
podcast reach out, I could always use
help. If you want to listen to more
podcasts, come help me make them.
Dave? Yeah. If you have listed
the podcast after nine that
you're planning to do, I'd like to get
that because I want to get started with
just doing basic text conversion on
this. That assumes that these are
the priorities, is that correct? These
are the ones that we want to get in
front of people. I don't know
what the priority is there, Dave, but I
will say, like, there's definitely value
to having a transcript. I actually
looked at Pod Dean who is our podcast
platform the other day and they will
transcribe our podcast for us actually
at if you really want to know what the
value of transcription is, just the
value to just put it into text. Now, I
don't know if that comes with periods or
punctuation or I don't know what that
output looks like, but there's
definitely value to having a transcript
there. I'm not sure that these are
necessarily the priority, but it's just
going through the back catalog, it's
helping me catch up. So I just kind of
started where I wanted to start at the
beginning. Why not start at the
beginning, right? I don't know. What I
love about these podcasts is they're
short. They're like from four to maybe
15 or ten minutes long.
And the first time that a speaker
speaks, they introduction themselves and
there have been some probable clippings
and rearrangements which are very
subtle, that help that listenable
piece be like coherent.
It's like an extended thought, even one
that's distributed across multiple
speakers. So like you hit play,
listen to it and then you can think and
reflect because sometimes when it's 2
hours on a paper, it feels like it's
like a rail car coming through. It's
like every single idea and thing. And
people say that they pause the live
streams and there's so much and then
also as the priorities.
That's something we can figure out and
discuss. But won't it be amazing when
the live stream is the
front car of that train, piercing into
the future, hashtag doing it live? And
then there's transcripts for all the
live streams and that can be on one hand
connected to the ontology a transcript
of the live stream itself could exist.
There could be some clipping and some
transcripts for the podcast. So as we
develop our informational biology,
all of these kinds of connections and
tasks are in play. It's just a question
of how late can you stay up, which I've
wondered about for a long time. Dave
needs no sleep. The other cool thing
about the podcast is that it's slide
free. So where when you're on the
YouTube watching the live stream, often
it's associated with some visual image
and sometimes there will be like a
description of the image in the podcast,
but it's nothing that you need to pull.
Over and look at, which is sometimes if
you're trying to watch the YouTube
videos on a long drive, it's like that
might not be safe, but the podcasts are
definitely commute friendly because you
don't have to see anything. You can just
listen. So that's another it just
offloads the visual input as well. Good
for the treadmill, stuff like that.
Great point. Okay, on to
eight. So some updates
on our I'll
just call it social media. We have our
Twitter with 1359
followers. We have about, I think we
cross 300 members in the discord.
Over 770 subscribers on YouTube
and some several hundreds of
people reached in Facebook
and anyone who is interested in
automating social media, that would be
an excellent affordance Bleu. Yeah,
definitely. I was just you took the
words right out of my mouth. And
Facebook is very new, so we have like
just 40 likes on our Facebook page. So
if you're listening to this and you use
Facebook regularly for whatever, I mean,
it will ping you to remind you about
podcasts and sometimes live streams.
Sometimes I say because like I said, we
need an automated so that's your
expertise and you want to always be
reminded about the live streams. Get in
touch. Yes. Just to be able to preload
a buffer here in
the front car of the train, it's
sometimes hard to clean up the pieces.
So if you're feeling like that's
something that's interesting to you,
then there's many opportunities to have
engagements on different platforms and
just feel free to just engage
in the comments and in the threads.
However it makes sense.
Great. Enough with social media.
Okay, onto nine.
So now we're heading more towards the
tools. Part of this discussion,
primarily the work of Jacob Smithel has
Beren just excellent on Active
blockfronts, which is a package that
we're developing in order to facilitate
cognitive agent modeling. And if you
look up Active blockfronts on GitHub
you'll find the open source repository.
What we've done with Active blockfronts
is implement active inference entities,
the kind that you will see graphically
described in papers or the kind that
have been implemented in Python via
PMDP. And we built upon
PY MDP, as well as a complex systems
modeling framework called Cadcat. And by
integrating the active kernel
of the entity action exteroception loop
with the complex systems modeling
framework, we hope to have engineering
grade approaches towards modeling
complex cognitive ecosystems. So if you
are interested in Python or Julia or
other aspects that are computational
related to active inference and you like
complexity and complex adaptive systems
and everything else that you might see
on this slide, active Lock Force
Instance is an open source project. So
go ahead and fork it,
make your contributions and come get in
touch with us if you'd like to be a
little bit more in the loop and really
looking forward to seeing how this
project develops in the coming years in
tools. Also, we've been having some
awesome discussions around robotics and
embodied cognitive entities. So we
have been characterizing kind of like a
literature review on different cognitive
agent modeling frameworks. Active
Coherence Lab is often proposed as a
unified cognitive entity model.
And so we've been just curating many
other cognitive agent modeling
frameworks from the past and present and
then assessing them in terms of their
language, what cognitive features they
implement, whether they deal with
embodiment, what is their mathematical
underpinnings, and so on. And meanwhile
characterizing some of those cognitive
features and elements like anticipation,
memory, counterfactuals, abductive
reasoning, different kinds of cognitive
features or motifs, and then trying to
understand how do these different
cognitive model frameworks line up on
the rubric of wanting to have
expressivity across all of these
different cognitive features and to
integrate them. And that's a little bit
more on the symbolic cognitive.
We've also been thinking a little bit
about the embodied, whether the embodied
and spatial and bodily or the embodied
and robotics. So here is
a screenshot from the
work of JF. Claudia, who's been an
awesome participant in this past
quarter, and some active robots
that are Karl and Andy. I think people
can probably guess what their last names
are and there
isn't too much more to add here other
than check out this woefully under
acknowledged channel and work. And if
you're interested in any of these areas
like related to cognitive modeling and
robotics and embodied cognitive systems,
those are the kinds of things that will
be awesome to scaffold in the lab.
Okay, and to our
final of the eleven projects active
Metamodelling so ActInf Lab
metamodelling aka Alma. So there's and
A, and an L, and there's an M and
there's an A, and I think that was
Jessica's suggestion because Alma has
nice connotations as well. This project
is using meta modeling tools like Coda
to provide the capacity for lab scale
generative model modeling updates and
reconfiguring. So the ability for the
lab to reflect and to modify itself and
its niche in order to design the kind
of participatory niche that facilitates
successful policy selection by lab
members. Like what does the lab need to
provide the individual as the action
state of the lab, sense state of the
individual in terms of the communication
such that that participant is chill
but also making the right decisions that
are productive. And we're using
primarily Coda. That's why the font is
bigger here. But we're also implementing
the active entity ontology for science
that we discussed on the research slide
and active block prints just two slides
ago as a more formal way to get at
some of these meta modeling. And this is
a figure from our 2020 paper,
that first early paper on systems
engineering and active inference and
remote teams, where we also looked at
the informational niche, the shared
informational niche of the team. This is
their shared folder, their shared code,
a document, their formal documents,
their drive, the chat threads. That's
the shared epistemic niche where actions
to modify the niche by one participant
can then be like stigmaji modifying
the environment so that themselves later
or other participants then or in the
future take different action selection
as mediated by the way that that sensory
state updates their generative models.
And then we have narrative. And so we've
been very interested for a long time in
rhetorical and narrative approaches to
cognition. And so now we're just
beginning to see how some of these
approaches can come into play in the
context active coherence lab and in the
lab. So that's like the meta on
active lab. And this is also an awesome
project set of affordance if you like
Coda, if you liked Douglas Hofstadter's,
Gerdle Escherbock, if you like act infer
Serve. All of these would be great
diagnostic cues that perhaps you would
like ActInf lab metamodelly.
Yes, Steven. Yeah, thanks for sharing.
I was wondering how this also might even
be able to tie in in the future to micro
phenomenological kind of modeling, that
kind of approach. So we've got the meta,
the narrative, the story,
and hopefully maybe some sort of
microphone biological approaches as
well. But I think we dot two walk, but
we'll get there. So thanks. When you
said microphone logical, I thought, oh,
like the experiences of children. Yeah.
Cool. So that is it for the project
updates. They're all ongoing.
Let's just kind of go over some next
steps at the lab scale.
Several areas that were especially
looking for assistance or contributions
on would be on the legal side.
For example, potentially connecting with
a firm that would be interested in
providing pro bono assistance who has
experience with education, nonprofits,
intellectual property tech, etc.
And also helping our lab navigate a
course towards financial sustainability,
whether through grants or other
mechanisms, but just finding a way that
we can reward and stabilize the
contributions of participants. And then
at the project scale, any and
all participants who want to be in the
strange loop, in the strange attractor
want to be on the path towards
contributing active inference lab. Lab
as they also grow and develop as an
active inference and as a person. So if
any of these projects or some other
opportunity that you see and want to
take the initiative on any of these
reflect affordances for you. So
hopefully if you're listening this far
in a minute and 6 hours in or wherever
it's clipped out in a podcast, then just
recognize that these are all reflecting
the past contributions of participants
like yourself. And this is just an
opening. It's only the first quarter of
2022. We're just beginning and
so there's so much in the field and in
the lab to be done that there will
be something to do that's meaningful and
chill and aligned with your preferences
and expectations and availability. Just
belief it okay.
So that takes us close to the end and a
little modification of our common ending
slide. Where do we
go from here? What are people still
curious about learning and applying and
what are we going to do differently
maybe in the next quarter?
Yes. Bleu. So I think I already put it
out there at the beginning, but I'm
really like interested in not talking
about things anymore, spending less time
talking about things and more time
actually doing things. So that's what
I'm going to do differently in the next
quarter and that's me on a personal
scale has nothing to do really with the
lab, but I just want to just work now.
I just want to put my head in the books
and get to it. Awesome. Yeah.
Sometimes it
helps to get caught up through
conversation and just being in the
synchronous meetings, but 1 hour per
week is not how we build
a course or not how we go through a
textbook. And so that is a very
important balance to keep in mind.
Esteves or Dave, any other thoughts?
Yes or no? There's a lot
of good work going on. I'd say just keep
doing it and talk about
talk about what's working well, what
needs to be improved with the
bottlenecks are mentioned. Some
bottlenecks sometimes
maybe some of the fun projects that
could be pushed back in favor of some of
the more difficult things that actually
will end up being leveraged heavily.
The ontology.
It may not be fun to slog through this
stuff, but it's going to really pay off
and get some transitive closure
aspects of it.
Awesome. For those who are studying or
curious about active inference but feel
kind of like on their own, whether no
one else in their local niche or network
or lab or university or organization is
working, active inference lab, that's
like one of the most powerful things is
just knowing. Like if you have an idea
that you're not even going to pursue,
but just somebody should do this or it
would be cool if this existed, having a
space where you can add that pebble and
maybe down the road or maybe sooner than
you expect, somebody else seeing that
pebble is stimulated to act. And so
that's what can happen when we have
shared ways of working and that's just
what we're beginning to see. Stephen
yeah, sort of bouncing off that as well.
I keep thinking about stages of
readiness, which I'm
normally working with community
participants who are marginalized, but
I've had that myself feeling a bit
marginalized feeling, am I ready? And it
was like a little jump, but it can be a
chasm trying to get to that stage and
I think that can be for a lot of people
you don't quite know on different
things, whether you're near that
threshold or not. And you're often a lot
closer to being ready and you maybe just
need someone to give you a kick up the
bum and say, just go for it.
But having said that, that's when you
appreciate the quality of getting
some things under your belt on the way
to the line. So I think, like Bleu
Sajid, it's time to act. And for me
personally, yes, the stage of readiness
I'm at is very different to where I was
a year ago, for sure, both in
my knowledge when I look back to where I
was, but also in my heart. And that's
not an insignificant piece of the
equation. So, thanks. Awesome.
I'll just wait one more minute if anyone
who's watching live has any questions
that they would like to see addressed,
but totally agree, it's a multi
year journey. I mean, we're all on a
lifelong journey of some sort, but
hopefully even active inference lab
journey is multi year. And so being
able to connect our policy selection,
our behavior decisions in the next
microsocade of the eyes, the next place
your eye is going to look, the next
action you're going to take in terms of
opening up. A hyperlink or reaching for
a book or a pencil, but being able to
connect those very rapid actions with
a bigger picture and with a longer
temporal time scale and acting amidst
uncertainty. That's what active
coherence is about one aspect of it.
And so if anything that you've heard
resonates just hopefully see this
roundtable presentation as like an
invitation less than a stand
and deliver because there's so much
openness in the area and in the lab and
it maybe can feel like one is starting
late. But that's just human knowledge
development. It's a treadmill that's
been going and through coming together
in the lab we can actually leverage each
other's contributions and catch up on
Fields that have thousands of hours of
reading and hopefully get somewhere cool
together. So,
Dave, Bleu, Esteves and Yvonne and Alex
from earlier and all the other lab
participants, big thanks for this
amazing quarter and it's
been a fast one and on
to the next one. Okay,
bye. Thanks all.
Have fun.