Hello, cohort one. It's meeting 18.
We're in our second discussion on
chapter seven. Let's go to the questions
and see what we can explore today or
see where else to go and or look
towards chapter eight. But there's any
number of ways we can do it. So go
first, just on chapter seven.
Does anyone want to turn to
any of these questions, add another
question, add another reflection or
a thought that arose in the last week?
One question that I had was,
are there any ways or suites
for, for example, taking in an
analytical expression and then providing
equivalent phrasings that might
have other advantages?
Ali you mean by translating it into
natural language or.
Like what we saw in equation 2.5 and
2.6, like, to take in an
expression and then output
isomorphic or I guess not isomorphic,
but equivalent expressions, expressions
that have the exact same value as
calculated.
And when we look through the derivation,
sometimes it's possible to trace the
trail. But to know which representations
of perhaps even the same functional
or same term,
it seems quite relevant.
Actually. There's an AI assistant
for deriving formal proofs for
mathematical theorems, but I haven't
used it myself, but I'm not sure if
that's what you mean. I'll look at the
name of that and just 1 second, I'll
post. Maybe.
There'S a way to reformulate
these specific terms from, like, a
Bayesian mechanics formalism,
like posterior predictive, predicted
entropy. That looks like something that
Dalton probably described as well.
Question is whether you can just
interchange it.
Yeah. Does working with the particular
partition enable
equations to be operated with more
composably?
Because we can know that there are
certain operations that are
always, sometimes never going to be
valid. I'm just
kind of asking. I don't even know if
that's the right way to have it. Um,
so last time, we talked primarily
about the mouse
in the maze, and we are going through
the way that the chapter is layering
on features
of the model. So first we saw
the mouse just go for it,
and now we're going to be where
it gets the queue.
And this comes to our earlier points
about the resolution of the Explore
exploit tradeoff.
I'm going to add a question. Anyone can
give a thought while I'm adding it.
What are posterior predictive entropy
and expected ambiguity?
They're part of the decomposition of
epistemic value posterior.
Let me just make sure to say the
posterior predictive entropy is
the expected surprise or the entropy
of the distribution of observations
conditioned on a policy. So we're in
expected free energy world. We're
talking about evaluating policies
with respect to now, putting aside
pragmatic value. We're talking about
decompositions of how the informational
or the epistemic value of a
policy is evaluated. So there's two
terms here. First,
how dispersed is your distribution
of outcomes for that policy?
One can imagine that, all things being
equal, you would want to select policies
that have a tighter distribution of
outcomes.
Here we have an expectation.
Interestingly, this is italics e,
but it's not a fancy e.
Do people think there's a difference
that matters or do they think that's a
slight error?
I think that should be a typo. Yeah,
I'm going to add it to erata e
is TALIX
should be fancy e.
It's the expectation over
our hidden state estimates condition on
a policy and it's the expectation of
the expected ambiguity. So entropy
of the A matrix,
functionally how outcomes depend on
states. So this is saying I want to be
I want to be more is
it the case that it says, I want to be
more certain about observations and
how they map to policy and
I want to have a tighter A matrix?
Eric.
So, nice question. Why is there an
expectation on the right and not on the
left? I was also going to ask this isn't
entropy already the expectation of
surprise?
Just another point of I'm
sorry. So another
point of clarification for myself that
want to make sure this is right is the
O tilde is observations.
And what we're looking at here is a
functional Q.
So that's
a distribution of observations
that will get over policy and that's
what's being adjusted in the free
energy. So we're going to explore the
distributions Q and the O Tilde's
are going to be past observations.
We're not looking forward there. We're
looking past because those are actual
observations. They're not predicted
through the hidden states s.
So straighten that out.
Are we sure that O are only past
observations? I believe that past
observations are accounted for with
respect to how they influence the
prior.
But does O tilde also include future
observations? Well, if so,
then it has to be an expectation over
something, mustn't it?
But this is conditioned upon a given
policy. Then this
is the time series of observations
expected under that policy.
Is the left term the
Q expected distribution of
observations conditioned on policy.
Jacob.
I was just going to say that I think
I've seen this in other parts of the
book as well, and I think they use the h
and then just the expectation notation
for entropy kind of interchangeably.
Okay, if they do, but then isn't this
like a double expectation?
This is the expectation of surprise on
the queue, but this is the expectation
of the expectation of surprise.
That'S.
Yeah, that I don't
know.
Eric okay,
but the left term just Ali,
please.
Well, shouldn't that first line,
I mean,
shouldn't both of them be
at the argument of the expectation
according to equation 7.4?
Because in equation 7.4 we have the
negative Epistemic value,
but it's somehow different from this
equation. Yeah, that's.
Okay. So in 7.4 we see
a restatement of
expected free energy. Equation two,
six.
Let's leave pragmatic value to the side
for now.
Here we see fancy E-Q-S tilde
pi. So this is looking like this
probably could. Or should we
also see Hposhpos
minus H-Q-O
pi?
Okay, so let's take the negative of the
first line. The negative of the first
line. You can kind of just flip
the terms. It's the expected ambiguity.
Now minus the posterior predictive
entropy.
Then an expectation is being taken over.
That.
Sorry, my bad. I thought the square
bracket was encompassing the whole
expectation term. Sorry.
No, you're right, actually. Well,
there's a lot of layers of it,
actually. It's right as it's written.
Okay, wait. I always color my brackets
when I'm trying to do this. Okay. The
outermost bracket there actually may be
a bracket. I don't even know. Let's try
to figure it out. The outer bracket
starts here on the left, and then it
closes. Okay. Pragmatic value. If we
take that as a standalone if
we take that as standalone,
is anyone else seeing a bracket sort of
scenario? If we look at the brackets as
a whole, this first bracket closes this,
right? No, I don't think so. The first
bracket closes at the end of the S tilde
parentheses bracket. Yeah, that's why I
was confused, too. I agree. I was
thinking, should we evaluate the
brackets locally? But yes, they are.
Okay, good.
So it's exactly the negative of equation
7.8. Left side here is the
negative of the
first term.
Let's just say it in terms of picking
good policies. We want policies
are better, with more clarity about
observation outcomes. That's the first
term. And a tighter a matrix.
That's the second term.
Okay. Middle line.
This is a KL divergence between
the product two products of
distributions. Both of them
are dealing with O in
the first and S in the second. The Q
distribution in the second part is the
same for both.
So maybe there's some interactions in
how distributions of different kinds
multiply, but it
may be fair to interpret this as the
POS is
the A matrix and
the Q O. Pi is
how observations are shaped by
policy.
Or another way to say it might be POS is
outcome expectations conditioned upon
hidden states of the world, whereas this
is outcome distributions conditioned on
what we do. To me, that just looks
like base law there because
you've got at
least in the left side
a little bit, because you've got
conditioned on S and then S conditioned
on pi. So you're just basically
saying you're trying to figure out what
O is from pi through this intermediary S
delta.
Another angle would be where is this
zero? Well, this is zero when
these two are identical.
When the
epistemic value of a policy is low,
when the resulting O distribution
is being unconditioned by the policy
that we choose. Whereas for
policies that change how we think about
the A matrix, those policies
have higher informational value.
Because POS is kind of like a policy
agnostic mapping,
but we're like drilling down to kind of
subvariance partitions of
informational value. These are different
ways to look at what makes a
policy have epistemic value.
The first one line was coming down to
clarity around the tightness of outcome
distributions. The second
one is related to how policy
deviates our understanding of the A
matrix.
Now let's turn to here's another.
Italic e. Not a fancy e. Thank you,
Ollie, for this link. I've heard of this
one, the Cock proof assistant, but I've
never seen it used or anything.
Yeah, this looks pretty interesting.
I wonder if anyone has done that kind of
formal work on proving certain parts
of FEP. And then a more
distal question would
be if we have formal ontology
representations, for example with Sumo
or otherwise, could we
make proofs around the ontology and
the Sumo suggested upper merged
ontology? We explored some of those
things but didn't go super, super far.
It was just take
somebody who knows that area. Okay,
the bottom term bottom line an
expectation over Q. But now our Q
is on outcomes not focusing
on the hidden states.
Then it's an expectation about outcomes
of a KL divergence
between this
is about hidden states. This KL
divergence is zero when
outcomes are not
when in addition to policy, outcomes
don't change how we think about hidden
states. So when outcomes
influence how we think about hidden
states, this is going to be higher.
And what
does on the right? This is a triangle,
meaning defined as so QS
pi, O is defined as
and this looks like a Bayes theorem
situation.
Like kind of that chaining that Eric
just mentioned.
Like you have P of O conditioned on S
and then you have S conditioned on pi.
So then those kind of like it's
like a way to get from O through S to
pi. Whereas this one on the bottom is
just like going directly about O
conditioned on pi.
Which interestingly is I don't know if
this is like in one of these or in some
subsets of them. One can think
about that kind of structural model like
the minimum hidden Markov model, not
even in its full framing, but just like
what are the three pillars of the hidden
Markov model? Observations, hidden
states, policy, yes,
transitions and so on. And so what
is gained by going through an
intermediary hidden state?
There's going to be situations where the
observable contains 100% of the
information for policy. Or we
can imagine situations where the ability
to choose policies based upon S,
which is where the actual POMDP is
intervening is better.
Whereas in a fully observable Markov
decision process, you don't
have S, you're just making
decisions on O.
Kind of just revisiting the point I
raised earlier about what Otilda is. It
seems to me that this only works when
you have the observations O tilde.
So I don't see how it could
be anything like looking toward the
future. Because if you actually want to
carry out that expectation,
you want to work out what Q is or use
it, you have to compute it and you have
to have the observations to compute it.
And the S tilde you have to have
actually pipe through and
use them. So help me understand if I'm
wrong with that.
Okay, here would be one thought.
The A matrix captures how hidden states
mapped observations. So whether we have
a really tight A matrix or whether we
have a super dispersed A matrix,
using the Gaussian form for the A matrix
ensures that we can always say what the
most likely observation is for
a given hidden state. If we had a
bimodal A matrix, then there
are some issues. But if we use a
Gaussian form,
which is the Laplacian approximation,
it's more tractable, it's monotonic,
it's more optimizable. So for a given S
sequences of S, we can
always derive the expected observations.
Again, those might have a lot of
uncertainty around them, but we can
always make a sequence of O's
corresponding to any sequence of S.
But this equation makes no expectation
at all. Nothing says nothing about what
the form of the distribution is that you
use, whether it's parametric or not
parametric or whatever. It's just saying
you have a distribution Q.
So this is how we evaluate it?
Yes. Is this true for all families of
distributions q Ali,
what do you think about that or
anything? Actually, it's interesting
that in the step by step active
inference paper, this epistemic value is
defined somewhat differently.
I'm not sure if they're exactly
equivalent with each other or there are
some minor differences between them,
but they've just defined the epistemic
value only in terms of the expectation
over the surprisals.
The. Difference between the Q and P
surprisals. So we don't have this
kind of expression as conditioned on the
S tilde here.
I don't know if they're the same or not.
I don't know how to copy the image into
this chat, but chat of the gatherer or
just put it in here. Put it in the
question. Okay. Yeah,
well, one thought is policy
is not an open ended policy
in its specification is always going to
be of a finite horizon. So if we're
considering policies of length two so
interestingly, this is a policy
that includes leading up to the
Presence. If this is the
presence, I think we had one meme that
was like what if my T minus one was T or
something like that. But this is a
policy that is influencing
and this is just the variant of 43.
But let's just say that we're
considering policy of true future
looking length two,
then we're exploring different ways in
which S is going to unfold with respect
to basically B one and B two.
Not using that in the SuperScript way to
mean like two parallel B's, but just
like there's our current, there's our
estimate now and then there's
the way that we have, let's just say
four affordances. So then there's four B
ones, and then now
there's going to be four options for S.
And then each of those four we could
apply the second affordance again. So
there's 16 policies to evaluate. Each
one is defined by either taking, like,
B one, B three, B one, B one, B four, B
four, and for each of those S,
in the next two time steps, we can emit
observations.
Ali and then rohan.
Sorry, my hand. Just stay away.
Sorry. Rohan.
Hello. Yes, greetings. Yeah.
So coming back to what the posterior
distribution is, right?
Isn't it just that we assume there's a
posterior distribution of states, like
an ideal posterior distribution that we
want to that
the free energy principle moves the
current empirical distribution towards?
Isn't that? I thought that's what we
were doing from context in chapter one.
Yes,
go ahead. Yeah,
sorry, cohort one, I think that's what
we discussed. Right? So it's essentially
trying to maintain some form of
homeostasis. So whatever policies you
have performed should eventually bring
the system to that ideal homeostatic
perspective. Right. So why couldn't we
just assume, like, a normal
distribution? So even if it is fat
tailed, for example, the empirical
distribution is like the P distribution
in this formula has
a heavy left tail, you can essentially
bring it back towards that by
essentially modifying the policy. That
was the context of this. Right?
Yes, broadly, you're right. So when we
look at the full free energy, expected
free energy formalization so here's
equation 7.4 or equation 2.6,
you're absolutely right that there's a
pragmatic value that's based around
reducing divergence between observations
and preferences. But in equation one
that we've been focusing on and trying
to really unpack, because, again, also
like O tilde is used in pragmatic value.
We're only talking here about.
But that would make sense, right?
Because you're conditioning
on your actions, having some effect
on the state, on your own state and your
state in the world or maybe some state
in the world. So you have to
continuously monitor until it comes down
to the expected observation. That's what
the generative model would spit out.
Right, so it makes perfect sense and
it's completely coherent in that way,
right? Yes. I hope
and expect and prefer that to be true.
What you're describing about bringing
the homeostatic variable closer to
preferences expectations, that is
pragmatic. Yeah.
It wouldn't be surprising that Hotel
does that in that P distribution as well
as what I'm saying. No, it would need it
to be there. You're right, it is needed
to be there because these are surprises
and entropies and so on about
observations. And then this part
is really digging into decompositions
of epistemic value. So there
might be two policies that are both
expected to bring your temperature down
or whatever, but they have different
epistemic values.
Does it matter if it just brings your
temperature down? It would look the
same. Essentially, it would have the
same effect. So why does it matter?
Why did we have to have this kind of
yeah, so there would be multiple
policies that would bring it down,
bring the temperature down. If the
preference is to bring the temperature
down, it does not matter which policy is
chosen. Right. So that's essentially
what I think it's being said here.
Okay, so as long as you minimize. The
expected here's two investment
opportunities from $100 150 plus or
minus one or 150 plus or -200 which one
do you want. That'S not
what you were discussing it is the
payoff space is very different. No,
it's not the same thing. They are the
payoff space expected ambiguity in the
$200 plus or minus $200 is very
different and your mutual information
will be very different because the
payoff space is different. Exactly. You
are essentially taking yeah, but if
something is going to bring down
temperature plus or minus two, plus or
minus four, it's not a huge difference
as long as it brings it down. Right. So
that's essentially what I'm getting at,
why does it matter? Okay, so in this
modeling, the body's expected
temperature is like the expected return
on investment and the variance around
the expected temperature is like the
variance around the investments.
Right, but they wouldn't be the same
policy is what I'm saying. Sorry. They
wouldn't be the same payoff space in the
second case. So if something generates
$100 but has a low probability
of going bust so that there's a high
variance, that's not the same payoff as
something that produces the same $100,
but that has a lower variance, the
payoff spaces are different and that
will be captured in that callback
diversions that you have there. It would
prefer the one with the lower that's
right, because the payoffs yeah,
but I think the discussion was around if
multiple things lead to the same
epistemic value and they have the same
payoff, why does it matter which one is
taken? Right. There's that last piece.
There may be multiple policies with the
same pragmatic value and
then epistemic value is the difference
maker that favors policies that have
more clarity about observation outcomes.
Right. So pragmatic value
would say.
That'S not necessarily true. Let's say
that. Okay. When the payoff space is
completely unknown that the steps that
you're taking at T equals one, two,
three will bring down the will
have the same pragmatic value. But one
of these actions will lead to some very
bad consequences at step T equals 15
because you're giving up something else.
It will be like paying space because.
If we're talking about temperature,
we're in the space of temperature.
Okay, all right, so let's
just bring it back to the finance. The
space is dollars. That's the dollars
space.
Yeah. Okay, so we could use dollar as
numerator. So we benchmarked the
dollars. How many dollars we're making
profit. So I have two investments,
both of them generate $100, but one of
them requires me to borrow $100 in order
to generate $100. The other one would
generate $100 over, say, 50 times steps.
This would be quicker. The second one
where you borrow $100. So it would be
quicker because you're borrowing $100.
But there's an interest rate that you
have to pay out.
So you will have to generate much more
than $100 in order for this to be viable
because you have an interest rate to pay
off. Okay, try to follow up here.
Policies are defined in terms of
sequences of affordances to take. So the
affordance here that you're highlighting
is borrowing or not?
Yes, but there are actions that
would be like if you have a very high
fever, in order to bring down that high
fever, sometimes it makes sense to
borrow that $100. Whatever metaphorical
variation of that borrowing that you
have to bring it down to something more
manageable. Right. So it depends on how
close you are to some sort of threshold
where it's intolerable.
I mean, putting it in more mundane terms
that, hey, I have a bad toothache.
It doesn't make sense for me to borrow
$100 to fix my tooth. I could just brush
my teeth and hope that it goes away,
but I have a knife in my back, I need to
get to the hospital. It makes sense to
pay $100 because you're going to die if
you don't. Okay, let me try to try to
see this is how I'm seeing that is when
we're near homeostasis,
then we take actions that basically keep
us there, and we try not to add risk to
the situation. Whereas near the limits
of our homeostatic tolerance, we may
engage in high risk behavior because
there's already a non negligible. Risk
because the payoff space is much larger.
Yeah, the payoff space, the positive
payoff from your own life.
No, it's not. The space is no. So when
you have the knife in your back, the
payoff from borrowing $100 will save
your life. When you have a toothache,
borrowing $100 might cause more risk
that you go bankrupt. Right. But you
will still survive. If you have a
toothache, you're just short $100,
which you could have used elsewhere.
There is no way you can use that $100 if
you're dead. Yeah, there's a much higher
payoff borrowing at that point than it
is with the toothache example. It
depends on where you take these actions.
I got you. I'm seeing the space are the
axes. So here we have dollars and life.
And so you're saying that yeah, but. It
is a multidimensional, this one. So if
you think about it as, let's say yeah,
so let's make it more concrete. Right?
So if you have a drone and
you have a trade off between battery
life and staying in the air,
and let's say one of your propellers
goes out, just redistributing power to
the other motors so that you stay in the
air even though it reduces your hover
time. Makes more sense because you could
land versus trying
to fly around and then crash eventually
because you lost one motor.
But whereas let's say that the
other option would be let's just go
faster to a certain destination when it
doesn't really make sense to do so,
you're just reducing your battery life
to get to a destination faster. But if
something happens on the wave which
causes you to lose your motor, then you
don't have enough battery in order to
enough battery power to distribute to
the automotive so that you can hover and
come down safely. Does that make sense?
Eric. I wonder
if we could table this particular
discussion. It seems to be going and get
back to some of the other questions in
the chapter. We had a question
that was pending from last week that I
think is kind of critical to the
understanding of the chapter, and I
wonder if we could just want to make
sure we have time for it, because we're
running out of time here. Yeah,
and that's the question about what
the relative role is of how
it actually operates, that the rat
learns some information prior to
deciding which of the two branches of
the maze to take. And the way they seem
to frame the chapter is that, well,
they set it up so that the rat has
its preference for epistemic value.
Because of epistemic value of learning
which of the two branches to take is a
bigger term. It'll first go to the
bottom branch and learn
which of the two top branches has the
payoff. Then once that's resolved, it
knows that, then it decides which of the
top branches to go to and it gets its
reward. So my understanding of that is
that and this is my claim in this
question, is that the
rat has a preference to resolve
epistemic uncertainty regardless
of whether it's useful or not. So if you
added more uncertain questions like,
what color is my apple today?
But there's no apple to be gotten,
it'll still want to resolve that
question and any other questions because
those are uncertainties. So epistemic
value, it'll collect that epistemic
value, and then finally it gets around
to collecting its reward.
That's in contrast to a model where the
purpose of resolving epistemic
uncertainty is to gain the reward,
which requires look ahead.
So in other words, the planner or the
policy would be, I try to learn
what's needed to collect the reward. I
do that, and that's posted as epistemic
value with a purpose,
then the order of operation is,
okay, I figure out what I need to know,
I learn what I need to know, then I go
and do the exploitation. So that's what
I would expect that this kind of framing
would give us, but I don't see that
that's what you're actually giving us.
All right, here's how I
see that. The example that we would want
to see would have a
bunch of uncertainty resolving
this one picks a number between one and
ten and tells you what it is. This one's
a number between one and a million. So
it's an incredible information resolving
button.
Then the question is can the relevant
sources of information be sought after?
I think the examples is prepared
in several ways. For example, the rat
already knows the semantics that
this is related to here that's
been just the structure of the model is
already preparing that any
uncertainty reduction about this
basically it's already encoded in the
model that this bottom queue is
information about this.
So this is kind of like saying and
this relates earlier, not only are those
implicit structurally encoded aspects
of knowledge but also there's
parameterization questions like we
discussed if it has a
dire urgency for food to
the earlier questions about like the
urgency of the imperative it may just go
for it. And so I'd rather have a 50 50
shot now than a 98% in two timesteps.
So it depends on how it's parameterized
but even more deeply it depends on the
construction of the model, what kinds of
relationships are implicitly and
explicitly being linked and
it's like a deep level of modeling to
understand what would be like a more
neutral way to frame
this question. And then it's like well,
how many layers back do you want to
pull? Like you could have a preplay
where a rat has an association matrix,
there's three information sources and
it's allowed to freely explore without
any shock or food and determine which
one of these information sources has
like a causal relationship to these
edges. And then there's a learnt queue
that now we're in game time and now it's
going to rely on its past learning about
which information resource is relevant
for the Pragmatic value and
then it's I mean there's just how many
layers back does one need to pull before
the rabbit is not in the hat? I think is
going to be a serious question because
even toy demonstrations have been seen
as slam dunk and they're not.
Well since they're bringing up Palm DPS
here palmdps are really good for
planning but they don't have this rat do
any planning. It seems like they're
really not aspiring very strongly
to build a smart rat here and they're
not achieving it either.
Yeah, it's true because here
the first movement again presuming that
the parameterization is such that
epistemic value is salient.
The first move is dominated by epistemic
value and they say well, now that that
value has been tapped, now it can step
into pursuing Pragmatic value with even
increased confidence.
But it's not considering the
set of time horizon two policies that
is not being explicitly encoded or.
That means that. Even implicit yeah,
these are transition matrices. These are
just the four options depending on where
you are. You can stay,
you can go down.
Yeah. Does section. 73 address
planning.
And if it doesn't, why do we need g?
Why can't we just use a one step
variational free energy approximation?
It's saying, what's the most likely
thing for me to do right now?
Is a question about now in the past.
Well, I think the answer to the question
is exactly as you said it before, which
is they baked in this particular
hardwired rat, for which in this case,
the best thing to do is to first
explore, learn, and then exploit.
So they designed it to do only this by
rote to do the right thing, as opposed
to the rat actually doing any
look ahead or any intelligence to do the
right thing. Yeah, it's structurally
implicitly hardwired,
and then it's fine tuned because again,
there's structures where it wouldn't do
this and there's tunings where it
wouldn't do this, but in
the tens place and in the decimal point.
This example exists in a very limited
manifold of models and parameterizations
where one step optimal policies emulate
two step planning. Like, I just happen
to love sacrificing pawns and taking
castles, so I'm willing to sacrifice a
pawn so that later I can do a castle.
But of course, you can't walk around
with the belief that you love
sacrificing pawns.
Yeah, I actually wondered why
there wasn't enumeration of policies in
the planning section.
Okay,
learning hyperpriers hidden states on
hidden states, seeing hidden
states as outcomes of other hidden
states so that they can be learned or
fixed.
Little bit of technical details on multi
parameter minimization theta being just
the vector of parameters for the
generative model and deer Schlee
distributions, which I think could
be gotten into, but that's kind of
distribution specific creatures
select the most appropriate data to
improve their generative models.
I think there's more that we can dig
into and explore on similar wavelengths
like risk plus ambiguity, but then now
there's an information gain. I thought
we just had risk plus ambiguity.
Then we didn't really yeah,
people point to structure learning, but
don't they always as a way to get around
these questions.
But then it's the structure of the
structure learner, and then people end
up with these turing machines that don't
plan.
People hope that Bayesian model
reduction will be attractable and
provide heuristics for structure
learning. But I haven't
seen any empirical examples that come to
mind where Bayesian model reduction was
used to identify actionable lower
dimensional useful models.
But we know that structure learning on
the state space of hierarchical models
is going to be essential active
inference or beyond, because people
thought that the explosions, the
computational complexity class of just
branching time, active inference or
anything within a model. This is going
to be like exploding upon that by
several exponents.
And we have these fundamental questions
about the continuous time
interpolations.
Why are there continuous interpolations
in chapter seven when
it's the discrete time chapter? Okay,
next time we come to chapter eight, I
think this will be quite interesting.
We're going to talk about dynamical
systems, motor control, lock of Ultera.
We'll have some justified continuous
lines, LaPlace assumption,
Lorenz stream number 32, stochastic
chaos and Markov blankets.
Hybrid models with discrete continuous
fusion and some advances
in continuous time modeling.
Thanks everybody. See you soon.
Thanks everyone.