Hey everyone. It is October 21,
2022. We're in cohort one of the
textbook group. It's meeting 21 and
we're having our first discussion on
chapter nine.
Chapter nine is model based Data
analysis. Let's look at what the section
the headers are.
There's a short introduction,
a discussion of metabasian methods,
which is going to be very interesting
and in some ways is even like an entry
point to thinking about entity
modeling in active inference. And so
that'll be kind of fun. We'll return to
variational LaPlace resonating
with our just completed discussion on
chapter four. And LaPlace then
section 9.49.5 are going to help
us see where data in terms
of like gigabytes of actual good
day, Yakup, actual data from
measurements and so on, where these come
into play with models. So how does one
go from a furnished trainable model
to a parameterized specified model,
which actually is explaining variance
in real world data sets? And then
there's some examples of GMs and some
models of false inference.
Well, I added only one
general question from a
lighter reading. I think
as we all here move through this,
we can generate a lot of other key
points and questions.
Ultimately, the models described in this
book are only useful if they can answer
scientific questions.
We could rehearse the introduction
again, but let's just go into it. So,
metabasian methods. This chapter deals
with the utility of active inference
formulations in analyzing data from
behavioral experiments so one could
imagine all kinds of bodily,
verbal, digital behavior.
This goes beyond proof of principle
simulations we've seen in previous
chapters and instead exploits active
inference in answering scientific
questions.
Broadly speaking, there's two related
reasons for fitting a computational
model to observe behavior. The first is
to estimate parameters of interest.
The second is to compare alternative
hypotheses.
So to parameterize from data
is one opportunity,
that is to make some model
of brain function and then understand
within one person or one group or two
groups how you
can consider those parameterizations to
be phenotypes.
Phenotype is something of a
biological organism or system that's
measurable. So like femur length is a
phenotype, but also a phenotype doesn't
have to just be something that's
measurable on the body with a ruler.
Like phenotype might be distance ran
in the first 50 seconds after the hawk
flies through the sky on a cloudy day.
And so then that is still a measurement
that could be inferred or discussed or
made. And we're talking about
computational phenotyping because the
data and observations for sure are like
a basal phenotype, like the button being
clicked was measurable
phenot to show. But also we
could talk about the precision variables
in our cognitive model as being
phenotypic.
And also model comparison can
be used. So whereas this first modality
of parameterization is like the data set
is fixed, we collected 240 fMRI data
sets. Now we're going to parameterize.
So we're going to give some plasticity
to our model and we're going to fit
parameters so that our model is like the
best resembling it can to these 240 fMRI
data sets we have. In the second
modality, we're treating in some ways
the models as fixed and
then evaluating to what extent different
models stack up.
And that can be used at a very fine
scale to look for different models that
fit better to a given data set.
But also, this is where we can talk
about actual biological
explanations and predictions. So, like
to give an example from yes, please,
Ali. First.
Sorry, a related question to this
whole discussion is I
think it was in Section 9.2, it says
this goes beyond the proof of principle
simulations we have seen in previous
chapters and instead exploits active
inference in answering scientific
questions. I didn't quite understand
this statement here because in the
previous chapters, we were
also engaged with modeling
the real scientific phenomena. Right.
So what does proof of principle
simulation here exactly mean and
how does it differ from the
approach from answering
real scientific questions?
Yeah, good question. Does anyone want to
give a thought? Or I can give a thought,
too.
I mean, literally, just these following
that the first and second reasons to use
active inference in this way.
Instead of just modeling something and
saying, oh, that looks like what
we intended to model, or oh, gosh, it
looks really predictive, or whatever
getting more rigorous with it to
specifically enumerate parameters
for a particular model.
And then compare multiple models. Like
trying to say which one is
more precise. That's a different thing
than what was being done in the book
previously. Like, we're just building up
the model and seeing how it kind of
worked before, and now we're like
talking about putting it into a
machinery that's going to select on
models like which one's best fit
or whatever.
Well said. Yeah, I totally agree.
Although arguably, like the chapter five
Neurobiology, the tables of examples
were answering scientific questions,
but those generative models were not
largely presented, but in the papers,
one could have gone in. But yes, the
previous generative models were like,
built from the ground up and then like,
oh, look at this intersting behavior.
Now we're building the machinery to take
in real data and
fit that. And then there's the two
uses of parameterization or the two
uses of data fitting to find the best
parameters for a given data set and
model, and also to compare models,
model comparison. All right,
now we get to the very excellent figure
9.1. So 9.1
is the metabasian inference.
What does anyone see in this figure?
Ali.
Well, as pointed out in the text, the
inner box somehow represents
the generative model of the phenomena
we're observing, but the outer dashed
box is somehow our generative
model as the observers. So the term
metabasian, I think used here
to denote this kind of change of
perspective to a
higher level of viewpoint to
add another layer of hierarchy to
the already hierarchical generative
models we had before.
Yeah, great. Well said.
We could have had an arbitrarily nested.
Well, just to make a simple point, this
is the discrete time formulation POMDP,
Figure 4.3. And that can be nested in an
arbitrary way and composed and
metabasian is like putting the
wrapping paper on the gift because this
outermost layer is us.
Brock.
Um, so the
last time this came up was in
the context. I think it was in the other
cohort. But we were talking about the
provenance of the model, the impetus for
it being as a tool for
diagnosis of patients for nontypical
sort of neuron.
I guess I'm curious maybe if
there's a simple way to understand it
from that perspective. But I also have
another question, I guess, which is if
this is us modeling,
it seems like it would be like
infinitely recursive because every time
you add another layer, then there's
another layer that's not being modeled
of how we're actually modeling it. And
therefore we would have to but then if
we accounted for that, then there
would be another outer. I don't know if
that's just infinite regression towards
the hidden state, one or the other or
that's nonsense. Yeah,
it's not. I think let's
talk about the setting of the
clinical neuroimaging.
So the inner model is
going to be the cognitive behavioral
model of the patient just speaking of
the participant, the recipient of action
as the patient. They're selecting green
or blue coins or whatever. They're doing
some behavioral paradigm isolating or
choice or decision making. We're
modeling their action,
perception, attention and so on.
Whether we formalize it or not,
the experimenter's behavior is
influencing the parameterization of
the patients. Like, we are choosing
populations and sampling
patients here
is like the parameterization of the
experiment.
We'll have 20 people. They'll come in
for two sessions. We're going to do
eleven of this.
And here's, like the data coming out of
so this O here is the observation that
the patient sees and their inference on
what they're seeing.
Experimental stimuli are actually an
action from the experimenter. We're
pushing the O to their screen. So this O
tilde is their O sequence.
We're getting data from
the experiment.
We could choose to be
ignorant or implicit about our
parameterization or
maybe even this is a nested model.
We made a governance decision in the lab
to decide who gets to decide this.
And the constraints were the cost and
the availability nested
modeling of the outer loop.
And what about infinite recursion? And I
think one silver lining or saving grace
or whatever, or just strength of the
Bayesian graph or active inference
framework is we
know we can always dive in
and build from a node or we can just
treat the edges of our base graph as
like a Markov blanket with the unknown.
So we could say we made a simple model
of decision making here and then
this could be a multi agent simulation
and each of those could have another
nested model and then we could.
Then maybe it's irrelevant or maybe we
want to know anyways. But what good
will it I don't know or it doesn't fit.
We do want to know. Yeah.
Let's just say that the Pragmatic value
for us is high statistical
power and sensitivity for diagnosis of a
neuro condition. So we
want the inner loop to be
in the point. We don't want to be
spending money beyond diminishing
returns on our experiment. We want to
actually diagnose and help the people in
this limited situation.
Then one could do model comparison with
just I'm ignoring all of this. I'm just
going to parameterize I'm going to call
it like I see it. Then one could have
another. But if one were to engage in a
research program where we collected one
data set, then yeah, let's just
call like we see it. But now we have the
opportunity to design a second cohort of
fMRI experiments. Should we do two
people for 100 sessions or 100 people
for two sessions? Who should those
hundred people be? So at that point,
having a policy selection outer
loop enabling seems pretty
relevant. Now, we could
make that simple. Maybe we always pick
30 participants. Maybe it's we either do
a small experiment with three or we do a
big one with 30. It's just simpler.
Those are the two pathways we have. Or
maybe it's et cetera.
But then you could do model comparison
and evaluation on those
increasingly complex outer loop models.
None of that would be influencing the
structure of the cognitive model of the
patient. So for all you block,
for instance, heads in the chat, one
could imagine that there's human
fMRI cognitive model. This is a
versionable cognitive model,
open source. And then different
lab groups could have open
or closed models with open or closed
data around their decision making about
how they're using a core model.
This is also just on a more qualitative
point. And then I'll leave. This is
where we can start to talk about moving
beyond implicit biases. Not just like
purging implicit biases or anything like
that. It's just like we're doing
investigation and exploration. We're
externalizing and exteriorizing our
priors and we're working such that
the relevant features that are in the
box are all externalized
in terms of the scientific apparatuses
parameterization and that's at
least something where we can move
towards. And someone could say, well,
you haven't made your hyper hyper hyper
priors explicit, but isn't that a better
conversation to have than you didn't say
why you chose this many people for the
experiment. It could be like you didn't
state the meta governance of how
you came to the decision to do 30
participants.
It makes it really a lot easier to think
about comparing and counting, showing
that you accounted for your methods.
And it's the same you're doing the exact
same experiment, right? Might be
able to move the needle a little bit on
some of the reproduced earth replication
crisis, things like in that vein.
Yeah, great point,
Ollie.
Adding to what well, just mentioned.
As a side note, I think approaching
this kind of I mean,
this approach to model based or
better, the model based data analysis
takes the infinitism
stance as an implicit,
somehow philosophical stance.
Because if we don't think in terms
of infinitism, I don't think we were
able to model adequately
these kind of metabasian reasoning
because we'll get at some point to,
as Brock said, just infinite regressive
reasons. So at least in my opinion,
it somehow implicitly takes
the infinitism stance here as
proposed by Peter Klein, at least
in large part because, as infinitism
claims, will need somehow
the subjectively and objectively
available reasons to model
or to construct justify true belief.
In other words, the reason must be non
repeatingly and infinitely available to
us in order for us to be able to
construct that true belief. So I'm
not quite sure about it, but it looks
very similar to infinitism stance.
Yeah. Interesting introduction.
Wasn't familiar with this area.
Like approximate Bayesian computation,
bounded rationality, the composability
of Bayes graphs. These are we
get to eat our slice of cake and
recognize that there's the rest of the
cake and the table and the world outside
of the restaurant and so on. Like we can
just say the GM that we made was the
thermometer and a temperature value.
And someone can say, but what about
humidity? And it's like there's a
composability, but we're
not within the Positivist or the
falsificationist. Like, well, my model
of temperature and thermometer is
positive evidence that that's all that's
happening. Or it's the best model we
have. We're just waiting for it to be
disproven. We can have like a Bayesian
portfolio of models and all
of them can be understood as maps,
as composable maps.
Could this lead to Bayes optimal
experimental design of research programs
like statistical power? The famous
statistics quotation is like something
about an autopsy. Like the statistician
is not going to diagnose it. They come
in and they tell you what went wrong
with the autopsy. But that's not
fundamental to statistics. That's
actually just a little bit of like a
joke about the practice of research,
which is like the biostatistician. Just
speaking from my own research
experience, they're called in for
assistance on a complex, already
collected data set. And so it's like,
well, we had three mice in March and
then we had six mice in April. How do
we balance this versus the Upfront
conversation to help design a high
statistical power experiment? And so,
like statistics Upfront,
it's going to increase the
reproducibility and alignability of
experiments. It is a sanity check,
if not a formal verification that the
experiment is going to tell you
something.
And it allows for replicating
experiments, selecting experiments based
upon their statistical power.
Okay, following sections, unpack an
example of generic inference that may be
used for metabasian inference, the
variational LaPlace with hierarchical
models. Then there's going to be a
simple recipe that's related to one of
the other questions up here. Okay.
Variational LaPlace may be used for more
generic likelihood functions than those
encountered earlier, which were defined
as Gaussian. So previously, the family
of functions that we are doing
variational inference with was
Gaussians. Now,
we can generalize beyond using only
Gaussian distributions by
saying, whatever it is, we're going to
do a Laplacian approximation. So even if
it's like something very strange, and as
mentioned in cohort two discussion
just an hour ago, LaPlace approximation
has two parameters the mode, the center
of the bell, and just the width of the
parabola. It's guaranteed to capture
some of the variance of the
distribution. For distributions with a
central tendency, gaussian or otherwise,
it can do well for distributions that
are like multimodal. It does not do well
because it gets tricked to finding the
mode, which may only capture, like, a
minority of the overall bulk. And again,
the SPM textbook lays out side by side
LaPlace variational bays, non parametric
sampling approaches.
From those Laplacian approximations,
we're going to do variational inference.
So the real distribution
might be unfactorizable or not. We don't
know what family of functions it even
is. But we know that the
LaPlace approximation that we make on
those distributions for sure will be
amenable to variational inference.
And because of the quadratic nature, we
can do gradient ascent. So just like the
ball going to the bottom of the bowl,
this is just an inverted parabola. So
it's just gradient ascent on the
mountain. All right, parametric
empirical baseage
of a matrix to represent the
experimental layout is heavily
used in SPM. This is
looking a lot like a regression.
This is actually a little bit of a short
section 9.4.
This part here comparing the evidence
for a model where the second element is
allowed to deviate from zero or the
precise belief at zero, that is actually
very much again like regression testing.
If you're testing for the effect of a
given factor on height
that is related to the p value you get
for height is related to the
model that includes height and the model
that doesn't include height, and then
their sum of squares is compared within
the appropriate statistical test,
family t test, z, test, F score,
all giving you a p value. So this is
very much like statistics on
regressions.
One thing, maybe there's a deeper
reading where this is clearer, but one
way to talk about parametric empirical
Bayes, is that, well, first off,
it's parametric. You're dealing with
parameters, so sometimes that's not too
helpful. But the empirical part means,
like, the way we're going to get our D
matrix, our prior, is from
the data. So let's
just say that we're measuring height in
the classroom. We might be able to use
chapter six to specify and furnish the
model. But then as soon as
we make that first and then we might set
our prior, we say, well let's have a
super loose prior. Let's say that it
could be like uniform across all but
of course who knows what the maximum
height is. Maybe it's not a human
classroom. So we can't just specify a
uniform distribution across every
finite value. And so a way to kind of
break that. A priori
challenge where you want your prior
to be loose enough to accommodate the
full range of the possible data but also
sharp enough so that you're not just
like starting on like it's just an
absurdly uninformative prior. All priors
are informative. Even a uniform prior is
still informative. The thing that
matters is the strength, the weakness of
the prior and the family of the prior.
So what you could do instead would be
you could measure ten heights or even
one and then use the mean and the
variance of that sample empirically to
set your prior. So set just the mean of
the prior on height as the mean that you
got from ten and then you could just
over disperse the variance.
So if there's somebody who's outside of
that bound now it's like
you can be more confident. So this is
widely used to take an empirical data
set and then use the data set's
empirical values and summary statistics
to parameterize the generative model.
And then the ball goes from there and
also the expectation maximization
algorithm where you have a given data
set and you update the parameters in the
generative model and then you generate
data compatible with that model and
continue. That is very close to PEB.
Okay, 9.5 instructions
for model based analysis. So let's
copy these out because
the question was like how is this figure
9.2? I guess section 9.5 and
it's summarized in 9.2.
Here's the six steps.
Oh, someone added a great okay,
so this is a little bit of a review of
the textbook but we're starting with
data collection. Maybe the data already
have been collected. So we're putting
aside the situation where we're doing
the meta modeling on ourself and then
doing experimental design and then
collecting the data. We're just going to
take it from the data are collected.
A POMDP again discrete time
in this case is structurally prepared
according to the recipe in chapter six.
Pumdps would
we say are equivalent to specifying a
likelihood function or they embody or
they entail a likelihood function. What
is the arrow between two and three?
Does merely constructing a POMDP in this
format uniquely identify a likelihood
function or
what work has to happen right here?
Just a thought we can learn. Go ahead.
I don't think these arrows necessarily
mean that this particular
component of the modeling process
necessarily translates perfectly
to the other stage. I think they're more
likely to show the dependencies
among each steps. So in the case
of the third stage or the likelihood,
the construction of the likelihood
function, obviously it depends on what
our PMDP model functions.
So I'm not sure if we can
if they were 100% isomorphic,
I guess they would be redundant. Right?
So yeah, I think those arrows show
dependencies rather than translating
into each other.
Thanks. I think
I broadly agree.
And there might also be some other ways
to draw it, like the prior beliefs.
Is this theta.
I think this is using the figure nine
one ontology this
theta is big theta.
These are the experimenters parameters.
The model is
the cognitive model of the entity.
Italic u tilde is the observed data.
So here's the observed data getting
passed with
the POMDP and associated likelihood
function.
We can the likelihood, okay, the PMDP
describes variables in their
relationships. The likelihood function
allows us to create p, which is the
distribution of observed behavior u
tilde conditioned upon experimental
parameters, theta observations, which
are in this case the ones that are
provided the stimuli, experimental
stimuli and the model.
Then the parametric empirical Bayes
comes in when we actually get the data,
it comes in in six. But we're getting
there, we're on the path. When we have
the data flowing from the experiment,
we can then do the model inversion.
Rather than describing the
distribution of behavior that would
be generated by theta o m,
we're going to invert it so we can talk
about the distribution of parameters.
Experimental parameters conditioned upon
MoU Bayesian
equation allows us to have a
proportionality between what we really
want to know this top
line and a
I don't know if I can call it a joint
distribution, but these two multiplied
distributions, which is the probability
of the experimental parameters given the
model and separating out
the probability of U conditioned on
all the rest. So this is leveraging the
sparsity of the inverted model to
facilitate a form that is amenable
to linear regression type equations.
This is like y equals MX plus B.
It's not, but it is. This is
like the same structure y
MX plus b,
but then these bars and their associated
variances which come from LaPlace,
this is the p value and the effect size.
So for this third modality, the effect
size is zero and the variance is such
and such. And then for this one we could
say the p value or the base factor for
this factor mattering,
it's high. The evidence for this
mattering is extremely high.
So this is like if this were a bar chart
and if we were in frequent statistics
land and it were like ten plus
or minus one, then we have a z score of
ten. We're ten standard deviations away
from zero. So the p value of the
effect size being greater than zero is
whatever it is for a p value of a z
score of ten, very low.
Again, this is like where the real data
collection is going to be happening
and interfacing. So now,
here's their description. Collect
behavioral data. Formulate the POMDP.
It takes parameters as input outputs a
fully specified but not yet solved POMDP
specify likely likelihood function,
specify prior beliefs.
Often these will be centered on zero
with precisions reflecting plausible
ranges. That's interesting.
Note solve
for posterior and model evidence.
Newton is probably a reference there to
some gradient derivative
based gradient method. I'm not exactly
sure. Group level Analysis treating
the estimated parameters for each
individual as if they were generated by
a second level model. This is exactly
structurally ANOVA the
group level analysis of variance.
Like we had people throw the ball.
There was type one and type two a person
and then whether type two is there an
effective type. You make two models.
One of them is a model without type.
One of them is a model with two
categories of type. Then those two
models can be compared in
terms in the frequentist world, in terms
of their hierarchical likelihood.
In the Bayesian world, however, a
limitation of the hierarchical
likelihood ratio test is that the models
must be strictly structurally nested.
They have to reflect direct,
simplifications or elaborations of each
other. In contrast,
Bayesian modeling allows us to use the
Bayes factor, which can compare models
that don't need to be strictly
nested.
So you could test
very structurally different models
against each other. It's kind of like
information as a common currency.
In the Bayesian approach,
I considered variable one, two and
three. And then someone else could
compare variable four, five, six. And
you can be like, well, how, how much
good are those two different models
against what we care about in terms of
informational criterion? AIC BIC the
Bayes factor. Whereas if somebody
said, well, I did model with one, two,
three and the p value was zero one and I
did this with four, five, six and the p
value is zero one, those can't be
directly compared because the p value is
against like a local null hypothesis and
there's just like, probably other
issues. So it's one huge advantage of
the Bayesian. We're 50
years past the rubicon or 400 or
whatever on Bayes. But Bayesian
formulations allow for the generative
recognition model, the tail of two
densities. So you can specify something
that generates and recognizes data.
That's one advantage. Another advantage
is that you have access to all the
statistical tools of frequent statistics
and you can also access
this like informational statistics.
I'm sure there's way more rabbit holes
there. But like, broadly speaking,
instead of taking experimental
observations in frequentism and then
mapping them onto a t distribution only
and then saying well now, because of the
p value, let me publish this paper.
In the Bayes world, there are richer
comparisons and more nuanced
penalization functions of how many
parameters versus how much variance
explained.
Just for example, if anyone thought
Bayesians were too confident or if it
wasn't the leading modern
strategy for dealing with uncertainty.
This design matrix for a linear model,
the SPM design matrices are like very
interesting looking.
So the textbook has many, many of
these matrices. They're encoded on a
gray scale. So like,
what's happening here? Here are images
through time. Each row is an image,
could be an image in a time series,
could be like different static images.
Here, third column is time. So this is
time .0,123,456.
And then here's condition one and two.
First condition, whether one is white
and black, it doesn't matter. Here
condition, let's just say white is one.
Condition one was in effect,
condition two is not, and vice versa.
But you could have overlapping
conditions. So it's like a graphical
representation. And this
is also common to see this kind of like
waterfall. Here's patient
12345. Here's the
three conditions in a randomized order
for the 12345 patients.
Here's their global blood flow, here's
some other measurements, et cetera.
But it turns out with so this summarizes
the total design of the experiment.
And it turns out like you
just smash
it like a matrix multiplication,
like the design matrix multiplied by
the observations. And one
can imagine, like if the observations
have no relationship with the design
matrix, there's a null hypothesis that
you could get from random matrix theory.
If the experimental design strongly
influences the observations,
there's some informational. Outcome 96
in our final few minutes, examples of
generative models, two experiments
outlined in nine five. The details are
not important. Oh,
but it's two isocating models.
This is a continuous time left.
Tracking a moving target right
was a categorical eye tracking,
as we've mentioned and discussed,
doing some kind of a webcam eye
tracking cognitive model would be
massive.
It's also very sensitive
technology, I think, because it would
be able to determine somebody's
cognitive model and their attention in
different ways.
But it would be interesting.
I was going to say they actually already
do that specifically for championship,
like first person shooter games to try
to catch people using Aim bots.
So they try to predict where your eyes
are going to be based on the data in the
game. And if you are shooting
or you're acquiring the target faster
than your eyes could have acquired
the target, then, wow.
Yeah, interesting. Maybe even some
of the behaviors already are
out there. So it's not like this is
maybe the data already exists. It's like
that moving target one. Yeah.
And interpreting this as like
an Occupancy density,
but then having a cognitive model where
that is like an uncertainty reduction or
a salience or relevance observation,
which is implicitly what these usages
are. Disney trailers,
models of false inference, julius
Caesar, we had the Obama, now we have
the Caesar.
Discussion of phase optimality and
disorders,
different pathological and neurodiverse
conditions, addiction, impulsivity,
compulsivity, delusions,
hallucinations, interpersonal
personality disorders, ocular motor
syndromes, pharmacotherapy prefrontal
syndromes, visual neglect, disorders of
interoceptive inference. So if
there's a parameters set that works,
well, there's going to be various
parameter sets that exhibit different
outcomes. And then, as per Foucault,
society is the definer of madness and
all of that. And the DSM asterisk
but broadly speaking, these are models
of pathology.
We outlined an approach that uses
theoretical models described in previous
chapters to pose questions to empirical
data. This lets us use active inference
as a non invasive tool to probe the
computational processes that individuals
use to make decisions. So funny.
Well, the model is not invasive,
okay? I don't think any model is
invasive. Ultimately, the six
steps in Figure 9.1 but
it's not. That's an error.
It's Figure 9.26.
Steps in Figure 9.2 provide a generic
method for designing experiments to non
invasively, interrogate, implicit
generative models people or other
systems use to drive behavior.
That's an opportunity to answer
questions about the function of the
nervous system in health and indices.
All right, thank you, fellows. Looking
forward to the conversation next week as
well. Thank you.
Peace.