DANIEL FRIEDMAN: Hello and welcome everyone. It's January
3, 2023. We're in active
bookstream. Number 1.4
on governing continuous transformation.
Off to you, Bleu.
BLEU KNIGHT: Great. So we are the Active Inference
Institute and this discussion is over.
Governing continuous transformation.
This is a recorded and an archived
Livestream. So please provide us with
feedback so we can improve upon our
work. We are a participatory online
institute that is communicating,
learning, and practicing applied active
inference. You can reach us on social
media at all of these different links
here. All backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome to discuss and contribute to
this work. And we will be following good
video etiquette for live streams. If you
would like to get in touch to
participate in a future Zero Livestream
or one of the upcoming discussions,
please reach out to us via social media
or email. And again,
our links. So today we are
going to cover section 1.4.
So we're just going to go kind of over
where we are in the book, the keywords,
and then the different subjects and
things that we pulled out of this
section. So just to start off, we will
maybe just introduce ourselves. I am
Bleu. I am a longtime institute
participant and an independent
researcher in New Mexico. And I'll pass it to Daniel.
Daniel: I'm Daniel, I'm a
researcher and institute participant. I'll pass to Tyler.
TYLER SULLBERG: I'm Tyler. I'm a DAO
researcher and practitioner in
California. Is there
any introductory comments or do you guys
just want to jump right into it? Jump
in. Okay, here we go. So this is the
section that covers the free energy
principle. And that's also the title of
this chapter. And I think the first
keyword on our keyword. So we pulled
out a lot of these keywords. I mean, we
pulled them out, they weren't
highlighted by Bijan or selected by him
at all. And this is just kind of the
topics that we thought that would be
better to dive deeper into for a more
thorough understanding of the material
presented in this chapter. And this is
not like a final word. This is maybe
just an introductory perspective and our
take on what's maybe happening in this
chapter, not a review. So we're
definitely open to correction and
updating our model of this model.
All right, so abstract. Tyler, do you
want to read this first? Action force
us. Sure. So the Free Energy principle,
the first order principle of police
action empowering self communication.
FTP commands the generative process
active coherence lab dedicated to
minimizing the information theoretical
mathematical difference between top down
predictions and action generated bottom
up upstream line in pursuit of
minimizing error, surprise and entropy.
The power of forsonian active inference
is fundamentally fourfold. It's a pure
belief setting in dynamic and non
stationary environments, the active
inference agent carries out ensemble
exploration to account for uncertainty
by making inferences in Bay's optimal
fashion. The reward signal, so
characteristic of reinforcement learning
is removed. And finally, active
inference sets the collaborative human
machine AI potential so integral
to the multi intelligence firm as the
mathematical expression of beliefs form
of probabilities, provides the very
common denominator to line humans with
machines. Wow.
Big is true. Okay. And the author
goes on to say there are only two
distinctions that matter what is known
and unknown and what is in our control
and what is not. There are four states
active action, internal firm resources,
sensory perception and external unknown
and hidden behind the Markov blanket
according to Free Energy Governance free
Energy Principle powered AI, which he
uses here, this capital A and lower keys
I to mean active inference. So free
energy principle powered active
inference is the future site of
organizational becoming. So we can
unpack that, I guess, starting with this
claim, which was in the abstract itself.
So maybe we don't need to reread
it. Or was it exactly stated there maybe
not fourfold,
the four claims. We'll just start off
this first one. The power of personian
active is fundamentally fourfold. It is
a pure belief based setting in dynamics
and non stationary environments. So what
does that mean? Like, what is Friston
active inference? So maybe we want to
just step back a little bit and talk
about the FEP. And the definition
or explanation that Bijan picked out for
this chapter is the free energy
principle stems from the idea that
living systems can be distinguished from
other self organizing systems because
they active. Avoid deleterious phase
transitions by bounding the entropy of
their sensory and physical states under
the FEP. To be alive simply means to
revisit a bounded set of states with a
high probability. And that's from this
2019 Badcock et al. Paper.
And this image is from Kirkhoff et al.
2018. And I always like this
when I think about life and self
organizing systems.
This picture just really speaks to what
it is to kind of be self organizing,
a hierarchical scale.
And this like revisiting a bounded set
of states with a high probability kind
of speaks to the non equilibrium steady
state density that is like a constraint
of life. We kind of have to live within
a certain temperature range, a certain
glucose range, and all life has like an
optimal range of states that they stay
in. But if your fever gets too high,
like if the temperature goes too high or
too low, like you will dissipate. So you
revisit this bounded set of states with
a high probability and that's kind of
your non equilibrium steady state
density. Do you guys have any comments
here on the FTP and self organizing?
Maybe? I'll give one comment.
This is a via positive. It's describing
what the FEP is. But we could look back
to those four claims and think about
what this is not the Via negativa.
So rather than being believe based in
dynamic settings and adaptive autonomous
agents, it might be a framework oriented
around some sort of static or perennial
understanding of the world. The second
point. Rather than being centered around
epistemic exploration and the value of
reducing uncertainty and gaining
information, hearing new perspectives,
it could be oriented around pragmatic or
utility value, which ties very closely
to the third point, which is that a
framework, contrary to active inference,
might center a reward function that maps
different states of the agent or the
organization or the world to some sort
of reward function which is the heart of
reward learning. And then the fourth
point also kind of ties in that rather
than thinking about ecosystem of shared
intelligence intermediated by composable
frameworks like active inference, we
might be looking for like the one
framework to simply rule them all and
therefore not think about the human
machine or HumanHuman relationships as
collaborative and emergent but rather
just be looking for the one computer.
We're just going to turn it on. The
business is going to run.
Awesome. So getting into active
inference a little bit more, so we're
kind of unpacking here. We're going to
unpack slowly these, like, four claims.
And so Prestonian,
active inference or FEP powered active.
So in active inference, there are four
states. This is what Bijan claims active
action, internal, firm resources,
sensory perception and external, which
is unknown and hidden behind the markup
blanket. And Bijan quotes Friston
here and says, in active inference, the
agent makes choices based on its belief
about state of the world and not based
on the value of the states. And so that
speaks to what Daniel was maybe just
mentioning about reinforcement learning,
and we'll start to unravel reinforcement
learning a little bit more, but where
reinforcement learning is really kind of
driven by that pragmatic value function,
active inference is driven by your
beliefs about the world. So not how much
value can you gain out of moving left or
moving right? But I fundamentally
believe that I should move right because
that's my policy that I operate
on.
All right. And where
these claims start to be unpacked in the
paper, Bijan says, one could argue
that nearly all physical sciences can be
reduced to a metrology in service of
confirming a variant of the principle of
least action. This is important because
it means that physics does not offer any
ground truth. It is just search for
measurements that endorse an
appropriately formulated prediction
based upon a variational principle. And
this quotes a Friston 2019 paper. I
don't know that paper off the top of my
head, but as funny as I said, Bijan
says, and then I started reading it,
I'm like, no, Karl said this sounds
very much like something that would come
out of a Karl paper. Okay. And so
what is this principle of least action?
We've talked about this a lot before in
many different livestreams, but I looked
it up just for what is like a really
easy, simple way that I could explain it
in a minute or less. And I found this
definition on scholar PDF that says
a true dynamical trajectory of the
system between an initial and final
conversation in a specified time is
found by imagining all possible
trajectories that the system could
conceivably take computing the action,
which is a functional of the trajectory.
And just as a reminder, a functional is
like a function of a function. So
computing the action a functional of the
trajectory for each of these
trajectories and selecting one that
makes the action locally stationary,
traditionally called least true
trajectories are those that have the
least action. And so this is like the
Laziness. The lazy society. Everybody
makes the lazy choice. Right? The true
trajectory is the one where you kind of
just stay put. Daniel, do you have a
comment here? Yes, although on the
previous slide, we looked at the
particular partition where action states
are the outgoing dependencies. And here
we see action again with principle of
least action action. But importantly,
to abide by a principle of least action
isn't simply to take the lowest energy
action or the least movement. It's more
akin to a conservation law. Like, the
total energy is conserved of potential
plus kinetic when the ball falls off the
platform. So that means that there's a
path of least action with the Bull
dropping. Now, that is not the path
of leased movement, but it's a path of
least action given an individual setup
because the total energy is conserved.
And so we're interested in paths of
least action over the particular
partitioned states, internal, external,
and blanket states. And so it's a little
bit like, not just
simply confusing, but least action can
include the selection of very energetic
or risky behaviors.
That's cool and just kind of, like,
maybe tie that to a real world example.
I think about the principle of least
action. I prefer my body temperature
to be, like, 75 degrees all the time.
Right? Do I live in the tropics? No,
because there's, like, a lot of things
about living on a tropical island that
are not optimal for me. So I live in New
Mexico because that's my optimal place.
But I wear a jacket in the winter, and
in the summertime, I wear less clothes
or drive around in my air conditioned
car. I live in my air conditioned house.
So even though I'm still expending
energy to maintain my physical
temperature, that is the path of least
action for me. I compensate
for the change in my equilibrium state
through my actions. Okay.
And we will talk
more about energy in a minute. So
unpacking hae jeong Parr of the claim.
The active agent carries out epistemic
exploration to account for uncertainty
by active coherence in Bay's optimal
fashion.
Okay, I know
what Bayes optimal is, or I think I know
what Bayes optimal is. But just to kind
of like, what is Bayes optimal fashion,
and how do you make coherence in
Bayesian optimal fashion? And it's cool
because in a quick Google search. I
always like to search these fundamental
things just to see kind of what pops up.
I think I know what Bay's optimal is.
And I pulled out this 2019 paper, like,
what is optimal in optimal inference?
And it's interesting because going
Hinton Bayes optimal. I mean, I think
about Bayes optimal as like minimizing
prediction error. Or it says here
classically optimal Bayesian inference
balances prior knowledge and encoding
observations to identify the model with
maximum posterior probability.
And so these authors actually take this
a step further. And I really enjoyed
their thought process here. So they
said completely, we might say that an
inference procedure is optimal if it
maximizes benefit per unit cost, in
which the benefit is some monotonically
increasing function of accuracy.
But they proposed a generalization of
this approach that kind of splits this
cost benefit curve into two components
where the first component describes the
benefit, perhaps the reward obtained as
a function of accuracy. But then the
second component, so that's the
minimizing prediction error that I was
speaking to earlier, right, in terms of
accuracy. And then the second component
describes accuracy as a function DA
Costa, which can include time, memory
and computational resources needed to
process information. And I think that
this is like a fundamental thing that I
might overlook. I might be able to get a
way more accuracy answer.
Say, for example, what is the number
pie? And I could just say like 3.14. I
could actually go through, I could say
like 3.14,159, like off the top of my
head that's like whatever number of
digits of pi that I have memorized to
some accurate point. But I could come to
a far more accuracy answer of that if I
sat there with a pencil and a piece of
paper for the entire rest of my life
doing long division. So I could come to
some infinite number of units past
the decimal point and I could go on and
on and on forever. But is it worth it?
Is it worth it in terms of memory effort
to calculate that increasing accuracy?
Or is 3.14 good enough? Right.
That is kind of the thing that the
functions that they're describing here,
like this benefit, this two dual
component, like, yes, we want accuracy,
but we also want it to be fast or want
it to be we want to get the maximum
benefit for the minimum resource
expenditure. So I like that they are
describing accuracy as a function of the
Costa, the effort that goes into it. Do
you guys have any comments here?
Okay, why am I going into this?
Okay, so Tyler and I got into this long
talk about energy. And we
got into I can't remember, I guess it's
not maybe in this claim, but it was
somewhere in the paper. Maybe I should
look and try to pull it up. But we
really got into discussing energy, like
what is free energy? What is like
kinetic and potential energy and
what is free energy like in FEP? And
we've gone to ActInf Livestream that
dive way deeper into this. And I think
it's live stream 17. That is the one I
pointed you to, Tyler. Alex Kiefer
does a great unpacking unraveling of
free energy in that way. But I think
it's important here to point out maybe,
Tyler, you can pull that quote out of
the paper while I'm talking about this,
but I think it's important to point out
that information theoretic entropy is
different than thermodynamic
entropy in information theory.
And there are many times in the paper
where the author specifically says,
like, we're talking about information
theoretic entropy. But then it seems
like that the other kind of entropy is
Hinton at. And so I kind of wanted to
just like, draw a line between
information theoretic entropy and the
other kind of entropy, like the second
law of thermodynamics entropy,
thermodynamic entropy. And these two are
distinct but not entirely unrelated. So
information theoretic entropy is defined
as like in if you have a function x or
some event x, the negative log of the
probability of x is equal to the
information. So here you can see like,
the probability versus the information
is this graph on the left. So where
there's a high probability of an event,
there's like, low information. There's a
high probability that I will take a
breath in the next 30 seconds. So me
taking a breath in the next 30 seconds
doesn't contain any information, but you
guys can predict that I will talk about
the FEP and free energy governance in
the next minute if I start talking about
my dead dog. There's like low
probability of that happening. And so
there's maybe a much higher level of
information, like, whoa, where did this
come from? This is way out of left
field. So there's more information in
like, an unexpected claim. And so
you can see like a probability
distinctions versus entropy. But that
relates like the Shannon entropy. Where
the entropy? If there's a
high probability, it's low entropy,
right? So I look at this in a coin flip.
So if we know that the coin is always
going to come out heads, there's not any
entropy in that. Like, say it's a two
sided head coin, so it's always going to
come out heads. There's no other option.
The coin always flips heads. But where
in a fair coin, it's 50 50, right? So at
the right end of the second graph, it's
a probability of 0.5.5, like half of
probability that it's heads and half of
a probability that it's tails. This has
the highest entropy because it's random.
Like we don't know what's going to come
out. And so that is what is meant here
by information theoretic entropy in
contrast to thermodynamic entropy,
where that is like what we think about
when we think about physics and the
Second law of thermodynamics entropy.
We think entropy in the universe is
always increasing. There's like a lot of
disorder, the disorder in the Universe,
like, if you clean your house and you go
away for 20 years and you come back and
your house is a mess, you're not going
to be surprised at all, right? But if
your house is a mess and you go away for
20 years and you come back and your
house is perfectly spotless, that would
be weird, right? That's like you're
scheduled for someone to come in and
clean it. But the disorder in the
universe is always increasing. And that
is what it's meant by entropy in terms
of the Second Law. And we also think
about this kind of entropy as energy.
This is where Tyler and I got into
talking about energy. But entropy is
the energy that is not available to do
work. Right. In a system,
there's like some amount of energy. I
consume so many calories in a day, and
this is like very simplified. But of
those calories, I say I consume 2000
calories in a day. I can use only like
1500 of them for work because some
energy is always lost in heat in the
conversion. In any energy conversion
process, like converting energy to work,
you will always lose some energy as
heat. And so that is kind of another way
to think about this, thermodynamic
entropy. Tyler, were you able to find
that quote where we talked about this,
or now? Yeah, the quote is fairly subtle
and that he goes right between
information theory and thermodynamic
theory kind of seamlessly, and he
doesn't make it clear that these are
like two very different things, that
there's a potential tenuous connection
between. So he says, FEP hence has no
purpose of its own. It powers the
process of active active inference lab
dedicated to minimizing the information
theoretical maximum difference between
the top down predictions and action
generated bottom up stimuli in pursuit
of minimizing errors of present entropy.
Variational free energy and
thermodynamic free energy are inversely
related. If variational free energy is
high, then thermodynamic entropy will be
high, and thermodynamic free energy,
the energy available for doing
productive work will be low. So I think
what he did there was a subtle he just
goes between informational and
thermodynamic free energy kind of
interchangeably, and they were like,
wait a minute, there's actually a
difference between these two concepts,
and the connection between them is
something that the community doesn't
have a great handle on. Ant this point.
Very cool. Daniel, do you have any
comments there on that?
It's a pretty complex and developing
area how the informational entropy is
related to the actual physics and
biology. It's kind of like the
connection between Friston free energy
and Gibbs free energy. How does reducing
divergences on informational spaces
translate to the amount of available
energy? And there are situations where
survival could be secured one way or the
other. There just isn't, at this point,
a general answer to how they're
connected.
So when Tyler asked me how they're
connected, what is the relationship? My
answer is Maxwell's Demon is the
connection really between thermodynamic
and informational free energy? And
there's actually, I think, a 2018 or
2019 paper that quantifies this
relationship between thermodynamic and
informational entropy at the quantum
level. So I don't know if that applies
to all scales, but it's at least cool
that and I don't remember the paper
offhand, but if you search it, maxwell
Semen quantum information, you'll find
it, and it's pretty recent. So it's neat
that people are thinking about concrete
and direct ways to transform and
translate information theoretic and
thermodynamic entropy. And so we just
kind of wanted to unpack that because in
that claim, it was like, whoa, there's a
lot of things happening here that it
might be more useful for the audience to
have a deeper understanding of what
is known and what is unknown. And how
deep does this rabbit hole really go?
So it gets pretty hairy.
Okay, cool. All right, so back to
reality, but back to things that we can
concretely talk about. So, the reward
signal, so characteristic of
reinforcement learning, is removed and
replaced with one sole purpose surprise
minimization. Effectively, the agent is
empowered to minimize surprise by way of
a generative model of the partially
observable world only perceiving itself
and the world via outcomes. And so just
for people who might not be familiar
with reinforcement learning hold on just
a second. Sorry.
Getting over a sickness sometimes. I
didn't want to cough up to the
microphone. All right, so in
reinforcement learning, there's, like,
a couple required components. So you
have a policy which maps the state of
the environment to an action, and
that's, like, for an agent, right? So
we're always talking about agent here.
So an agent has a policy. Like, if the
environment is in this state, I will
take this action, and policies can
change and update. And then there's a
reward signal, which is given at each
step. So we're talking about, like, a
time step type of thing. Second one, I
take this action. My reward is two
carats, right? So say my policy is to
turn right unless I see immediate danger
on my left. So I turn right, and I turn
right, and I get two carats. I turn
left, and I can't turn left because
there's a media danger over there. It's
against my policy, whatever. So the
reward signal is the number of carrots
that I received right there at that
first step. And then there's a value
function which actually tracks the
reward over time. And the objective
in reinforcement learning is not to
maximize the reward signal at each
instance, but it's to maximize the value
function over time. And so in a
circumstance where I turn right to get
two carats, but I could have gone
down and then right and gotten 50
carats. So maybe I should have gone down
and right. And so this is kind of how an
agent will learn in a reinforcement
learning environment to maximize the
value as opposed to just maximizing
incrementally the reward. So after every
action the agent takes, the environment
sends a single number. That's the
reward. The reward that the agent
receives depends on the agent's action
and the state. And so the agent's only
goal is to maximize the total reward,
which is the value function over the
long term. Any comments here?
All right, so precision tyler,
do you want to read the quote at the top
of this? Sure. So the Beijing brand has
optimized not its expectations. It also
has to optimize precision. This means
that one has to predict how much
precision is affordance to various
sources of sensory evidence relative to
prior beliefs. Thank you.
And so this is like a definition from
Wikipedia talking about like classifier
systems and precision and recall in a
classifier system, which is like a
predictive system, or it can be Bayesian
classification. So there are retrieved
items. So we're going to say of this
field of images, the ones in the circle
are cats. Right. So we're identifying
these circles, the data points within
the larger circle as all these things
that the classifier says, these are all
cats. The precision is of all of the
things that the classifier says are
cats, how many are actually cats? So
it's the true positives that are in
the system. And then the recall is like
how many total how many relevant items
are returned. So that's the precision
here that's referenced by Frustrated.
Do you want to read this one toothbrush,
Tyler? Sure. All right. So when dynamics
change, sailings should be prevented
from potentially increasing free energy.
In the context of corporate governance,
1 may think of pattern recognition as a
one form of salience. The more senior
and experienced board members are, the
more likely and they feel comfortable
with mental shortcuts such as pattern
recognition built through prior
experience.
When I search for salience, I just
randomly search for pictures of salience
to make this pretty red apple picture
appear here. But when I searched
salience and I looked at images, a lot
of them were like stakeholder salience.
And so I couldn't even start to try to
unpack this. Like it was some corporate
definition of salience and some
corporate model of salience that I don't
know if Bijan is referring here to more
indirectly, or Tyler, if you know
anything about the stakeholders salience
model, but maybe we could ask Bijan if
he is referencing that or if he's just
talking about salience the way that we
talk about it. As in things that we
attune our attention to because they're
relevant for the task at hand. Or like
things that stick out or things that are
memorable or relevant. Right, yeah, I
don't think there's like a corporate
governance, like, technical definition
force. It I think it's just like you
have limited attention. There are things
that the portal is more likely to focus
on and they have to constrain their
attention on limited information. Yeah,
but I was intrigued by the fact that
there is like a corporate salience
model. Like oh, it's beyond talking
about corporate salience. What's that?
Because it's just something that I've
never heard of before. Well, it's
something we've seen with many active
coherence ontology terms, that there's a
broad everyday qualitative sense,
like salience is something that you pay
attention to. And then there's also a
more technical, usually Bayesian sense
such as salience is actually referring
to the precision in terms of a variance
estimator that we place on incoming
sensory data. Whereas low attention
means that data points coming in are not
salient. They're not used to update the
model. High attention is coming
together with high attention to incoming
data that does update the prior
a lot into the posterior. And so which
patterns are salient is
itself learnt. And we can think about
that as the regime of attention with all
the strengths and weaknesses, the
expertise and heuristics bring along
with.
Yeah, and I think they go on
to say, I think gen impacts that more
in the book about salience and pattern
recognition.
Okay, so single and double loop
learning. Tyler, do you want to take
that? Single loop learning occurs when
errors are detected and corrected
without altering the governing values of
the master program. Double loop learning
occurs when Northern Dalton and error is
necessary to alter the governing values
of the master programs. Most governance
models are at best, single loop, rule
based learning systems that struggle to
activate double loop learning.
Thank you. And I found this little
loop, this loop diagram, which is like
actions and consequences. Actions and
consequences. And that's like the single
loop. But this double loop learning goes
into understanding governing variables.
And this is kind of like, I think about
some kind of meta analysis where you can
zoomed out more in the double loop
learning. Yeah, with our favorite
example of the temperature in the room,
if the single loop is just the knob that
we're controlling on the heater or the
air conditioning, the double loop would
be taking a step back and thinking,
well, could we also open or close a
window? And so if we only stay within
the single loop, maybe our heater or
cooler has limited capacity. And so
there's times where the environmental
challenges are going to take us outside
of the range of what can be learned or
accommodated with a single loop. And
it's those times, especially when
opening up into a double loop space or
like a hyper prior space is what is
actually required to get the generative
model operating in a way that's
survivable.
I would never open the window with the
heater on, but boy, I changed the
weather shipping on my back door this
year and it. Made such a difference. So
that's a more realistic like a governing
variable like you have a leaky house or
poor insulation or something like that.
All right, deliberate ignorance.
So that is choosing not to know.
So Bijan talks about this and says the
more senior and experienced board
members are the more likely that they
feel comfortable with mental shortcuts
such as pattern recognition built
through prior experience. That's what I
was going to say earlier about this.
Again, I thought it was this next slide
but when they talked about here pattern
recognition as one form of salient but
in this deliberate ignorance it says it
is a form of prior based heuristic or
too often simply deliberate ignorance.
However, in a discontinuously non repeat
game environment, pattern recognition
without maintaining sensitivity for
small but nonetheless transformative
variations put survival at risk.
Therefore we need a process and a
measure of errors that optimizes
survival. Hence action, centric free
energy, minimization powering, inactive
AI. And so I thought about this like
okay, we're talking about corporate
strategies. So in pattern recognition
that's super useful force something like
a game of chess. Chess has like
these are the pieces, these are the
rules. There's only so many ways that a
piece can move and yes, super
complicated. But over time a master
chess player can start to recognize
patterns in the game or like certain
sequences of moves that result in
success. And so if you know those
success, that's pattern recognition.
But in a non repeat game like where the
rules are always changing and the pieces
can move in a different way like imagine
now we're playing 4D chess where we
could go also like XY but we can also
move in the z direction, jump over
pieces and so forth. Like if you add an
extra dimension, those prior
patterns that you knew for XY chess
now doesn't happen, right? They don't
even apply or aren't even relevant here.
So failing to update your prior
pattern cognition is going to not lead
to successful strategies. Just to make
this a little bit more concept. A very
common example of this that I've
emergence is that sometimes when you're
doing business strategy and the business
is still running and you might have
customer service claims incoming while
you're doing this core business
strategy, generally you want to ignore
all these customer service claims
because that's just like noise and you
don't want to pay attention to it. It's
going to overwhelm you though
occasionally you'll sometimes hear some
very unusual customer experience claims
that kind of implies something much
bigger and much more serious is going
on. System will be within the
organization and you need to have this
like spidey sense and this is where
there's often used in business settings
like the Spidey sense of knowing like oh
wait, something bigger is going on. I
need to switch gears into being super
micro rather than being macro. So I
think it's a good example of when you
have to kind of switch your model of how
the organization is working really
dynamically and go from deliberate
ignorance to choosing what information
will be selling to you.
Conor okay, and then sophistication
which I thought this was relevant, I
can't remember the quote that said this
again. Bijan actually started to unpack
this in figure four. And he said we
alluded to. Sophistication back in
chapter one. And this also applies to
this like double loop learning.
Sophisticated inference is where you
have many tangential steps that
can unfold. And this also
applies to the principle of least
action, which we're talking about,
which is like a decision tree search.
Like if you're standing here at step
one, you can go which is like the top
level here. You can go to any of these
four points. You one u, two u, three,
you four. So if you're here at the very
beginning step and then each one of
these points have their own branch
choices that you can make. And then each
one of those choices have their own
choices. And so this is the
sophisticated inference which is
unpacked in this paper, sophisticated
inference. And then we've done on
different live streams here before.
Also, we didn't do this paper, but we
did deep effective inference.
I think that was maybe also 1713. I
can't remember, but a long time ago it
was like a 2020 early Livestream with
Dayan. Smith so in this sophisticated
model, it's unfolding temporarily
through time. And this applies to both
like the trajectory when we're talking
about least action trajectories and also
to double loop learning where you're
looking at like maybe governing
variables over time.
So he starts to unpack that here in this
chapter. Goes a little bit more into it
than in chapter one. All right,
so now we're on the fourth part of this
claim. We made it all the way to them.
Active inference should provide the
basis to set free the collaborative
human machine artificial intelligence
potential so integral to the multi
intelligence firm. And note those two
separate like AI abbreviations.
So Bijan makes a claim social Fields are
not as real time as electrically charged
and chemically powered, neural
responsiveness. But the underlying logic
and principles nonetheless determines
firm performance and survival. All
living self organizing systems, as is
true for organizations, strive to reduce
entropy in pursuit of minimizing
surprise. But organizations other than
living systems are too often trapped in
what anger is 1995 termed skilled
incompetence, meaning that organizations
are programmed to deal with error and
threat in ways that are
counterproductive to their own
intentions, not least because
organizations struggle with unlearning
and deliberately suppress subtlety.
Maybe refers back to that deliberate
ignorance that we talked about earlier.
Do you want to talk here, Tyler, about
organizational becoming? Yeah, sure. So
just on that last slide, I got a couple
of thoughts on that one part that was
interesting. About this was like
explicitly connecting free energy to the
firm, which I guess that's the whole
point of this book. But I think that's
actually quite a large claim to say that
firms also exhibit free energy. So I
just want to point that out. But then
also I think a really important aspect
of free Energy governance is the DAG
between stimuli and action and action
stimuli where that is a lot larger in an
organizational space rather than
something kind of like a neuron, for
example. And that makes, I think a lot
harder to operationalize and really
understand free energy in like a firm
context as well.
So the next slide that goes into
organizational becoming, this is a term
he doesn't really define explicitly
throughout the book, but he does mention
it quite a number of times, so I think
it's worth calling out. So he says
strategic renewal is as organizational
becoming categorical imperative of being
in the game. And so again, he doesn't
explicitly define this, but I think what
he's implying is this idea of becoming
as like this, like deeper philosophical
term that goes back thousands of years
where the organization isn't a static
thing or it's not something that becomes
something into an end state, but rather
it is like a dynamic process. And it is
always a dynamic process.
Bleu Daniel, do you have anything you
want to add to this? You have the
Heraclitus River quote,
which is a statement of the dynamic
nature of becoming. And then
in contrast we have being. And so people
often talk about being and becoming as
a noun centric and a verb centric way to
describe something is something is
that's like being or is it becoming?
Which is more of a process based focus.
So he refers to it as the site of
organizational becoming, not some sort
of ready made tool that's going to be,
but rather a process that will be
applied, or is already being applied as
a distributed site of becoming.
Cool. Do you want to read this one too?
Tyler sure. So FPP is not supposed to be
craving the powers assistant to exploit
uncertainty and complexity in pursuit
performance and survival by way of
curiosity driven epidemic foraging and
exploration. Correspondingly, Free
Energy Governance is a next generation
learning system designed for a
discontinuous world. Eachaining the firm
from dominant top down logics empowering
continuous strategic renewal through
purpose directed generative inferential
and cross hierarchical prediction error
minimization.
I wonder here if organizational becoming
and strategic renewal, I wonder if those
are maybe being used interchangeably.
We've talked about strategic renewal or
maybe strategic renewal is like a
fundamental like an organizational
becoming or organizational becoming
includes strategic renewal and other
things. I don't know. That's a good
question for Bijan, who we will get to
ask lots of questions of next week. Do
you have any additional concepts here,
Daniel or tyler okay,
Free Energy Governance, I'll let you
take this one. So free Energy Governance
effectively transposes the active
coherence framework to the firm and
adopts FEP as a first order principle
underlying a new logic organizing built
around three core dimension so
structure, hierarchy, cognition,
environmental enactment, capabilities,
sensing and sense making. The framework
is centered around crosshair will
generative process of sensing and sense
making to institutionalize continuum
strategic renewal as a matter of active
inference in pursuit of firm
outperformance and survival.
Nice. So here we are at the
end of the Free Energy Principle
chapter, the end of the first section on
the FEP in the Free Energy Governance
textbook. Looking forward to having a
good discussion with the author next
week. Do you guys have any final
thoughts on this section or chapter or
anything? Overall.
I think a question to unpack is going to
be how does a descriptive theory of
everything in Free Energy Principle help
us make normative or even adaptive
decisions for ourselves and for our
organizations? Every single information
architecture or strategy that a given
group implements will be describable in
terms of the particular partitioning
into internal, external, and blanket
states. They're all going to be
describable in terms of Bayesian optimal
inference, given some generative models
and encoding stream of data. So how do
we take something that is kind of like
the number line, it just is, and it is
neutral and then proactively apply it
up to and including the last mile? Do
people need to actually know about
information entropy to be part of a
system that's designed with these
strategies in mind, or is there going to
be some other way to communicate and
apply it? So how we actually move it
to the space of proactive decisionmaking
today and what that looks like in
different sectors and for different
organizations is really exciting.
Awesome. Well, I'm also looking forward
to reading the next sections of the book
and kind of going beyond the background
section into what's next, what is the
implication? And looking forward to
Bijon's comments next week. Tyler, any
comments are good. All good for me.
Looking forward to next week. Yeah, me
too. So if anybody has questions,
please go ahead and submit them. You're
welcome to email them to us or submit
them here in the comments, but do it
before the 11th, which is why our
meeting with Bijan will be and if you
want to participate on the live stream
and have read the chapters in the book
and watch the live streams or one or the
other, get in touch. Okay? Thanks,
guys.