Hello, everyone. It's May 26, 2022.
It's the fourth week of the first cohort
of the active textbook group. We're in
our first discussion of chapter two
today. We're going to go over the
questions that are posted for chapter
two. Then we'll see where that takes us
and what ID of the book have been
explored. And that'll be the main focus.
Also, just a note on the math learning
group, those meetings have been
occurring on 19 UTC on Wednesdays.
And so in the math learning group,
you'll find information about how to
participate. You'll find
and be able to edit resources on
learning different topics. So this is a
really helpful activity if people want
to share the resources that help them
learn about different ideas and that'll
help people search for a video about
this. We have a notation table that will
help us as we start to look at the
notation more. There's some math
learning basic questions, like around
math, anything related to the textbook
content can go in the main questions.
Math learning group is part of the real
textbook group. So these are not the
questions to be answered like the other
ones that we're going to go to are, but
this is just about math. And then also
there's some math oriented overviews.
Like, I wrote this summary of the first
two thirds of chapter two. So if people
want to be like, continuing to distill
and represent what they're learning and
what they're asking, that's all good.
Okay, any other notes that
anybody wants to add before we start to
go into the questions? You can raise
your hand or you can type it in the
chat.
Okay, so we're
in the first week of discussing chapter
two, the low Road to active inference.
So just to kind of warm us up,
what is the low road?
Got? A low road is the
Bayesian Brain approach. Right here is
the Proximate next
big concept, I guess previous,
but it's kind of based on I guess.
Yeah, I mean, you can see right in the
picture, it's based on basing it's like
mathematical. The way I conceptualize it
is like literally the
low road, meaning very primitive,
very mathematical, very hyper
analytical, foundational, kind of
an analysis way of looking at it, I
guess that's not necessarily
living or anything like that. Right?
Whereas the high road is kind of more
about the other side of that.
All right. Okay,
so we're going to be learning about the
high road and low road. Those are the
two paths that are offered in chapter
two and three of the book. So hopefully,
again, it would be awesome to have as
many people as possible speak and feel
welcome to share their views during this
session. So everyone is especially
encouraged to put questions or comments
in the chat or raise their hand to speak
or find other times to have synchronous
communications and especially to make
contributions to the coda. But really
appreciate that everyone has come out to
go through these discussion questions.
So we're going to now go to the
questions that have been placed into the
questions table. And just the more
questions, the better they can be super
short. It can be anything that you're
having uncertainty about. If you come
across a table or a figure or a sentence
in the text and you have a question,
please write the question down. It will
be extremely, extremely helpful.
It doesn't have to be with extensive
references or citations. It can just be
what does this mean if you're uncertain
about something and then if you were
certain about it, you could still write
a question like what would you ask
somebody to test or to understand what
they understood about it? Okay, so we're
going to start with
this first most upvoted question. But
there's still time in this session and
also till next week in our next session
on chapter two, to add more questions if
you wrote them down somewhere else and
also to upvote questions. But we're just
going to start with the most
interestingly voted questions.
What is the relevance of the support
and surprise for the different
probability distributions in table 2.1?
So what does anyone see in table 2.1
and what are support and surprise
people? Mike yes.
So table 2.1 looks to me like
a guide for selecting distributions. If
you're building out one of these models
with support saying what
set of numbers would fit within
this distribution selection? And then if
you chose this distribution, how would
you look at the support equation for it?
Can you unpack with a surprise part?
Yeah. If you chose this distribution,
how would you look at the surprise
component of it?
And we're going to get to surprise and
Bayesian surprise in the coming
questions. So support using
the definition pulled here from
Wikipedia, the support of the function
is the subset of the x axis, like the
domain where there's a y value that's
not zero. So it's where the function is
nonzero defined.
The Gaussian, the normal
Belker of distribution, has nonzero
support at all numbers.
Fancy r and then other distributions
have different variable, different
values that they're having non zero
values at. Like the gamma distribution
is defined over the interval from zero
to infinity. So if it was like how many
of this thing do you have that might be
a reason to use a distribution that's
only positive numbers? Or if you were
wanting something that could have
positive or negative numbers of any
size, the Gaussian is a distribution and
then another one that's like a relevant
support difference would be like the
deer Schlee being defined only within
the zero to one interval, which helps
connect it to probabilities. So the
support is where that function,
that distribution family is defined.
And then what is the surprise?
Does anyone know the name of the little
squiggle they are using to represent
surprise? I think it's called Fracture
i,
aka fancy eye.
We're going to come to the definition of
surprise in a coming question and
without going into every variable and
trying to overlearn something, the
surprise of a given observation, like a
data point, let's just think about the
Gaussian. X is the observed
data point and Mu is like the mean
of that normal distribution, which is
also the mode. So it's like the center
of that distribution. And then this
capital pi is a variance estimator,
I believe here. So how surprised one
should be by a new data point coming in
is related to the difference between
that new data point and the mean.
So if the new data point were exactly on
the center of the distribution, this
whole term is going to go to zero. So
one should not be surprised at all by
exact data points on the mean of the
distribution. But any data point that
has not exactly on the mean is going to
have some non zero value and so it's
going to be a function of how far the
data point is from the mean and some
scaling by the variance.
So if we were expecting 100 with a
variance of ten versus 100 with
a variance of one in one case, like
getting 101 is like a one sigma event.
It has a z score of one. Just speaking
loosely here, whereas in the case
of it having a variance that's very
small, then that might be more
surprising.
Any other comments that
people have on Table 2.1?
I have a question.
Yeah. So while
I was reading through the chapter going
back to section 2.2, right, perception
as inference. So when he says, when they
say that the brain is a predictive
machine or a statistical organ, that
infers external states of the world.
Okay, here's my question, because I'm
primarily from a telecom background. So
most of our things are to get messages
crossed between two distant transmitters
receiver, right? So we build noise
models. So without any noise you don't
get signal. So you need to know what
noise model looks like.
For example, if the power spectrum of
the signal is what you expect from,
let's say we are using a Gaussian
distribution of noise, right? So if it's
the same as you expect from the
Gaussian, you do nothing. So that's just
noise. So you don't classify the data
point that's coming in. If it is more
than this, then okay, so there
might be something interesting about
this. There might be some signal here.
So we define that signal to noise ratio.
A lot of this chapter seems to be
dealing with the fact that we
by default know what the signal looks
like. So there's no attempt to build a
noise model here. That would be like,
okay, so maybe the sensor in this case,
our eyes for example, has some
parameters it can detect between,
say, a bandwidth,
okay, so it can detect light between
certain frequency ranges, but maybe it
performs very well in a certain
frequency range and not others. There's
more error in other frequency ranges,
right? So the noise model should
incorporate such things, imperfections
in the sensor, imperfections in the
connections between the sensor and
processing equipment. But there's no
attempt to do that in this entire
chapter. So I'm just curious as to what
exactly is the predictive machine here?
What is being predicted here?
Great question. And in general, every
question that people have, they're going
to be 100 times more impactful if they
can be written down. This is just the
second chapter. It's introducing us to
the essence of starting with just Bayes
equation. It's the first equation here,
starting with the foundation of
increasingly advanced noise filtering
approaches. So check out Livestream 43
to see how colman filter and advanced
multilevel Bayesian filtering schemes
are used and learned and fit with free
energy, minimization and so on. But
you're right, that is not approached in
this chapter because it's starting with
the essence of Bayes equation and
then going to build towards another
kernel, which is going to be the kernel
of the variational free energy. And then
that in this one layer case is
going to be able to be elaborated and
parameterized and fit within nested
models to accommodate, like, learning on
hyperparameters, learning of noise
models and so on. But it is not in this
chapter. Okay, yeah,
I'm sorry if I threw us off track. No,
it's perfect. But they're good
questions. And then Jacob asked, what do
you think of the surprise, the
distributions involving a sum product of
the project, probability distributions,
except for gamma.
Actually, I guess the Gaussian kind of
as well. Yeah, maybe I'm
thinking about this wrong, but I thought
that the surprise was like
the information gain or
equivalent. And so for the Gaussian
and the gamma distributions, it's always
for one single element
of the distribution for one x. But for
the multinomial and derivative lay,
there's something over all of the
possible probabilities, which makes it,
I guess, an entropy function.
But is there a difference?
For example, one could have a
multidimensional Gaussian, a two
dimensional Gaussian, and then the
surprise for the two dimensional
Gaussian would be represented as a sum
over the different dimensions.
So they've shown the Gaussian and the
gamma in the uni dimensional case and
the multinomial and the zero schlay in a
multidimensional case. So in that case,
is it.
I. Thought that x was just one element
of the domain. So x
is just if we think of the Gaussian as
this kind of bell shaped curve on the x
and y axis, we really want the f of x
value to get like the Gaussian value,
but x is just the input value.
Is that correct? Believe I. That is
accurate because, yes, x is the domain
of the function and then the sum is over
eyes. So if we had a multinomial
Gaussian or multi dimensional Gaussian
in I dimensions, then it would have a
sum over eyes.
Yeah,
I guess I still have uncertainty about
why we don't do that for the single
dimensional Gaussian as well. Because if
we take just one point on the Gaussian,
I understand why that would have a
certain surprise. But then in the same
way, if we take one point in the
Dirichlet distribution,
shouldn't that also have an equivalent
equation for surprise? Why in the
Dirichlet distribution are we summing
over all the eyes,
but in the Gaussian we are considering
just one point on the probability
distribution? Or maybe Derishley
is multidimensional.
And that's the reason I think the uni
dimensional case would be just without
this sigma I. It would just
be this.
But if anyone has any other thoughts,
especially if they want to contribute
them in writing to improve our
understanding, that'd be awesome. Let's
continue to the next question.
In Section 2.4 they write we now
introduce the simple but fundamental
advance offered by active inference.
This starts from the same inferential
perspective discussed above, but extends
it to consider action as inference.
In your own words, what is the simple
but fundamental advance offered by
active inference? So what would
anyone write or like to share?
What is the advance of active inference?
Sorry, is it just bringing action into
the equation? So predictive
coding and Bayesian brain are
specifically about perception, visual
perception. I think the key thing with
active inference is that it's well,
it's not just that it brings action into
the equation, it's that it treats them
as essentially the same thing, that
they're kind of united as
part of the same process, which I
think is kind of a new development.
Thanks for the awesome answer,
Ali.
Yeah, I think Alan Bartheau, or Bartho's
in the brain's sense of movement,
has a particularly relevant
description of action and perception.
And he writes that perception is
simulated action. And I think
that really speaks to the
advance made by active inference.
I mean the integration of action and
perception. Or in other words, as
Bartheau claims, the simulation of
action and perception is,
I guess, really novel development.
I think I read something, but I can't
remember where I read it, but I think it
was roughly that. On these existing
Bayesian brain theories,
an agent perceives in order to act,
whereas under active inference an agent
acts. Action kind of precedes
perception. So active inference
essentially flips this traditional
schema in terms of which one feeds into
the other. Yeah,
I was just going to say that adding on
to bringing action into the equation,
it flips it.
Where do your priorities come from?
Where do the hyper parameters get
specified? Where does the model start?
Where is the agency kind of in all of
these other models, really no affordance
for that or it's hard to very emergent
as here it's very explicitly specified.
Some affordance for that. Thanks brock,
Mike and then anyone else who raises
their hand. Yeah, so I'm thinking
if you have priors you have some prior
assumptions, then do
you necessarily need to take action in
order to sort of envision what your
perception might be? So it's almost like
getting into imagination or something
like that. You have a set of priors that
can drive what you imagine your
perception to be before any action is
taken.
Great question, Blue.
So I think that this was
elaborated on a lot in Section 2.7
when they talk about pursuing a policy
because there's consequences when we're
planning and making predictions, that
has consequences for both our perception
and our action.
Even in a conversation when someone
says, oh, have a nice day
is expected at the end of that, but have
a nice rabbit would be like, what?
You're not expecting that to come at the
end of that sentence. So when you plan,
it interferes with your perception
because you didn't plan for them to say
have a nice rabbit. Right, but it also
interferes with your action. And so I
think the
novelty or enhanced aspect of active
inference loops into the fact that
perception and action are continually
impacting one another.
Yes. Thanks, Blue.
These are some of the core memes and
themes, and it really is important to
understand how active inference is
similar and different than other work in
this area. Like variational. Bayesian
inference is not introduced by active
inference. Bayesian models of perception
is not introduced by active inference.
Bayesian models of action is not
introduced by active inference. So it's
about finding what has been done to
understand what is being offered and
then whether one chooses to take this,
like, history of science, development of
science view or we kind of
just want to state plainly what it is
without wondering what the advance
relative to other frameworks is. These
are all really critical ideas. Like the
signal processing framework was brought
up earlier and predictive processing,
predictive coding,
anticipatory systems are often
purely about sense.
And just to give one thought on that,
it kind of makes sense for a video
encoding algorithm, for example,
because every piece of the camera is in
focus, but vision requires
action. And so that's where we're going
to be bringing in all these other
important concepts like attention,
sensory attenuation, and the
active decision making component of
vision to resolve uncertainty, which is
what gives rise to a generative visual
field that seems like there's color
everywhere and seems like there's high
resolution everywhere. Though that is
not the incoming sensory information.
So by fully taking this generative
modeling perspective on perception,
which in live stream number 43.0,
maria did an awesome job of connecting
this even before Helmholtz and Kant.
It's Plato's cave and it's part of this
long discussion about perception.
And action could be a variable.
So there's perceiving and then if action
is a variable, then active inference is
providing not just a unified framework,
like a Bayesian graph framework, for
some variables that are interpreted as
perception and some variables that can
be interpreted as action selection or
policy planning.
But there's a tractable approximation
by shifting from the in reading this
answer, by shifting from an exact
solution to the mathematical problem
Bayesian inference to an approximate
solution variational free energy, which
is going to provide a bound on some
quantity that might be intractable to
compute. So it's going to give a
heuristic for the action perception
cycle.
But this is a really great question. So
people can continue to return to it
because people will probably ask us for
a long time to come, how is this
different than blank? Or what is active
inference? These are some of the things
that we would want to have in mind.
Ali.
Yeah, again, going back to Bartheau and
his definition of perception as
simulated action, I think it also
relates nicely to Merlopanti's
phenomenology. Merlopanti has a famous
statement and has a famous
insight as vision is the brain's way of
touching. And so you
see, for instance, as we
move around space, as we construct
our sense of spatiality or
our sense of temporality or everything
else, we don't just begin
with the representation of space or
time. I mean, the image of movement
constructs because we move and not
as a consequence of our movement.
Thanks. And we'll continue
with the questions, but that's an
awesome area to go into with
phenomenology with four E cognition
extended, embedded in culture, et
cetera, et cetera. And many, many of the
live streams and papers have been on
those areas. So it's cool. It's a bridge
from formal models of perception,
cognition, and action into qualitative
and philosophical areas.
Okay.
And then oh, thanks, Morris, for adding
that the
idea of interrelated action and
perception has been around in cognitive
science for a long time, like dynamical
systems theory and inactivism emphasize
that. But active inference brings a
coherent formalism to the table, which
is a nice advance. Well said. Next
question. Figure 2.2.
Figure two. Two point illustrates Y as a
result of an internal generative model X
and an external generative process x
star.
In order to measure surprise, wouldn't
we need another value of Y-I-E-A
separate Y that encodes prior beliefs,
if Y can be objectively measured from
external signals? Is there a third Y
that's considered the observation?
First, I'd like to actually go to
this question about two notions of
surprise because
they might come to bear on this action
perception loop. Once we move from just
Bayes equation and calculating surprise
on parametric distributions to thinking
about prior updating and cognitive
entities with a generative model that
constitutes a prior, with incoming
information coming in, we're going to
start to see why this notion of surprise
and Bayesian surprise are similar and
different. So using the apple frog
example so the unobserved hidden
state, the latent state of the world,
is whether there is an apple or a frog
in a bag, for example, or just in this
person's area. And then what can be
observed, just speaking coarsely, is it
can jump or not, and we can totally go
down the rabbit hole with what is truly
observed and things like that. But this
is just what are in the context of this
model. The unobserved state is the
actual identity of the object and the
observation is going to be the action or
not. We take the opportunity to unpack
two different notions of surprise, both
of which are important. The first we
refer to simply as surprise. It's the
negative log evidence where evidence is
the marginal probability of
observations. So we saw that first sense
of surprise with the fracture I in
the previous table we looked at the
second notion of surprise is referred to
as Bayesian Surprise. This is a measure
of how much we have to update our
beliefs following an observation. In
other words, Bayesian Surprise
quantifies the difference between a
prior and a posterior of probability.
What are the similarities and
differences between the two notions of
surprise? Okay,
we'll see what has been said and then
hear what other people are thinking.
So,
page 20, they wrote that
Bayesian Surprise scores the amount of
belief updating as opposed to surprise,
which is simply how unlikely or likely
that observation was.
So in that Gaussian case, the surprise
is like about one data point coming in.
Given how the distribution is
parameterized right now, how surprising
was that one data point? And then
Bayesian Surprise is going to be about
how much that distribution is updated
after processing that data point.
Similarities? They both depend on how
well the Agent's Generative model
matches the external world. And they're
both measuring Surprise or Bayesian
Surprise in the same units, which are
information theoretic quantities of
information, i, e. Nats or bits.
Differences. Plain Surprise marginalizes
over all the model's degrees of freedom
under the model's prior distribution
over its adjustable parameters that
would be great for someone to unpack.
What does it mean to marginalize over
the model's degrees of freedoms? And
then Bayesian Surprise lets the model
choose the best set of parameters it can
to fit the observed data and then
measures how much of an update
that was Mike and then
Blue and then Ali. Yeah. Under the
first similarity, I'm wondering if it's
this dependency on how well the Agents
Generative model matches their
perception of the external world as
opposed to matches the external world.
Agree with that. Great addition blue
and then Ali. Okay. I think my hand was
just left over. Left up. Okay. Ali?
Well, I believe that the plain Surprise
is a kind of raw statistical surprise,
but Bayesian Surprise is a kind of
surprise is a kind of processed
surprise. Or I'm not sure if I'm right
in saying that plain Surprise can
probably be described as an objective
surprise as opposed to Bayesian surprise
prized as a subjective surprise.
But as I said, I'm not sure about
the plausibility of these descriptions.
Great comments.
Even the surprise alone
still depends on the parameters of
the generative model. So it still is
within a processing or a filtering
frame, albeit a fixed one.
So they talk about like,
let's look at the figure where there's a
graphical overview of this apple and the
frog.
And this is kind of giving some graphics
and words to fill in this apple frog
example. So initially the person has
this likelihood model in the back of
their head where they have beliefs about
how likely apples are to jump. They do
it 1% of the time and how likely frogs
are to jump. They do it 81% of the time.
That's the likelihood. That's about how
observations depend on hidden states
of the world. Their prior
beliefs are that there's a 10% chance
that the entity is a frog and
these are mutually exclusive options.
There's no third option here. That would
be like another category model structure
learning on the model. So we're staying
within this model for now and they sum
to one because they're a probability.
Then there's an observation which is
jumping and then the posterior reflects
the updated beliefs about what the
entity is. And so it's like, it's so
much overwhelmingly more likely that
frogs jump that seeing something jump
updates the prior from here to here.
So in this case, one can calculate the
surprise of the observation without
doing any updating at all. One could
just stay fixed in their prior belief
and then could describe how surprised
they are in Nats by given observation.
In this full Bayesian cycle, there is an
updating of the prior to the posterior
and then that updating can be described
in terms of how much the prior was
updated. And so that's like here, the
model is updated to the
observed data. This is now the best
fitting model. And then we're
calculating the difference between these
two distributions. So regular
surprise being zero means the data point
was exactly as you expected.
Bayesian surprise being zero means the
distribution was not updated. High
surprise means that the data point was
extremely unpredicted. It was extremely
unlikely whether or not you update your
model at all. High Bayesian surprise
means that the distribution was changed
a lot as a function of seeing that
happen. Ali.
Well, perhaps I didn't understand it
correctly, but isn't it the case that in
the plain surprise or more generally
in the Bayesian formulation of the
probability of events, the likelihood
and both the likelihood and the priors
are somehow inherent to
the phenomena inherent to the events,
independent of the observers?
Yeah, great question. I hope I'm not
going off on a branch here, but this is
related to the difference between
frequentist and Bayesian approaches to
statistics. So Frequentism does
have viewed from the Bayesian
perspective, frequentism does have
priors. They're uniform priors, which
are not uninformative priors, they just
are uniform. And so in frequentism
we come across like the maximum
likelihood solution or the maximum
likelihood parameter, which is just
like, well, if all outcomes were equally
a priori likely uniform prior,
then we would just need to evaluate the
likelihood and find the model with the
maximum likelihood solution.
Bayesian offers another degree of
freedom and says, well, sure, you could
pick a uniform prior that would give you
the maximum likelihood solution. Or you
might want to have a prior distribution
over that space so that if something is
twice as likely a priori and then you
observe less than two X evidence for it,
you still might want like the Bayes
factor or your posterior to reflect that
one rather than just jumping instantly
to a different maximum likelihood
solution. So yes, priors and likelihood
are implicit, but they're using a
different ontology than Bayesian
statistics. But we're in the bays or the
post bays area now.
But there's so many connections to
classical statistics and in SPM, the
textbook there is parametric
classical statistics, non parametric
classical statistics, and Bayesian
statistics. So they're more
similar than not. It just is
about seeing where one of them is like a
special case of another or a
generalization of another.
Okay, let's see if we can do one or two
more questions during this session.
Okay, so let's return to the previous
question. So we're looking at figure
two, which is something
we're going to see different
representations of this entity
as generative model, world or niche as
generative process. And then here
the hidden states are those that are
unobserved as data. Y is
referring to data points that are
observed as data. There's a
cognitive hidden state which is like a
prior in this generative model. And then
there's some hidden state x star. But it
could have been any letter or any shape
about the hidden state in the world.
The observation is going to everything
that happens in between. Here is
cognition, like the sandwich model,
like sense, think, act.
That type of model is just referring to
that little boomerang. Data come in
cognitive processing, action selection.
So we're in that figure. The question
was, in order to measure surprise,
wouldn't we need another value of
Y-I-E-A separate Y that enclose prior
belief? Great question.
Let's just assume that there is a
Gaussian generative model.
So the entity has like two parameters in
its cognitive model, the mean and the
variance. Then Y comes
in and given the parameterization of the
generative model, all that's needed is
the data point to come in for the
surprise to be calculated. So another
value is needed. But whether we call
it ABC XYZ is
just a mathematical abstraction. So yes,
prior beliefs are important. The prior
beliefs that can be interpreted as the
parameterizations of the cognitive model
are required if
Y can be objectively measured from
external signals. Is there a
third Y. That is considered the
observation. So one could
imagine a lot of like, real world
scenarios where a more complex model
would be required, two people looking at
the thermometer or all these different
sorts of situations. But unless
somebody can unpack this a little more
or explain what they were asking about,
then I don't think a third why is
required. Mike yeah, it was
my question, so I can try and unpack it.
And so sticking with the thermometer
example at the heart of that last
question is, if we have a thermometer
that's registering the temperature,
can we consider that as sort of the true
observation that is the actual Y as
measured by this instrument? And then
therefore we can compare our sort of
internal Y with the actual Y?
Okay, so I have a really similar and
related question that's like
two questions down, but it's
in a different section. But let me just
place some things on here and it goes
back to what we were saying about what
exactly is the hidden state. So is the
hidden state the temperature and the
data is reading from the thermometer
that's like the data Y, right? Like this
Y in the middle. But then what is how I
feel hot or cold? I'm perfectly
positioned to be at 75 all the time. So
I know if it's like one degree too cold
or one degree too hot, I've got to turn
up the heat or turn it down or whatever.
But my registration, my sensory input is
not at 75 degrees. My sensory input is
I'm hot or I'm cold. And so this is like
where I mean, we were talking about this
yesterday in the math group. There's
this really fuzzy line for me. I would
love for someone to clarify that. So I
do get what you mean about this.
Shouldn't there be another why? There's
the why out there in the world, 75
degrees and then there's how I feel
about that why.
Okay, thanks. So variables
are not like, innately tagged with being
observables or hidden states. It's a
model specific framing of what is going
to be modeled as generated data and
what is going to be modeled as a
Bayesian prior. In multilevel Bayesian
modeling, the priors themselves are
generated from a higher or deeper level
of the. So one can be serving, in fact,
multiple roles. This is the minimal
prior generated data expectation
maximization type, single layer Bayesian
kernel. So we're going to think about
this temperature example. There's a
hidden state of the generative process
which is going to be the temperature of
the world latent unmodeled. So this
isn't even claiming that there is such a
thing as temperature. This is just a
latent unobserved temperature that
is giving rise to thermometer readings,
which might have, like, different sorts
of noise. Then there's another hidden
state, which is the evaluation of
temperature. And so this
is just a schematic. And also,
whether one is labeled x or Y or L or
triangle is like a norm and a
convenience. But the
letter doesn't matter itself.
It will be used mostly consistently
within the textbook. But there's only so
many letters and there's not a lot of
coherence on notation use.
What else could be explored here?
Yeah. Mike and then Ali.
So as I keep ruminating on this, which
is probably more than I should, it seems
like there can be infinite wise, right?
So to the extent that you are taking
action which will change your
perception, then you are as a result
triggering potentially new Y's in the
system, right? So you just have this
infinite potential for what Y can be.
This speaks to the composability and the
flexibility of active inference. So like
Y could be one pixel of visual input,
it could be a 4K video, y could be smell
and a 4K video, y could be LiDAR
and this and that. So Y is just the
generalized input of sense and
then action might be related to this in
a very direct way. Like Y could be
visual input and action could be your
eye movement. So that case is going to
be explored a lot in the book. However,
it could also be you're getting
something in and then the actions are
just totally unrelated. Maybe they don't
affect the hidden state, the causal
process in the world at all. Or maybe
actions enable different wise to enter
the picture. This is just the total
essence kernel and then even
trivial cases require some more
apparatus. Ali?
Yeah. I have a question. Is it correct
to say that the minimization of
variation of free energy, aka the
Surprise is exactly equivalent to
the maximization of expectation,
the wholly linear relationship between
these two? Or possibly we have some kind
of plateaued areas between these two
extremes?
Great question. So this is something
that we'll come to next week
in our discussions on chapter two. So we
have not even discussed variational free
energy yet today. We talked about
starting with a low road on some of
the atomic calculations that are going
to come into play, like Surprise and
Bayesian. Surprise in a Bayesian
framework and beginning to partition
active entities and their action
perception. Loops in terms of a
Bayesian graph that's going to be
amenable to flexible modeling of
perceptive, cognitive active and out
there in the world variables. Variables
with those interpretations. And then
variational free energy is going to come
into play as a way to bound surprise.
So let's have some questions and
discourse and we'll come to it next
week. But it's an awesome question.
Jessica?
Hi. Yes, I have a question, I guess
related to this figure 2.2,
let's say, in regards to how we
interpret what we observe.
So I understand you have a prior that
might you're anticipating
something like some other people's
behavior or how things should be that
might be different from what you
actually observe. But a lot of times,
at least in terms of when we're thinking
like human beings, an action
in the world, how you interpret it has
to do a lot with your own
views or your own experiences. And maybe
that connects to the priors, but the
interpretation might be very different
from people to people. The
interpretation will vary a lot because
everybody has different experiences.
So those could be encoded, I guess, in
the priors, but it's not connected per
se to the prediction part. Or maybe it
is. So I'm trying to kind of connect
that idea of our personal
interpretation based on our experiences,
which could be priors, make us see
what's happening in the world
differently than other people.
So that why will look very different for
you than for me, just because we have
lived different experiences. So it's not
like an actual why. You cannot
really say this is a fact because
it's an interpretation. At the end of
the day.
Great question and points. Yeah.
Understanding how the
individual setup of a given entity is
related to its past experiences and how
that could be modeled by priors is an
important area. And some
of those rich dynamics are not in this
minimal nucleus.
But it'll be awesome to start to think
about what does have to be in the box
here to give rise to
those kinds of dynamics.
So that's going to end this discussion
next week. We will also be staying in
chapter two and taking it more towards
variational free energy and expected
free energy. So that should be fun.
We're going to in this room transfer
immediately to the Tools meeting. So if
you want to join for active Lab Tools
meeting, everyone is welcome. And
there's no prerequisites or anything
like that. If you want to hang around
and join Tools, stay in this exact
gather space. If you want to continue
talking with other people about the book
or anything else, just head up into one
of the rooms above. And if anyone who
wants to can just continue any
discussion that they want. But in this
space we're going to continue now with
Tools. So thanks everyone.