hello
and welcome everyone to the active
inference live stream
this is act imp stream 8.1
it is november 10 2020
welcome to teamcom everyone we are an
experiment in online team communication
learning and practice related to active
inference
you can find us at our website
activeinference.org
you can find us at our twitter at email
our public key base team or on youtube
this
is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback
so that we can improve our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and as far as video
etiquette for live streams go
mute yourself if there's noise in your
background raise your hands so that we
can hear from everybody on the stack and
use respectful speech behavior etcetera
today we are excitingly in act image
stream 8.1
and it's going to go a little something
like this we're going to start with some
intros and warm-ups
and then we'll get to the sections of
8.1
in 8.1 as well as 8.2 we're going to be
discussing the paper scaling active
inference by
chance at all in 2019 thanks to blue for
the suggestion of the paper
we're gonna go through the goals the
abstract and the roadmap
and then we'll have a little notation
and math
overview we'll also take a look at the
figures with a special focus on
what each figure is showing or
representing or invoking
in today's discussion 8.1 and
next week's discussion 8.2 we're going
to be discussing this same paper
so save and submit your questions and
also get in touch
with us if you want to participate for
the rest of 2020 we're going to be
discussing
this paper 8 as well as 9 10 and 11
which you can learn more about by
checking our twitter
so check it out there all right here we
are in the intros
welcome again shannon i'll kick out
other so for the introductions
we'll go around
and just introduce yourself and your
location
and we'll uh roll with it as people gain
and uh
lose the chat so just say hello in a
short introduction
and then pass it to somebody else i'm
daniel i'm in california
and i will pass it to blue
hi i'm blue and i am in southern new
mexico
in las cruces and i will pass it to
sasha
hi i'm sasha i'm also in california
and i will pass it to yvonne
hello my name is ivan i'm
in moscow russia and i pass it to
alejandra
i think she disappeared for a second so
let's go to alex
okay
hello i'm alex i'm also in moscow russia
so welcome everybody
cool and alejandra has been on before so
hopefully we know her but when she jumps
back in
we can hear from her so for these
warm-up questions and also it's pretty
cool to have a slightly smaller panel so
i'm really looking forward to hearing
everyone's perspective
on what they got out of the paper what
they brought to the paper
it'll be really cool to hear about so
the first question
is what made you excited to read this
paper
and or to learn about these topics
so while people are raising their hand
and feel free to do so
something that initially made me excited
to read this paper was just about
learning how active inference could be
applied to the kinds of problems that
people apply other machine learning
algorithms to
so that's a starting point blue
so i pitched this paper i um hadn't like
thoroughly
like digested it when i when i picked it
i had read
um the first author's other paper in
class computational biology but like
applying um
like agent-based models and like
modeling parameters
to uh active inference was was like
really what intrigued me and
the um this paper i especially liked
because of the ability to apply it in a
continuous framework as a as opposed to
like something
in discrete time steps and i thought
that that's that was significant and
important
cool welcome alejandra do you want to
just give your quick intro and say hi up
never mind uh anyone else want to add
something that made them excited to
learn about this topic or read about the
paper
yeah thanks again for the suggestion
blue the second question
is what is your experience or background
with computers
slash computational modeling and what is
something
interesting that you've been learning
about or studying recently in the area
and i think that my goal with this
question was to
show to our listener viewers
that there's many computational
backgrounds that intersect
in active inference so it's a community
that includes some
people who are really on the cutting
edge of the computational modeling
and that's what we see reflected in this
paper so
big props to everybody who is reading
and talking about it because it is
at the cutting edge of that type of
machine learning research but also
there's this deep tradition of
action-oriented research
and embodied cognition and so many other
areas that
might not necessarily entail a
computational background or even a
computational approach in how they're
studied
until this type of intersectional
research so
does anyone want to just something that
they've been learning about
in computers or what type of computer
modeling have they had experience with
so i can start a lot of my computer
work had been in bioinformatics which
does deal with computers but it's very
different kinds of
questions than the machine learning
community however increasingly there's
application of machine learning
to bioinformatics so this was just kind
of like a different perspective
on machine learning outside of the
biological context that i had mainly
seen it in
and i'll just throw up the third
question in case anyone wants to
answer that one which is what kinds of
problems might
machine learning based upon active
inference be
applied to so you can just raise your
hand if you
yep go ahead sasha
yeah i would say i guess to some of all
these questions is a very limited
experience in working with computers
uh but my background is in neuroscience
and i'm always curious
to um learn what
uh machine learning um has to offer
for understanding the process of
learning and how that can link back to
neurobiology concepts um and
so i'm interested in understanding these
equations
and having uh a better grasp on
um what the relationships are like
cool because learning is really a
biologically inspired
topic it's based upon learning in
organisms or the kind of control that
organisms enact in their environment
and that's not even getting into the
whole neural network
slash actual brain debacle so definitely
these kinds of learning questions any
other thoughts on
this one
blue
so like you my background is like
bioinformatics but i've like branched
out
since like getting out of my doctoral
research into like
doing all kinds of different
computational and agent-based
modeling type applications even quantum
computing a little bit
this system particularly um
interests me because like sasha i'm
interested in learning like how things
learn
but also like from the beyond brain
perspective
like stay in biology but think about
biological systems
just at a very simple level like slime
modes or something like this
how do these systems learn right because
still there's some element of learning
that happens and when you can kind of
deconstruct it into like a computational
like model then you can start to like
recognize
input output into simpler biological
systems beyond the brain
cool and let's return to that
multi-scale
cognition when we're a little bit later
on but i wrote that down so we can
definitely return there any last
thoughts on the warm-ups before we get
into the paper
cool all right so today we are going to
be talking about this scaling active
inference paper which is an archive
paper
and the paper presents its goal as
or what it does as we present a model of
active inference that is applicable in
high dimensional control tasks with both
continuous states and actions
our model builds upon previous attempts
to scale active inference by including
an efficient planning algorithm
as well as the quantification and active
resolution of model uncertainty
our model makes two primary
contributions first
we showed that the full active inference
construct can be scaled to the kinds of
tasks considered in the reinforcement
learning literature
this involved extending previous models
of deep active inference to include
model uncertainty and expected
information gain
second we highlighted the overlap
between active inference and
state-of-the-art
approaches to model-based reinforcement
learning welcome back alejandra
and some of these topics were introduced
or at least
initially brought up in the act in
stream 8.0 so if you're
a little bit just unsure what is model
based versus non-model based
reinforcement learning or
what is reinforcement learning or what
is machine learning it's all
good there's kind of a sequence of ideas
that you can follow to understand
why this paper is so exciting and just
go to active stream 8.0 if you're
curious the way that we can phrase what
the big goal or question of the paper is
in terms of non-active inference
vocabulary
would be how can we apply active
inference to challenging control tasks
and like blue mentioned these are the
ones that often involve continuous
decisions being made
so like turning up a dial um or down or
steering wheel
rather than like chess or checkers or
connect four or the mario kart example
which now i will never forget and then
how to connect these
continuous challenging control tasks
which have elements of planning and all
these other things happening
and connect these tasks formally to
reinforcement learning
any thoughts or questions on the goal of
the paper
cool so the abstract which we'll just
run through
is in reinforcement learning rl agents
operate in partially observed and
uncertain environments
isn't that the truth model based
reinforcement learning suggests that
this control of these partially observed
and uncertain environments
is best achieved by learning and
exploiting a probabilistic model of the
world
so just to be clear this is what
traditional model-based reinforcement
learning is
model-free or unsupervised reinforcement
learning would be learning the very very
direct relationships between outcomes
like reward
and states model-based reinforcement
learning abstracts a little bit above
that
and it considers how learning occurs on
a probabilistic model of the world
active inference is an emerging
normative framework
in cognitive and computational
neuroscience that offers a unifying
account of how biological agents achieve
this control
in this framework inference learning and
action
emerge from a single imperative that
maximizes the bayesian
evidence for a niched model of the world
and so
learning inference and action are all
part of the organisms
generative model and we're going to see
how that gets specified and how it plays
out
the challenge is that implementations of
this process this integration between
inference and action if you will have
thus far been restricted to low
dimensional and idealized situations
so this could be for example playing a
very simple game
or doing a two by two matrix like a
prisoner's dilemma or there are other
cases where active inference has been
used
for slightly higher dimensional but
still quite idealized situations like
reading from a known set of options
here we present a working implementation
of active inference
that applies to higher dimensional tasks
with proof of principle results
demonstrating efficient exploration and
an order of magnitude
increase in sample efficiency over
strong model-free baselines
so just by reading that we can look
forward to some improvements
on classical algorithms and as far as
this
magnitude increasing sample efficiency
the reason why they're focused on sample
efficiency
is because these distributions that we
want to understand
the shape of are not just like a simple
curve
there's a lot of dimensions to them and
they're very rugged so small changes can
change your height
so to speak quite a lot which means that
the challenge
is to sample effectively not get trapped
in one area or not to over sample one
region at the cost of another
our results demonstrate the feasibility
of applying active inference at scale
and highlight the operational homologies
between active inference and current
model based approaches to reinforcement
learning so
what would be the implications of that
well it'd be pretty epic
if all of the hype and buzz that we hear
about
machine learning or reinforcement
learning or all the places where we know
reinforcement
learning gets applied ranging from
recommendation algorithms to
maps to just all these types of things
could
active inference play a role in that and
what what would that do for our
conception
of these kinds of algorithms and there's
probably a lot of directions to take
that but
that's the equivalence is if there is a
homology
and potentially even a superiority of
active inference techniques in certain
cases over reinforcement learning
then it liberates us from some of the
baggage of the straightforward model
based
reinforcement learning or the critiques
of reinforcement learning but also opens
the door to some new ways to implement
strategies and understand the systems
that we're working with
cool so the paper has a
pretty clear road map this is like
driving
on highway 10 in new mexico and there's
a introduction section uh the
relationship to further work is actually
section 5 which we'll get to in a second
but the paper begins with an
introduction and a consideration
of active inference as a topic
it then moves directly to the model and
lays it out
in the six subsections 3.1 through 3.6
from a mathematical perspective we're
going to be focusing primarily on
one two and three because those are the
parts that we've
heard the most about and they're the
most relatable so the generative model
and the recognition distribution are the
p and the q
mind your p's and q's and this is
everything that we've been talking about
with the two directions between the
agent and the world
and the weather we think about that in
the bayesian structural computationalist
perspective or the inactivist
perspective
the whole tale of two densities
integrating internalism and externalism
all these things come together in 3.1
3.2
learning and inference is where we're
going to draw the
bow together with reinforcement learning
and about other machine learning
algorithms
3.3 is where we're going to come closer
to control theory
because we're going to be talking about
setting policies for action
then 3.456 hopefully when alec is here
next week we'll have a little bit uh
more detail there
maybe we could even see a simulation or
hear about some of the degrees of
freedom
that the authors had in the model why
they chose to do what they did
the part that will be very cool as an
experimental biologist
is the experimental section and here
it's an interesting approach
to do one set of tasks that conveys
exploration of a state space and another
set of tasks that conveys exploitation
so they're saying like
this model has two hands you know it's
good at exploring but it's good at
exploiting as well
then there's the connection to previous
work and the three areas that they
tie it most directly to with the
keywords as well as in this closing
section
are related to deep active inference
which in contrast to
i guess shallow active inference would
mean that you're not just minimizing
your surprise about your instantaneous
sensory
information but you have a deep or a
counter factual model that goes through
time so that's like the example of
taking a jacket even though you're not
cold yet that's deep active inference
you're reducing your surprise about
future states of your temperature
under a generative model where if you go
outside and it's cold you're going to
get cold
but shallow active inference would be
like you wouldn't put on the jacket or
you wouldn't even take it with you
because it wouldn't be a relevant
affordance in the one second time frame
but it actually is relevant in the one
second time frame under a deep
degenerative model of temperature
the second to our model-based
reinforcement learning which we've
mentioned a few times and information
gain
information is reduction of uncertainty
and when we're reducing our uncertainty
about environmental causes
it helps us plan better actions but we
also need to reduce our uncertainty
about which actions to take
and that's called policy and that's what
link relates us here to control theory
then there's a discussion and conclusion
okay before we
jump into the math and the actual
sections are there any
thoughts or questions on the roadmap
all right here is a partial
notation reference and i just separated
them onto two sides
and so if you're only going to look at a
few parameters
if your parameter overload hits in at
six the ones on the left are the
important ones
these are the ones that will help you
get eighty percent of what is happening
and then the next
ten percent are the ones on the right
and then there's a few other ones which
aren't on this page that are
more like the esoteric statistical
parameters
the big parameter is s with a hat just
like sasha
with a hat and that's the true state of
the environment
so s with a hat is what is actually
trying to be predicted
and that's like the actual temperature
of the environment or the actual amount
of sunlight
but that's not what the agent is able to
track directly
it's able to make an estimate of the
environmental state
and you can imagine there's times where
that's an easy estimate to make there's
times where it's a hard estimate to make
and then this is the difference between
the discrete and the continuous case
would be
if the state that you're estimating is
isn't day or night it's a zero or one
that's a discrete case a continuous case
would be like what is the
amount of light and that's a continuous
variable so there's a lot more options a
lot more
shades of gray infinite of them that's s
is the agent's internal ongoing
estimate of this environmental state
that it's trying to track
and we can think about it with just one
s or there could be multiple s's like
is it humid or is it dry that's one axis
another one is it light or dark
o are the observations so in the case of
light being estimated
that would be like the observations of
light on the retina
in the case of temperature it's like a
thermometer reading
a are the policy actions by the agent
and those are arising from pi
which is a policy and a policy is like
a layer above action so for example
action would be
moving my left foot my policy would be
if i hear this sound then i move my left
foot
another policy would be i always move my
left foot
and so there's different kinds of
policies that can be very nuanced they
can be conditional
they can be related to each other or
they can be very straightforward and
stand alone
t with italics is the time steps of the
model so this is just a
modeling parameter that's going to come
up again and again and it has to do with
how time is measured in terms of epochs
or states or continually okay then just
to the right side
we have little and big theta and a
little theta
is often used just to mean a parameter
of the generative model
and the bigger theta is like the space
of all the parameters
so those are kind of used similarly then
lambda
is related to the likelihood
distribution it relates some of the
statistical parameters
and then f is the free energy and
this represents like if you could be on
this
super smooth variational optimization
landscape
just with just as if you would really
want to be following
s hat but you actually have to follow s
with free energy
if we could be following f then we'd be
doing perfectly you just strictly cannot
do any better than that
however we can't directly track f so we
have to track
g which is the expectation of free
energy which we'll also
be able to look at okay any
thoughts or questions on notation anyone
seeing similar notation to
another field or a difference is there
something that we want to
that you'd imagine that a control theory
model would have that isn't in here
all right anyone can just raise their
hand at any time i'm not sure where
several of our colleagues have gone to
let's start by thinking about the
generative
model so this is a generative model p
of a bunch of variables and this is
going to be
kind of like what the organism is slash
does we're going to leave for a second
some of these
uh avenues that can be arising with the
niche symmetry which we've talked about
in the context of yellow bloombergs and
actual constance work
and there's the a lot of other things
that we've brought up let's just try to
isolate what's really relevant which is
that the agent is doing some type of an
implementation or is some kind of an
implementation
of a generative model of a couple of
things at once
it's generating a model of observations
through time the tilde on top of a
variable means through time
so observations through time and states
through time
you can think of as a function of policy
choices
pi and parameters of the model theta
so for example one of my parameters in
my theta is like
um if i get hit by a bike then it's
going to hurt
and then i my generative model is like
under the policy of looking both ways to
cross the road
i predict that my states will include
not being hit by a bike and so i won't
have any pain observations
under that same policy you could imagine
other types of state and observation
predictions
and then there are a few subsequent
mathematical
details about the insides of this
equation
it's a little bit bracketed no pun
intended and the top
and that's a shorthand and then we can
explore
and unpack it a few more levels so like
on that first row
we can see that that p o s pi theta
those um uh relationships
can be unpacked on the other side of the
equal sign the right hand side
to like just the probability of the
parameters existing
and then just the probability of the
policy existing multiplied by
this big other thing so why would that
be the case and we won't go through all
them in this detail but i think this
one's really helpful
to understand for active inference and
people just raise your
hand if you want to talk but just to
keep it like informational
and fun i'll just keep going until
somebody wants to ask a question
so the reason why p of pi
is there the probability of the policy
is like
if the policy is unrealistic you don't
even want to consider it you want to
basically
take unlikely policies impossible or
implausible policies
and systematically not consider them so
if if i'm trying to get out of the way
of the incoming bike
and i'm spending a lot of my time or my
clock cycles or a lot of my cognitive
infrastructure on
action strategies that involve me doing
a spider-man and
swinging from a building it's it's so
implausible that it's probably not going
to be effective
so we want to have something in our
model that represents likely
or possible policies being considered a
little bit more richly than
impli implausible policies and similarly
for p of data
which is a little more abstract because
it's just a parameter of the model but
it's like saying if it's an unlikely
parameter state it's also not worth
thinking too much about
i don't need to plan for it being
negative 40 in california
however our russian colleagues might
need to plan for that so it's going to
be
niche dependent and contextual whether
they need to plan for it or
not okay now let's go into this big pi
uh notation on the right side of the
right-hand side of the first
line of equations this is kind of like a
sigma sigma
adds up the elements of a series so like
sigma
of you know one plus one over two plus
one over four or something
and the pi is like a big multiplier and
it's saying from the first time step t
equals one through all of the time steps
big t
do this calculation what is the
calculation well it's the probability of
observations given states so in that's
observation at a certain time given the
state at that time so it's like
if this my estimate of the state not s
hat just
s with no hat if my observat if my state
is getting hit by a bike
there's going to be a very likely
observation of it hurting now that
doesn't say whether it's likely that i'm
getting hit by a bike it's just that
it is the case if it is that state then
there's going to be this observation
so that's the mapping between
observations and states
but it's observations probability
conditional
with a straight line on the state being
a certain way
okay that's the first part and the
second part is the probability of
that state arising conditional on
the previous state and the previous
policy and the parameter
and so again with this like bike model
it's like
what is the probability of my estimated
state s of t
at that time being hit by a bike given
that i wasn't being hit by a bike before
and my policy was looking both ways and
my theta model parameters tell me that
if i look both ways
it's really likely that i'll stay safe
for example
but stay safe isn't what's directly
specified by the model theta
it's actually specifying the likelihood
that a given policy and state mapping
are going to relate into the future with
a certain state
and then separately we can consider what
observations arise given a state
so it's a little bit like just
showing our work or being very clear
with what is the actual state of the
world
s hat what's the estimated state s what
are the
um mappings between policies states and
future states that's the right side
then what's the mapping between
observation observations and states in
that first part
okay any thoughts or questions because
the rest just kind of
continues from here in a similar
way um okay
we'll just keep on you know write down
any cool questions that are
coming to mind yvonne yeah go ahead
well you're muted first but yes then
continue
uh thank you could you please explain
one more time what
the small theta is it's a parameter of
its parameter of
the generative model but what is it yes
great question so we can actually
list we can go just just to show it in
the context
of the paper
and this by the way is in 3.1 but it
introduces
some of the other equations earlier
the theta are the details of the model
that relate the transition distribution
so
here we're looking at the states and the
previous policy
the s t minus 1 and pi of t minus 1 and
how given
theta it maps onto s of t so what is
theta
just from looking at the equation what
is theta going to be telling us it's
going to be telling us
how to map t minus 1's state and policy
state estimate and policy to the time
t states so let's just imagine that it
were a linear
model so i had a linear y equals mx
plus b and that was how we were going to
map
forward just totally a simple way to do
it then
theta would be like a vector containing
m
and b or theta would
the the domain how many dimensions of
the model
there are is how tall theta is going to
be in a sense
but theta are the parameters of the
model that
say what the transition distribution is
so uh yeah if it was a linear model then
theta is kind of like a wrapper around
the parameters of a linear model which
is the slope
m and then the elevation b
if this were a neural network with a
million parameters then theta would have
a million parameters
but it's kind of specifying the
likelihood that
the s of t minus 1 and pi of t minus one
map onto s of t so let's just say that
theta were one it just always map to one
for some reason then it's like whatever
these two are
it's gonna map to one that's like you
know f of x equals one yeah
that's the parameter that's the simplest
possible model is whatever the previous
states and policy are
we just map to one the next one would be
f
of uh x equals you know
insert your model there and so it is a
statistical point
about what's a parameter of a model and
like aren't these all parameters aren't
they all variables aren't they all
random variables
aren't they all going to be variables in
my python code yes to all of them
and that's why there's a little bit of
nuance and that's actually why we go
into the details here because you can
get pretty tangled up
and confused in the gray zone with
what's a
estimator and what what is the what is
the scientist estimating what is the
organism
estimating and a lot of times when we
just look at it it's a little bit
clearer
and we can think about a few layers of
unpacking with
the top most level of understanding is
this
uh big p top equation then we can unpack
it and define
well what does that really mean how do
we pull out the likelihood of the
parameters like the likelihood of theta
from the likelihood of policy
from this time dependent series how do
we define the distribution of p
of o of t given s of t like the second
line and so
uh each of these we get continue
unpacking and then each of them gets
specified
in functions in programming which
hopefully we'll
hear from alec about next week and there
sometimes it becomes another level of
clarity
when you look at the function definition
and you can say oh this function is
actually taking in variable a b and c
and then instead of seeing them as just
o sub t s sub t
the variable's name could be states
through time
or there might be a more descriptive
name so i know that especially if you
haven't looked at these equations for a
long time
or uh perhaps many equations for a long
time
sometimes like you get halfway down the
pages like what what is mu
of theta again but it is referring to
something specific
it's just a little bit of a shorthand to
make sure that
uh it fits visibly in a containable
space
so any other thoughts but good question
there with the parameters
so just one of the other um yeah yeah
sasha go ahead
um yeah thank you that was really useful
to walk through those steps
especially with the bike example and it
um kind of brings to mind
uh cases of
when something is very unlikely to
happen but
the um but it's certain to have uh
really bad outcomes so like
uh you know it's really going to hurt if
you get hit by a bike
versus things that are very likely to
happen but
don't have uh
but are not certain of having a bad
outcome like i don't know um
stubbing your toe on something um and so
these are things that are weighted
differently in in a model
uh based on the certainty of
uh and severity of the outcome so i
think that's really cool that this is
all incorporated into one model
yeah and when we specify why we're
making certain decisions
first we're just laying these equations
out to describe our little control
theory robot playing mario kart or
playing control theory games on
n64 but what if people had a little bit
more nuanced discussion
on collective decision-making topics
like somebody thinks well i think it's
totally unlikely
that the minimum miles per gallon of
cars could be 40 miles
by 2030 and someone else says that's
super likely
actually it's totally possible it's
totally likely i think that it can be
done or i think that this other
policy that you're suggesting is
implausible or
that it will have a bad outcome and so
people can disagree on whether a policy
is
actualizable or not for various reasons
it might come across as an ethical
constraint or a legal constraint or
logistical whatever it happens to be but
for whatever reason
that p of pi is low for them and then
we could unpack that and say okay all
these different elements are there
depending on the situation
and then somebody else might say i'm
with you on that outcome being unlikely
i just don't think it's that big of a
deal
saying oh yep i think that that kind of
a tsunami will happen once every 100
years
but i think that my transition matrix
from tsunami damage to being repaired
it just says that that's an easy
transition so we don't really need to
plan so heavily around it because when
it does happen we'll be able to rebuild
quickly for example
so these just allow us to give a little
bit more detail
into our infrastructure really our
architecture of decision making
and so i think blue that's definitely
where we can take it back to this
multiple scales of decision making
question
just to look through a couple of these
other equations before we move to q
here is the probability model of
observations given states
and so again that's like if the state my
estimated state not s hat
if my estimated state is getting hit by
a bike or stubbing my toe the
observations will be such and such in my
appropriate receptors
and that is given by a normal
distribution which means big
n on the variable o of t
and semicolon parameterized by mu
and sigma squared which are the mean and
the variance
and then those together mu and sigma
squared it turns out that those are the
hard parts to estimate
just like the problem or the challenge
of doing a linear regression on a
billion data points would be estimating
the mean and the variance
so you could fit the mean by adding up
all the numbers and then dividing it by
the amount of numbers
and for fitting the variance you could
use like a least squares model
but still that would be the computation
that you could do on pen and paper but
would just be very hard
in this case we're going to be doing
what is called
a amortized learning or a functional a
functional is like a function of another
function
and what we're going to be doing is
estimating
these statistical parameters with
this function lambda and then we're
going to fit the neural network
about that function lambda and so even
though neural networks are often
understood as providing additional
degrees of flexibility
like being able to learn conditional
relationships between data
um this took me a little bit to think
about but the neural network
is actually just facilitating us in this
model it's not saying that it would have
to be this way for all future active
learning
but it's actually still just fitting a
neural network model
of a normal distribution so we're
finding the parameters mu and sigma
use it which are very difficult to
estimate as you can imagine for a
non-linear control task
but we're still fitting it with a
function around
a normal so it's kind of this
interesting juxtaposition
of using advanced techniques like a
neural network
um high parametric techniques to
actually drill back down to a mean and a
variance
and then so this is this p-o-s-t is this
first part of this
um series and then s of t given the
previous state in the previous policy
is the second part here so this part
here gets
estimated with f of lambda and then the
uh second half of that series through
time has another normal distribution
with uh mu of theta and sigma squared of
theta
and then those two get looped up into a
functional
over those two similarly like s of t
is the right hand side what's being
conditioned on and we're going to be
estimating the
mean and variance of what is conditioned
on and then here it's similar
we're making a function that is
estimating what is being conditioned on
okay then we have this uh
early parts of the equation which is the
probability of the policy
is basically um it's going to be pretty
simple in this case but this is where
you could have a lot more degrees of
flexibility
this is sort of like an initial skeleton
paper as far as
what could be done with this framework
and that's kind of cool that's actually
what defines it in some ways as being
research and as being cutting edges this
isn't the
fine tuning of the parameters this is
laying out the framework that's going to
help us in a lot of other contexts
and then the probability of the policy
this is the part where we actually get
to free energy
okay so if we remember from the
notation slide f is like the free energy
where we strictly couldn't be making any
better decisions
if we knew that but g is the expected
free energy so just like
s is the hat s with the hat is real
state of the environment that's like
what we'd really want to track
and free energy would be what our policy
decisions would strictly want to be
converging upon but we don't get s
hat we get s and we don't get f we get g
what is g where does it come into play
well the probability of a policy
is now here sigma is actually not this
is sigma squared a statistical parameter
and it's kind of annoying but it is this
way that this sigma is a soft max
function which basically is like the
make a choice
function in math it just is s for
softmax here
sigma for variance here and what this is
going to be
is the negative expected free energy and
sometimes there's some negatives and
some logs getting thrown around and
these are all just ways to really just
say
pick the best given the expected free
energy
of policy and so this is how we get to
certain statements which have definitely
been
discussed on this uh live stream before
where it's like the agent picks the most
likely policy
and it's like wait but is it likely for
me to win or lose
what if it's a i know that it's unlikely
for me to win or lose
um if it's 100 that i'm going to win how
is that me picking the most likely
policy
but that's actually what um is happening
but it's not just simply the likeliest
policy um there's a little bit more
nuance which we'll look into with g
okay so that was sort of the p side
let's
maybe a little bit more quickly because
we will recognize a lot of the variables
and also
a lot of the structural relationships
between equations
here's the cube so we have p and q
between the agent and the environment
in a sense these are the two
distributions that are linking it not
that one is being computed by one or one
is computed by the other
but thinking about in that bayesian
computationalist framework where we have
like the data
going in one model goes to the hyper
parameters and then the hyper parameters
generate
leading to um the uh hey shannon and
welcome back
if we if yeah um going back to the
observed states of the world
so q is going to be distinguished from p
p is this implementation of the
generative model of the world
where is q is going to very distinctly
have different parameters
instead of p o s pi theta here we have q
of s through time policies and theta so
this is a slightly simpler
uh mathematical formulation and
it is going to be unpacked as
q of the states through time and the
policy and the model parameters
is again uh we see the likelihood of the
model parameters
and the likelihood of the policy coming
out in front
um and these are similar to the p but p
doesn't have to equal q
and then a slightly simpler
uh piece here which is just about the
states given the observations
uh and so this is like literally given
the retina
shadows what is the state estimate of
the world
so this is um it's like here in
in p if we look at just
this uh second line this is the
probability of observations given states
so this is given that it's daytime
there should be a lot of photons if the
estimated state of the world is night
time there shouldn't be any photons pos
okay but it's o given s
now in q we actually have
s given o so the p is different than the
q but also the orders have switched
this is called a recognition
distribution
because we're basically doing an
estimation of the states
given the observations so q is kind of
like the incoming
way that the observations are going to
be connected to the state estimators of
the world
that's the recognition but then the
generative model which is the p
that entails understanding what the
hidden states of the world are
s and your estimates of them that is and
then
generating out observations that are
linked up to policy
and so here there's a slightly different
way that the
parameters of this model and that the um
policy
mapping is done with these a few more
statistical parameters
but similarly which we don't need to go
into too much detail in here is
these are also going to be distributed
using some statistical distribution
that's going to help us
estimate them and similarly we can take
all the statistical parameters
so for a normal distribution it's a two
parameter model
mean and variance but you could have
distributions with one or with more than
two
variables but whatever number of
statistical variables you want to
estimate
we're just going to wrap them into a
function and figure out some way to
estimate them
and so that's a degree of freedom
you can think of in the model is that
there's different you could flip out
this normal for some other type of
distribution
or you could have another way to
estimate the
distribution's normality okay
that's p and q but it is really
important and interesting what they are
any thoughts or questions or we can just
keep cruising
okay yeah um alec
uh yeah i want to
ask uh maybe in terms of so p
is for generative model q
is for recognition distribution and
recognition model
and as we discussed in previous session
a generative model exists or
acts uh in uh dynamics
so you have uh generative model in some
way of
it's like was example with dominos so
when you act
and act in accordance to this generative
model
and in example of road and
a bike this generative model
and defines the way you are looking on
both ways and when go if you don't see a
bike
and uh in this terms so
what will be a recognition distribution
recognition model
it's will be understanding how bike is
looks like
or what is rule how road
is looks like and so on or it's the
wrong direction for my
understanding a good question and it was
it was actually
i had to email alec to clarify a few
things
because i looked at this q distribution
i thought wait it's a recognition
distribution
but where are the observations how can q
be recognition when there's no
observations
and then it turns out there are
observations that are
uh related to q but it's he just said
basically it's the norm
in the recognition distribution
literature like this part of the
bayesian
computational fields this is what they
call those two
models the recognition distribution
which is from the observations
to the generative model parameters which
ironically as a norm
doesn't include the uh observation
and then the generative model again is
the one that's going from the
organisms parameter estimates the world
to predicted observations and that's how
expectation maximization works
now we had all these interesting
discussions alex which you're alluding
to
of for example does the organism have
the internal model
that's generative or is the generative
model enacted
in terms of the relationship is it
that's the internalism versus
externalism discussion that we had and
so i'm going to try to
combine what alec informed me about as
well as channel a little maxwell here
and i think the answer is going to be
there's multiple philosophical lenses
that you could apply um to real-world
situations
and this is only what is specified in
the math and in the programming
and so if you include it if you include
in your
recognition distribution is the uh
luminosity
and the edge and the color and those are
the observations
and you're recognizing you're doing
image classification on recognizing a
bike
just simplifying it but there it is then
that is
strictly only what is in the recognition
distribution it's going to be about the
mapping of the observations
um of the state's given observations and
your observations could include
those variables that we just talked
about so if it's being conditioned on
that then that's what's happening
and then even given a single
formalization of like okay the
observations are
the um overall brightness and the amount
of movement or something like whatever
it happens to be
it could still be a a pluralistic
philosophical scenario
where somebody could say okay that's a
modeling convenience but
really those observations are in the
space between the organism and the
environment
and someone else says yep it's a
modeling convenience but i think those
parameters
are something about the neural firing
and someone else says it's both of them
and someone else said so i would be open
to
uh correction and also would love to
hear alex
perspective on this but i think the
answer would be these papers that we
read tale of two densities
and integrating externalism and
internalism are actually
about how by framing it within active
inference
we move beyond those philosophical
debates or another way to say that is
build a bigger tent that includes both
of those perspectives
um in a way that's compatibilist because
those are the debates that people had
about these models so like in the
reinforcement learning literature it's
like
okay is the reward the signal
you know is it a pleasing you know
aesthetic body form
is that the reward or is that the signal
of the reward
and if it is the reward then isn't that
a circular definition like organisms
seek out what's rewarding
but it's not like you just want to see
the aesthetics there might be some
second
intention for example and so how do you
actually draw
out these questions is it happening in
the organism's head with a reward or is
it enacted
and that was sort of the philosophical
groundwork
and now we're for a minute putting those
bags
of all different stripes down and
looking at just the way that we're gonna
specify it and how it plays out in
simulations
knowing that potentially one person
might have a bayesian structural
computationalist perspective of these
examples we're going to look at in a
second
and somebody else might take a heavily
inactive
example they might say oh well the the
cart that's on the hill
it's like the cart hill combo organism
that's being or something like that but
at the end
whether the person thinks that it's
enacted or it's just a bayesian
computationalist approach
they're still going to at least be able
to point to the same equations and
ultimately the same code as well so
that's like uh hopefully explanation of
how the active inference framework and
the specifics
end up unifying these general debates
which potentially without such a
unifying framework it'd be intractable
because somebody would say okay well i
think that q is happening in the brain
the organism
somebody else says i think that q
happens in between the niche and the
organism someone else says i think q's a
modeling shorthand someone says i agree
with person one and three
or one and two and now we're saying okay
they're kind of
all correct and just all ways that we
can phrase
the specifics of what we're talking
about here so not that everyone's
correct because everyone's correct and
there is no wrong answer
but under this reconceptualization
of action and inference we find that
some of these previous questions or
phrasings
become like yes and instead of either
slash or
okay to move a little bit more quickly
just through these
uh a few equations before we can i think
just highlight a little bit
on the experiments and then probably
return to the multi-scale
question that we talked about earlier
and also about what other areas could
control be interesting in and also what
questions would we want to
ask alec and other attendees next week
here is equation one and this
i put after because i think it helps to
understand that p and q and
the mappings but this is what is
ultimately being minimized so again
we don't get f that's the real free
energy and that's
the one that we would really want to be
converging towards
which as they put it um converging
towards an approximation of the
posterior distribution of
prop the p model of states policies and
parameters given observations so that
would be like the best possible
state trajectory through time and the
best possible policy
given the observations of the world you
know given that bitcoin is at this value
and ethereum's at this value
the state trajectory that's the best for
me entails this policy
so that's clearly what we want to know
but that is intractable
so we needed to use some type of a
convergence towards this intractability
and this is where a lot of the more
specific and technical details related
to for example
the kobeck liblar informational
divergence
the informational distance between two
distributions is related
because um there's those distance
metrics are bounded at zero
like you if two distributions are
identical their distance is zero
and as they get more and more distant
that number strictly increases
and so it turns out that there's some
ways to have like this hypothetical
perfect distribution
and then have a distance between where
you're really at
and this hypothetical perfect
distribution which is always a positive
distance
and then try to converge towards that
hypothetical perfect position
by minimizing the distance function and
that distance function is informational
but it still is a distance metric
in a certain way and wrote out a few
details um the e is the expectation so
it's expectation
of states through time policies and
model parameters
and it's going to be something that
combines the q
and the p the natural log which makes it
a little bit easier to do the machine
learning
techniques and a few other benefits
scaling it
and bringing certain values below the
number line
and then that is going to be always
greater than or equal to
that's this part right here than just
the observe
the observations so it turns out that by
doing this estimator
we can bound um some but there's a few
things that get bounded but they're not
even all phrased here
um yep
so the last thing i wrote there was
given that the q is um
focusing on basically between p and q
you get all the parameters
so what you can do by optimizing the
recognition density and the generative
model
back and forth whether actually like a
two-cycle engine like expectation
maximization which is how it gets
implemented in code
or dynamically and continuously as in
the case of
an active organismal behavior
what has to get learnt upon but here
what tractably can be learnt upon and
conditioned upon
is that mapping of how observations
states and policies are linked
in a nuanced nexus where they're all
taken into account
rather than running a classifier that
goes from just observations to states
and then a second layer model from
states to policies
that would be a little bit more along
the lines of traditional machine
learning
but this is why it's a different
approach okay
then um again we don't get g
uh we or we don't get f we only get g so
here is another
phrasing of f that's being played out
through time
so here is um building on three and four
we're looking at the variational free
energy not just for an instant
here this is like a kind of timeless
understanding of free energy you don't
see t
in here it's through time with the s
tilde and the o tilde but it's like
not a specific times and then this one
is actually
a function through time this is
observation t so this is like
that specific observation and then
here's where we see
the divergence the d distance divergence
the kl distance between the q and the p
and those are
not usually exchangeable so like this
it's not like driving between two cities
so this um section again you can
unpack some of what the equations
actually say
but this learning and inference section
talks about
how to update or do inference
do learning based upon the data of these
parameters
here is where we get to g so we don't
get f we only get to estimate g
so the way i kind of broke this down was
we want to do more than just
update our internal model to balance the
price on observations
so if all you wanted to do was test
retest accuracy on an image classifier
data set
all you'd have to do would be bound
surprise on the cross-validated
versions of that data um or on
subsample or testing and training splits
but we want to actually do a few
different things we want to reduce our
uncertainty in the future
so that's tau or the cursive t don't
know which way you'd say it
in terms of the policies that we take
now so it's quite different than just
minimizing our surprise about a linear
aggressor given a static data set
we want to reduce our uncertainty about
observations in the future
as a function of the policies we're
taking now and this minimizable
this tractable expected free energy
function g
takes as arguments policy and the future
time point
so as a function of the policies that
are um available and you know two years
in the future
how am i gonna manage certain
aspects of life and it's gonna be an
expectation
that's conditional on um uh
several things conditional mainly we can
highlight is conditional on policy
we're doing an expectation that's
conditioned on policy because we want to
know something
about the states of the world and the
observations and the estimated states of
the world as well
given a policy and then that
is going to be strictly bigger um and so
natural log
that means that it's like basically
worse in some ways but it depends a lot
on whether it's like positive or
negative
that's kind of confusing stuff sometimes
um like whether it's a negative log or
like the subtracting or the positive log
and what it's always bigger than is the
negative
expectations of the observed states in
the future given a policy me
here's me observing that i have 50
bitcoin um
and that's this part too the p of
observations given policy
so what i'd really like to know would be
uh
some type of model that just tells me
what states i can expect
in the future what observations i can
expect in the future
um which relate to the states because of
the uh estimating the states
given the observations but here we're
going for the observations given the
policy
and it's the uh log and then
this last part is kind of the important
part which is the log of the generative
model which is the observations given
the policy that's how things will go
that's
well if we take this policy on miles per
gallon then we will go
between uh you know 1.5 and 2 degrees
celsius
now there's so many degrees of freedom
that go into that but that's like
what we'd want to estimate would be
relating
how policies literally are going to play
into observations
which then tell us about states the
world estimated like s without a hat
which should be hopefully related to s
with a hat the real states of the world
but still the focus here is on the
observations
that are conditioned on policy that kind
of takes us to
policy selection and they
write that policy selection is achieved
by updating q
in order to write to minimize f via
g and the
uh need for this paper was that
when you have a short temporal horizon
you can just run out
every possible policy like every
possible set of five chess moves or
every possible set of all the
tic-tac-toe moves there can't be more
than nine moves in a game
every single step if the branching is
small and the time horizon is short
you can evaluate g in full so it becomes
rather than sampling over a distribution
literally just calculating a table and
then sorting
however when you have deep temporal
horizons you can't really evaluate the
full branching tree because there's too
many options
so you have to sample from that
distribution so that's the sampling
problem
the second prop and that's the deep
counterfactual sampling problem which is
even difficult or
under uncertainty the second part is the
mario kart paradigm
which is that in continuous action
spaces there are infinite policies
meaning that some other way is going to
have to come into play because
not just are we sampling uh deep through
time
we're sampling potentially related to
counterfactuals which there's infinite
counter factuals
and we're talking about continuous
action spaces where there's infinite
policies
so if my only trading affordances are
should i have
zero or one or two bitcoin then
i could ask which one of those three
options discreetly is better
but if there's infinite and i can do
continuous variables
uh even smaller than one you know
breakdowns like then should i do
1.0001 what if that's very different
than 1.0002
now you might say well those two should
be super similar and you should be able
just to sample every
little interval and estimate the
distribution right
if it's a smooth distribution then it's
going to be easy to optimize maybe you
could discretize it
maybe you could do some other way to do
smooth optimization but the problem is
actions and policies are not smooth so
maybe if you're going into that turn in
mario kart
you could aim at the corner and just try
to take it as fast as you can
or you could slow down and do a slightly
different angle or you could do some
other skidding maneuver
so there's multiple separate ways that
you're going to be able to take this
turn
potentially with different risks and
reward and they're all very nuanced
so that is why the deep through time and
counter factual aspects
respectively uh which aren't as much
dealt with here at counterfactuals but
through time absolutely is
and then the continuous actions which is
really the key
introduction of this model that takes it
out of the paradigm of
classifying images and puts it into the
paradigm of
continuous control theory and then it
turns out that
there's a lot of trajectories through
time given how things can go
and so there's some uh implementation of
a way to sample
trajectories that is utilizing what's
called a monte carlo sampling approach
or mc and uh there's the markov chain
monte carlo sampling m c m c m c squared
um and monte carlo just means that it's
uh related to monte carlo being a card
playing
reference in english and it's like the
way that you can shuffle a deck is so
big
how are you gonna estimate the number of
ways that you can get a royal flush or a
pair of fours or something like that
instead of just actually doing well it's
1 in 24 times 1 and 52 times 3 over 52.
the way you do it is you just sample
randomly and then you say okay i took a
billion samples and
1 million of them had this feature and
then you just take the ratio as your
estimate so it's a sampling and that
kind of
harkens back to earlier where we wanted
to talk about getting the efficient
sampling because that's kind of what
it's about
is in the markov or sorry in the monte
carlo
sampler which could be markov chain
based we want to get
good sampling we don't want to sample
only the hands with a royal flush
like if we had a poor randomizer because
then we're going to get an estimate
that's wrong
all right then they go into a little bit
more detail
about the g the estimated or the
expected free energy
which is still as it was before about
policy in the future
and now it's going to be uh this
broken down and this is also where they
draw some of the homologies to
reinforcement learning
and info gain into the uh
the informational gain kind of like the
reward and the info
so this is where the explore exploit
also comes into play
which is that if one is only optimizing
locally
they may be exploiting they may be
getting reward for a short period of
time but then it doesn't lead
to a um like
we'll see in the hill climber example
but if you just reward
only and only exploit sometimes you
don't do very well but if you just
explore
you might not ever get to exploit
anywhere good and so the whole trade-off
and the whole challenge of modeling is
this balance between explore and exploit
between searching deeply and searching
broadly
and so the holy grail would be the right
way
to search deeply down the routes that
are interesting and informative
but not down the ones that don't tell
you that much but we don't know which
paths are going to be informative or not
until we go down them however if we have
a deep generative model
we can say in terms of me winning this
chess game
this branch is not informative for me to
search down
not because there aren't trillions of
options but because i have two castles
and they have no pieces
other than their king so i'm gonna win
so in terms of me winning
it doesn't give me any information to
keep on searching down that route i
already know i'm gonna win
and then there might be another avenue
where there's fewer options per se like
less branching
but there's more uncertainty that's
resolvable more infogaine is possible
with respect to the policies and winning
all right let's just do a little bit on
the experiments before we close out so
the two experiments that they
go into so hopefully all of you
experimentalists
um buy sasha um hopefully all you
experimentalists will like this part
and the two examples are the mountain
car and the uh
inverted pendulum task and the hopper
task so the mountain car
is an example of exploration so what's
being learnt
is the policy between position and
velocity
and then getting higher up the reward
function is like getting higher up and
so
the car doesn't have a strong enough
engine just to drive up to the flag so
it's going to drive up
and then the perfect policy would be
right when you're stopped
flip the engine into reverse and keep in
reverse until you stop on this side
and then get a little bit higher up this
way but this shows you why you can't
locally optimize why you need to explore
because let's just say you're driving
uphill you're slowing down you're
slowing down
you start slipping back slipping back
and you're like no stay on the gas
continue accelerating forward now you're
slowing your descent
so when you get to here you're not
moving that fast
so then when you're on this side you'd
say no no i still want to get to the
flag
and so you end up just sort of like
being very shallow down and focusing a
lot of your time here
on the um middle and on the right side
so if you just
simply move towards the flag you're
probably not going to get there
if the engine is too weak however if you
actually say i want to explore i want a
policy that helps me increase my
range so i want to go as far as i can
here and then wow if i enact a policy
where as soon as i hit my maxima i just
try to explore
further this way and then i enact a
policy switch and go back to going this
way wow
i might actually reach the goal purely
as a function of exploring
now again this is like a little model
situation
where it turns out that exploring does
help one realize
the goal that's not always the case but
it isolates that feature of the model
needing to be able to explore the second
case
in the exploit paradigms it's usually a
little bit more obvious
what needs to be exploited and about
whether you're doing it well or not so
in the inverted pendulum task it's like
a railroad car
on a rail and there's a heavy ball m
that's on top of this pendulum that's
inverted
and then the car can like move backwards
and that kind of
moves this joint to the left and that
pushes the um pendulum
in this case would straighten it out
whereas if this car starts taking off to
the right
then this pendulum is just going to fall
and so the reward is the height of the
pendulum so it's trying to maximize its
reward
by enacting a policy and so the policy
that's best
would be to keep on exploiting that
perfectly straight up line where you
actually are in the zone of optimal
control
and then the exploit task on the right
is about
increasing the distance that's traveled
by a little jumping
thing does anyone else have any like
thoughts on explore exploit
or um what what else does that yeah go
ahead blue
so this i thought was super interesting
um as i was unpacking
this paper so and
maybe i should just kind of like lay a
little bit of this out there so the
reward
is only given in this extrinsic
value which is like the exploit portion
of the free energy equation
like given in number six and so you know
i don't know you didn't say it
explicitly but like here in the
exploration
experiments the reward just uses that
um exploit parameter and doesn't do any
exploration based
on state or parameter information gain
and then
in the exploit task it only uses that
exploitation parameter
so like there's no need for exploration
i just thought that that was super
interesting and like what would happen
if they included exploration
in this explore in the exploitation um
paradigm so like why did they leave that
out like it was just kind of weird to me
well good question like that makes me
think about let's say there's some parts
of the railroad track
where it's different angles and so
yes you want to maintain the pendulum
being upright but also you might want to
explore around a little bit
to find a region where you can control
it better so that actually makes me
think of like doing a track stand on my
bicycle
there's some times where there's some
slopes of pavement that are easy to do a
track stand on and some are really hard
to do it
but the way you get from a hard position
into an easier part of payment you have
to explore and that means breaking the
track stand
so definitely real control tasks
are related to the combination of
explore and exploit why did they use
these two
i think that the reason why and let's
hear from alec as to the real answer
is that these are part of the open ai
benchmarking
set of like little micro computable
benchmarks for learning algorithms
here's the open eye
ai um let's see if we can even open it
here yeah
so like here's their website and uh
there's
a bunch of uh documentable cases
that allow comparison between different
machine learning algorithms and so i
think they're just outlining
the minimal single dimensional like sort
of extreme
classic test cases there's a ton of
cases where we can already see it
wouldn't work like a double pendulum
that's chaotic or
there's other kinds of things that this
model just doesn't even try to do
but this allows us to directly compare
two
other algorithms on the exact same task
instead of inventing something that
would like either
not take advantage of active inferences
strength or
be like kind of an unfair example by
making it
too nuanced like if we added in a reward
another type of something that a
generative model could take advantage of
then we couldn't compare it to some of
these other agents that don't use that
kind of information
is that i just think they were using the
minimal case to ex
to demonstrate what explore and exploit
could look like and then future work
hopefully would be about
things that involve both right and so i
get that and but it just was
like interesting to me then i guess
because
the there's no reward in the exploit
parameter
that that's why they had to keep the
exploit parameter in the explore task
do you know what i mean like what i just
wonder what would be the results if you
took
out the exploit parameter from the
explore task would it then not succeed
because it just would wander around
aimlessly
or would wandering around aimlessly or
like without a reward to get higher
would that just produce like a random
result do you see what i mean i see what
you mean
so there's there's one there's one
driving strategy
where it's truly just making policy
that's unrelated to its elevation
and um that depending on how that plays
out it might get
somewhere it might not most likely not
because the space of the strategies with
relationship to getting the flag is
low but yes i i i agree that's an
interesting question like
when is it enough to just explore
like when is novelty search simply
enough
when my novelty search be strictly the
best
when my novelty search eighty percent
plus
twenty percent let's keep a little
reminder of our elevation when might
that be
relevant and tractable strategy which
parts of these
explore and exploit are calculatable for
example
it might make sense to evaluate or
exploit
a current distributional value but
how do we explore the space of economic
strategies like
i can't explore every single possible
economic strategy but i might be able to
exploit
some ratio by doing arbitrage so there's
some control tasks where
the exploitation is really
straightforward and visible and the
exploration's hard and then there's
other ones where
maybe this car can't see the flag so
maybe exploring is the only thing it can
do
and so the really great question those
are kind of
interesting about these things being
traded off so there's the explore
exploit trade-off
and how that gets implemented there's
also the model
adequacy minus complexity which is we
want a good model but not too complex or
over fit one
so there's no a priori best way to trade
off those two
and then um there there's just all these
interesting
trade-offs that we can explore the space
of let's just look at what the results
were
so here the x axis is like where
positions is from
the other side farther to um 0.5 which i
guess could be the flag
or at least close to it i try to line it
up maybe it's
the other way or something like that but
we can see that the position of the
greedy
agent who just drives up up up up and
says no and then just goes up
no this one stays tightly bounded
in a medium velocity uh regime
and within a sort of sampling a ton from
this part of the distribution
think about that like an upside down
bell curve and it's like sampling a ton
from right here but it's not sampling
from up here so that's how there's a
relationship between sampling and
control
because to get to certain states it's
like sampling those states
the epsilon uh greedy agent which has a
slightly different implementation
it does sometimes appear to get outside
maybe
by the end if it's 100 epochs it was
starting to take some
trips out further but and at slightly
higher
uh speeds and slightly further out but
it doesn't spend most of its time doing
so
the active inference learner of course
they wrote the paper
so it's going to be the one that
succeeds but it does
in 100 epochs learn very fast and it
does get to some pretty high speeds and
some pretty
distant positions and then just briefly
to like compare it with the other
task the two exploit tasks
are laid out here and they are comparing
it to this ddpg
agent which is a model free learner and
so people can look into details or one
could imagine that maybe there's other
algorithms they could test it against
these are all the kinds of things we can
ask alec about
but we can see that um a which is the
same as c
c is just the first part of a i just
zoomed in on really close
but it's like right away in both of
these after either like
five epochs like five trials five
seconds
or um after maybe 30 or 40 or 50
the active inference learner just starts
to take off in terms of
once it's hit on a solution sometimes it
just
it strictly improves it with some noise
whereas
the ddpg the two things that you see are
first off it spends a ton of time near
the baseline
so it takes a while before it locks on
to any useful combination of parameters
and then when it gets off baseline
it ends up um sometimes succeeding
but still um it's like
perhaps because it's locally optimizing
or we can ask why it is
but they're just not sampling highly
rewarding states
even after it gets off the baseline it
does stay off baseline but it doesn't
ever get as high as the active inference
learner does
extremely rapidly so this is kind of
where they're
drawing their evidence for the claims
about
the potential superiority or preference
for active inference
now yes you could probably train a ddpg
on some massive data set and get better
performance than they got they probably
just used a
straightforward implementation so that's
where research happens
that's what people study is okay well
can we do a dd pg whatever that is
plus this other feature that is being
used by this other group or
what is it that's actually causing the
active inference learner to get off the
ground so fast and
could we even get it off the ground
faster in the case of this hopper task
or
could we make a more reliable reward
function for the inverted pendulum task
but this is control theory at its finest
really and so this is what it's all
about
is learning policies that map states
onto reward
so those are the key pieces that's why
we spent so much time talking about the
equations that are relating between
observations state estimates and
policies
because that's what it's all about is
the observations coming in
and then the policies being selected
based upon the estimated states of the
world
and then actions coming out that's the
markov blanket
of the organism's perspective at least
and then outside
uh world in these examples is simple and
unchanging like gravity is gravity for
the pendulum and for the hopper
and it's not changing but we can start
to think about well what if there was
a diurnal gravity rhythm
how would the control theory change well
there could be a generative model
in the agent's control uh mapping of
those
p and q that involve some sort of is it
day or night and then i have a
conditional policy whether i think it's
day or night so we can kind of
see how it starts adding layers there
and
yeah that's basically it
but let's have any last thoughts does
anyone like
what was something cool or unexpected
what's something they'd like to ask alec
about
or that they're curious to learn more
about now
chill oh shannon go ahead
hey um yeah so i was thinking about um
blue's question
and why not use the um exploration
component in these
inverted pendulum and hopper tasks and
wouldn't it be
because there's kind of only one state
that is maximum reward so for completely
vertical
or if we hop as far as possible but if
there were
potential states that would have
differing values of reward then we might
expect to see something different if we
use the
the exploration component of the active
reference model
great point like if it were a bimodal
distribution
then you can't just try to keep it as
close to the maximum height as possible
because you wouldn't know if you were
locally optimizing or
globally optimizing and you might want
to be sampling across the whole
distribution just so
you know or you might want to spend a
lot of time at rewarding states but
still
have some understanding of the total
distribution to understand if there
might be
more rewarding states that you're just
not visiting at all that is the whole
challenge of local and global
optimization
and so you're right that in this
mountain car example
local optimization is global you're
going to get to the best flag
just by ex by you know so to speak i
know this was in the explore
strategy but in this one it's clear as
you brought up if you're
having the pendulum at the maximum
height you're simply doing as well as
you can
period you don't need to explore other
ways you could do a loop-de-loop and
that's the challenge though is you gotta
you gotta walk through the valley of
death
to get from the local optima to the
global and that's where these algorithms
uh dare not tread because they have to
walk
through improbable or non-preferable
like moving away from your target states
in order to get to the next peak which
might be absolutely higher
in the exploit paradigm or might reveal
new territory in the explore paradigm
so there's reasons why you want to get
through the valley of low likelihood
whether you're exploring or exploiting
or a combination
and that is where there's so many
options there's so many weeds and
tangles in the valley
that the way that we're going to cut
through it with a machete is infogain
and we're going to explore paths through
the valley that are the most informative
for us
given our understanding of our own
policies
and so that's like if you have a 4x4
versus
a small team versus you're a drone
different policies different affordances
mean that you're going to be exploring
this valley differently
and then there's whether you're
exploring for the sake of exploring and
learning new turf or whether you're
exploiting because you just want to have
a high elevation or whether it's a
little of both
those are all some nuance you can add in
but the insight of active inference is
like
let's actually think about what would be
informative trajectories to take through
that valley
based upon a generative model of the
landscape and
taking our own policy affordances into
account if you don't have a generative
model landscape
you're going to be doing something like
locally just going downhill or locally
going uphill
so you need a deeper generative model
landscape and if you don't take your
affordances into account
then you're lost because you might be
unknowingly optimizing something that's
going to be
appropriate for you know the drone to
fly over but then you're on the ground
so you actually can't make it up that
hill
but it's a policy that might work for a
different organism and it's just not the
one that works for you i know we're kind
of like mixing metaphors but i think
it's a fun
way to think about these optimizations
because we are implementing a control
process something that we modeled with
control theory and then also we're
seeing it play out in like a very
abstract computational
framework here cool
yep so then they talk about the
relationship with previous work i think
i'll just put it on the screen people
can
um pause it if they want to look but
with that i'll just say thanks to
our cohort here for participating super
interesting stuff and next week we hope
to have alec
on to discuss some of these questions so
you can check the calendar event to
provide a follow-up
survey where you can add some details
how could we improve or
what questions would you like to hear
conveyed in 8.2
and for those who are not participating
live please provide us with feedback or
suggestions or
questions that we can cover and just
stay in touch but that was really great
so thanks
a lot everyone for the discussion