hello and welcome
everyone this is the active inference
live stream it is act
imp live stream 8.2 and it is november
17 2020
so welcome everyone listeners and
participants
welcome to team com everyone we are an
experiment in online team
communication learning and practice
related to active inference
you can find us at our website our
twitter
our email on our public key base team or
on youtube this is a recorded and an
archived live stream so please do
provide us with feedback so that we can
improve on our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are
welcome here in learning about these
questions and as far as video etiquette
for live streams goes
just remember to mute if there's noise
in the background and raise your hands
so we can hear from everyone on the
stack
use respectful speech behavior etc
today in exciting act imp stream 8.2
we are going to have introductions and
warm-ups and then
we will at whatever rate make sense
welcome shannon we will walk through the
sections of 8.2
as with 8.0 and 8.1 we are going to be
discussing the paper scaling active
inference by chance at all 2019
and alec thanks so much for coming on to
the show today
we're going to talk about the goals in
the roadmap of the paper hopefully
from the author's perspective we'll then
have a little pause just for an open
q a because there's a lot of different
directions this paper can take one so
we'll just pause there
and then we'll continue through the
figures just two of them
and just address a few different domains
of follow-up questions about the paper
and then if we want to slash still have
time
we can go through some of the notation
and math again
for the rest of 2020 we are going to be
moving into
papers 9 10 and 11. so check it out on
twitter
paper 9 is going to be about
consciousness
paper 10 is about scripts and about
social interactions in paper 11 is about
modeling under the sophisticated
effective inference framework
for the intros and warm-ups if everyone
could just introduce
their name and their location whatever
else they'd like to state especially
our first time guests and then just pass
to somebody who has not spoken
so i'll start i'm daniel i'm in
california
and i will pass it to alec
hey everyone uh yeah i'm alex chance uh
i'm based
in brighton um final year phd student
at sussex and thanks for having me on
the stream
we will go to um sasha
hi my name is sasha i'm also a graduate
student
and i'm based out of davis california
i will pass it to stephen
stephen you're unmuted but um it doesn't
have any sound maybe just reload and
temporarily let's just go to shannon
hi guys i'm shannon i'm
based at the university california in
merced but currently in south dakota
i'll pass it to blue
hi i'm blue knight i am an independent
research consultant
and i am based out of new mexico i will
pass it to
alex
hi my name is alex i'm in moscow russia
and i'm a researcher in systems
management school
and i pass it to v1
hi my name is iran i'm in russia moscow
and i pass it to stephen
steven are you here i'm gonna try again
does that work yes
yep okay hi i'm steven i'm based in
toronto i'm actually studying a
practice-based phd through canterbury
christchurch university in the uk
and i'm pleased to be here and now
hi i'm now andrews um and
i'm in cincinnati doing a phd
cool a lot of different stages and areas
so it will be a great
discussion to bring to the technical
side with this paper for the
warm-up questions people can just raise
their hand as they'd like to speak
and i will just put up the first two
questions
they are for today's discussion what is
something that you are excited about
and then the second question is what is
a question
you're wondering about so while people
are thinking about it or
raising their hand one question i was
wondering about was how do we
trade off between explore and exploit in
the two figures
we saw examples of explore or exploit
but what
is required to enact something that is
able to
mediate between the two of them or find
a compromise between those two
strategies anyone
have any thoughts or want to raise their
hand
steven yeah i'm also excited about the
explore
um and the exploit side as well to be
honest because i think
that opens up a big shift in the way
that we socially interact in the way
that we organize ourselves
so trying to look at a real foundational
way to sort of approach that
is going to be quite helpful i think in
a lot of fields of practice
cool alec and then anyone else who
raises their hand
yeah am i i'm neither don't need to know
you sound good sound good
uh i just wanted to comment on your
comment
because i'm also very interested in that
but i guess i'll go on the
record saying that i'm not not convinced
that active inference
provides sometimes it's said to provide
the solution for the explore exploit
that and i i don't
think it does uh i think it really
recasts it so
you know now it's not a question of
bouncing
exploration exploitation but uh they're
both zoomed into this
different objective function but in
practice uh
there isn't a sort of magic balancing
act that you
you get out of this um so i think it's a
good way to recast the exploration
expectations
but certainly not a solution to the
problem awesome
blue so i kind of have like a tangential
question i and thank you alex for your
comments
because it just plays right into i think
what's missing
it's very clear that um if the
environment is homogeneous
there's no real need for exploration
because
the agent is not going to gain any you
know any additional progress by
exploring the environment but
i just wonder where autonomy factors in
right like
so you know some agents have more or
less control over their environment
and there's no like real room for this
or not that i've seen anyway in
the um active inference framework like
where the
differing levels of autonomy of the
agent play into
the need to explore versus exploit
cool good question stephen
yeah i think that that point about how
to
look at the agent starts to bring in the
inactive
component a lot more i think and the
generative model that's kind of sitting
inside
the person and existential kind of
sense-making
so i think that's that also yeah it's
like pushing this back
from a real world perspective and saying
okay
maybe we need to work back the other way
from complex
multi-sensory experiences towards active
inference as well as
using active inference to do modeling of
maybe kind of very
clean sort of low dimensional
approaches it's like should we also be
coming back from the other direction
um and i did i've got an activity called
conceptual action sociology an activity
where people move around space to
understand
how their orientation is during a moment
of encounter
and i've asked people to unpack it in
terms of the three different areas of
active inference the sort of pragmatic
gain
epistemic foraging or or
risk mitigation or salience and it's
actually really interesting
when they break it down that way and
start to think about what was i trying
to do
but from that kind of high dimensional
kind of
synthesis of being in a really immersive
moment
and they actually people seem to who
don't know anything about active
inference
actually we're quite intuitively seeing
quite a lot of shifts in those three
different areas of focus depending on
the type of
um event or moment that they were
reflecting on
because they were going back to an event
and thinking about the focus of their
attention at that
particular moment in time and how much
were they sort of bringing these three
areas in
and then i suppose between that you
could infer something about
the exploration sort of
desire to learn or the exploitation
gain but i i agree i think it does
depend on the moment that's in question
so yeah there's a few things that kind
of this is sort of
tapping into which i'm really interested
in cool
and to tie that just together with a
recast idea from alec
it's um kind of like nature nurture
explore exploit
people don't know about these binaries
they're not natural kinds until they're
taught them
and then the resolution to these kinds
of dichotomies or binaries false or not
is not some parameter that varies from
zero to one that trades off
for example when evelyn fox keller was
moving beyond nature and nurture it's
the mirage of a space between it's about
reconsidering the situation
so that there doesn't have to be
something like a bipartition
so that's definitely the direction that
we will try to take it because it's a
really cool idea
the second or i guess the last warm-up
question is
and on a related note what would be an
interesting
control system or any system to model
with active inference
so we're going to go into like a trolley
car and a
um hopper i guess and a pendulum
and i think it'll be fun to hear about
those but um we heard
about this the social and the spatial
there's questions that we've raised
about biology
communication anything else that
somebody wants to
bring up or whether it's yeah mel please
and then sasha yeah um
so i'm what i'm excited about i'm really
excited about
uh this kind of work um
as i'm a philosopher but um
with this sort of stuff the accident
prince fep stuff i'm like please stop
theorizing just like
let's play with this um so i'm really
excited about this kind of work
and um the question that's motivating me
is really sort of figuring out um what
the boundaries
of these various models are so what
boundaries of active instruments
are relative to the free energy
principle and then relative to
eg predictive coding models and that
sort of thing
um someone brought
recently on twitter i guess
there's a there's a biologist at my
university um this thing really kind of
groundbreaking work
in in like perception cognition um
perceptual cognition and stuff um in
[Music]
i guess butterflies but mostly uh
jumping spiders so
to say um the the morehouse lab nate
moore house
is doing for example um soltista has
like very
uh elaborate like um
mating dances and things and they're
signaling to each other um
and they're doing stuff like like the
evolution of color perception
in in these jumping spiders um it's
really fascinating work
and they mentioned recently um
or nate mentioned recently that um the
lab is
doing some like simulation work on
on how we evolve additional color
percepts
um so so you can right you can
you can if you have uh
certain like genes and proteins for for
um
pursuing certain colors you can you can
kind of like shift
the probability distribution the
the range of of color that those pick up
right um that's something that that
evolution can kind of
modulate but um the evolution of an
entirely different
um an entirely new color percept is is
something
different um and so
they're doing some some like insilico
work on that
and i i thought yeah that's what that's
what active influence that's exactly
what active influence should we do
that's what we should be doing it's
great
so i think that's what we should be
striving for thanks for that
very interesting summary sasha and then
anyone else
um thank you mel for bringing up the
jumping spiders
um they have incredible eyes you should
all look it up
um but i i'm interested in this
from a developmental perspective and
what active inference
can contribute to um
how systems develop and communicate
and specifically uh humans
um how our in utero environment and the
activity
of that process shapes the development
of
the human um and kind of on a more broad
scale how this can play into teaching
and how active inference can be applied
in the classroom
at different educational levels but in a
way that um
sets up the environment such that agents
are
encouraged to explore instead of being
dragged through the material
as uh students often are
so that's that's my curiosity in this
kind of you got this game
cool yes a lot of vygotsky fans
slash colleagues through time
on this discussion any other comments
but really great points there about like
the evolution and the development of
perception
and then at the level that we can at
least experience
or enact agency can we choose to see a
color is different can you look at that
ambiguous pattern and choose to see it
one way or another
can we understand uh many of these
perceptive questions
as being related to maybe not simply
explore exploit maybe having an element
of multi-scale
agency i think there's a lot of ways
that that could play out in people's
life
while also recognizing that we're not
talking about just metaphors here or
narratives
we're also talking about this specific
framework with the paper that we're
going to discuss
now so let's talk about those details
but then maybe you know we can dip back
to the other systems but let's think
about how this paper
and also our special time with alec will
help us understand these broader
questions at least
where we want to go after this short
discussion so the paper
scaling active inference we read the
goal last time
um alec maybe if you could just however
you want to or however long just what
what were you setting out to do or how
did the collaboration come to be
what were you asking before how did you
get to this paper and this goal
um so i guess historically the sort of
historic
uh lead up to the paper was just i'm
very interested in reinforcement
learning machine learning and also very
interested in active inference so it was
a
those sort of uh natural overlap but in
terms of
the motivation i think
the two communities don't really speak
to each other
as much as they should and so much of
the work that's happening
in reinforcement learning um
especially model-based reinforcement
learning has direct analogies to the
work that's being developed in the
active inference community
um so stuff like the use of variational
methods variational auto encoders the
use of
dynamics models the use of
trajectory-based planning
uh or just planning in general these
algorithms
have a lot of similarities between the
two um the use of intrinsic
objectives these information game terms
is widespread in both the use of
belief-based planning
so all the things that we sort of
touched on on the paper so
in my mind when i started that out that
the aim was really just to
construct an agent using the machinery
that would be
common and um relatable to the machine
learning
crowd but that was consistent with the
active influence very much
um and i guess the secondary goal was
also
to put together an initial attempt to
look at
whether what needs to be put in to get
some of these ideas to
scale um uh with a particular focus
on you know this wasn't a biologically
plausible
suggestion but looking at some of the
objective functions the expected free
energy
at scale um i think is of interest
rather than you know where it's commonly
looked at in these
uh small discrete screen uh teammates
style environments
cool really helpful in a lot of
terms that we've heard but to link
together the ideas of the variational
inference with the belief and the
trajectory based
planning those are all really cool
things
i just have a question about the at
scale part so one
aspect was that you introduced the
continuous state space
as opposed to the discrete but is there
anything else that's meant by
at scale or what does it mean to scale
in this context
well i mean so
i guess the
scale just means is almost defined in
relation to what is currently
uh common in the active influence
literature which is where your entire
world is
often designed by four or five states um
and there's transitions for you so this
paper um
presents a framework that can be applied
to you know observations of
um you know ten thousand a hundred
thousand
uh and so your state space or your
observation space is much larger
um so that's what i meant by scale is
it's putting forward a framework that
could be applied to a higher dimensional
task than the ones that you
can't consider and there's also a second
thing which is not really captured in
the word scale but also the complexity
of the dynamics um so some of these
tasks actually have quite a small state
space you know
four or five but the complexity of their
dynamics requires
um large models of a number of
parameters to them
um there's kind of a scaling aspect and
there's scaling in
the space of complexity of your diamonds
cool very interesting stuff and at any
point people can just
raise their hand but i think we can keep
on walking through
these areas and last time we
did walk through the different areas in
the road map just
how we introduce active inference and
the current state
and then walk through the specifics of
the model show some
proof of concept experiments relate it
to previous work
and then discuss and conclude with some
of these sentiments related to what alec
is saying and i also found it
interesting there's the scaling
dimensionality
then there's the introduction of
continuous state spaces not just
discrete
and then often as machine learning
people might
use the word scaling to mean it's about
the number of observations the size of
the data set
um and that relates to like the compute
scaling relationship
as you add when you double the data set
input is it the same amount of training
time is it twice as long is it four
times as long is it four thousand times
as long
and um so really interesting because
there's also the scaling in terms of
the understanding in the world and
people talk about scaling and innovation
and entrepreneurship and how do you
scale a solution
so there's a lot of parallel meanings
and a fun
and concise title because uh you know
that the finding isn't going to be in
the title
there isn't just a simple way that says
oh this protein does this in this
species
we're talking about developments in a
modeling framework
but we also want to be specific about
what those advances are
and how they relate to systems so maybe
just on the roadmap
alec or anyone else just anything to say
about it or
why was it arranged this way personally
i was just kind of wondering why the
previous work is at the end is that a
difference in our um
academic conventions or is that just
because it was more results oriented
yeah i mean you don't get a lot of
leeway in machine learning style papers
um i mean previous work and i'd go after
the introduction or
at the end but it's always you know
introduction some methods or presenting
a model
normally quite short and tests from the
experiments thing previously
exceptionally
very short discussion that's kind of
stunned across the field but um the
reason i think i chose previously at the
end was just because
i discussed active inference which
naturally leads him from the
introduction
and that introduces a little bit of mass
which then naturally flows into the
model
for like a previous work might have
broken up that flow
uh a little bit but it was more or less
cool um makes sense um i think we can
walk through the next sections
so right now we're in the just open
pause for questions i have a few
written down just as far as just big
questions because
we're trying to be a bridge in this
discussion
and through our conversation between
those who might be hearing about active
inference for the first time but they're
coming from machine learning
thinking about how cool methods perhaps
with philosophical implications
might be utilized and there's also a lot
of people who are in the active
inference
side of things or the inactivism side or
the philosophy side
where the details the machine learning
might be their first time hearing about
it so
how will we just come from where we are
and think about what questions and
what kinds of fun things to talk about
we'll make that rich
steven first and then anyone who wants
to
yeah i'm just curious because i know
that the scaling question
has been maybe looked at more from a
philosophical
perspective in the kind of active
inference so what this paper really
helped me
do or helped me was it like broke that
fear of
questioning the kind of these models
because the like people like yourself
and um
anil and that are saying look there's a
challenge here in the scaling
like this stuff is being kind of used at
these low dimensional
spaces and basically it showed like a
gap
in the literature in terms of how to
action that which kind of
helped me because it sort of gave me a
bit of permission to say okay
it's okay there's a gap there and it's
not that i just don't understand
everything
it's just not easy to scale and i think
this paper was
the first one to explicitly say that
because all the other papers tend to
talk about yes we know how to scale but
in a philosophical way
but this is like okay well this is the
problem from a
practice perspective
cool just one note on that if anyone
else wants to raise their hand
i really love this idea where there's
the gap in the literature
and there's there's a billion gaps on
literature um it's about which ones are
salient and fundable
and relevant so there's many gaps in
literature and then when we find that
gap
which is often very niche like in a phd
and i thought wow this data set has been
collected from this ant species but not
this other ant species there's a gap in
literature we don't have this data set
on this ant species
and then seeing that as a opportunity
and something that's okay
even if it's not your traditional field
of study
it's okay because you're at the edge
like at the gap with us
talking to the author and talking
through the equations but this is what
it looks like to
look across the gap and try to connect
because somebody else has identified it
as a research question or maybe you have
alec yeah
so i just wanted to comment on that as
well and uh entirely agree
with what you're saying um to come to
maybe the defense
of uh the existing literature on active
inference i think it's
viewed a little bit or this maybe it's
just me interpreting
what they're saying but um that may be
the the problems that they're
um testing their agents in for instance
some of the teammates
are actually viewed uh as quite complex
in a different
dimension so a lot of these
reinforcement learning tasks stuff like
atari uh
most of atari most of you know the stuff
where you're really pushing to get
state-of-the-art results with
a huge amount of compute and deep mind
competing against there
they're often you can often get by with
just this model-free reinforcement
learning that doesn't require any notion
of beliefs or any notion of proper
epistemics you can get
away with conduct explosions so what i
think
the active inference community has tried
to do is look at simple tasks such as
the teammates that
actually well you can solve them without
beliefs but are far far more
amenable to being sold with a
belief-based scheme and with this
directed
uh exploration and uncertainty reduction
um to show the kind of complexity that
the framework can come up
but then you could also respond by
saying that this is also thought about a
lot in reinforcement learning and
there is the question obviously whether
the kind of
process theories they put forward will
apply
when you've got uh when you've really
got the scale that reinforcement
learning
yeah let me add on to that because it's
a really great point so
a lot of times what's perceived as
cutting edge or modern or advanced
research in machine learning
i mean go to go check the lay media and
it's going to be about this many
graphical processors or this size of
data set or this accuracy or
this level of skill using massive data
and it's very much
on the performance end and on the eeking
out a little bit more performance from
increasingly large data sets with
increasingly
large types of models but
it's actually in some sense a local
exploration
it's locally exploring certain
frameworks and ways of doing machine
learning
which is just computer statistics and so
what this is like
with this paper is a return to
simplicity and it's a return to a
slightly different way of
conceptualizing some of the parameters
and how they're related
and the big data just train it bigger
train it uh better
is kind of like thinking that we can do
x without a belief we can train on go
just by watching go and we can train the
laws of physics just by watching physics
we can learn language by just
watching regularities in human language
these approaches
um there's merit to them this isn't just
about one way being better
it's just that what is being done in
this paper is to
take the free energy principle and
active inference which previously
had made these kinds of philosophically
at the very least
tantalizing claims like the relevance of
a belief guided trajectory based
optimization and search taking these
very fasting ideas
a little bit out of the sandbox into the
next level of the playground
where now we can actually start to
compete or at least compare and contrast
directly
with the kinds of benchmarking
algorithms that are used
so maybe one day you know active
inference go or active inference chess
but today we have the simple control
theory parameters
which is one level closer to these kinds
of use cases that are
happening today one level closer than
the teammates or the
the three-state uh decision is it a
mouse or a hawk or a cat
that type of stuff cool just the
questions that
i put up just thinking about how can we
continue to
deepen our understanding which we'll
move on from but just like
what's something you wondered about just
always stick with that and anyone can
raise your hands well
what's something you learned about while
studying the paper whether it was
something that they wrote specifically
or whether it was something that you
kind of went down a rabbit hole and
started studying about definitely that
happened
for me and then lastly like what's
something you're motivated to do more
or um learn about now that you've read
this paper and had this discussion
yeah mel thanks and then anyone else
yeah uh i guess i just wanted to jump on
that and say that um
i'm i'm used to seeing people sort of
try to compare um reinforcement learning
with with accent prints or
or related approaches and it's nice to
see something more that's more of a
synthesis there
cool yes so i think that
if there's any other thoughts feel free
but we'll look again over the
experiments
and then we'll sort of work kind of in
and out
about broader topics but let's try to
understand what was really done
because this also is the point of
contact with people who might be very
familiar with machine learning and
optimization
control theory but for them it might be
the first time hearing active inference
so where's the common train stop where
we're on board with the machine learning
community they're interested in these
kinds of tasks
they frame it as explore exploit and as
we've been talking about maybe there's
like a bit of a re-imagination or a
re-conceptualization of this
relationship explore exploit or what are
these variables that's what we want to
get to at the end so let's for sure
remember that
but for now let's think about being in
common
with benchmarking different data sets
and different machine learning
algorithms
so maybe we could talk about explore and
exploit how these communities think
about these
and maybe your observations about how
they're different alec
in terms of first the example that you
chose to highlight
as explore so maybe tell us about the
mountain car and then when you tell me
i'll go to the figure one
but like what is this what does it have
to do with exploring what does the
machine learning community think about
it how does active inference apply like
what is happening here
yeah so mankind's quite an interesting
one um it seems so simple it's to
when you do it in the fully observed
environment there's two states one
action uh this is the continuous version
so it's continuous actions
so you know it's like the simplest task
that machine learning people
present new papers but it's actually one
of the hardest so
um you know dqn vanilla dqn
doesn't stand the chance of solving this
what is dqm
sorry uh deep
q networks let's remember that so that's
the taking like the old
um the old idea of q learning which is
kind of
was the biggest idea of reinforcement
running before this whole deep phase
and just uh amending the deep neural
networks it's the one that um
be atari
uh yeah the first like deep mind nature
paper i can't remember the details
but it was it was kind of the the birth
of the deep reinforcement moment
great so that one has challenges on here
and then just continue yeah
i mean basically the reason is because
you only
get a reward when you reach that
flag up at the top and before that your
um you know that takes about 180 steps
so 180 actions that you have to
string together before you get any
notion of
a reward so just pure reward-based
schemes
uh really struggle with this they
essentially have to do more or less
random actions
until you get um out of the hill
um so yeah it's a struggle and that's
why it's kind of exemplifies exploration
because
you need to care about learning about
the dynamics
um or some other intrinsic quantity
if you want a chance at finding out how
to solve this class
cool very interesting blue this is just
really reminding me of a lot of what
we've talked about with explore
exploit a lot of the perspectives you've
brought about
how exploring how and when and where
does it matter so pretty interesting to
hear
alex just how you phrase that and and
also just like to hear that it's 180
sequences of actions so this is not like
control theory like connect four this is
like walking you know
who knows how many degrees of freedom
there are but this is many tasks that
have to get strung together in long
sequences
and then you said something about how um
it has to learn something intrinsic
for example the relationship between its
velocity position and policy a little
bit more nuanced nexus
of action rather than just learning like
simply whether you know go means fast
and stop means slow
steven and then anyone else yeah can i
just ask a question about that when you
say
stringing together um actions because i
i kind of had this feeling that it was
kind of a case of like
you keep the by by there being a desire
to explore
in itself through free energy that the
car realized
that it could go up the other side of
the hill further because it could just
have a reason for going there because of
trying to
minimize the desire to ex free energy
around exploration
and in doing so it gets that extra kind
of
momentum to get up the other side of the
hill but i haven't really gone into a
detail so just wondering how
this kind of sequence of steps and maybe
just
finding yourself firing up far enough up
the other hill
to get enough potential energy just to
go down and up
and make it to the flag i wonder how
those two sort of relate
great question alec maybe if you have a
thought on that
yeah yeah so i think your intuition's
mostly correct so
how it plays out is that this agent is
evaluating
different sequences of actions some of
those actions are going to keep it where
it's already been which is at the bottom
of this hill
uh and then some of the actions are
going to
take into a place where it's uncertain
about the outcome
um and that onset and that uncertainty
is essentially
valued by the agent it wants to resolve
it so it's going to say okay what
happens if i
do a little because it has to go left up
the hill
i should have mentioned that before it
has to go left up there actually i just
go away from the flag
uh to gain momentum to go around so it's
gonna you know it's never gone left up
the hill and then accelerated um
doesn't know what's going to happen it
does that that's valuable to it in terms
of
epistemics and then it realizes oh wow
yeah let me let me link that um to the
question the sequence of actions
so imagine if you were going to do a
control theory optimization on
shooting a a bow and arrow so shooting a
bow
um is a complex motor movement uses
probably many joints there's a lot of
you could do different speeds different
ratios it's going to be dependent on the
bow just like this is going to be
dependent on the slope
and the car so it's an enacted
affordance that you're trying to
develop in action sequence for and your
action sequence in
a game is often just a one stepper drop
the connect 4 token
here i'll reevaluate after i see what
they do
but if you're going to be evaluating
prospectively an
action sequence in the world it often
has depth
so it's like getting out of my chair
shooting the bow
there's state spaces are very there's
multi um
joint so it's multi-dimensional and it's
continuous
so that's why the multi-dimensional and
the continuous are so important and then
the depth through time
is so important because you can't just
be doing a get out of my chair
or a shoot the bow and arrow short-term
one-step optimization there's no
opponent for you to then take a look at
their move like in a chess checkers go
paradigm or even a video game paradigm
to some extent this is something about
planning in an enormous state
space and thinking really constructively
about these intrinsic relationships so
in the bow example
you might be attuning to the tension
between the proprioception in your
shoulder and how tense the bow
is to know if you're at the end of your
range of movement
or the bow is and if you train on one
that was half size and
then you go to a larger one or if your
arm is hurting that day or
all these differences differences in our
abilities these things all become
enacted
in the relationships that we're learning
about the intrinsic variables
so in the depth through time and
intrinsic variables if you learn
that hey if i actually reverse and start
accelerating downhill
a hundred time steps later it's just
better like if i go to sleep at this
time a hundred time steps later
it's just better and so these allow for
very non-linear policies to be selected
because there can be temporal depth
that's learnt as a function of the
actual physics basically of the setting
not just like counter factual you know
if 13 moves down the row this person
does this with my rook
that still is in a very if then context
and this is taking it into a totally
different domain with a
proactive action selection policies
yep so that's why this is such an
interesting paper and approach and like
again a branching off point that's why
it's foundational in the machine
learning because just
like alec described like if dq learning
cannot accomplish this task then yeah
it's all great to be a human at chess or
go
but if that algorithm or even that
architecture
can't defeat this challenge then we're
developing
something that's incredibly specific
which is great we should have good
map routing algorithms and things like
that but we're definitely going hyper
local down a rabbit hole
if it can't solve this but it can solve
go i don't know if it is that case
um a machine learning person would be
really welcome to help
fill us in on some of these details but
that's the kind of stuff that
is um interesting and broached in this
topic
so just to see what that looks like
empirically like the first hundred
epochs
um are plotted in terms of the state
space
coverage which here is just the position
on the x-axis and then the velocity on
the y
and the flag is at 0.5 right alec
like the flag represents being at
position of 0.5 but yeah continue from
here just anything you want to add on
figure one or what what does this mean
what is happening here i guess no your
description was great
the flag's not 0.5 the flags
what is it oh yeah 0.5 yeah uh but i
just kind of wanna
um self-deprecate myself and say
that uh these results are kinda they're
not
i mean they're not bad uh but um we had
a follow-up
paper where we got this all working
properly um
called reinforcement learning for active
inference um which is uh
very similar but we use a slightly
i can discuss the differences i think
they're interesting if we want but uh
just that the the results are so much
more impressive we can still uh
it's kind of that's both uh hitting on
this
and also um here's the paper
advertise that that work so in that work
oh yeah if you can actually just show
the figure and that we can check so
there it can solve the mountain car in a
single
trial and i have also the sort of state
space spots that look a bit better so
here's the so just like the left one
yeah
so if you kind of go i yeah we shot the
video can you just
the first time it goes into the ring it
just uh solves it straight away which is
much nicer uh so
the other the other one in the paper
that we're looking at today
um so the hero is being solved every
time that it does it and it responds to
this outweighs the
gotta love it
um yeah i guess that was just a caveat i
wanted to highlight that um
it can do a lot better business um but
i'll be happy to discuss the differences
because it's just one part of the
architecture
sure yeah what takes us from here to
what we just sort of peeked into in this
paper like what was the one thing that
you added or changed
yeah so when i wrote the original one to
um so to get this kind of what what
carl calls parameter expiration or
parameter information again it's
essentially trying to reduce
uncertainty not about what's out there
in the world but about your own model
if you have beliefs about um your model
uh and it's kind of in a sense you know
what you don't know
and to get that you have to have a
distribution
over your model and in this case our
model is a neural network so you need a
distribution
overview on your network there's two
ways in the literature to do this
in the first paper scaling active
inference we tried bayesian neural
networks
there may be more principles you know
you're actually using variational
inference to estimate this
distribution over each of your
parameters but
in practice they don't work
nearly as well as what we tried in the
next paper
which is called the ensemble approach
and the idea there
is you just take in this case 25
dynamics models and training them on
different batches of the data
and that's kind of like a proxy for a
non-parametric bayesian posterior over
the um dynamics model um you can
do a little people are kind of working
out how close it is to actually proper
baiting beliefs but
um you definitely get a notion of
uncertainty there so
here um and there's lots of interesting
reasons as to why
uh principled reasons as to why ensemble
models would work better than
um bayesian models it's also easier
in practice to estimate stuff like um
information game
um so that just turned out to be a
hundred times
and in the machine learning community
people generally find more success
more success with uh deep ensembles for
both
uncertainty calibration and directed
exploration
that's very cool thanks for the great
explanation there and so just to sort of
re-hash that or say it a little
differently the approach that was taken
in this scaling active inference paper
to estimating
some of these essential parameters was
done with the bayesian
neural network which alec just described
it's like one way to do it it might be a
way that interfaces pretty cleanly with
a lot of other
software packages or approaches but it's
the skeleton of the model and that's the
diagram and then we think about how can
we improve it and so one direction
is more analytical or more principled as
you described it
and that's like the fully bayesian sort
of specifying every little
uh hidden state and that approach can
provide some interesting avenues at
times
but an approach that is also relatively
easy to implement
from a programmatic interface level and
also makes a relative
minimum of assumptions about the
specific mechanics of the system
is this ensemble or deep ensemble
approach so the deep adjective
is just meaning you're going to have
like a multi-scale or i mean a
multi-level neural network with hidden
layers or it's just going to be deep and
modern
but it's kind of like just an adjective
the ensemble approach
is describing having a bunch of
different models that are going to be
trained up on the same or different
parts of the data set
and then you could look at the average
of the ensemble or you could look at
some other weighted combination of the
ensemble's performance
and so it's almost like bridging the gap
from individual
testing that's like the single model
testing
to now the ensemble approach is like
we're gonna have a classroom and then
the best answer from r9
group all working on it independently
the best one will push forward or we'll
average
and then even another level beyond that
is like the truly emergence
which is actually what the ants are
doing where the ensemble
works as an ensemble in a way that is
itself
shaped by development and learning and
evolution so right now the ensemble
modeling is still like sort of
well if you just split it up into many
parts you can cover more state space
you might be able to train the model in
parallel you might make sure that no
single model over generalizes
there's so many benefits that come
simply from batching and ensemble
modeling that go beyond just saying
what's the best single model or what's
the best
parameter range in this type of model
the ensemble can consist of a single
type with the different parameters
between the different ensemble mates or
they can be heterogeneous in some
aspect so just really cool you went with
what was implementable
and a common point of departure with
machine learning community
and the bayesian neural network kind of
peaks in one direction towards a more
analytical more principled fully
bayesian approach and then on the other
side to
modern approaches in machine learning
like deep ensemble learning
cool let's look at figure two and what
is conveyed here so this is the
hopper task oh we'll go blue first go
ahead sorry i didn't see that
can you back up to the last figure let's
do blue and then math
and then so um
i just wanted to ask and this is kind of
related to the next
figure but um i just wanted to ask that
uh
when you did the hopper task and the um
pendulum so i know that that was only
based on the extrinsic value
like part of the free energy equation so
you like you left off the exploration
because
like exploration probably had no value
in in that problem i mean i'm assuming
there
but i i was wondering here like on the
exploration problem sorry did i say
exploration before
exploit anyway so here with the
exploration problem
um did you ever think about leaving off
uh the extrinsic part of the equation
and just using like the information
gain as a reward like can you structure
it that way would it be different
like if the object of the agent was just
to gain
more information about the environment
do you think that it would have
succeeded
in um you know climbing the hill because
it would get to a new part of the
of the environment or how do you think
that would work
yeah yeah uh not in this paper but it
does um
so that other paper i mentioned the
reinforcement through active influence
because it solves it in the very first
task it literally can't
be because of reward we tested it
without reward as well to
confirm this but you know it hasn't ever
experienced a reward and it still solves
the task so it's exactly what you're
specifying it's just purely trying to
reach all the parts of
the uh state space uh if you just left
it with expiration what you
tend to find is that it will solve it
for say the first 10 trials while it's
still
the peaks of the uh hill
are the most kind of interesting so they
have the most extreme dynamics with the
most variants um
but then after a while uh the top of the
hill is no more
interesting than the bottom of the hill
because it's kind of explored but
whereas if you've got the rewards
and the exploration kind of slowly
transfers from solving it because of
expiration to solving it because it
knows
how to get rewards
awesome thank you i didn't see that
follow-up paper and i like i'm going to
go read it right after this
i know we need to do a uh after party
active after parties with next paper um
but uh mel and then anyone else
yeah just um what you're describing
with uh like stringing a bow
something like this um i think that was
what really got me excited about
active influence in the free entrance
from the first place is is the idea that
um with something like like a
towers of hanoi style problem are people
familiar with that uh-huh it's like
you've got you've got
three sticks and and you've got disks of
various sizes on the stick so you've got
to get them in
in a in a like a ascending order right
um
and the idea is that uh
the puzzle requires that you you go
backwards before you can go forward
and if you're just
minimizing or maximizing some function
on a single level
um if you've got a like a 1d
optimization you're you're going to
not be able to solve a problem that
requires that you backtrack
in order to make progress um and
something like
academics the free energy principle
where we've got
temporal depth we've got hierarchical
depth of the model
um is really equipped to solve these
kinds of problems in a way that a lot of
traditional
um problem-solving approaches are not
i totally agree and i think there's a
quantitative and a qualitative so at the
quantitative level
there's control policies that we can't
have fit computers look beyond some
locally non-favorable states to get
around so we want to do these
quantitative policies that's what this
paper is about
but at the qualitative and really the
philosophical level
how do we come to grasp with processes
where yeah we're not always strictly
walking a staircase directly
to the top of the mountain or it might
not seem like we can do it at all
initially if we just look and there's so
much there
with how we think about challenges and
about exploring
one actual uh link there because blue
asked about what would happen if you
just let it go wild on exploring
and alec what you said is that the
learning gets you to the top
pretty quickly because in that sense
it's similar to this
model that also prioritizes reward but
then after getting to the top
you spend a lot of your time learning on
the most
extremely variant areas of parameter
space
so it's so much like curiosity driven
learning
where a lot of times curiosity driven
learning with no
reward or scaffolding it ends up
learning learning learning a ton
shocking amounts but then also spending
a lot of time in the most extreme ranges
of space and that doesn't always just
play out like in the kind of online
gutter but even in the literature we see
a lot of the attention
being spent on the extreme hyperboles
and then the middle ground where it's
like yeah it's kind of balanced and we
can work on it together
that is not as extreme of a viewpoint
and so people spend less learning and
attentional regimes on
these kinds of projects so there's a lot
of like
parallels that we can quantitatively
model but also help us think about
how we can say no you're just trying to
make me explore the top of the hill
i get it but the flag's on the other
side so i've heard about the other side
of the hill
how are we going to enact a policy to
get us to the flag together
that's a little bit better than your
hill is worse than my hill for example
how could these kinds of things be
ported onto like human decision making
is a cool area
any other questions on one otherwise
let's talk about two a little bit
well just just one quick piece just
picking up on what blur
said there i thought it's quite
interesting is if
there's this idea of exploring the
environment
in different ways but say there's
exploring or information going
in terms of personal preference so for
instance
maybe it was a bit more of a con i like
to always
feel what it's like to go slightly up a
slope and turn to the right
that feels cool all right so then you
have this kind of like
it's not necessarily it's like an
information gain about having funds
so would it like say the car was like
hey i really like to do
this type of things because cars like me
like doing that i know you know if it
was a living animal
so it kind of ties into what sort of
exploration of
the world and then what exploration of
just being
an entity that likes to do certain
things and that could end up
taking you there in another in another
way or together they
help great alec
yeah i just wanted to point on that
because this is uh i totally agree and i
think it's
one of the most uh promising kind of
directions or perspectives that active
inference gives
and i wrote about this in a in another
paper that i can link afterwards
uh of this notion of i don't really know
what to call it
but goal-directed exploration that you
derive from something like expected free
energy and that means
you don't necessarily or it's just too
inefficient just to have
everlasting expiration with no
constraints you know
and it's also too inefficient just to do
have exploitation what you need
is some objective function like expected
free energy or model evidence that
contains these two things so that you're
not selecting actions to just explore or
just to exploit
that each action is kind of shaded with
both of these things
and that way you're getting a
exploration that's
um geared towards your goals and it
greatly constrains the type of
exploration and i think from the engine
you know that also fits with our kind of
experience maybe
of daily life or maybe not but i think
from an engineering perspective
that's crucial because in real world
tasks there's just too much to explore
and you need
to prioritize that exploration i think
there's something excellent
yep that's so beautiful and even another
layer
is the ensemble of mountain cars so now
imagine
we all see different things and we don't
know the way to get to the top of the
mountain
we don't know the policy we don't even
know what the end point is we don't know
if the one that we can see
close by is the best one or if there's a
way better one way further away
and then everybody is who they are and
they all have their own landscapes
and then through the ensembles modeling
collectively
with or without information sharing of
whatever kind the ensemble
as we're seeing gets better performance
there isn't just one best policy of
mountain car
there are so many different ways to
ascend the mountain and then you open it
up with what the objective functions and
the policies the goals could be
and it really is a a great space shannon
and then anyone else
hi thanks i was just um thinking about
your ensemble of cars here
and comparing this to like flocking
behaviors in birds or even
um people who are foraging together and
maybe i was wondering how so maybe this
entire flock is minimizing its
free energy by getting closer to reward
which is
food but any individual bird in the
flock
is just following local
rules about like how close to fly to
other agents or when to follow them or
when
to break off and find a new
like go away from the rest of the flock
or drag the flock along
with them and i wonder if every single
bird is
having their own little mountain car
model or if there's just one gross model
for the entire flock as a mountain car
finding
finding its food yep well
one angle on the forging and affordances
is imagine that
ensemble of human foragers but they're
not exactly the same
size or they don't have exactly the same
preference or they have slightly
different vision
some people see closer or further they
see color or they don't see color
and so all these differences are what
allow the ensemble to explore and
exploit especially with information
sharing oh hey i
was over under this tree and i found
this but somebody else wouldn't have
found it
so we can all use the ensemble to take
advantage of our
um you know differences of the nest
mates or the flock or cognitive
diversity
and then in the question that you raised
about
is there a single uh layer being enacted
by the flock
or is there a little mountain car as you
said by each bird
so from a modeler's perspective if it
turns out that we can explain
variance about the bird's trajectory by
putting a linear regression
on it it doesn't say it's linear
aggression that the bird is doing just
that it helped us explain variance in
the world
so similarly the low bar here is that we
can use this kind of model
just like we could use another type of
control theory model or
action policy selection model to explain
variants about the real world
and especially because we see organisms
succeeding in fact it's really the only
ones that we do see
this helps us explain those successful
systems as opposed to like funny little
gifs of you know a robot flailing and
then whether there's like one layer
that's being enacted and then
the group is purely epi phenomenal and
there's no downward causation
there's no influence of the group states
on the lower level states there might be
some systems like that
there might be other systems where
there's an analytical solution like a
well-defined solution
at the bird and the flock level there
might be another one where it's well
defined at one level
but then because of interactions and
emergence it isn't as defined or isn't
defined by the same class of model
at a higher or a more coarse-grained
level
anything yeah that's great yep cool
let's look at
figure two so similarly as you did for
that on mountain car which was like such
a helpful
direction to take what can you tell us
about the hopper
v2 or the inverted pendulum which i
don't have here but those were the two
tasks maybe more on the hopper
or the pendulum whichever one just what
are they about what will machine
learning people recognize or know these
models as signifying
um so hopper isn't
um particularly expiration based it's
quite a dense reward that you get so
you kind of get rewarded or disregarded
for each of the action
but uh it's slightly more high
dimensional
i can't it says two dimensional there
but that's just the lip
that's not when i speak say dimensions i
mean how many observations
uh it receives um it's more than two
it might be like 16 i'm not sure uh and
it's just generally the dynamics you've
got to learn you know you've got maybe
four actions which are real value
numbers between
minus four and four you've got to learn
how that changes
16 variables over the course of your
however long you're planning so
it's a much harder task to learn um
so i guess that's why it was included
in in this just that it's generally
regarded as a bit of a
harder task in the machine learning
community cool and so what is happening
in figure
2 what can we say how is it different
than ddpg
and what actually is ddpg for reference
ddpg is uh of descending acronyms and
reinforcing deep deterministic policy
gradients um so what is that one doing
and then what is active inference doing
that's different
that maybe enables it to have such
better performance
um so what is uh dvpd doing so it's just
a it's a model three reinforcement
learning program so you have a policy
that maps from states to actions
and you essentially do a lot of maths
from
something like the bellman equation to
get to um
update for your um policy parameters um
the reason that it's doing so much
better and the reason that model-based
reinforcement learning
in general does so much better um is
because it's essentially it's a planning
algorithm so
um what's the best way to describe this
yeah um
due to the fact it's model based it can
learn from every single
um bit of data that i've received so
that is
in terms of each state transition and as
well as the reward signals
um whereas this model free reinforcement
learning is
is just simply landing from that single
bit of information that gets each time
step which is
uh um the corresponding authority so
however your rewards are thinking um
so i mean eventually ddbg after enough
epochs would probably uh
asymptote around or higher than um
model based that's a kind of general
pattern you get with model based on
model 3 reinforced on learning
model base is far more sample efficient
uh
but model 3 takes a hell of a lot more
samples but is
asymptotes gets levels out a
higher reward let me also add a layer
there
um with a few other aspects from machine
learning and the idea of the ruggedness
of the landscape
so if you're doing this task which was
described as a dense task
another way of thinking about these is
you're trying to keep something upright
so it's like very obvious if you're
succeeding or failing and in the big
landscape there's really
easy to tell differences between
succeeding and failing that being said
policy planning especially when you have
four variables of control that are
projecting out to like 16 potentially
non-linear
connected outcomes when you're trying to
do that there may be many strategic
mappings there might be many policies
that help you keep the pendulum up like
for example going a little bit back and
forth
with a certain speed or you can go a
little further with a different rhythm
so there might be many many different
ways even for a single joint of control
many policy sequences through time many
learned relationships
that help you stay in that yes no area
now if you have a model free
reinforcement learner
it means it's learning basically the raw
connection it's model 3
so-called between the reward and the
policy
and so it may spend a lot of its time
exploring locally a policy because it's
like in the spotlight
it's working and then it goes to a
slightly different area it's not working
where do we go from outside of the
spotlight it's all dark no idea model
free
with a deep generative model it's not
like this spotlight in or out
reinforcement it's like we're learning
these intrinsic relationships
which actually helps us get a grasp of
the maps that are going to guide us to
search on the territory
a little bit more exhaustively but then
that part at the end which was so
interesting that
the model free sometimes gets to higher
final performance in some context that
can be because a
truly model free search can result in
some wacky combination that wouldn't
have
necessarily been approached that it just
uniquely potentially not in a resilient
way but it uniquely allows some
performance on a task and so that
reminds me of like the evolutionary
computation where
its goal will be to travel distance and
then some will actually go down the
walking road
and those start slow but they can walk
forever and then other ones just like
fall and so it's kind of like hacking to
get over
um a barrier without necessarily uh
a deeper understanding of the ecology
because it's so blindly pursuing just
performance
so there's a lot of stuff there but this
is like really an illustrative example
and it does highlight a lot of the
differences between the model free
performance and the state of the art in
that as well as what potentially active
inference can bring
any thoughts on too or now we'll just
have some general
areas basically the first area was
implications i know we've probably
talked about some of them
but three areas that i thought about
were like robotics
resources and allocation and then rugged
landscapes this one probably in the
southwest um
so any thoughts on these i think we've
almost touched on
related ideas but if anyone wants to
like speak to one of these areas
of possible implication whether they do
they don't see what an implication could
be
or what would another domain of
implication be
um yeah alec go ahead
so um i also
i'm becoming increasingly interested in
so are some other people
in um whether some so i'm very invested
in this idea of kind of a bayesian brain
and um as actual infants kind
infrastructure as fast as uh but whether
some of these ideas from bayes and
machine learning that are used in this
paper so stuff like amortization
um might also be employed in nervous
systems
um so you know we've had a few
very very uh big proposals for how the
brain might implement bayesian infant
stuff like population coding predictive
coding
uh the process theory that's most
commonly associated with vector
inference in this terms of message
passing but it might also be
you know this amortization is also um
another real possibility of how the
brain implements some type of um
influence so i think it could have
implications for understanding
neuroscience
wow did not expect that message passing
and predictive processing predictive
coding
type models can be understood alongside
amortization models
as an alternate implementation or
mechanism of bayesian
brain as a specific testable hypothesis
so this is where the rubber hits the
road
with the modeling and with showing the
deep mathematical isomorphisms between
these different kinds of relationships
like there might be some paper i'm sure
there is where like message passing is
equivalent to bayesian networks and then
that allows us to
bridge to big areas of literature and so
if we
do a lot of investigation in bayesian
brain and then we find out wait there's
actually multiple ways that could be
implemented in different systems
whether that's through message passing
so maybe that's more applicable to a
computer network
maybe it's also going to be implemented
by policy planning
ensembles so then whoa what else is
doing this kind of bayesian
like processing so there's so many cool
directions there great topic because
also
robotics or at least the question of
implementation of action and selection
of policy
and from sensors and with actuators
resources in terms of informational
attentional whatever they may be and
then rugged landscapes is just
that's everything that is policy
selection under uncertainty
for any kind of system that wants to
stay alive
let's go oh sorry sasha or blue oh
see you later blue oh wait sasha out
blue
please thank you wait muted but yeah go
ahead
uh so i just i had the same reaction
that you did like bayesian brain
amortization like wow i just was
wondering
uh alec if you could maybe just unpack
that like in a very
simple way or elaborate more on on that
yeah uh sure so um
the best way so i mean amortization um
as it's realized in stuff like various
norton codes but also
other schemes um we can like maybe
discuss a bit more together what defines
amortization
are just an instance a way of learning a
german model
and well more precisely doing inference
the key
defining features for me although i
don't think this has ever been
properly defined in the literature is
this notion
of having an encoder um how that would
play out in the brain
um how it could play out in the brain
it's just kind of a
feed-forward mapping um a few forward
part of
say the visual cortex that maps from
some data or a lower part in the
hierarchy to
some posterior parameters higher up
in the hierarchy and when you have stuff
like um
population coding or predictive coding
there's not this notion of
quickly in a fee-forward manner mapping
from data to parameters you've got this
kind of iterative procedure that
slowly um and sequentially updates the
beliefs those posterior beliefs based on
the data
based on some learning so it's another
um
root towards bayesian inference it's far
far more fast
and doesn't require recurrent processing
and that kind of
speaks well with some things you know
about the brain it's not all the brain
the brain definitely does have required
processing but a lot can be done in
a kind of feedforward manner very
quickly uh
and and the second thing is that um the
parameters that you're optimizing of the
encoder
are optimized um over the entire data
set whereas
in something like predictive coding it's
optimized individually
the posterior parameters of your beliefs
are optimized
based on the current data point uh and i
think that has some
that might uh speak to some of the
generalization capabilities of those
influence
um and that's something that we're
looking at
so more obviously i hope that kind of
answers your question
no definitely thank you so much totally
epic
to connect that feed forward encoder
model
to the machine learning um side so
instead of doing like a back and forth
expectation maximization where you're um
just updating back and forth
or especially a uh like a back
propagation type thing
where there's very very complex
interactions about how parameters are
trained
this allows us to kind of train on the
fly and just learn as we go
now to the second point which is the
usage of the entire data set versus
point by point
this is like we're learning on the fly
but um
we're learning on the fly in the state
space that we want to be learning about
with respect to the entire data set that
we have access to
which is a little bit different than
like you're kind of trailing your finger
along a time
series and then you're updating based
upon
that data point and what you believe and
what you've recently seen
that's like a kind of point-by-point way
to use a whole data set
to update parameters versus this
variational approach which actually
enables like almost a simultaneous
utilization
of the entire state space i'm not sure
if that's totally
correct but those are just two parts
that hit me about the two
sides that you mentioned alec
stephen and then anyone else
so i've not heard of this amortization
so it's quite interesting
is it's almost like in reverse then is
it it's like you
you'd have a a big complex place
of knowing and you quickly discount
stuff and the process is about discount
in a way
rather than building up the model is
that is that kind of
the the idea uh
i'm not sure if i've understand
understood exactly what you're gonna
hear but for my
from i'm not sure if it if it is but
maybe we could get into that a bit more
how would you define alec how would you
define amortized inference like we see
it here in the paper but
how would you define it you mentioned
some benefits we've talked about them a
little bit but like
in this kind of new way of thinking
about it what what does it mean or what
would it mean for the brain to do it or
what
happened programmatically i mean so this
is what i was getting earlier that
doesn't really have a
clear definition um i i trying to fight
in two ways one
is how it's generally used if you see
amortized inference
in um machine learning uh
you're generally you should think of a
encoder network so you've got a neural
network it takes in your data
and it will output literal values for
your parameters
that would normally and those parameters
are the ones that would normally be
optimized in traditional uh variational
methods
here it's just um they're just spat out
by the network
um and then you have some other um
learning
method which which updates that encode
if you uh and also your your genitive
model but um
in terms of what amortization actually
means going back to the
word i think derives from economics um
i think it's this idea that you come
into the second point that i made where
uh you're sharing the parameters of that
encoder
across all of your data so you're
amortizing the cost of inference um
is how i think about it i could be i
could be very wrong um
so that just means you you kind of don't
reset with um each new observation or
you're not trying to optimize with
respect to um each new observation and
then kind of discarding information
you're
just sharing that encoder um the
encoder which is the relationship
between the data and the parameters
across uh your entire lifetime so you're
amortizing the cost of influence
that's how i think about it so you might
find a better quote
so is it like is it like you so as
opposed to just discounting data it's
discounting ways of chunking up the data
or ways of
analyzing it and if that makes sense
like you could have lots of different
models and they say okay
i'm going to apply them in a more
efficient way over time
as you start to infer it's almost
inferring what models
should be deployed is that the kind of
idea and you start to take away the
models which are less useful
in a way i guess you could another uh
kind of
people sometimes refer to it as learning
to infer
so in which might be what you're getting
at um
so in normal inference you're just doing
inference
but here you're learning how to do
so the learning um yeah so maybe that
was what
um you're going out with your kind of
model selection
cool thanks yeah that that makes sense i
don't know but i'm
trying to find my way through there's a
few dimensions so it's really helpful to
unpack it there's the learning how to
learn
there's that meta learning element but
also this is
really important in the paper is the
number of parameters remains constant
with respect to the size of the data
so if i'm trying to estimate the mean
and the variance of a normal
distribution
i know that i want to squeeze down
whatever data set i have into two
numbers
and so if i have three numbers coming in
the pipeline i still want a mean and a
variance
if i want a billion numbers to come in
the pipeline i still i want
mean variance and so it turns out that
by knowing and by specifying ahead of
time
that you know exactly the size of the
outcome
it allows you to uh scale a lot better
because you can know that no matter what
you're going to put in on the inside
it's going to be able to be distilled
down very rapidly whereas another
method that results okay well we put in
a data set and then we find out
how many principal components explain it
best that might computationally
scale in a way that is very um
disadvantageous with respect to the size
of the data
whereas this method can um do that and
another then as a
sort of corollary there it's happening
through a single forward pass of a
network which can be ab initio
sort of like de novo setting it up from
the beginning and or
updated in a learning fashion and so
there's there's a few dimensions and
alec i'd really look forward to you know
seeing what you continue to do with the
amortized inference
seeing as that concept becomes a bit
more formalized
because this seems like really powerful
and then if it also turns out that it's
an implementation
of bayesian statistics or bayesian brain
then it just taps into the entire
message passing
compute graph um bayesian net framework
which already has been the
um most helpful for machine learning in
a lot of other areas too
very very cool so i guess
in the next steps which is really i
guess the last thing that we'll talk
about for the last few minutes i just
thought of a few
areas to go into for next step so alec
definitely
you take the first pass but the areas
could be like computationally
what does that mean hardware software
from a math perspective
what could be analytically shown or what
relationships would be good to know
um from an applications perspective what
robots
need this kind of software update and
then just educationally how do we
come to you know control our attention
so that we understand these concepts as
well
or what did you start working on after
this paper i guess it was nice oh yeah
no worries no worries
i guess you did this one or where are
you at steps are
um i guess on this line of thinking that
the
um this line of work the stuff that i'm
still thinking about is
what was mentioned right at the
beginning which is the balance of uh
exploitation and exploration and whether
the active influence perspective
buys you um anything in practice
um because you know we've got this nice
objective
functional expected for energy and we
can optimize actions with respect to it
and it does contain exploration
exploitation and it motivates
exploration
and exploitation from first phase and
principles but in practice
you're gonna be in any model you're
going to be
uh fine-tuning those um the balance
between those
um you've got a bit more of leeway to do
it because now you can
um change the shape of your prior
beliefs for instance
a few other parameters that are gonna
lead to that play off rather than just
having some uh
scalar weight that defines them so some
of the stuff that i've
been looking at is yeah learning prior
beliefs uh in order to facilitate
exploration exploitation um
because i think to summarize that yeah
the balance between exploration
expectations
is probably one of the big unsolved
questions in
um control reinforcement learning
neuroscience etc
um and for making these machines work um
as well as we'd like them to and active
inference
offers a new route to try and solve that
i don't think it has been solved
awesome that's really exciting there's
just so many aspects to the
control theory question when there's a
lot of solutions that could work and
maybe it's even unclear what it would
look like to work
especially as we think about some of
these systems that go beyond
the merely just keep a pendulum standing
but what if it's
give someone a massage well that's a
little bit of a different question it's
relational
or how are you going to exercise in a
way that's comfortable for you
these are control theory questions that
are literally about action sequences
and so when we start thinking about how
we're going to apply it to different
systems
having a framework that is at least
moving in this direction of
what you said as like with the
reconsidering the explore exploit
by adding things like reconsidering the
shape of your priors
so how can you step into a framework
where the explore exploit
is a dimension that could be calculated
or described
or kind of summarized but isn't simply
the underlying framework of the model
we're going to get exploratory behavior
we're going to get so-called
exploitative or
narrowly searching behavior that is not
being ruled out by what we're discussing
we're talking about another way that
optimization could proceed that doesn't
use
simply the explore versus exploit or the
coefficient weighting of these two
through time or statically to um outline
its whole
learning approach so stephen first and
then
anyone else if they want to give any
like last thoughts but this has been a
great
conversation so stephen and then anyone
else
i mean also if you're going to the real
world environment you've got this
exploit situation but in high stakes
situations you've also got
um like they often talk about risk
mitigation versus gain optimization
if you're in a kind of um a conflict or
you know a legal situation because it
may be
that it's a question of you know which
is in a way
gain optimization is a bit like an
explorer but it depends which way you're
going it could be an information
game but whatever you're you're trying
to do
those two two aspects sort of come into
play depending on
the state of the of the situation
you know so you know explore exploit is
less relevant when you're standing on
the edge of a cliff
playing a game you know because it's
like there's a risk mitigation issue so
anyway i thought that might be
interesting i just thought about you
know doing
learning action policies but if you're
learning an action policy where you
could die
if you're rock climbing or something
it's going to change how you learn
and so when you're trying to minimize
risk versus failure
attempt or minimize the number of
opportunities you have to see
it successfully performed or you can
only infer it by observing it
these things may contain a ton of
information
in terms of how real systems learn where
failure is not an option
mel and then anyone else who wants to
close it out
yeah sorry this is i guess a sort of an
ignorant question but i
i thought some of like the beauty of
these acting prince in itp approaches
is is that they're sort of doing a kind
of like multi-level dynamic
outcomes razer type thing so they're
maximizing
predictability while well also kind of
minimizing the complexity
of what they're doing and
so i guess what i don't quite understand
is how the amortization
of inference process works but if you're
fixing a
param doesn't that kind of uh
constrain the ability of of these
approaches to to do that kind of
outcomes razor
um not really because the
parameters of your encoder aren't the
parameters that you're
they're not the free energy parameters
they're mapping to the free energy
parameters
so you could map you know to
uh you know free energy just says that
you've got to maximize uh
yeah the accuracy of the likelihood
while minimizing
the complexity so as long as your
encoder maps to the part of police
states that is
maximally uh accurate and also minimally
complex then you're still
minimizing on complexity while
maximizing accuracy
uh and then obviously there's what we
haven't discussed is that learning
schemes for
so the way you learn your encoded
parameters is so that they output
something that
does conform to minimal variation of
energy yes okay so you're not actually
constraining
you're not actually placing like
additional constraints on on the
params of the actual not on the
parameters of the encoder
on the output of the encoder yeah
um i guess that's a good point uh so the
encode
i guess a problem with amortization is
that um the encode is kind of not part
you shouldn't think of it as part of
your generative model it's just almost
like a
a tool that can um map
to the belief space of the genesis
number
um
just on a closing note there that really
returns us this dual instrumentalism
with rappers and rappers and is it what
the system is doing or is it how we're
looking at it these questions are
very rich and so it's a great
conversation
really thanks everyone for participating
this was such a helpful discussion and i
think definitely while re-listening
we'll all pick out some questions for
ourselves to follow up on and some
curious things to learn about because
there are so many good ideas brought up
so if people who are on live if they
check their calendar event they will see
a feedback form which would be helpful
and anyone else who's listening or
watching
please provide us with feedback
suggestions or questions
but other than that just um stay in
touch
and everyone awesome work for this
helpful discussion
and we'll see you soon
oh