Hello, everyone. It is June 9, 2022,
and it's chapter three,
week one, and it's the first cohort
of the textbook group. We're going to go
to the questions. There weren't any
ideas added for three, but if people
have any key themes or any ideas that
they picked up on with three, they can
add them here. Otherwise we'll go to the
questions. And also
if people have questions in the chat,
or it would be also great just to take
notes or add questions and continue to
upload them. And then next week we'll
continue the discussion on three. So
this is just the opening set of
questions, maybe just the first ideas
of the book. Turning to questions, now
that we've at least gone through
chapter two once and part of chapter
three, or the whole thing of chapter
three, what is the high road to active
inference?
What does anyone think about the high
road to active inference or about this
low road high road construct
that is used in chapters two and three?
Just broadly, how did the approach of
chapter three feel different than the
approach or the topics of chapter two?
JF and then Ali.
I just want. To make the Joe comment
that the. High road approach is what
first grabbed. Me when I encountered the
free energy principle. That what really
fascinated me, that there. Was an
attempt at a unifying answer.
To self organization,
cognition.
That this could. All be brought together
around some relatively.
Sparse number of concepts. That's what
grabbed me much more than the lower
road. Thank you,
Ali and then Ben?
Well, yeah, reading chapter three
actually clarified my previously held,
in fact wrong belief that previously
I thought that a low road was a kind of
bottom off approach and the high road is
top down approach. But now I see
that low road was basically tackling
the problem of active inference from the
inferential point of view and from the
statistical and inferential point of
view. But in the high road we have
a much more generalized and much
more, let's say, all encompassing view
to tackle the problem of active
inference, namely by way of defining
markup blankets and all the properties
of living organisms and so on.
Awesome. Thank you, Ben. And then anyone
else who raises their hand. And also you
can take notes on this idea of the book,
like high road generally. Ben and then
Mike. Yeah, I think for
me as well, this chapter three and the
high road has been an easier road in.
And the thing that I noticed about it
was, it seems to me, so they say in the
introduction, that active inference is a
normative theory. I feel like the high
road, to me, feels there's much more
normativity in the high road. It's an
account of what organisms have to do.
And I think compared to the previous
chapter, I think chapter two felt a lot
more descriptive for me. I'm not sure
other people would. Maybe that's just
the way that I was reading it, but it
felt like chapter three was a lot more
kind of it had a more normative force to
it that I really enjoyed.
Thank you, Mike.
There we go. Sorry, my computer was not
responding. So I went through a similar
experience as Ollie described in terms
of going into it, thinking about bottoms
up and top down and coming out of it,
thinking about it differently.
I feel like in chapter three there's
still a lot to unpack around the Markov
blanket. So that is still capturing this
inferential nature of things. It still
has a Bayesian quality like what we saw
in chapter two. But it
also, for me at least, it still feels a
bit opaque at this point in terms of
this sort of indirect influence that's
taking place across the Markov blanket.
Awesome. Okay, any other
comments? Otherwise we're going to go to
the questions and we'll approach many of
those topics.
Okay,
first question regarding the
Markov blanket explanation. On page 43
and box 3.1, they write,
no additional information about the
future is gained by finding out about
the past. Assuming we know the present,
how can this be true? That's one
question they
define regarding the Markov blanket as
the set of variables that mediate all
statistical interactions between a
system and its environment. What is a
statistical rather than a non
statistical interaction?
They write that they've supplemented
conditional independencies with
dynamical constraints so that the flows
do not depend upon states on the
opposite side of the blanket. Why does
independence between the flows on the
two sides of the blanket matter so much?
All right, great. So who
would like to give a thought on this?
First question? How can it be true about
Marco blankets that no additional
information about the future is gained
by finding out about the past?
So I added a note in there. You can tell
me if this is correct or not with regard
to Markov chains that as I understand
the Markov chain in its present state is
effectively capturing all the
information about the past. So I assume
that translates into the Markov blanket.
Yes. Great comment. And a Markov chain
is used very
broadly. And just to give one
example, it's like the current state of
the chessboard, knowing more about
previous moves doesn't tell you more
about the future. And so it's like it's
a one Markov chain because the
dependency is only about that one time
step. Now if it were to violate that
condition of being a one Markov blanket
through time and have like a three
Markov blanket, that would mean that the
same board position, depending on what
move happened three before, was still
having some influence on how the system
evolved. That wouldn't violate the
Markovian property, it would just make
it a different kind of Markov chain.
And that is commonly used in the
temporal modeling, like in time series
modeling and in transitions of
stochastic processes. The Markov blanket
is abstracting. It from this
time sequence idea. Like the now is a
blanket between the past and the future.
And we could think about spatial systems
like a Newton's cradle or something like
that, as well as spatial temporal
systems or just abstract causal systems.
So how can this be true? It's true by
definition because that's what the
definition of a Markov blanket is.
Whether that description is adequate or
maps on to carving, nature of the joints
and all these other things are
respectively statistical model
comparison and ontological philosophical
questions. But it's true by definition
about Markov blankets. Lyle yeah,
I think actually you just pretty much
covered it. But I would just say this is
the same condition if you're building RL
models of different kinds of autonomous
systems, this is the same restriction.
I think your comment about the nested
blankets is interesting because in the
RL space we typically don't have that
kind of richness. But what we do then
would be, for example, we want to know
the distance. And in that case
we would just create, basically create a
state variable, which is the
history of the state transition.
So we fudge it a little bit. But your
explanation that in this
conception with nested Markov blankets,
then that would be the more
comprehensive solution to that issue.
Thanks. Just to kind of clarify, there
like one hack or workaround would be
like you make the list of all of the
last possible three moves and then you
make a one Markov blanket with all the
last combinations of three. That's
right. So it still uses the machinery of
a one Markov chain, which has the
simplest transition matrix, but it could
encompass the last states. But it sort
of compresses them into a one Markov
chain format. Yeah, I mean, very often
you want to know the average of the last
20 time steps. You're just trying to
smooth something, right. And it's just
way too much work to build all that
machinery in there. So you
make that average. Actually a present
variable is what you do. Great example.
If something really does depend on the
last 20 time steps, or you want to do
model comparison as to whether it's a
better model that is conditioned on the
last 15 or 20 or 30, you can just
condense it with summary statistics and
descriptions. Again into this one Markov
framework. Otherwise the combinatorics
of how the 20 influence each other is
vast. Brock I
guess that's related to what my comment
was just going to be. That the way they
worded it. If you're not rigidly
thinking about a singular Markov
blanket,
just practically speaking, finding about
the past usually does give you
information about the future. If you're
talking about outside of a singular
Markov blanket. Right.
Adding the words no additional
information about
the future of the Markov blanket is
gained by finding out about the past.
The Markov blanket kind of balance that.
But in the case of the machine learning
example and comparing models, you're
necessarily talking about a much larger
markup blanket than just a singular one
there, right? Yes, same thing.
Yes. And just like many concepts have
like a broader conversational, informal
sense in a narrow, more technical sense,
assuming we know the present means fully
knowing the present, fully knowing the
blanket. So it's like but I could still
learn things about the past. So that's
not to say that there isn't novel
information that you could discover
about the past. Like you could still go
back in that chess game and learn
information. So it's not that there
isn't information in the past. It's not
that it wouldn't even be interesting.
It's that for the purposes of how the
present goes into the next time step the
present blanket in this temporal Markov
chain, which is like a blanket through
time, it contains the information you
need for the transition frequencies.
Okay. They define that it's the set
of variables that mediate. And also the
Markov blanket using last names,
personal opinion is not helpful because
not only are there multiple Markovs,
but the Markovian property is not
something that's technical or defined.
So maybe someday we'll have better ways
to describe and be more specific that
don't involve invoking ambiguity around
names. That being said, it was worked
out analytically by Markov and sun and
others, but most recently it was Pearl
1988 and causal inference with Bayesian
perspective. So this is not like an
active inference, ism it's? Drawing upon
a total Bayesian statistical framework,
any Bayes graph that's not fully
connected is going to have some nodes
that intermediate. So that's going to
relate to this question. So what is a
statistical rather than a non
statistical interaction?
Ali and then anyone else who would like
to address that?
Well, I think it has something to do
with the way these interactions are
parameterized and modeled. Because, you
see, every phenomena can be
parameterized and modeled from many
various perspectives and frameworks
within various frameworks. And the
reason I think they put the term
statistical in parentheses is that they
mean that these variables mediate all
interactions that have been
parameterized statistically. So I
think it refers to the nature
of parameterizing and modeling these
interactions as opposed to
distinguishing between statistical and
non statistical interactions.
All right, so anyone else can raise
their hand, but just here's a few
thoughts on that. A statistical
interaction is the edge in a causal
Bayes graph. And people might
be more familiar or have seen like
structural equation modeling, where
nodes are variables and edges are the
correlation between or among variables.
Conditioning on the structure of the
graph. In the causal Bayes graph,
the nodes are variables and the edges
are statistical causal influences. So
causality and statistics is not always
the same as what people mean by cause in
the real world. But like granger
causality and just this notion of like
coarse graining and cause.
It may line up with the
sort of narrative natural language
description that somebody has between
when they're speaking. It might be
narrower than that, it might be a
different thing than that. It might be
more general than that.
What would a non statistical interaction
be?
There's various ways to approach that.
It's kind of pointing towards some sort
of like a touch could be an interaction.
But what if things are touching but
those variables don't change as a
function of their touching? Then do
those things interact or not? That's one
question. And then cause there's like
just tremendous real world and
philosophy questions like what causes
what, what's the difference making
cause? What's the cause that makes a
difference? Necessity and sufficiency.
There's so many questions in this like
causal philosophy and this is
highlighting. We're talking about the
model. We made a Bayes graph with
height, weight and shirt color and here
are the statistical effectors. And so
we're not saying that there's no
interaction between this and that in the
real world. Now we're within the model
and we're talking about the causal
graph. And again, unless the Bayes graph
is fully connected, there's going to be
some partitioning scheme that
will result in some set of nodes being
conditionally independent from another
set of nodes when conditioned upon a
blanket. So it's not like features of
the real world or even variables in a
statistical equation can just be
unilaterally tagged as blanket states.
It's always a partition that
coinstantiates two sides,
internal and external. But there's a
symmetry and the blanket. So it's not
like features of the world or even
features of the model are intrinsically,
internal, external or blanket states.
But that's a partitioning scheme that
can be applied to Bayes graphs of like a
vast various structures
of Bayes graphs. And Bayes graphs can be
applied to a vast number of real world
situations. And many, many papers
and live streams discuss sort of like
all encompassing Markovian monism Markov
blankets all the way down nested Markov
blankets. Are the world ranging to the
critical perspectives, not necessarily
detractors, but just those who believe
that the usage of the concept is out
of alignment with ways that people have
used it. Mike and then anyone else.
Does it make sense to think of a Markov
blanket in the context of an internal
agent state and an external environment?
Is the Markov blanket serving as this
kind of a decoupling component because
of the way that things are conditionally
independent based on the variables
inside the blanket?
What do people think?
Yes.
I mean, for the internal state to be
different than the external state or
have some other equilibrium other non
equilibrium state that the external
environment is in, you would have to
necessarily have I'm
not sure if decoupling is the right
word, but some sort of conditional,
dependent and independent sort of zone
that separates those two regions.
So here's figure 31. Thank you, Brock.
The active in the sensory states compose
the blanket now in various
live streams and papers, the history of
the concept again from the analytical
pre computational phrasing of insulation
of fluctuation of random variables to
Pearl's Bayesian and computational
framing. However, Pearl's Markov blanket
concept doesn't have a delineation of
active and sensory states. It's only
like there's one kind of fabric in that
blanket. It's just blanket states.
Friston maybe this also will be
shown to be traced to other places and
ways. But one of the core things that
Friston at all have brought into the
picture was interpreting within the
blanket states the states that have
incoming dependencies to the system of
interest as sensory and then the states
that have outgoing dependencies from the
system of interest as active states. So
people may already see challenges and
complexities that arise with the arrows
and the directions. And a lot of that is
addressed in the how particular is the
free energy principle of Aguilera et al.
We're going to continue talking about
this entity partitioning Ali
and then Lyle.
Well, I think we should point to a very
important typographical error in
this picture here because in this
figure, active states are expressed in
terms of external states and markup
blankets and sensory states are
expressed in terms of internal states
and markup blankets. But it should be
vice versa. I mean, the flows of
internal and active states are
independent of external states and the
flows of external and sensory states do
not depend on internal states. So we
should change x and mu in those
two equations.
Yes, sometimes with a possible typo
like that, it's so Egregious blatant
that it's challenging to even know. But
we can absolutely ask the authors. But
just to read the equation and think
about why it is that way. The dot
is the rate of change of a variable. So
the internal states are mu and so this
is the rate of change of internal
states, rate of change of external
states x and the rate of change of u,
the active states and y the sensory
states. So we're looking at how these
partitioned states in a Bayes graph
change through time. The states that are
the blanket and the internal are the
particular states. Those are referring
to the particle that's like figure
versus ground, the particle that's
moving around the curious particle. The
active entity is the particular states
that is partitioning the thing,
literally the thing away from the niche.
Then there's the blanket states that are
intermediating that interface. And then
we'll also talk about autonomous states
which are just the internal and the
active states. So the equation is saying
the rate of change in, for example,
active states is a flow function
F and a noise function.
Both the flow and the noise function the
subscript is referring to like that one.
It's kind of like IPSO in Latin like,
it's the flow on Mu and the noise on Mu,
the flow, which is what the principle of
least action converges us towards in the
limit, when the statistical fluctuations
from the Omega are low, is a function of
certain variables. And so this is saying
the flow of active states is
a function of external sensory
and active states. However,
as Ali has pointed to, the arguments
that should be guiding the flow of
active states are actually the blanket
states and internal states, not external
states. And then analogously sensory
states should have a flow that's defined
in terms of blanket states and external
states, not internal states.
Lyle and then Ali yeah.
So actually I think you're getting right
right at the question I had because I
was confused about the bi directional
arrows, particularly between internal
states and active states. Right?
And I think you're drilling right into
that. I still don't completely
understand what that picture should look
like. But I have trouble conceptually
I sort of get a conceptually, I feel
like I get the Markov blanket, but that
representation. I have trouble working
through the details on that.
Cool. So, guest stream number seven.
How particular is the physics of the
free energy principle? It explores
different entity niche
causal relationships. Like,
for example, we could imagine a simple
around the clock entity model.
External states induce sensory states.
One directional arrow, sensory goes into
internal, internal to active, active to
external, like an UDA loop or something
like that, but just an around the clock,
no bi directionality, no connection
between active and sensory. Given this
partitioning, one could imagine that
topology of cause, one could imagine
all kinds of topologies of cause, some
that violate the Markov blanket
condition, like internal states and
external states that are no longer
internal and external because they would
have a causal link. But even preserving
the Markov blanket condition, we could
imagine different topologies, different
sparsities of couplings between these
different states. A bi directional arrow
is kind of like there would be a non
zero cause. And in the other side of the
matrix, it would also be a non zero
cause versus a unidirectional
relationship where like variable two has
a causal influence on three, but three
doesn't have it on two. In this paper in
Guest Room 7.1 and that paper and
further line of research, they explore
what sparse coupling structures,
causal architectures of the entity niche
relationship and interface would grant
different statistical capacities. So I
could be wrong on this, but active
inference is not a commitment to this
specific coupling architecture.
It may be possible to design or describe
or imagine systems that have different
causal architectures, maybe even
true at this basal most kernel loop,
but certainly true when we start
thinking about nested structures and
cognitive structures and so on. So yes,
it is a little unfortunate about this.
However, this is just
thinking about causal relationships of
the particular partition and
we're describing statistical
relationships here causal influence, as
inferred from like, time series data
with Granger causality or other methods
on specific random variables. So this is
not the conversational notion of cause,
but what I'm thinking is eventually
resulting in things happening in the
outside world, or aren't things in the
outside world eventually changing
things? Yes, but just like the
chessboard through time, the blanket is
statistically intermediating. And again,
that's why it gets so messy with the
application of like well, the retina
must be the sense states.
If one can read that example and
not fall into the quicksand, it could be
didactic. But to tag retina
as sense state is like the tip of the
iceberg of a partially specified model,
often one where the measurements have
not actually occurred and so on. So then
that can be extremely difficult for
those with less familiarity with a
formalism to generalize accurately from,
because shouldn't it be like retina
sense states and then the arm is the
active state, but it's a partitioning
that coinstantiates and it's model
dependent, it's not describing features
of the real world. Ollie?
Yeah, I just wanted to .1 of Ramset
at All's recent fascinating paper
on Bayesian mechanics, which I put the
link in the chat. And in that paper,
especially in section three, they have a
very illuminating discussion
about these whole business of
partitioning and markup blankets. And
one sentence that's pretty relevant to
our discussion here is that the key
point to note is that the flow of
internal and active components I e.
Their trajectory through state space
does not depend upon external
components. And reciprocally, the flow
of external and sensory states or paths
does not depend upon internal states or
paths. From page 15. So yeah,
if you refer to that article, it has
been elaborated much explicitly.
Also, in four days we will have
Dalton and Maxwell et al. For a guest
stream. The paper just came out.
Now we'll be able to have a discussion
with them and learn and ask them
questions. So if people have suggestions
for guest streams, that can be
accomplished. If people want to
facilitate or participate in different
streams, if they have questions for
different streams. Being there live,
but especially getting involved eagerly
and actively and early is the biggest
leverage point because that allows us to
design the material so that it's, like
permanently useful rather than
potentially ad hoc questions that arise
during which can be super important and
hopefully people can see some
affordances for participation and
development. Let's just get to this last
question and we have other questions,
but these are essential and it's one of
the opening formalisms of the chapter.
Just to conclude here though, why does
independence between the flows on the
two sides of the blanket matter so much?
These are good things to think about.
Just one short thought would be without
independence between the flows, there is
no distinguishing one thing from
another. Ali.
And also I think it relates to what
we read in chapter two about hidden
states because that's what the word
hidden probably refers to. I mean,
internal state does not have direct
access to external states and vice
versa. So that Markup Blanket pretty
much formalizes this hiddenness,
yes, awesome. And partially
observable models of the Bayesian
type which are used in partially
observable Markov decision processes,
expectation maximization, any kind of
Bayesian priors and hyper priors and so
on. All of these have Bayes graphs
that reflect conditionally independent
variables. So it's not that they're
independent in a conversational way,
like they don't have any way of
communicating, it's that they are
specifically involved in a causal
network that has conditional
independence. But we'll hopefully
develop more answers and notes here.
We'll move on. What is the differences
between and among the terms Bayesian
brain hypothesis, predictive processing,
predictive coding and active inference?
Might you be able to suggest references
or resources for where these
distinctions are delineated? Sure, so
anyone can add more. But here's, I think
two key resources here. The first is
live stream 43. In 430,
Maria gave a really excellent overview
of predictive processing and predictive
coding from a historical perspective.
And briefly, she proposed that
predictive coding can refer to a
unidirectional data encoding scheme of
the kind that we see in signal
processing, video compression, so on,
whereas predictive processing is
referring to a bi directional
architecture where predictive coding is
implemented in this ongoing top down,
bottom up way. Bayesian brain
hypothesis was also touched on and we
connected this to active inference. But
43.0 is a long technical review paper,
but we have three discussions on it
predictive coding, theoretical,
experimental review, recent paper,
very good source for the predictive
processing encoding. And predictive
processing encoding initially was more
of about a sensory framework.
However, at the end of that paper they
show, okay, now we're going to do
predictive processing on action. It's
active inference. So predictive
processing about action is six
of one and half dozen of another within
a margin of reasonable approximation,
similar, but there's also some key
differences like reliance on different
formalisms. But these are all things for
us to explore and unpack as we work on
the ontology and so on.
Specifically, predictive coding active
inference in the Bayesian brain. This is
an interview that a departed colleague
and I did with Karl Friston in 2018 and
we specifically asked the Bayesian brain
hypothesis, predictive coding and the
free energy principle are often equated
with one another. You yourself have
suggested that the three frameworks are
variations of the same basic mechanisms.
So 2018 was a very different time.
Active inference had not been delineated
from FEP in the same way that it is
coming to be now. And there was a lot of
other differences between then and now.
But he gives an extended answer. So for
people who want to learn about that,
his extended answer and Martin's
Restatement of the Bayesian brain
hypothesis are still some of the best
places to find clarity on that issue.
Does anyone have any other thoughts or
questions on this?
Just one other note, while anyone can
raise their hand, is like the Bayesian
brain hypothesis sometimes could
be used in a very instrumentalist way.
We're using Bayesian statistics to do
neurobehavioral research. It might be a
realist implementational claim,
like the brain is doing Bayesian
statistics or something like Bayesian
statistics. So this hypothesis floats
kind of among the layers of Mars
analysis, like implementational
algorithmic, computational.
And people do use it to mean different
things. And in Bayesian
graphs, in Bayesian statistics, it can
be about perception or it could be about
action. So Bayesian brain hypothesis,
depending on how somebody frames it and
what specific models they're talking
about, might include, for example, all
of these, because these might be applied
in a Bayesian framework to talk about
the brain. Ben.
Yeah, I think you've covered it really
well, but I wish I'd have had access or
knowledge of the result, the talk that
you just mentioned. Because trying to
differentiate predictive processing from
active inference has been a kind of
source of pain and confusion for me over
the last few months. And I thought
another way of putting it, perhaps
because I think I know the difference
now is essentially some
presentations of predictive processing
are active inference in the sense that
they're highly embodied, inactive,
embedded. And so if you have a
predictive processing that draws on
these Fourier accounts of cognition, it
tends to just that just is active
inference. Active inference is kind of
necessarily inactive and embodied. And
there's a paper I should say there's a
paper by I believe it's called Wilding
the Predictive Brain. It's by Andy
Clark, Kate Nave, Mark Miller and George
Dean, I think, which basically takes
predictive processing as a theory of
neural processing and weaves in these
kind of cognitive, these four E
narratives really, really well and kind
of fleshes out a much more active
inferencey picture. The paper brings
predictive process and active inference
together really nicely, I think.
Thanks. Great suggestion. And just
without going into too much detail, if
this is the causal graph architecture of
a predictive processing system, one can
imagine that, like, Mu is being a
Markov blanket with respect to these two
epsilons or so on. So predictive
processing doesn't highlight as much the
Markov blanket. Formalism predictive
processing is not a physics for
particular systems like FEP is,
but it's not incompatible. So maybe
they're just different fingers pointing
at similar or different parts of the
moon. So there isn't an incompatibility,
especially as over the recent years,
active inference implemented predictive
architectures and approaches, and
predictive processing started to undergo
that Pragmatic, inactive, four E, five
E, whatever, infusion which
led to them modeling action as a
variable. And so all they did was they
just made it. So instead of the free
energy being only about sensory
observations. And expectations. They
just tucked action in and it doesn't
radically restructure the architecture.
It just means that action is a variable
in these equations. So 43.1
or zero, one and two are all good places
to look. Okay,
this was just a short question.
Internal state and external state were
added to the ontology. But sometimes,
like, if you have a quotation mark and
then an at, it won't bring it up.
So sometimes you have to type it with an
at first.
Okay, in our last 15
minutes,
okay, these two are good. Maybe we could
do a first pass on them and then in the
coming week, like add notes and more
questions to discuss. They wrote,
if one defines preferred states as
expected states, then one can say that
living organisms must minimize the
surprise of their sensory observations.
I'm not clear on the ontology here. Is
it that preference is the same as
expectation or that formally we can use
them in the same equation or something
else? Does active inference make
ontological claims like preference is
actually expectation, just as heat is
actually the excitation of molecules
more generally? Is the free energy and
physics just an analogy or is it an
ontological assertion? Who would like to
approach one of the aspects of this
question?
I would like to take a stop, but again,
I guess guess yes, please. I guess
it's not saying that they're the same,
but that if we're minimizing free
energy, we're trying to make it the
same. But if they're surprised,
they won't be the same. I guess the goal
is to get them as close as possible.
That will be my guess on this. Thank
you. Good insight. I'll also point to
two ways that expectation is
conversationally used. The expectation
with the fancy e is the expected
mean of a distribution. Like, expected
returns might be about the future, but
it's actually referring to the mean
estimate of a distribution. In the
Gaussian case, the mean and the mode are
the same. Mode seeking and mean seeking
are equivalent. There can also be a
variance estimator and so on. So the
expectation of a Gaussian is like
tremendously informative. Expectation
can also mean things that are predicted
about the future.
That's a conversational. What do you
expect it to be tomorrow? Both can be
conjoined. Like what do you expect the
temperature to be tomorrow? Is the
expectation of a distribution of the
uncertainty of the temperature
distribution at the time point tomorrow.
So they're not exclusive definitions.
It just has to be understood what this
means because it'd be like, well, if our
predictions about the future are our
preferences, then there's all kinds of
tangles that one might find himself in.
Also the
I'm not remembering which number it was,
but the dual usage
of the same term to reflect the
organism's preferred states and also
the centering of the distribution at
that time point and at other time
points. And then just like jessica
mentioned, this operation of free energy
minimization is in service of reducing
the divergence between the preferred
state and the expectation of
the preferred state, which could be set
or learned, and then the observations
that are coming in. So in one
equation, it leans more towards the
English description of a preference.
Like the organism prefers to be at 72.
And in the other sense, that is like the
expectation of a distribution. And
there's some observation distribution
with a minimization of a divergence such
that if the observations were
realizing preferences, then those
distributions would be aligned.
So, yes,
these terms are more like phenomena or
natural language tags. Also,
it'll be awesome. In the last two weeks
of June, in 46,
active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology. This will be
extended, extended discussions on,
like, wanting beliefs, intentions.
Which variables in active are
appropriate for being described that
way? Does it contradict one or the
other? Those are like things that we'll
explore. So the
equations are just what they are. And
then in some usages,
a variable is like the organism's
preferred states, what it's trying to
reduce its divergence between. And also
that is like, where it expects to be.
And that's what licenses the use of
surprise and minimizing. Surprise
because an observation right at the
center of the Gaussian is minimally
surprising. We talked about that in
chapter two. An observation that's
outside of the Gaussian is highly
surprising. So if we have some sort
of distribution of outcomes,
we could ask how closely are they
aligned with our preferences in terms of
surprise due to this dual use
of the same variables?
Does active inference make ontological
claims? Do theories make claims? Do
people make claims? E. G preference is
actually expectation, just as heat is
actually excitation of molecules.
Anyone can raise their hand at any time.
We'll talk about that in the folk
psychology. But it's an interesting
question. Ben yeah, I wonder
if it seems to me like these questions
are taking us maybe into the map
territory debate that I think we spoke
about last time, about how realist
or concrete should we think about the
kind of ontological claims of active
inference? It's certainly the last part
of that question, I think, about whether
we should take it as an analogy.
So, yeah, I think it's quite a big
question, but I don't know.
Okay, I won't find the slide here, but
is the free energy in physics an
analogy? Not sure if this is saying,
like, the Gibbs free energy or if that's
actually talking about the variational
free energy or the expected free energy,
which are statistical so I don't know if
it's an analogy or an ontological
assertion other than just
to connect it to a linear model with a
Gaussian Error distribution. Is that an
ontological assertion that there is a
Gaussian Error distribution in the
world? No.
So are statistical quantities
ontological assertions about the world?
Maybe there's some nuance, but broadly
speaking, no.
And also, just like on the Math learning
group, we've expanded our operation due
to many active participants. So just
note that the meetings are at 19 UTC
on Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday and
Thursday. And they're in the discord
voice chat, not in this gather. But
we've been working on the resources on
the notation, basic and background
questions, as well as overviews of the
math for different chapters, like
basically just summarizing and then
several people, and this is an example
of the broken link. So, like
variational, free energy is deleted. So
just one time somebody has to come
through and just add it back in. But
these are natural language descriptions
that will be very easy to transmute into
computer code and translate amongst
human languages and provides a lot of
legibility and comprehensibility. So a
lot of the math group has been modifying
the equations and everybody is welcome
to join those discord sessions and
contribute with questions or with
knowledge and expertise. Like, no matter
where somebody is in learning or
discussing these equations, they are the
essence of active inference. So
questions, random notes, related
thoughts, expertise are all essential
for us improving our shared
understanding. And then just in the last
five minutes, page 42, they wrote in
Advanced organisms, preferred states can
also extend to learned cognitive goals
and go on to say that advanced organisms
like humans, can achieve preferred
states by increasingly abstract social
and cultural strategies. Like they
talked about thermoregulation and then
all the way up to, like, air
conditioning distribution systems. My
question is, if they are cast in
terms of active inference, must all of
these preferred states and strategies be
ultimately linked to survival in some
way? Or in the case of advanced
organisms, can free energy be related to
something other than survival?
Mike and then anyone else?
Yeah, it feels like this notion of
survival and preferred states gets
conflated in a sort of odd way.
Not everything is about survival.
Right? And so you might have some
measurement of surprise if you're in a
temperature that's 120 degrees, but it's
survivable for a period of time,
whereas if you're in a temperature of
300 degrees Fahrenheit, not survivable.
Right. But if you contrast that with
other things that could be equally
surprising or outside the distribution,
as you described it earlier, the notion
of that all swans are white, but then
you find a black swan. And so you'd
never conceived that there might be a
black swan before that lives outside
your distribution and creates a
surprise, but it's not necessarily
survival rated.
Thank you. There's sort of a missing
severity in there somewhere.
Okay. Thank you, Ollie. And then Lyle.
I think Live here is used somehow
in a more direct way, meaning system
that resists dispersion and energy
dissipation. So it's not necessarily
biological survival.
Yes, great point. Systems that fail to
persist, survive, will not continue to
be that thing. And that's just in like a
physical sense, repeated measurements
are only enabled by systems that are
persistent at that timescale, not
eternally. And so when we want to have a
theory or a framework or a physics for
things, then they have to look
as if they are minimizing free energy.
Otherwise they will simply not be that
thing. Ben and then lyle.
This was my question. I suppose just to
kind of clarify it quickly.
One of the things I wonder most about
active inferences. It seems to me, at
least in my life, I'm quite often making
decisions and having preferences that
seem so abstracted from my attunement
with my environment or my continued
viability as a system. Like my
preference for which mug I'm going to
drink coffee out of in the morning. It
seems in some sense removed from
my free energy the way that free energy
is described in the literature.
That's kind of what I meant.
Great. In yesterday's
45.2 we asked specifically, like,
how can all behavior be optimal when
mistakes are made? Or I'll be asked the
question, like, what about when there's
like sacrificial or altruistic behavior?
And there's a great answer
in 45.2, but suffice to say that with
different priors, all behavior can be
cast as optimal behavior. So the
normativity isn't referring to what
should be done or what is best, but it's
rather like a process normativity. Lyle
right, yeah. This for me tees up the
question I continue to have about the
approach, which is how does the concept
of novelty, which some
organisms would pursue,
fit into this concept of I mean,
how would it even be represented here?
And novelty is not just a human trait,
but you would see it across all kinds of
creatures that would seek out
novel and surprising experience, not
expected. So for me, it's kind of an
open question about how that's captured
in this framework. Yes, the beginning
and ending of 45.2 carl's focus
was on curiosity and there's
various ways to approach it. And it's
an excellent question about novelty of
different types and scales. And within
the hierarchical modeling, one can
understand novelty of different kinds.
And this again is just like the kernel.
This is like the single linear
regression. And then there's like model
selection across hierarchically nested
linear models, much development beyond
the kernel. But this is like a kernel.
And especially when thinking about
expected free energy, a path can move
to a novel area because it's part
of an expected trajectory that does
reduce risk and ambiguity and so on. So
that's the deflationary approach to
novelty pursuit. Jessica and then we'll
end the discussion.
At the end. You mentioned it. I guess I
see novelty as sort of like the
epistemic origin. And so it's like
you are seeking new
information, new things, in order to
minimize that uncertainty.
Not so much that novelty is uncertainty,
because if we look at Nova's
thinking that, oh, it's new and
therefore it's going to be surprising
and so we want to minimize those things
then yes. Or also if we look at
uncertainty equal to risk, we can say
like novelty is because of the unknown
represented risk and if we're minimizing
uncertainty, we're trying to minimize
risk. But from what I saw a little bit
on chapter two, it's sort of like we're
not necessarily trying to minimize risk
or the unknown.
Depending on our preferences, we might
tolerate high risk. And what we're
trying to minimize is the surprise of
what we expect. If I'm in finance, and I
expect very high risk in an investment,
but I already know that and
high risk comes back.
My uncertainty was minimized, even
though there was a lot of risk or there
were a lot of unknowns or novelty
and things like that. But it was already
in my expectation of what was going to
happen. So I was already minimizing
that, even though in reality it may look
like that there was a lot of uncertainty
in actuality, but in my model there
isn't. So that's kind of like how I
explained that to me a little bit and in
terms of novelty for adventure and
curiosity and things like that, I
equated more to epistemic foraging as a
weight of learning and updating the
model and that's why we're doing it.
Thanks, Jessica. I'll just add one
closing note on that. I would argue that
it's the pragmatic absolutism,
the reinforcement and reward learning
centrism that has curtailed an effective
theory of novelty or curiosity because
radically different kinds of actions
have to be coerced into a value
framework, whether it's deep Q learning
or reinforcement or anything like that.
There has to be like a novelty bonus or
all these other ad hoc unprincipled
approaches. They might be super
technical, they might be super
effective, but they're not driven from
first principles in variational free
energy f and expected free energy g.
There's this minimum of two with
pragmatic value which is to bring
alignment between the preferences and
the observations and the epistemic value
associated with what is casually called
novelty or curiosity. At that scale of
potentially a hierarchical model, So
active inference does provide
partitioning and an imperative that
helps us address the phenomena of
curiosity and of novelty in a way that
is quite disparate from trying to coerce
it into a value of curiosity.
Is expected pragmatic value or the value
of basic research is the expected
utility that it could bring. But these
are all really awesome and open and
ongoing questions. So we will close the
recording and then have just a 1 minute
break. Then in this room we'll continue
with tools, organizational unit and if
anybody wants to talk about something
else, they can go to a different gather
room. So thanks everybody and see you
next week.