You.
All right. Hello and welcome everyone.
It is July 7,
2023, and we are in the first
introductory session of the course,
active Inference for the Social
Sciences. This is going to be a really
exciting course and journey that we're
all going to join and co create
together. With no further ado,
I will pass it to please mute turn off
the live stream Avil. Thank you.
Complex systems and feedbacks with
cyberphysical systems will be a theme.
We told you it would be. I will pass now
to Avil for the introductory session.
If you're watching live, please feel
free to write any comments or questions
in the chat and I'll relay them at the
end onto the lecture. Thanks, Abel.
Go for it.
So, hi, do you hear me? Well, there was
a sound issue. Okay, cool. So I'm
avoid I organized, I guess, the course.
I had the idea and worked on
the curriculum. Do you see
the slides? Well.
Looks good. And just make sure to close
the YouTube video or mute it. So, hi,
do you hear me? Well, that was Sunday.
Sure. Okay, cool. Okay. I did not know I
had to do that. So this
is the introduction session of the
course. Very unsurprisingly. My name is
Kerriu. I am a funding member of Kairos
Research and I am a non funding member
of Active Inference Lab, which co
organize the course.
And first I will basically present the
teaching team. So we have Danielle,
which is with us, which is a PhD in
Ecology and Evolution, studying ants
behavior in an eco evo kind of way,
who is a president and co founder of the
Enactive Transitutes and who is
interested in, among the things art,
philosophy and cognitive security. Then
we have Ben, which is also here with us,
which is a second year PhD candidate in
Philosophy at the University of Sussex,
which, like me, interested four
E cognition, which is Embodied,
Enactive, Embedded and Extended
cognition. We don't need to get into
that now. He will explain to you. And in
Enactive Processing, which is basically
working on the cognitive science of
technology. And then we have people who
are not here today, which are mao
Albarasa, PhD candidate in the Cognitive
Computing at University Morielo,
which is head of Product Innovation and
Research at versus private sector
research lab in AI and the mathematics
of AI, which specializes in wildlife
inference. The theory we're working on
right now, script theory, which she will
Extended maybe I will talk a bit of it
today, but she will be the one who
explains what script theory is to you
and modern artificial intelligence.
And we have Lauren Gonzala, also a PhD
candidate, also in philosophy, but in
Wollongong, I believe this is how you
say it in Australia, which is centered
in philosophy of mind and in the status
of information processing, as the term
is used in cognitive science.
And then there is me. So I made a career
timeline because when I talk about what
I did, people get confused. I did
physics, math, I did engineering, I did
cognitive science. I did research in
ecology and evolution. I did a master's
in complex system physics, and I did,
like, one year, apparently, given my
timeline or two, no, more than more,
two of independent research as part of
kerose research and as part of the
French Society of Cliodynamics before I
started the PhD I'm doing now. Which is
something about the enaction between
mind and material culture. We will get
into that at some point.
And the question motivation I have are
essentially describing the relation
between phenomenology. So the way we
experience the world and physical
reality, which I have the fringe view
that somehow phenomenology is
constructive of physical reality, which
could have weak and strong
interpretation. I subscribe to both.
I'm trying maybe more importantly here
to explain or at least describe how
sociocultural life form, let us say the
regularities that in the life, social
life, human social life are constructed,
which is hard. And I'm trying to build a
research that is effective at doing
knowledge, not word piles through
our work in Kairos research. So these
are specific reference. You will get the
slides at some point I guess I will
publish them on the website and then we
will be able to check it out if this is
of interest to you. So let us get on
the actual relevant content.
So what we are going for here is
basically explain the very basic demarch
of the course, explain how it's
of relevance, how the framework we
propose is of relevance to social
science and present a few case study to
make the case. And then we will talk
about course layout. But this is pretty
quick. So first I'd like
to talk about the explanation of
cultural dynamics. What does explaining
cultural dynamics even mean?
Depends who talks. There are many
types or views on what is scientific
explanation. I say we can cluster them
in three broad categories. One is
numerological, so it's about laws. And
what it does is to take regularities,
just say here is this regularity and
consider that these statements. So the
law has an explanatory capacity
toward the regularity. So for example,
for those of you who are familiar with
the work of, and I forget
names,
foundation, the foundation trilogy, I
believe it's trilogy. This is pretty
close to what they call psycho history.
So basically trying to find laws of
behavior and using them to predict
history in a regular lawful way,
then we have mechanical explanation
which are more typical of the life
science. And what we do in mechanical
explanation is to look at the structure
of a system and model the structure and
try to use this model to predict
specific regularities that are of
interest. And you have
approach to social sense that is I'd say
quite close to that which is
Cliodynamics, which waits a lot on the
Nomological side but still is centered
on dynamics and mechanisms and
explanation by calling onto
structure in specific societies. And
then you have a functional explanation
which asks what constraints exist so
that the system does what it is that the
system does. Here again, you will also
use a lot of contextual modeling, very
often evolutionary game theory. So
simulation where we suppose that agent
can have specific traits and those that
reproduce more or that have more fitness
give their traits around and you
have the discipline field of study of
culture evolution that does that very
concretely by just asking how culture
evolves. So what cultural threats can
get more fitness and be transmitted a
very evolutionary centered approach to
social change. So,
to sum all of this up, basically we
explain things by calling on to
regularities always and we can
talk about regularities in the
phenomenology. So what the system does
in of itself in the structure that is in
the language system activity or in the
function that is the constraint that
exists over what the stem does and
you have a specific brand of explanatory
strategies that try to Legify behavior
to make Nomological lawful explanation
of human behavior and of sociocultural
change. And it's not immediately
evident how they do that, how they think
it's a coherent idea to begin with
because well, humans learn culture
change so what laws could they be in
a field which is changing with time
always? So in
my opinion it is more a question of
rhetorics than of epistemology because I
do not think the answer is coherent.
The answer is, as far as I'm concerned
that people they just Raify
regularities that are observed in
experimental settings often that are
quite heavily fabricated as kind
of cognitive laws of behavior.
And because those people usually
agree in spirit to the mechanical kind
of explanation they talk about cognitive
mechanism or mental processes but only
insofar that those mechanism or
processes are explanatory of cognitive
laws. They do not do the work of looking
at the structure and function of the
systems. They just claim there must be a
mechanism that explain the vague law
that I have observed over 20 people
that came to my lab and these
laws, they are assumed to scale for the
explanation of social activity. And so
you have it, you have the recipe for
universal law of social change.
And basically the whole argument
stands on the idea that you have a
presentation or mental processes or
cognitive mechanism that somehow entail
that the subject's behavior is regular
through time and between individuals.
And you never have the work that would
actually in any capacity prove it for
reasons that we will not get into
because it would get math heavy and
renty. So if the
rules and regularities of human behavior
can change through learning, through
culture, evolution, through whatnot,
how can we exactly model or explain or
even describe this agency?
This is not dwell in anomaly callful
framework because when we do natural
laws, we look at regularities, we claim
here is a law, this regularity is a law.
So it explains that it exists and
this is a circle. Because as far
as I'm concerned, it's a circular
reasoning. Like the regularities explain
the regularities, which explain the
regularities. There is no way out of
this. You can recurse this all day long.
The only fact that you observe the thing
is your explanation for the thing. This
is not, hopefully, how we do Things in
Science. And you have a process
of explanation that is more complete.
If you look at structure and function
written lodge you can look at a specific
system which has specific structure.
And you can look at what the system
does, the function that the system
enacts a specific point in time. And you
can look at how this function, this
activity, shapes the system later on
at T plus one. You can have
developmental approach to things that is
centered on how system unfold how they
learn, how they evolve through time that
is doable there is no law against that
and it could actually work. So yeah,
let's do that. Let's explain natural
phenomenon by describing how the
underlying structure work but also by
trying to explain how it's brought about
how the system's activity explain the
way it takes shape through time.
So a claim that we will make
here that is itself could be
contentious but we don't have to look at
why it is not relevant here is that
active inference, which is a specific
new trendy theory of human cognition can
actually explain how regularities
underlying social activity be
constructed through time.
And let us look at what active inference
says precisely. So we
won't look at the math ever, we won't
look here at the specifics of the
theory. The only thing we are going for
is to prove that this theory indeed does
what I think it does, which is explain
or at least describe in a nontrivial way
the evolution of social regulatories.
So if active inference framework is
true, then cognitive agents perceive the
world through expectation they have
developed about the world. So perception
is an active process. I do not
perceive things with my eyes and compute
higher and higher level of traits of
what I saw. I basically expect things in
front of me and I will actively look at
the things that are most likely to
inform me. And something that is
critical about this framework is that
the prediction it also underlies action
or policies. So let's say trajectory of
action that I enact, I will do the
action that I believe I am more likely
to do. I will do that in virtue of me
believing I am more likely to do this
action. Whoops. So in
that framework, active inference is
understood as a process of enaction of
a specific model that is causally
shaped both by an agent's dynamics and
an environment Cliodynamics and this
relation well, brings a model that
corresponds in abstract way to the
structure of the dynamics of
the relation. And this model I can also
look at it in a way more concrete sense
in that it is what's in the lies what
drives the agent dynamic? You have a
duality between the Cliodynamics and the
epistemic mental states that we put,
that we project, that we can observe in
the dynamic. So a very important
aspect of this is that world's entirely
agency, as we would understand the term.
There is no distinct step of perception
which informs the agent on what the
world is like and based on which the
agents decide freely what action it
will take. There is a constant
prediction of what is going to happen
and this is enacted by the agent both
through perception and action. So what
drives decision here? What drives
generally the flow that analyze
the agent behavior is the agent self
model and that has interesting
consequences. So I have notifications.
So we'll cut them sorry,
what? Let me drink. I will drink. I need
to drink it.
So one consequence of this feminism is
that normativity so the values and
norms it's hard to go around that word
that drive behavior. They are not in the
brain, they are not something that the
agent abstractly relates to. They are
Embedded in the very process in which
the agent understands and gorges and
navigates the world. And this
is very relevant for a human cultural
evolution because well, we are cultural
creatures. We learn expectation
about each other both explicitly by
looking at how people do things and then
expecting them to do the same things
again and implicitly through the very
process by which we relate
to other people like norms, like
language. And the way you look at
this learning through be, it can
be reduced essentially because of the
properties of active inference to what
people call regimes of attention. So the
way I pay attention to things, the
specific things I will look at in my
process of understanding and navigating
the world,
the flow by which has been that is the
same thing as a set of value and a set
of expectations. So what
is important here is that normativity
and values and things like that, they
are Embedded in my cognition in a
much more basic way than conscious self
reflection. Although of course conscious
self enaction can inform that flow. It
is Embedded in the shared expectation
I have with other people. And there is
no warranty, no result that I can
actually be reflexive about it because,
well, the way I predict things, it's
based on the statistical regulators that
have seen in the world and because the
way I pay attention, it's entailed
by a predictive model of what is going
on around me. I'm very constrained,
very much constrained by the statistics
I have of the thing I have seen around
me. So regularities drive, how I pay
attention, which drive implicit or
explicit value and normativity. And you
can add dimical steps, you can add
reflexivity, you can add, I don't know,
accountability, you can add a lot of
things, but you cannot remove the very
basic way in which cultural values and
cultural expectation are Embedded in
perception.
Yes, this is a repetition of what I
said, the patterns in the flow of
attention that are Embedded that I have
developed through the very fact of
engaging with a cultural niche. And they
constrain my actions towards specific
outcome. They entail specific values,
specific norms, and they entail,
at least they constrain very heavily
the intention that I'm even able to
conceive to generate. So there
is an equivalent way to see this, which
is engagement with the cultural
landscape. So every agent, they
experience the world not in the same
way, of course, but they experience the
same. Let us say that each
person's experience of the world, it
predicts very strongly the experience of
the world that other people will develop
around them. So there are structural
properties of the landscape,
of opportunities and perception and
possible action that we experience.
There are properties that are
transferred between individuals
robustly. This is the case, for example,
of norms. If I
look at a law, any specific law, all of
the people in the same country, they are
subject to the same law. So maybe some
of them can just ignore it. They live
too far from the city. We don't have
cops here. Maybe some of them are above
the law in some capacity. It's their
relation. But the basic constraints that
the law entail, it is experienced by
everyone in a different way. We will all
expect that specific people will react
to specific situation in specific way.
And this is a real property of the
landscape that we experience. So the
way that this landscape shapes
exploitation in a robust way, we can
look at basically it as a constraint.
So not as a derivative property of a
landscape that I can or cannot
experience, but just as a statistical
force that shapes behavior in a
specific way. And looking at things
like that, it means that I can see a
given sociocultural field in two
complementary way as a set of agents
that navigate common well, not quite
common, but mutually constrained social,
cultural worlds or as a set of
constraints that produce itself. And the
way agents reconstruct the world around
them in their mind, the way they
understand it in a creative manner,
it is equivalent to the way the set of
constraints reconstruct itself. Which is
important because if I can
look at this whole world as a set of
constraints over statistical constraints
or behavior that reproduce itself, I can
look at it as a living thing, strictly
speaking, because this is how we define
living things, at least in specific sub
branch of system biology that I believe
is relevant is to be believed about
that. So when we talk
about structural landscape, we can look
at them either as a landscape of
affordances. This is opportunity for
action that are experienced and enacted
by a set of individual agents which
interact so as to having some level of
coherence between the landscapes they
experience and enact. And I can look at
the same landscape as a system of
constraints that are exerted over the
behavior of this agent and that I can
define and study with no clear reference
to any individual agent in the same way
that I can study a dog without looking
at every single individual cell. What
you're interested in, biology or
sociology is usually aggregated
patterns, not what every single living
thing around thinks of. Every single
thing. So that was
the heaviest it got probably over the
whole course.
I do not expect you to grasp all
of the consequences of what I said
because it was very condensed and it was
very abstract. But the case I'm making
here is not that everyone has to
understand all the math right now. It is
that this framework, it has things to
say about relevant question in social
science. And to make this point, I will
not just give the abstract presentation
of how it's awesome because we have
landscape. Whatnot I will look at
specific fields, questions, case studies
in social sense and I will look at
basically how Oxygen France entails a
pretty specific model of that that is
well grounded in committee sense and
that is relevant and that is adequate to
the study of living, changing systems,
et cetera, et cetera. So first
agenda setting. Some of you will know
what it is, some of you will not know
what it is. So Azure
setting is something that is situated in
the work on public opinion.
Specifically, I believe this book is
called Public Opinion.
So ajana setting. It refers
historically, although you have a more
diverse way to understand it now to the
role of mass media like journals and
later TV in manufacturing Consent. This
is a textualization from the text of
no, I thought I had the book cover, I
forgot the name of the guy. I'm sorry
you have to look at the reference. But
it is used to study how mass
media can manufacture consent by drawing
attention to specific issues and shaping
specific expectation about the world.
So the idea is that you have a role, an
active role of the elite, what I call
the elite here, people which have
active inference of the flow of policy
or society. I will call them elite. And
so those people, they basically transmit
norms, they transmit normative
expectation. So consent to whatever is
the thing that they do, they want you to
do more specifically. And they do so not
by telling you do this and that. They do
so by building agendas. So drawing
attention to specific issues in specific
way. And you can see here people
who are I mean, it's prevalent in
political life. Everyone knows that.
But the US. Right wing is very
transparent in doing that. And so this
is a meeting between two experts in a
general setting, donald Trump and Ron
DeSantis, which basically
have convinced people that they
should not worry about things like, I
don't know, the price of life, whether
we wage war here and there. Why do
we have to pay millions? Why do us?
People have to pay millions to get
health care, but to how LGBTQ Democratic
people threaten the US.
Life in a very abstract way? Like, I did
not ever hear any consistent, coherent,
believable mechanism by which they
explained how LGBTQ threatens whatever
Republicans. But they do draw attention
to this topic. They do share the
expectation that Democrats and GBTQ are
predators. And they do so in a way that
is able to legitimize themselves
as become other people, to mobilize
people to actually be behind them and do
their bidding and to canalize political
life in a way that is convenient for
them because it keeps them in power.
And the role of attention,
the way you pay attention to things in
shaping behavior, it's just a redo of
what I explained in active inference.
If you believe that the forces, the way
we constrain attention is explicit of
behavior, then you believe in active
inference just expressed differently.
So this is a case where you have a
classical, let us say, concept in a
circle sense that essentially reduces to
concepts of active inference. It's not
to say, of course, that astrology is
irrelevant and we should just do
cognitive sense, but this is pretty rare
to have such a direct response between
topics that are disciplinary this far
apart. So this is something we should
definitely pay attention to. So,
second case study nationalism.
Basically, this case study is entailed
by what I said over the Republicans
because the move by which they
legitimize their rule, it is just say we
share an identity here, us,
conservative, traditional values, et
cetera, et cetera. And this identity,
it entails specific norms. And for
reasons that we are usually left out of
the frame, I so elite people run
DeSantis, Trump, Napoleon, whoever. I
get to tell you what this entity entails
in terms of behavior. You don't get to
speak, really, because you are not
someone who has newspapers that parrot
what I say, what you say, because you
have to keep constant with this subject.
And this is very consistent with the
Cliodynamics by which we constructed
nation states. So for the historical
context, the idea that we have
ethnicities and this is somehow
relevant, normatively, like the Slav
should organize together or the, I don't
know, Hungarian should organize
together, and we should get to agree to
things that we do and then do them.
It's very recent. It's extremely
recent. Dates? Well, I won't get into
the specifics, but let us say in this
specific formulation, it dates from the
19th century, when you add a bunch of
very powerful bureaucratic
administration that took hold
respectively, of France, united Kingdom,
Prussia and they had the capability
to rule most of the social activity,
but they did not have any clear argument
why people should listen to them in any
capacity. And the way
it worked is that those administration
they basically started claiming that
they were somehow representative of a
given ethnical and linguistic community
and that in virtue of being part of this
community you should listen to them and
pay them respect and actively work for
their goal to be fulfilled. And of
course it is not that easy to make this
claim but what happened is they invested
a huge deal of energy and organization
into actually having people buy that.
They built schools, they built prison,
they built psychiatric hospital, they
built a lot of infrastructure that
enabled them to transmit norms in a very
robust way and transmit identity in a
very robust way. And in doing that they
managed to embed most of the micro
social relation you could have into
their specific ethnicity and into
the normative power they lend to this
ethnicity. So at some point, you know,
I always forget farmer in a lost
village in France you only meet at
tax time. So main arm come and tell you
give your grain and you give your grain
because else you're dead. And at some
point, those people send you a teacher
and they send you newspaper, and they
claim, hey, you are French. You have to
speak French. You have to be friends
with us. You have to fight our wars.
And because there is so much energy
that is pending that people actually
bite or die. That is another option
because the other
side of the coin is that states that
legitimize themselves through
nationhoods they have basically to be
all the time invested in ethnic
cleansing. Because people who are not
the right ethnicity they are not
considered element of these states. So
they have to be submitted or removed
which is a bad thing to do. This is a
very bad thing to do ethnic cleansing.
And I'd like
to illustrate this whole notion of
identity capture through the African
Renaissance monument that Abdullah Wade
So, the president of Senegal had
constructed in the capital. So it's very
glorious. It is very good example
of identity because it shows you the
norms, it shows your glorious image of
the African man and it shows
how you have to be supportive of
children, show them, protect them with
your big muscle and give them very wild
ambition, while African women look at
you like they were non agents.
Let us say that. So it gives a blueprint
around which society should be
organized. It gives you very
specific picture of who this is speaking
to. In this case Africans because I
guess Senegal gets to say what is good
for Africa. That is coherent
claim to make I mean sarcastic, sorry.
And why I like this specific monument
well, you have a lot lot well, first,
it's very expressive, the Ardotrion in
France it serves the basic same function
but it does not show you. It tells you
and the African society shows you what
it means in a very well obvious way.
And the second main reason is this you
have nothing around it. They just put it
in a pile of dirt and they invested
nothing in the infrastructure because
they were too busy taking money for
themselves, I guess. I don't know
exactly what did with tax money but
clearly it was more invested in the
symbolism of what African men should do
and why they should follow him
specifically and not in concrete
infrastructure. And in most
cases energy capture is very rodeal for
people who are captured. This is why I
call that capture because what you get
out of energy capture is a symbolic
sense of being part of the good team and
what you have to give is usually the
entirety of the work you do over your
life. It gets given
to the state or administration that
wants you to do things and do things for
them and sometimes they build
infrastructure but if they don't want
to, they will not. That is very
much a bad deal and I
gave it away. So national identity, it
was diffused to school and mass media.
It was Embedded in a micro network of
solidarity. So typically, the African
resource Monument, it basically tells
you that as a husband and father, you
have to give in whatever the state
ideology of Wad was.
And then it is leveraged for
mobilization and legitimation and
control. And you
have another I
did not say why it was relevant to
active inference. Well, it is relevant
to Enactive inference because all of
this is mediated by self model. All of
this is enabled because people have self
model and they enact the self model.
And there is no necessity of a reflexive
step where you actually think about what
is your self model and you are expected
to do a thing. You do the thing because
you expect yourself to be doing the
thing. And active in France, as we said,
you do what you expect to do. So this
basically explains why such symbolic raw
power it has actual consequences while
if you have more rational model of
humanity the question is why you build
big things and not infrastructure it
will be a rational response but this is
not what people do. People follow norms
and this is a way to broadcast norms
very efficiently and robustly. So due
to that I'd like to talk about structure
and agency so there is a constant
question in a social sense, usually
social sense talk about structure so
norms habitus way that institution
builds through life and there is a
legitimate question that is. Asked which
is if you believe structure to human
behavior, what is the place for agency?
So there are constant debates in every
subfield possible of social sense
regarding what is actually explained by
this structure and what is left to
individual agency. And what I want to
say is that this question is essentially
dissolved by the model of agency we
have. So as we said,
agency it's exerted through expectation
over myself. So because social structure
it becomes expected, it is enacted
through the agency of these specific
people that are within it not have an
opposition between how strong the
institutions are and how agentive people
are because strong institution are
institution that basically become
Embedded in your self model. And so
there are people freely not freely,
it's a bad term but from their own
accord they enact those institution.
And this is the whole thing about
anticapture, which I presented.
Nationalistic ideology is strong, is
efficient in building actual
mobilization because it makes you
believe that you will actually, if you
want a court, follow the social
order it gives, which was not
unprecedented, but pretty rare in a
premodern institution. Usually promoter
institution are I am the king. I have an
army. Give me food. And when you have
legitimation attempts to actually
explain why I should get the food these
are pretty much justification. This is
the elite people talking to themselves
about why they are justified knowing
that but you have no arguments and
that would be actually compelling so as
to why you would have to give the food
and you have no attempt whatsoever to
convince people who have to give the
food they should give the food. This
ideology they do not talk to the
people they ask things from, they talk
to themselves about why they
can't they are legitimate to take the
things. And so yeah,
in those case you have a pretty visible
conflicting between structure and
agency. Do I do what I'm told to do
under a threat of death or do I do any
other thing? Of course most people would
like to do other things but they can't.
And I will feel that they can't. But if
you accept that agency is built through
normativity, through engagement with a
sociocultural field of finances, of
productive action, you have to admit
that software exists at least in part
through agency. Because what agent
believe is legitimate, what agents
believe is right, what agent believe is
expected. It is very precisely
what constitutes structures and
that is insight
that is at least in part left out of
the conversation in some field. And I'd
like to show why the
direct conflict between certain agencies
it does not have a strong bonding.
Yes, again, I have said the thing that
the slide would say there is another
thing that is maybe closer to my core
body of work which is how active
inference afford indirectly an
archaeology of cognitive landscape. So
if socialization is made of constraint
over behavior and those constraints are
to some extent Embedded in the natural
environment of the people, then we can
to some extent study archaeological
landscape for themselves. We can look at
landscape like material landscape, the
object of study of archaeology, and we
can make some inference over the
constraints that this landscape entails
over collective behavior. I will not get
into detail as well as to why, because
it's far call. Making this inference is
difficult, but very concretely. We can
ask whether you're a key. So the
idea that some people get to say to
other people what to do and
certification, the idea that some people
are by nature above other people,
they can be Embedded in vertical
patterning. So you have a claim by
people who fund me escape project, look
it up, it's nice. You have a claim that
to some extent the rectification of
society around the Iron Age, it is
written, it is Embedded in vertical
patterns in material culture and
architecture. And maybe I will not
buy the claim outright, but it is very
compelling. If you look at specific
architecture, you get a specific
feeling. So this is the not cathedral,
but maybe Basilica of Frequency. I will
not try to say the name because I do not
speak Icelandic, and that would be bad.
But you have very progressive,
compelling curve toward the sky. You
have specific feelings that are,
how do you say, produced by this
architecture. And you have a very
specific way in which it drives
attention from something wide on the
ground to something that goes up. And if
I did not make it clear yet, if we buy
active inference, we buy that the
patterning of attention, the way you
give attention to things, it carries
norms, it carries intentionality and
in first person by introspection.
I think all of you can very clearly see
how architecture drives specific
patterns of attention and how those
patterns specific elicit specific
feelings. And we currently do not have
models that would be very specific and
very Enactive of how this work. But we
could this is huge work, but this is
doable work. This is not speculations.
And I do not know of another commonism
than active in France that would
actually make it possible.
And last, I'd like to talk about the
favorite thing in social sense, I guess,
which is thing like a state, scots
anthropology of states. So the
core argument of Scott's, I'd say it's
hard to identify a core argument in that
book. But you have ways in which states
so here equivalent to administrations.
They understand the world. They
understand the world through written
forms that they can pass around many
people, many institution to have
actually a coherent model of the world
that is pretty much abuse. And what
should be abuse but is not is that those
models are reductive in the sense any
model are. They emphasize specific
information and they leave out other
specific information.
And something that is very interesting,
I'd say, is that states they tend to
push specific models, specific
landscaping, specific norms in urbanism,
specific family norms that build
legibility. So the ability to be
understood by the state. So, for
example, you could have very sparse
settlements that are quite autonomous
and that do that thing. It is a
possibility. There is no law or physical
constraint around that. But it is far
easier as a state to manage what is very
close to it, right? So for a state,
it's good to have a population that
lives very close to the center of power
because those people, they are just
there. You can go tell them what to do,
it's simple. And you can go ask them
things. It's simple too. It's very easy
to manage that. And those
people, they would need food to stay
there. So we need some kind of food
production model that is easy to take
from and that is easy to organize and
goge as a centralized institution. And
this is monoculture, this is agriculture
as we understand it currently. This is
people that make big field, that make
the same crop always cereals. Well, not
always, sometimes potatoes, but mostly
cereals, because cereals, you know,
it's very dense, energetically, it is
easy to keep, it is easy to transport
because it is dense and it stay edible
long after recall.
You say recall in English cropping. I
don't know what is the word, but when
you take the food from the plants and
people have to stay there for very long
to cultivate that. So they cannot go
around and put potatoes here and there
and leave when they don't. So you can
just go to people and you know where the
people are and where you can take the
food and you know when the food is going
to be. Again, I don't know
the word cropped because it's
cereals. It's always the same time.
It's very visible in the landscape how
far you are from recollecting cropping.
So you cannot really have a way to cheat
that. You can just send many norms,
take the food, give it to the city, to a
different population, and you have a
very rationalized controllable society.
And we do not know that
this is the reason why we have cities
and monoculture, but we do have traces
that states very consistently tried to
have big cities and monoculture field
and mostly they succeeded.
And oh yeah, this is relevant to active
inference because in active inference,
the way you pay attention to things, it
is productive of your world, it is
productive of what cognition you have.
And here the capacity for
administration, the capacity for written
symbols that tell what things are, they
are critical to a state's understanding
of the world. They are what literally
produces the way states pay attention to
things. And the fact it was basically
major thing for them to have a world
that looks like this it is very directly
telling about the
fact it creates a world, it's a direct
instantiation of that and that is a nice
link to do and I'm happy I did this
link. So this is for
the case studies expectedly.
You don't see the corrections, not all
of them maybe you're convinced that
there is something there but most likely
you don't see very precisely what is to
be seen here. So the expectation is that
over the course, you develop a very
specific understanding of active
inference. The framework you develop a
specific understanding of how it relates
to social science, to questions that are
relevant in social science, and you
develop the capacity to have an informal
opinion on that critical informal
opinion on how this relates to question
in circle sense. So we
are doing the introduction lecture.
Hopefully I've convinced you there is
something to see here if not too bad.
And the next session will be in four
days, not one week, four days. It will
be about basically the basics
of active inference, what you have to
know to understand, not the framework
per se because it's math heavy, but what
the framework says about our life as
cognitive agent. So then you have the
discussion. You should know that for
each lecture there is discussion.
Lecture is vertical, people talk, you
listen. Discussion is more free form.
Every person has basically authority on
how they share the discussion but the
expectation is that it is a discussion
because it's the name we gave to the
thing. So after the basics we look at
patterns of collective behavior. So how
those elements on cognition, human
cognition or non human cognition, they
give tools to study the organization of
collective systems like ant colonies
or societies but we'll stay in not
specific to human approach. We'll be
interested in collective behavior but
will not be interested in the specific
patterns of collective behavior as
afforded by human cognition. Then we'll
look at semiotics and semantics, the
evolution of symbols so things that are
closer to humans, we'll look at how
Enactive inference accounts for
evolution of symbol and what evolution
of symbol affords for cognition and then
from here we'll look at very social
sensey things norm, script, narrative
language. So how this discussion on
active inference and collective behavior
and semiotics? They inform very
directly. They give a model specific
principled, predictive model of social
human behavior. And then we'll look at
so my thing, the way I like to think of
it all, which is social constraints and
we'll go back to the claim that there
are landscapes of social, cultural
cognition thingy thing. And those
landscapes can be looked at in
abstracted from the individual scale
manner. And this is explanatory of
cultural change. And then we go for the
conclusion. So we'll be interested in
your opinion of the course. This is the
first run we'd like to have feedback, a
lot of feedback on what you thought of
it and what would make it good.
So that will be for the conclusion
discussion. So here I
hoped that you'd present yourself.
We have not the capacity right now to
have students take the screen
and talk. But I'd like to know,
you can say in the chat what is your
background, what are your expectation
for the course? Whatever you want to say
about things, the world preferably being
related somehow to the course. That
would be nice, but yeah, please tell
things to Usher.
That concludes my talk. I thought this
slide made it clear we
have last thing, maybe we considered
making projects. So you making projects
that we read and maybe how
do you say grades. But I do
not think that we are in capacity to
give standardized
normalized degree or attestation that
has any value. So we decided not to do
it. So asking you to
do things, to do projects is a bit weird
if we're not going to grade it and
attest that you did it. But if you want
to do it, if you want to write things
and send them to us for review, this is
very okay, you can do that. We're not
formally invited to do that, but you can
do it. Well, I'll just add a point on
that and then meanwhile, if anybody
wants to ask a question in the live
chat, we did raise
this topic of different qualifications
and it's something that we've been
working on and continue to work on in
the Institute. So potentially in future
versions, but absolutely in future
offerings, we will have these kinds of
courses. But as Avel mentioned, this is
kind of a first run and so it's really
exciting just to even start that
conversation and see what people are
looking for in terms of certification.
All right, so let's go to some questions
in the live chat and comments.
Oh yeah, go ahead. I did not make the
escalation clear, but because it is a
first and because we are still shipping
the course, it is so much more important
that you actually tell us what you
expect out of it. Like what you want or
what you perceive will be here.
Expect in the active inference sense,
that is a bit perception, a bit action.
Please tell us about that. Awesome. In
fact, the only way to reduce one's
uncertainty is through active engagement
and one is literally applying active
inference when they do actively engage
in this epistemic way. So I hope that
all comes through. All right, a first
question from Sfumato in the chat. Does
active inference provide us with
predictive power, potentially focusing
on human or social scale issues?
What does it look like? Or where would
you say active inference provides us
with predictive power or unique
explanations and predictions?
So yes or no,
depending on the granularity of your
question. So what you look at Enactive
inference and not Enactive inference.
Active inference is a branch of
predictive processing. So it's a family
in cognition that consider
that your perception of the world is
based on prediction. You have two
specificity of active inference within
predictive processing. One specificity
is that it says that action are
predictive are based on prediction too.
The other is that it proposed basically
a mathematical formalism in which to
study that that grounds the claim but
also constrained the mechanisms a little
bit. Predictive processing as a family
is predictive of many things. It's
predictive of the fact that basically
you think you see things, but you are
not in capacity to perceive them right
now. So I see bit
of tissue, no fabric
that is beyond my computer and I see the
patterns in it but I know perfectly well
that the cell that are actually that
have the precision to see those
patterns, they are looking at the screen
now. So I cannot possibly know what the
patterns are except if I expect it and
this is what shaped my perception. So
this is predicted by predictive
processing and what is also predicted is
that basically the information flow in
the perception part of the brain it is
heavily top down. You have more
bandwidth that goes from visual cortex
to the retina than reciprocal which
is simply not compatible with direct
perception, passive perception kind of
model. It is, however, compatible with
the idea that we predict the content of
retinal activity and when our
enaction is wrong, then you have
feedback, you have perception error
propagation. So this is pure predictive
processing, this is explained by
predictive processing. This is
contradictory actively with most
conceivable variants of non predictive
processing. So yeah, Enactive processing
is Enactive and I'd say it's not
up for debate as I know active in France
it takes in addition the idea that the
actions are based on prediction. I do
not know what work, empirical work
existed to check whether this
is specifically the case. Maybe Daniel,
you know what has been done about this?
Complete your answer and I'll give a
thought. OK, so there
are conceivable empirical settings that
would check that out. I do not know of
them, so I will not claim that they
exist or do not exist. What is important
to me is the mathematical grounding
because most model of cognition
kind of assume that we have
computational power that is implemented
somehow, somewhere by meat.
And this is wrong.
We cannot just suppose that the big
properties that the brain have, they
must exist somehow, somewhere, we have
to actually explain it. And this is what
the mathematical formalism behind active
inference energy principle does. It
explains that we should expect chemical
system to be predictive somehow and
although it is not directly made in
math, it is pretty easy to see why the
brain should have a lot of power at
doing that because of the very
heavy tune power for the mecholatunment
it has.
But I would not if active inference is
empirically distinct from other case of
predictive processing. I am not sure
how. I cannot think of an experiment
or empirical observation that definitely
discriminates between active inference
and non active inference. Predictive
processing. I think it exists.
Great, thank you. Well, in many ways,
active inference is predictive
processing with action under
additional sophistication and richness,
supported by the free energy principle.
These are technical topics that we
explore in other discussions as to
whether Enactive inference gives us
unique explanation or enaction capacity.
One could look to, for example, the
linear regression or any other type of
statistical framework. Linear
regressions in and of themselves don't
make predictions because you need a
target to make a prediction about.
However, given a linear regression model
relating to health outcomes, for
example, you might use that model to
reduce your uncertainty, which is to
say, have predictive power about that
system of interest. And so in that
respect, active inference has been used
to develop a host of unique explanations
and predictions related to a variety of
cognitive and behavioral phenomena.
I'll just leave it at that, and I'll
read some introductions and such in the
chat. So Robin writes
hi, my name is Robin. I work in digital
governance. Yeah, go ahead.
What makes that I buy active inference
as a mechanical model of human cognition
is that you don't really get adaptive
enaction without some variant of action
being predicted, because the default
picture would be that you have to
planify a full action trajectory.
But there is no compatible way this
can be fast enough and robust enough and
not costly enough to underlie adaptive
action. So basically you'd say I have to
grab a cup. I would look at the cup,
see the cup, planify movements,
Enactive the movements. If something
happens, if I was slightly wrong about
the position of the cup, the algorithm
is too heavy for me to adjust. So you
not be able to navigate anything at
limit information or that is changing.
And we are very good at navigating
things at misinformation which are
changing. So until there is another
mechanical model that predicts attuned
adaptive action, I will have to buy
active inference as a model of
human conditions, basically because the
mass underlying is pretty solid, in my
opinion. Yeah, it's always a great
question. It's relative to what
measurements need a comparator. And so
active inference with Enactive value
relative to something unspecified
doesn't really make sense, but we can
evaluate it better or worse in a certain
setting, and so it's important to
compare it. So I'll just read a couple
introductions. Robin wrote hi, my name
is Robin. I work in digital governance.
I've been curious about applying active
inference to the construction of
governance for digital commons. Great
kickoff Sfumato wrote hi,
I've been studying fundamental physics
and now I am doing Cliodynamics with a
current interest in pragmatist
philosophy. I came to discover active
inference and see how to apply it to
cultural evolution ander says hello.
Anthony writes bonjour anthony
writes background poker player,
father entrepreneur, very little
knowledge on subject attend cognitive
security in Davis working on project
that active inference is very relevant
to expect to learn and engage and
Gina writes hi, I'm a biologist and
neuroscientist that wants to understand
the theory to do experiments with the
Xscape team. Cool. Well,
people can continue to add introductions
or questions in the Chat ben if you want
to ask or reflect on anything or
I'm sure there's more things to talk
about.
Yeah, I thought that was a fantastic
introduction. Some very interesting
connections that I wasn't expecting
there. Nice to see Manufacturing Consent
making an appearance and
a lot that I think I can hold on, let me
turn on my camera. Yeah, certainly a lot
that I want to pick up on and hopefully
circle back around to in the session.
That I'll be.
Cool. Cool. By the way, what I wanted
to say earlier, and I could check now,
is that I believed that Manufacturing
Consent was a Chomsky thing, but it is
not. It is a Lipman thing, which is the
guy that basically funded the very
notion of public opinion in the 30s in
the book called Public Opinion. The book
is co authored with Chomsky, though.
No, Chomsky was not. He was
maybe eight at the time. I very much
doubt he actually did a thing. I'm sure
I have a copy of. That book on my shelf
and I'm. Pretty sure there are no copy
of the book. Manufacturing Consent by
Chomsky. The expression Manufacturing
Consent is from a 30s book Public
Opinion by Walter Lickman that founded
the whole public opinion thing,
according to Wikipedia at least. I did
not looked for a specific book that
would specifically maybe last Public
Opinion because what do we mean
by public opinion? I don't know.
Lordbond does not go clearly, but maybe
something else goes, I don't know. It's
created for that. I can at least say it.
That's kind of the interesting question
about multiscale systems and emergence.
If we enable or grant that brains can
perceive or do things that a single
neuron can't, but that they have a
material relationship to one another,
then is public opinion just like a pile
of sand? It just represents the
summation of the nest mates?
Or does public opinion represent a
singular integrated unit in its own
respect, one that might have to be
sampled by investigating the material
constituents but still being something
different from that?
I'll just go to a question in the chat
or Aval, if you have a thought. Does a
pile of sand have semantics?
I loved it. For an observer or for
itself? Sorry? Does the pile of sand
have semantics for an observer or for
itself? Good question. For observer,
I guess. Not really for itself.
Clearly not really not. That is
symmetry. But I can put together brain
and public opinion, different
coordination mechanisms, but still
coordinated systems yeah,
complex adaptive systems in an
unfavorable sense. If the sand is piling
up at the bottom of an hourglass, it
certainly has semantics for an observer
who knows about hourglasses.
Michael says hello. Haptivist.
Greetings, Michael and asks a question.
Please further contrast the terms
regimes of attention and sociocultural
landscapes.
Contrast as in explain what the terms
are? I guess, yeah. How are those terms
similar or different?
I do not see basically,
we active inference people. I did not
have the ID propose regimes of
attention. So specific patterns in
the way your attention flows as
an explanatory mechanism. Let us say
what underlies the experience of
cognitive landscape. Cognitive landscape
you understood whatever is the array of
things that you as an agent experience
as your world. And then we active
inference people also claim that the
coordination between individuals in
cultural agency. So the way we co
construct synchronize regime of
attention means that there is a coupling
between the landscape that we
experience. So landscape that are
constrained in such a way I will call
social cultural landscape because it's
easier than saying cognitive landscape
that are constrained by sociocultural
processes. Is that satisfying?
Yeah, it's great. I'll just give another
view on that. A sociocultural landscape
is something like the ecological
landscape or the actual basis materially
of our system of interest, what we are
studying in sociology. And so it
consists of inert objects as well as
animate cognitive entities whereas
regimes of attention refers to the
dynamical patterns of attention which
is to say relevance and salience for
cognitive agents. And so the socio
cultural landscape, to use an example
from Avel's presentation,
might include the modified niche that
includes a monument and then a given
cognitive agent might, when they gaze
upon that landscape in an encultured
fashion, have a regime of attention such
that their eyes are moved towards
the point of a monument. But the regime
of attention is modeled as a pattern of
dynamics of a single cognitive agent.
And in Enactive inference we model
attention as covert or internal action.
I want to add something. I use possibly
abuse vitaminscape because
it has a very specific meaning
connotation, which is a space that you
can gaze at. A landscape
is a space that you can gaze at.
And if you go to a
more mathematical notion of space you
will basically find very closely the
expectation or formal entailment that
this space represent the set of
possibilities accessible to a system.
This is all there is to it. And this
is not what a cognitive landscape is.
It's not the set of possibilities that
abstractly an agent could experience.
It is what an agent experiences. No what
can gaze at know.
So this is why the notion of a landscape
is very heavily used. It does not have a
clear mathematical meaning it should
have because it has a very specific,
well conceptual meaning that is critical
to the understanding we have of
cognition and that is not afforded by
set theory. So most mathematics we would
use the brand
of mathematics we teach in school and
that physicists use. Most physicists,
not all physicists. Well, if we consider
like Waddington's epigenetic landscape
or if we consider the surface that
variational free energy is optimized on
as a landscape, it gives us a lot of
really good intuitions. It gives us
something to gaze upon as instrumental
modelers, but it is not the same as
the landscape of trees.
Even though each one of those trees
might be modeled by an observer as
possessing an epigenetic landscape or a
regime of attention or a free energy
landscape.
Well, if anyone has other thoughts or
questions, we can consider them.
Otherwise.
Just give me a second. I don't think
everyone has do
you see the image? Yeah,
it's small, but Waddington's landscape.
There you go. Thank you. Yeah,
Waddington's landscape. So it is a very
old thirty s. Twenty s?
Thirty s, I guess thing in evolutionary
biology. So Waddington is,
let us say, the founder of contemporary
developmental biology. And the landscape
are basically dynamical fitness.
I do not know how to not say landscape.
That is a problem. They're basically the
space in which agent can evolve.
The phenotype of the agent can evolve
during its development. And this
is a very grounded
visual metaphor,
symbolism, I don't know for the study of
developmental system. So this is why we
told Cough landscape for the gazing and
for this historical grounding of the
developmental studies in biology.
And also I literally am paid to
landscape archaeology. So yeah, let's
overuse it on landscape. That is good
for me. Cool. But it's an example
of using our spatial and
Embodied experience to get a grasp
on different conceptual topics.
Ben, you have any comments or I'd. Love
to hear a little ask about this image.
There's a couple of words that I was
expecting to creep into this discussion
that did not, which are attractors and
repellers Avel when you mentioned
dynamical systems. I wonder if you think
these are useful terms for thinking
about because attraction goes very
naturally with thinking about attention.
And I wonder if you think this is a
useful kind of linguistic tool for
visualizing the relationship between
social cognitive landscapes and
attention.
Do you see the social constraints
diagram now? Okay, I wanted to have it
if there is a screenshot laying around,
I wanted this to be the screen share.
So attractors and repellers. We're
basically talking fitness when we're
talking landscape, we're talking fitness
landscapes. So I guess it kind of
entails the notion of attractors and
repellers. Now, there are many reasons
why I'd stay away from the Mikola system
terminology because well,
the Mikol system, they entail the
preformulation of all possibilities of
the system, which I think is very wrong
to do for biological system and social
system system that undergo open ended
evolution and reconstruction. So I stay
away from this formalism whenever
possible. And attractor technically
mean subregions that you cannot possibly
get out, which exists
in conservative system, basically. But
in all cases that we're interested
about, it's technically not a tractor.
And we can't think of
it as a tractor at a specific time
scale. It's okay. But then if we have to
abuse the formalism this much, why not
not use the formalism? That would be my
flow of reflection about this
terminology. I understand the tractors
as states that have visited more
regularly than others. So is there
something about that that's not correct?
I will check it out.
Yeah. An attracting set is one that is
revisited, but there are of course many
sub definitions to be more technical,
like the attractor, is it just the point
or is it the basin of attraction? But
broadly on a landscape, as things
shake out, the attractor begets
some states that are revisited more than
those that are not. That's kind of the
tautological definition of the
attracting set.
An attractor is emphatically not
at least under standard definition set
of states that is visited more often.
It is characterized by forward
invariance. So the fact that once you're
in, you don't get out. So an attractor
is a manifold so subspace, let us say,
such that if you rain, you get out.
Well, there is a basin of attraction
such that if you get in the basin, you
get into the attractor. So if
you look at stochastic chemical systems,
maybe you will get out because a
stochastic means with random noise
basically. Let us say that. So if you
are specifically within a stochastic
chemical system, so nonical system per
se, then you can talk of attractor
and think of things that are not
actually that do not have this forward
invariance, just things that you tend to
stay in for a while once you win. But
you are not talking about attractor
anymore, you are talking about some
other thing. The functional liberty is
forward invariance, we don't have
invariance here. So let's not talk of
attractors.
We. Shouldn'T fall down this rabbit hole
completely. We can talk about this
another time. Let me go to another
great question. In the chat,
Michael says a philosophical
question. Science does a beautiful job
of describing and building testable
predictions of reality, but underweights
subjective experience. Human
subjectivity arises within experience of
observation, but includes
preconditioning as well as experience.
How should science informed observers
reconcile the limits of subjective
experience with the limits of
objectification?
Science build good models. Good models
are competent engagement. That is
basically it. So the
question of how to build a sense that is
effective to information is basically
the question that funded Kairos.
I would not use the word effective per
se, but that's pretty close.
And we'd have to in principle
sense is built to create precise models.
Precise as in does not create prediction
error within a specific context that is
heavily ritualistic and conservative.
And that would be, you could criticize
pretty heavily the institution of
science as a truth seeker normative
thing.
So you'd have to have a good level of
reform to basically enforce modeling
that are both robust and easy to
transmit socially outside the caste
of scientists. So Danielle and I and
many other people wrote a paper on
ontology for decentralized science which
speaks to it. And yeah,
so if you get science, you get good
models and once you have good models,
you can navigate competently. But and I
don't know but end both,
you would need heavy level of reform
institution of science to get
this process be more ergonomic,
efficient, compelling and socially
influential. And yeah, I think it's an
important thing to do when I try to do
it. So thank you for the question. I'll
give another angle on that.
Bayesian statistics qualitatively
equates to the explicit provisioning
of our priors and how we update those
prior beliefs. As new observations come
in, we may have high attention to new
observations and update our beliefs a
lot. We may not be paying to the
attention to the new stimuli and
therefore continue our prior belief.
So if we're not paying attention, it's
kind of like a belief with inertia
that's greater. And if we are paying a
lot of attention, then beliefs change
more rapidly and trying to capture
every single belief that
leads to a research team, whether
they're in academia or not, to carry
out, interpret, analyze and communicate
a certain topic that is
a really far reaching task.
However, Bayesian statistics and
Bayesian approaches like active
inference are helping us get a grasp at
the preconditioning that does
play an essential role with ongoing
experience. So the
question of how to engage with extant
institutions and norms and practices is
a challenging and ongoing work.
But in some ways the formal principles
that help us understand how context and
measurement come together for cognitive
entities and groups, those fundamental
principles are being communicated.
Maybe also I'd love to hear about what
you're planning to talk about.
Yeah, I'm not sure if I even fully
understand the question. The question
just briefly I took it to be maybe some
worry about the relationship between the
formalisms and computational models in
active inference and human subjectivity
itself. So how do they bridge the gap of
phenomenology there? It's a really
interesting question. I know that there
are some people who think that
phenomenology, human subjective
experience is just going to have these
transcendental aspects to it that can't
be captured by the formalisms.
That's something I won't be talking
about in my session.
What I will be talking about is I'm
going to speak on some things that did
come up briefly today. So many of the
readings that feature in my section are
readings that will use the term
predictive processing. So I was going to
say a little bit quite briefly about how
I think these different, slightly
different frameworks fit together and
what some of the similarities and
differences are, I was going to say move
quite quickly and superficially over
some of the core mechanisms. So
precision, weighting predictions,
generative models. And then what
I'm going to try and do is, before we go
on to the subsequent weeks where we look
at collective behavior,
normativity social scripts and things,
I wanted to try and build up a nicely
layered picture of what it's like to be
an active inference agent in the world.
And so the way I'm going to do this is
by swooping over some philosophical
territory. So I'm going to look at the
way active inference has said
interesting things about philosophy of
mind, particularly in terms of the role
of internal representation. If I have
time, I'm going to say a little bit
about Embodied cognition, some of the
four E stuff, aval, you got it right.
So it's Embedded, Embodied, enacted,
and Extended. And I'm not going to be
able to talk about all of those, but I'm
going to say a little bit about some of
them and how active inference kind of
brings interest in debates in that area
out. I'm going to say a little bit about
folk psychology and motivated action.
So talking briefly about what agency
itself is for an active inference agent
and. Whether psychology folk psychology.
It'S a kind of propositional psychology.
So it's a framework of propositions that
we generally use to describe and
explain human behavior. So it involves
propositions such as A, desires, B,
or X hopes that Y, and it
turns out that this propositional
psychology is pretty good for explaining
and predicting human behavior. But it's
not you say we, it's scientists,
laypersons philosophers.
So do you mean we in the sense that it's
a useful framework? I mean that you
should explain what the term is,
because folk psychology is quite
specific. It's not a word that is in
folk psychology. Okay, yeah. So folk
psychology is just basically the
linguistic framework we use to describe
human. Say, you know, if I want to
explain why Avel goes to the
refrigerator to grab a beer, I would say
you believe there's beer in the fridge.
You desire a beer, and then on the basis
of that, you form the intention to then
go to the fridge. And it's been the
subject of a lot of philosophical
interest because the kind of ontological
status of those concepts is very
unclear. So it's not clear whether when
we use folk psychological concepts, are
we saying that those concepts exist in
some meaningful way, or should we take a
more pragmatic approach and say that
this is just instrumentally useful, but
we're not actually positing the
existence of any kind of brain states or
anything like that. And there's been
some interesting work on how predictive
processing and active inference might
map onto folk psychology. Are they in
a necessary kind of tension? Because
obviously with Enactive processing, you
have just a very limited set of
primitives with which to describe and
explain human behavior. So I'm going to
say a little bit about that and then I'm
going to move straight into talking
about phenomenology and talking about
how certain aspects of the framework
have been said to underpin certain kinds
of experiences. So I'm going to use a
case study of addiction, I think
possibly depression, but I think I'm
going to talk about addiction. And with
this case study, I'm hoping to bring out
kind of tie together all of the things
that I've said up to that point and some
of the things that you've covered as
well, and I should say as well. In the
discussion session for my section,
we'll have a special guest as well. So
we're going to be joined by Professor
Mark Miller, who is a
prolific author of predictive processing
and neurophenomenology type stuff. He's
done some really interesting work on
happiness and, wellbeing, depression,
addiction, and really using the active
inference framework in some quite
imaginative ways. And he's awesome in
discussion. So hopefully you will find
the readings for my section really
interesting. And if you do, you'll have
a chance to kind of have a conversation
with the author for those pieces.
Avel. Any closing notes.
Actual inference rules. I will say.
One short question. I just want to get
it on there while we're here. Brynn
asks, as a psychologist, I am more or
less in the business of helping people
minimize their variational free energy
and expected free energy. Great
profession. But what are the markers of
free energy in the brain or organism?
Is it heart rate, neuromodulation,
galvanic skin response,
cortisol levels, et cetera? I say the
closest proxy would be those prediction
error things in the brain. So when we
have expectation and they are violated,
you have back preparation of this
information, the fact the expectation
was violated and this would be the
closest proxy to variational
free energy. I do not
think it would be the exclusive one,
but it is the main one.
And I don't think you could make an
exhaustive list. Basically anything that
is out of order so as to prompt any kind
of response of either updating models or
facting on things. It would be a marker
of prediction error, which is not
quite variational free energy, but is
also not quite not it.
So for expected free energy,
I have no idea whatsoever. I don't think
this framework has made connected
explicitly to physiology yet.
Am I wrong, Daniel?
It's a very interesting question, and
all I will say, all I feel like I can
say on it is one thing we're going to
talk about in my session, is how
prediction error is not always a bad
thing. So there's a really nice Aon
article that came out fairly recently
about the value of uncertainty. And one
of the things I'm going to talk about is
how predictive processing has perhaps
it can account for phenomenon such as
playful behavior, creativity,
engagement in challenging hobbies and
dangerous sports and things like this.
And how we get an account of exploratory
behavior and curiosity, which is kind of
rooted in the fact that for creatures
like we are for active inference agents,
the resolution of prediction error
itself is a good thing. And so in some
sense, we're always seeking it out. So I
think it might be a mistake to kind of
it's very intuitive to equate prediction
error of free energy with kind of
allostatic load and stress and
negativity, but actually it's going to
turn out that that's not the case.
Yeah. Thank you. And I'll give another
type of answer, which is variational.
Free energy and expected free energy are
statistical calculations about
statistical models. So bodies don't have
expected free energies. Models that are
made about bodies can have variational
and expected free energy. And so to that
end, whatever you put in your model is
either an observable or a proposed
latent hidden state that you didn't
measure. And you may find that different
experiential reports or different
physiological phenomena have different
relationships to each other. So indeed,
it has been explored, for example,
which neural firing rates are associated
with surprise or which hormonal changes
are associated with this or that change
in body temperature when the
generative model is made. The
deflationary answer is look at the data
and find out which cues you measure are
associated with your calculation of VFE
and EFE. However, I think it's a little
bit of a map territory situation and one
that's going to come up, I am sure,
many times in our course.
Great. Well, I'll just remind people to
go to the course website to review the
syllabus and also encourage everybody to
submit questions through the course
website. All of the teachers will review
the questions and we'll give the best
answers we can. And also, please, from
all backgrounds, we would love to hear
your voice in the discussions. So thank
you again, Ben and Avel. See you next
week.