Hey, everyone. Welcome to week twelve
of active textbook group cohort one.
We are in the Review and Synthesis
weeks. It's been a great three
monthish journey and it
doesn't stop here but we'll will go over
that. So two points of
process for those who are here live and
of course re watching and then we'll
move to the more conceptual parts. So
first in the onboarding page you'll
see these two columns. The two columns
are Rcping yes to join Cohort
Two, part one going through chapters one
through five if you would like to for a
second time. Many people will be just
doing it for fun or for learning or
however they want. And also there's the
opportunity to continue on with the
second half of the textbook which is
going to get into a lot of the hands on
modeling and we'll be especially looking
forward to developing a lot of the
notebooks and interactive formats that
will help us get a lot of understanding
there. So please check yes
for whichever row your name is in for
whether you would like to continue on
with part two as well as
retake part one as well.
You'd be welcome to be just a
participant and also feel free to get in
touch if you are interested in taking
some other role such as like
facilitating or scaffolding some aspect
but we can talk more about that for
those who are interested. So point one
go to the onboarding list and continue
on however you want.
Second point if you go to Future
Textbook Groups page you'll see an
embedded form as well as a link to the
form if you want it in a new window like
that. This would be exceptionally
requested and helpful for you to provide
some evaluations numerically and as
short or as long as you want on
providing feedback. Those are one
way that you can provide feedback
anonymously. The second way is building
on some of the ideas that people are
already adding here. This is an editable
page, so people can add thoughts as
they see fit about what would be awesome
for future textbook groups or any other
feedback. Or, as always, they can email
Activeinference@gmail.com if they want,
like a response to any specific points.
And then also it's provided here at the
link to Share for people who want to
join future cohorts. So that link will
be like getting people onboarded
into the next cohort which is September
2022 in this case. But this is going to
be like an evergreen form that will just
continue to have a list of people who
expressed interest and be onboarding
them into subsequent cohorts of which
will begin several per year going
forward.
And next week we'll be talking more
about the feedback specifically
and about projects and about carrying
on. Today is like a little bit of a more
conceptual synthesis and review and
again next week will be more like
logistical and project oriented
review. So just on these points or
anything else, does anyone want to just
raise their hand or unmute and share
anything that they liked?
Okay, let us conceptually
review, then we
read the first five chapters of the
active inference textbook.
Does anyone have overall thoughts that
they'd like to provide at the five
chapter scale? Then we're going to go
into a chapter scale. Then we'll be
continuing to dive in as Granularly
as required. But at the scale of the
first five chapters, you can see them
here on this preface page as
well as here in the chapters list.
As a unit of five chapters,
what were people's sense?
How did it update? Yes, please, Ben.
And then Ali. Well, I was just going to
say, I think, as I've said to people
before, I think, coming from a non
mathematics background, I thought that
these chapters were really accessible in
terms of the kind of conceptual things
that they were putting on the table.
But I just wondered what other people's
opinions were in terms of understanding
the conceptual toolkit of active
inference before you've built up a kind
of mathematical understanding, because
I'm about to start kind of learning some
of the mathematics behind it. And I
wondered what people thought of the
potential to fully grasp these concepts
without the mathematics and what the
relationship between the two might be.
I'm just curious what other people think
about that, I guess.
Thanks. Great question, Ali and then
Mike and then anyone else who wants to
chime in.
Yeah, it was a pretty exciting journey
for me, but I'll definitely need
to read over all those five chapters
once again, at least once again in order
to grasp more fully the contents
of those chapters. My own personal
opinion about the way Materials
is organized in the first part of the
textbook is I
couldn't see a kind of hierarchical or,
I don't know, structural organization
for these chapters as much as I like to.
See them because sometimes they
delve into theoretical
aspect of all the things much more
deeply than the mathematical side. And
sometimes it's vice versa. But I
think that if it was organized in
a way that, as Ben mentioned, we can
go from a firm conceptual
foundation into the granular formalism
and mathematics, at least for me,
that would be much more accessible
and much more I would be able to
organize the materials in a much more
coherent way in my mind. So one
thing that I really
enjoyed about these chapters is the
kind of you
see a kind of the vision it
tries to put forward regarding
the future possible research and also
things especially in chapter five and
the path that can be taken from this
point on. Thank you,
Ali. Mike and then anyone else?
Yeah, I'll pick up from where Ali left
off, I think it's somewhat remarkable
that they were able to fit everything
they did into those first five chapters.
And understanding. They probably had
some idea of how much space they wanted
in that part of the book before getting
into the practical or applied
components. In part two,
the high road, low road contrast and
sort of coming at the problem from two
different angles I think was useful.
Like Ben, I found the math to be
generally accessible, although I confess
I think I still go through this sort of
pattern where I feel like I get it and I
have this intuitive understanding of it.
But then there are things where I sort
of bogged down and looking at some of
the mathematical details or some of the
graphical representations related
to things like message passing have to
slow down and sort of take those apart
more. And I guess related to
that, I should add, I think this group
has been so good at taking apart the
ideas of the book. This is perhaps one
of the most effective settings I've seen
for really wringing concepts
out of a text. And the work that's going
on with the coda to build up the
ontology and take apart the equations
and things like that I think is just
tremendous awesome. Thank you.
The British call them maths, plural
instead of math as an area. And it
really does engage. Like there's
visual formalisms which could be
represented with a sparsity matrix or it
could be represented with other ways.
But there are almost like a
multiscale diversity of formalisms
ranging from more traditional equal
sign in the middle mathematics to
fusion, schematic, equation graphics,
different types of notations even within
the equation. And the difficulty
is not
signaled. Not that it has to be, but the
difficulty does provide a little
whiplash sometimes because it moves
variously in the main thread of the
text, the boxes and the appendices from
like, this is how linear algebra works
and this is what Bayes theorem is
all the way to. Topics that are
approaching physics flows on partitioned
states,
various kinds of fundamental, or like in
principle, relationships about
mathematics generally.
All the way to postulated
architectures where message passing
is implemented to achieve some
computational function and or thread the
needle with resembling neuro
computational architectures. The math is
doing a lot. Many things are happening
and so it's only
to be expected that the perception is
challenging and there's
probably a lot more to even say and
unpack there. Anyone else want to raise
their hand and give a thought on this
section? One Area.
JF and Then anyone Else.
Have kind. Of A general Question about
The Limits Of Mathematics,
the Notion Of Computational
irreducibility that You
Have To Go Through Every Step Of A
Process to Get At State n plus.
One from state n from state
n minus whatever. That certain
problems cannot be solved by
plugging values into a formula and
generating a future state. You have to
compute all the intermediate states.
I wonder where that fits in in this
picture. Are there hard limits to the
application of mathematics to
the problem of active inference? It's
just a general question.
Returning to some earlier comments
on the firm conceptual ground,
what is an area, no matter how narrow
or distal, from active, where people
believe that there is a
firm conceptual ground, they felt like
that provided a foundation for them to
learn further. Are we seeking an
analogy to some other field
of theory or practice or domain? Or are
we kind of seeking for an epistemic
territory that we haven't quite seen?
I'll just add I think that what
inactive inference, what you're talking
about there, Jeff, is literally blankets
and uncertainty, like the corollary
there of, like, computation and
irreducibility is that there's some
large amount of uncertainty in hidden
states in the world that you're just
never going to get at. The blanket is in
some sense not just how you're relating
to it, but some hard
limit on your
surprisal and things like that.
Thanks. Brock Blue had written
yes, Mike, please.
So responding to the question about
maybe adjacent SpaceX or spaces or topic
areas, I think there's certainly overlap
with concepts from system dynamics. And
certainly a lot of agent based modeling
has been applied to model systems that
have feedback loops and adaptation,
things like that. We discussed during
the past weeks relationships with
reinforcement learning. And I think
there's a belief that active inference
kind of cleans up some of the
challenging, or maybe not challenging,
but less formalized or less defined
aspects related to reinforcement
learning, such as how do you engineer
a utility function that makes sense in
the context of what you're trying to
model?
Thanks agreed about creating an
integrated utility function.
There's so many unprincipled,
not to say ineffective or not even to
say not elegant but unprincipled methods
of creating a chimera utility
model like delay, discounting,
novelty, bonus, curiosity,
bonuses, alternating phases
or hyperparameters,
as well as purely implementational
strategies like discarding burn in
parallel chains. There's like a whole
toolkit and indeed fields on creating
effectively integrated
utility models and putting
that work into the construction of the
generative model. And how the
generative model is partitioned from the
generative process allows
a generic free energy functional or set
of related free energy formulations to
play that role. So that's
one very interesting angle,
as well as the way that that process of
specifying the generative model and
generative processes and so on are
world models, whether in the
Yon Lacoun sense or in the
Adam Safron sense. These generative
models encompass world models and deep
learning approaches and various topics
like that.
So let's see. Blue wrote,
I wish there was practice problems in
the book to develop our understanding
yes,
to a large extent. And also whether
people want to reflect on any specific
questions or even just on this scheme.
These are many of these questions.
These questions can be open,
infinite game type questions about
the material. They can be clearly
addressable questions about the
material. They can be checks
for understanding, but we'll be
continuing to develop and improve and
curate questions around the material.
So I think it's a great comment
and this is why we have this
future textbook groups and all of these
affordances for people to stay involved
and be improving this, as well as
experimenting in their own spaces and
ways to develop the kinds of material
that are helping them learn and
understand any
more. Section one overview
thoughts,
chapters one through five and
the framing of the book being that the
first five chapters are more focused on
the conceptual background and the second
five chapters are going to be starting
with a recipe for designing the active
models and getting more into the
modeling itself.
So any section one through five
commentary the
book comprises two parts, page three.
These are aimed at readers who want to
understand active inference first part,
and those who seek to use it for their
own research second part. The first
part of the book introduces active
inference, both conceptually and
formally contextualizing it within
current theories of cognition.
How did they succeed and
where? Was there a divergence between
what you preferred a priori or
now comprehensive,
formal and self contained introduction
to active inference, its main constructs
and implications for the study of brain
and cognition?
I'm interested in the distinction
between understanding active inference
and using it for our own research and
the way that that's set up as those
being two completely separate things.
It seems to suggest that one could fully
understand active inference and yet not
be in a position to use it in their own
research, not having worked through the
second half of the book. And I think
that's quite interesting.
It is. Good comment. Thank you.
Not to spoil the ending, but the
last sentence is ultimately we are
confident that you will continue to
pursue active inference in some form.
There may be a multi year incubation
for different people in contexts many
people now or even in some amazing
decentralized science future. They may
not think of themselves as researchers
or of doing research,
though they may be even included on
research projects. So it's
a very interesting comment about
how they distinguish theory and
learning from part
two, research and practice,
however they
discuss applications.
But this isn't the playbook,
it's not the toolkit, it's not the
modeling tool ecosystem.
Mike.
Yeah, that's an interesting comment at
the end, and I don't know if this is my
perceptual bias, but there seems to be
this implicit assumption that active
inference is the way to go. Basically,
this is the tool to use within
the text. As a
result, what's not there is a discussion
of maybe these are cases where you might
not want to use active inference, or
these are cases where applying active
inference could create challenges in
what you're solving for.
Ali and anyone else.
And in fact, one of the most popular
criticisms put toward the active
inference or FEP in general is that it
tries to explain everything. It ends
up explaining nothing.
Yeah, I think there's a risk of maybe
not sufficiently constraining the
problem space or leaving things
undefined in a way that allow
for active insurance to be the solution
without a critical point of view.
They highlight behavior
and cognition. I mean, one could almost
see even the name active
inference as being a synthesis of
action behavior and cognition
inference in ways that as we're
discovering and unpacking, they're
integrated in ways that other formalisms
of perception as a type of
cognition. So we could just lump it
there other frameworks of behavior and
cognition have
not integrated or have approached from a
non first principles. Or maybe they do
follow first principles, like the higher
the impact factor, the better the paper,
something like that. That's a first
principle. No, just kidding.
But placing it within the framework
of cognition while also surfing
on a wave of something
like Pan cognitivism or like pan
computationalism does
expand the scope. And that's even
before one starts to enter into
the more recent research,
especially where there is a highlight
on system persistence,
not simply in terms of the resistance to
dissipation entropically, but in a
relational context as repeated
measurements, like in the quantum work.
So it's like cognition. Oh, like brains,
like that schema with the brain or with
like a person. Well, oh, by cognition,
it's any system with a blanket
that we're interacting with through
repeated measurement. Is that cognition?
Where did cognition go? Brock.
I kind of want to, I guess, echo all
those things that were just said about a
common criticism and this where does it
apply? Where does it not apply? But
also, I guess all
those things that you were just listing.
I always hear that from people that have
not engaged with
the material and from
my engagement with it, it seems like all
of the examples in which it is used are
complex, dynamical systems that don't
have great, that have, at best,
mathematical approximations and have
almost no or literally no kind of
analytical approaches.
It just seems like a good way to model a
system of things, of entities that are
interacting. And I
guess what I'm to put it
into one question is that kind of some
anthropomorphizing or whatever
projecting of like, well, it's applied
to this, it's applied to that, it must
apply to everything. And how can it
apply to all those things? How can it
apply everywhere? It's not applying to
everywhere. It's just applying to these
complex systems which are everywhere but
also don't have and we're not trying to
model the apple falling from the tree
or. These. Sorts of simple cases
or something. It's not being applied
there, is it? I haven't seen actually,
now that I think about it, any of those
sorts of situations where it's applied
to things that we already understand,
maybe in some back checking way, but not
in a way that's suggested that we should
use this much more complex approach
to something that's kind of check.
Already got that.
Thanks, Brock. Ali.
I kind of feel that some of these
criticisms stems from the
fact from a serious lack of deep
understanding of concepts related to
FEP and active inference. For example,
I came across a PhD thesis just today
in which it
tries to critique everything related
to Markup Blanket. But as I was glancing
over it,
I observed some serious gaps
in our argument throughout all the
thesis. And I think materials such as
this book can definitely help in filling
up these gaps of understanding which
even the serious researchers
are suffering from.
Yes, thanks. So to this
thread, I've never heard it about the
linear model. How could the linear model
be used in so many settings?
It explains nothing. Well, is the linear
model an explanation or is it an
investigative tool in the investigator's
toolbox? So at least
for me personally, doesn't need to have
broader reach than those who resonate
with it. But again, I always try to ask,
would somebody say this or could they
say that about a linear model? And then
if the active formalism with f
equals dot dot dot dot dot or g equals
dot dot dot dot dot, and all of the
predicates that it's associated with and
the partition and all of that, could
someone say that about y equals MX plus
b? And then if not, and there may be
cases where it is not the same, what is
it that's different about active
inference? Or is it a valid
and important and even reasonable
question, but one that might be bumping
up like what JF raised about
computational irreducibility or about
map territory even disguised
or camouflaged questions about
relationality? Well, how can complexity
science apply to so many topics?
We're applying complexity science to
whatever topic we want to. Where's the
issue?
Mike and then ron yeah, a lot.
Of it hinges on how the model is to be
applied and what the intent of model
application is. So taking the linear
model as an example, we might use
something like that to be predictive
about a linear system. And so there's
potential value there. When we do system
dynamics models, a lot of times the
value in doing a system dynamics model
is aligning the stakeholders around
what are the model components and how do
we think about those model components.
So working through a process similar to
what we've done in this textbook group,
although few do it as rigorously to
identify the system elements and how
they interact and interrelate and so
forth. And that can lead to more
advanced implementation like agent based
models. But a lot of times,
at least in my experience, those agent
based models are used for deeper systems
understanding more than, say,
predictive power for what the system is
going to do at some point in the future.
So again, it comes back to the reason
for applying the models and thinking
about how the model fits with that
reason and what sort of results you
would expect from that. Thank you.
Mike? Ron?
Yeah, I generally agree with what
both you and Mike said. So from a
practitioner's perspective, we do hear
criticisms of linear models, right?
It's not that we don't, but it's usually
about which domain is applied in.
But generally speaking,
well, let me put it this way because
active inference is probably more
complex and it takes a lot more time to
crop than Y equals MX plus b, which
could be one reason for these kind of
criticisms. And it's probably like
they're falling back into old habits.
Okay, why should I jump my old model as
opposed to adopting this newer, more
the? How much more does it explain than
what I think that probably is driving
a lot of the criticism.
Thank you.
I can't help but add a domain specific
example. This is a 2016 paper
that is speaking to like a multi decade
multi career brouhaha
about different approaches to modeling
evolution and selection. For example,
in the eusocial insects and in social
animals as well. And this article is
very fascinating because they use a
Bayesian causal graph to identify
situations where two different
formulations can and the multilevel
selection models have identical
predictions. Where the causal graphs
have identical predictions.
Any measurement you can think of as
being like on a Y equals x manifold
where it doesn't resolve your
uncertainty about which framework is
correct or not. Yet the literature is
littered with we measured these ovaries,
so kin selection is or isn't happening.
However, a vast set of those empirical
cases might be essentially falling on
this manifold where those two models are
not distinguishable. And so this
is a theory driven approach, like a
first principles approach to identify
situations that are
providing unique informative value. In
this case about canon multilevel
selection and knowing what territories
measurements will not have explanatory
value,
which relates to active inference.
Just like Rohan and like many people
have brought up, especially when we kind
of take like a meta science or like a
communicating science or onboarding
people into active concern,
people are asking explicitly or
implicitly why should I update my
cognitive model? What is the value of
active inference? Can you appetize me
with a two minute video so I can
understand it? Or with a two minute
video so it's enough to want to continue
going down that path?
There's a lot to say and there's a
lot of work to identify the
situations and the ways of truly
addressing and perhaps even resolving
long standing scientific
divergences. Like, if it is the
case that the explore exploit dialectic
is addressed in a novel way through
the free energy functional balancing
pragmatic and epistemic reward,
that is quite
a vast scope.
People continue to use, explore and
exploit today and it is the evident that
those ontology terms wouldn't be useful
in the future. In fact, some of the
discussions on like folk psychology with
the belief, desires, intentions can we
say what an active inference entity
wants or intends based upon its beliefs
and its desires? For example,
can we still talk about exploratory and
exploitative behavior as a phenomena but
have a different way of modeling
how that behavior arises or is
regulated?
What are the settings in behavioral
cognitive science?
What are the settings where systems
dynamics has been applied where we
can now use active inference to
identify? Where have we
been just throwing a thousand darts at
the same grain of sand?
Where are the vast fields
where we don't even know?
And as people have highlighted, the book
is written with a specific rhetorical
bent, both explicitly and implicitly.
For the regime of attention of the book
to be about active inference, one can
read as an implicit endorsements that
this is something that is valid or
valuable to pursue.
And especially at this stage in the
field, it is almost like an exhortation
to persist amidst uncertainty,
to learn and apply few
disjointed thoughts there but hope
it makes sense.
Let's look back to the sections of the
book.
Anyone can raise their hand or give a
thought like how
could the book you write begin?
What reviewer comments? Whether you're
reviewer one, reviewer two, reviewer
three. What comments would you have
provided if this were, like, a draft?
And you could even make structural
suggestions.
So I have a lot of comments there. Yes.
Blue. And then Ron. Oh, sorry.
I didn't mean to cut you off.
Having taught lots of classes before,
I think a list of key
terms and definitions would be
critical. And learning objectives
for each chapter,
like I said, like a practice quiz. Test
your knowledge of this. What is
surprise? Like, how many different forms
of surprise are there? Just some
practice questions to see if you grasped
the concepts prevented in each chapter
and especially what I was mentioning in
the chat like math problems can
you set up your own generative model?
Or even just the Bayesian graph? Can you
make a Bayesian graph? What would that
look like for give a question like a
verbal description and then give the
Bayesian graph answer or make the
answers available online so you could
test your own knowledge of the subject
first. I think that that would be
totally instrumental in using this
functionally like a textbook anyway, so
sorry. Thanks Blue. Nice predictive
programming. Rohan and then Brock.
Yeah.
As a practitioner, I work in the
engineering field. I'm a control systems
engineer. My preference would be to
immediately see some application not
necessarily to control systems, but
something that it begins with like a
project and explains how active
inference is better than its own
baseline. That would be interesting to
see. Like a perfect example of this
would be I don't know if you've heard of
Fast AI by Rachel Thomas and Jeremy
Howard. They have a very unique way of
teaching.
So they have a computational linear
algebra course. So the way they teach
the linear algebra part is by basically
implementing Gaussian loader, for
example, and then connecting it to so
you start with the code and then you do
the math, then you connect it to the
math. So something like that might be
far more useful, maybe not from a
point, but it would definitely be useful
for practitioners around the world.
Okay, so if Controls engineer gets
this okay, this looks like a better form
model predictive control. I can replace
my model predictive controller with
something that resembles active
inference.
We might actually make more progress
that it actually gets out of the way.
Thank you, Ron Brock.
Yeah, I've had similar comments
to that. Of.
Fast AI and Benchmarks.
That's kind of the ultimate way.
That's just the way that practitioners
change their attention now.
And that would be really useful. But in
the context of the book, I think
I agree with everything else that was
said too. I'm not sure how realistic it
is to do that from the point where
the whole field is at right now. Sorry
about that. But I
think just having some things in
context, there's always this comment
about it's a nonlinear thing. Text is
linear, so of course it will be out of
out of order. But often
the definitions of things are kind
of scattered throughout the explanation
of them and kind of italicized
instead of kind of brought up to the top
in some way.
You might expect, at least from my
pedagogical experience, everything like
all math is taught to define
your knowns and unknowns and variables
at the top and this sort of thing right
in the context of the appendices.
Again, I understand that
it's a lot, you can't add that all in
or whatever, but just if there was like
either every whenever the next
part of the appendices became relevant,
again, just like having it at the top at
each section you're like, okay, so we're
going to use part now, building on what
we've done already. Now we're going to
use this part of this section in the
appendices. In this section our
equation, one, two, three, whatever.
In this next section, like just stating
it up front again, just like a
big box at the top or whatever,
it just would help in way finding
and disentangling the
unfortunate linear format
of books that is mapped to this complex
thing.
I don't know, those general things would
be helpful. One other thing that is
maybe beyond the scope of this book,
but spoke to Ali about very briefly at
one point about the notation. Like even
in the basic example of the frog here,
like Bayesian notation,
it's incredibly easy to manipulate
variables when they're one letter and
subscripts, but. When the whole variable
is like ten or 20 letters, like p
of x equals frog jump condition on a y,
it becomes a larger I don't know if
this is just me and Dyslexic, I don't
know, but it just seems harder to
cognitively kind of work with that.
I don't know. Thank you, Brock. Yes,
the chunking is multilevel and
it will be great to explore ways to
learn around that. Here are
a few forays where we can copy quotes
and have in line definitions.
So for those who are interested in this
kind of work with an
open source textbook, it is not an
infinite task or even a non automatable
task to copy out the plain text and
integrate it with a versioning ontology
so that the definition can be even
rendered differently. It could be in a
different language, it could be every
single time that a term comes up.
There's like so much enrichment that
this seed can lead to of
the textbook and a
lot of it is for us to pick
up. Honestly. Rohan and
then anyone else?
Oh, I forgot to put down. Oh, no
worries. Thank you.
So in our last seven or so minutes for
this session next
week, we will continue with any
conceptual points and questions that
people want to raise. We'll also be
turning our attention a bit more to
making sure first off that please,
please everyone complete the feedback
form in the future textbook groups and
or add information here or contact
us because it's just one of the most
important feedback mechanisms we have.
We'll also be exploring a little bit
different project ideas,
several of these threads involving
different system models we've already
found a home for in the Active
Blockprints project where we're
meeting twice on Wednesdays weekly.
Other projects we're going to have new
vistas on during and after going
through the second half of the textbook,
which is still black and white static
PDFs, but we'll be able to augment this
heavily with some simulation
tools as well
as other
work like the Plain Text Enrichment,
or even anyone who wants to collaborate
on an audiobook version.
There's no lack of active
tasks today and these
are like high leverage point moments
where staying in the game and improving
the game will do tremendous service
towards reducing research debt and
improving the rigor in the applications
that we see. Rohan?
Yeah? Can I make a project suggestion?
That's fine. Yes please.
Everyone can? Yeah. Okay, so there is
put this in the chat. There's this
online lab by Georgia Tech's
Intelligence Systems unit called
Robotario that's basically a
bunch of swarm. It's to test swarm
controllers. So there's
a good baseline over here. It would be a
good idea to try like an active
inference version, like an active
inference inspired swarm controller to
finish the tasks. So this runs
on actual robots in that lab and
you can see the results.
This is awesome. I had
some colleagues who worked with some
of the ant groups here. It's right at
the intersection of JF's
work and many's interest in the embodied
and robotic angle. And we have somewhat
extensive multi
scale generative models of ants
which would apply to other swarm
settings as well. So absolutely we
want to scaffold those projects. And one
way to start, but not the only way to
start, is to copy a
version of these fields and add and
remove as relevant for you and give some
handle for others to be
involved or just stay in the game so
that more people can
join. There will be a flow of people
entering active inference forever.
How will we greet them? So what would I
need to put in over there?
It depends on how you want to carry
forward the project. But you can feel in
this row, add any notes you'd like and
more details on what you're thinking of
doing. And then however you want to be
more specific about directions and
just signal it in the idea.
Or you can in the notes or draft
catechism, which is what these templates
are based on.
And if there is ever something you're
not sure about, then ask around
and different projects are going to
proceed differently.
Okay. Yeah. So I'll fill that out with
my talks. Awesome.
Well, interesting meeting.
It's our penultimate discussion in this
section. Then we hope that
everybody who is motivated and ready
to do so continues for
part two and or rejoins
for part one, cohort two. Both of these
will be starting in September. So we'll
take August off of the textbook.
And at this point, the tentative plan is
that we'll have two sequential hours,
like section one and then followed
by section two so that those who are on
section one can see
how section two is.
We can explore different architectures
and stuff. And again, this is like why
people's active participation and their
feedback and the oversharing on
topic and just writing all the questions
that came in their mind and all the
things that they would want to ask
somebody to check. Like every
contribution is important. It does
anyone else have anything they'd like to
add before we stop the recording?
Stopping the recording? Oh, yeah.
Someone go for it.
All right. Stopping the recording.