You. Hello.
Welcome, everybody. It's November 1,
2023, and we are in the closing
discussion section for this
first instance of active inference for
the social sciences. It's been a
journey. I'm sure we'll have many fun
things to talk about and explore today.
So Avil, please take
it from here and maybe give an overview
of what we're going to do and talk about
today. Okay,
so this is the conclusion session of our
course on active inference for the
social science. We have talked
extensively about active inference,
maybe less extensively about for the
social science parts. So the goal of the
session would be basically to assess
what we talked about and how it is
relevant or not to the practice of
social sciences.
Basically, this is a discussion session,
so there is no clear plan. But I'd like
to address how formally active inference
accounts for agency and normativity and
identity as a kind of integrated
phenomenon, how it can compare or
add to our ground or clash
with, I don't know, sociological and
political. Model of agency and of social
evolution and of et cetera, et cetera.
All the topics that we addressed, which
are numerous and discuss
about the plausible future for active
inference, what it can be used to,
maybe what it will be used to,
certainly how it may change and how it's
relevant to yes,
that is the crux
of it. We have brought in Alexey,
who is a philosopher interested in
social ontology, specifically the study
of social kinds, which is from Kairos
Research. And I do not know who Colin
is, but he's with us. Hi, Colleen.
So how should we proceed? Danielle?
What do we do? If you'd like, maybe pose
a specific question or prompt,
which could be preceded by a statement,
and then we can all hear everyone's
voice on that. Okay,
so a good question would be ActInf
inference describes agency and
relativity and identity as a kind of
integrated phenomenon. I think we
should go over how precisely it
works.
So, yes, let's do that. I will find
some, do you say,
illustration? That will make it easier.
But let's hear people's thoughts on
that, please.
Can you pose your question just a tad
more clearly? How are agency,
normativity and identity addressed
separately and together in active
inference?
Mao, go for it.
So I think we like to look at things in
terms of interrelations. In active
inference, nothing is defined by itself,
it's defined in relation to other
things. And this definition in relation
to other things also defines the types
of constraints that will be pushed on
the thing, which is separate from other
things. Once you have this, you
necessitate these interrelationships to
be formative ontological and
fundamentally contextual. So no
relationship is perfectly reproducible
across a different context. It will take
on a hermeneutics or semantics, given
the exact context of the spatial
temporality of the entities.
Those are some first thoughts. Does
anybody have big objections to what I
just said.
Okay.
Yeah, please continue. Sorry. Let's
start with the concept of agency. For
instance, agency is just action
selection, right? So agents are modeled.
They have a generative model and they
use it to predict sensory inputs based
on possible actions. They chatted,
select those to minimize the difference
between predicted and sensory inputs.
So they're just trying to minimize free
energy. And this minimization is
fundamentally due to the relationship of
constraints in their environment. So
let's imagine that I am an individual
who sorry,
I saw a comment and I didn't so
yeah, so you have an individual that
tries to exert control over the
environment. Now, if you scale this in
nested structures, you can try to think
of power structures and how agency
within those power structures is
modulated by the different kinds of
constraints that are both embedded
within the environment itself. Within
the materiality of the environment and
also within the normative aspects of
the nested structures which pull and
push an individual within certain
paths through some kinds of deontic
cues. So that's how you get to the
notions of encoding agents beliefs and
preferences about the world within the
generative model through a form of
normativity, which is just a higher
precision over a specific type of
outcome or mapping. So your
prior beliefs here come from different
layers in the hierarchy and these act as
what we call culture or normativity.
I could stop here if you want to say
something. Apple so I agree with what
you said at a high level conceptual
scale, but I think it's important to be
clear about what formally governs the
statement because what we are formally
is much more limited than what we
agree the interpretation could be. So
can you see the screen I'm sharing?
Can you see the mouse doing AIDS?
Yeah. Okay. So at core,
active inference is a framework that
provides geometry for that is
not a very straightforward way to
put it, but what we have is a system
with a space of state and we have a flow
of the system. A flow is a function that
basically tells you where specific point
goes with time. And what active
inference says is that given yes,
given specific patterns of DEMICAL
coupling and of statistical repurposes,
we have agent like behavior. So the
simplest kind of the basic requirement
of active inference of the French
principle, which is a core motivation
for active inference, is that you have a
limical system, so something with states
and a flow and some noise because we
need noise to get information. And it
has a boundary in the middle of it that
statistically separates the external
internal states. By statistically
separate, I mean that every information
about what's going on on there that
is in there, it disappears when
condition on there. So of information I
have about this that I could read here,
I can also read there. And that's subtly
different from the coupling. But this is
formalism, let's not get too much into
this. And then you have more complex
behavior when you can partition sensory
inactive states. And your particle, it
can do things in this specific context.
Basically we can write a geometry for
the fluctuation of the system and this
geometry entails belief over external
states. So these internal states, it
knows thing in a sense about what's
going on out there through its coupling
through sensory and active states and
the flow it has internally, the way its
internal states move, they entail a
displacement of their belief. And this
displacement happens to be near optimal
given Bayes constraints. Blah blah blah.
And the real interesting stuff happens
in the case of strange particles, which
are particles where as you can see,
there is no direct effect from actions,
active states to internal states.
The only action you have is mediated by
sensory and external states, in this
case the active states themselves. So
the policy of an agent, it becomes the
subject of beliefs of the agent. And if
it becomes the subject of beliefs, you
can have statistical inference. This is
the crux of this framework. And if you
can have statical inference, you can
have like quite complex multilevel stall
inference over reward actions. And those
are basically what we call decision
taking or what we call planning. So what
we have here is formal architecture that
can derive the kind of complicated
agency, semantic, not only agency,
but agency that is embedded in a
specific conceptual framework that is
relative to this specific structure of
an agent and their environment and the
coupling in between. All that is traced
back basically to dynamics. So we have a
proof of existence that in a world that
everything is dynamics, we can have
agency, we can have complex decision
making under the form of inference over
one's own actions. And then
you have complications to apply it
directly, of course, because the world
is likely not in its barest form a
limical system. It does not have a list
of states that are okay,
there is not a list of states that are
possible and that's it. And there is one
coupling that takes those states to
themselves and nothing can change ever.
This is not likely to be the case.
But we have a minimal model of agency
that is purely physicalist, that is
purely based on the causal relationship
in the most minimal way we can possibly
represent it. And this is quite huge.
And this gives us a very strong
prior over what is
the stuff that agency is made of. And
the stuff that agency is made of, at
least higher order agency that we think
about here in the social context is
belief over oneself. And so to control
actions is to control belief of oneself.
And this is this duality this
dual aspect of statistical organization
as a complex cognitive agent that is,
in my opinion, at the moment, given the
capabilities of modeling and formalism.
We have the core contribution of
active inference to social sciences
written large psychology, neuroscience
like sense of social stuff because it
gives you very strong prior over
what agency is made of and the kind of
stuff that can exist out there in the
social world and the kind of dynamics
that bring about its stuff.
But there is a quite big bridge to be
made between the pure chemical system,
formalism of active inference and the
kind of topology evolution that happens
out there. And I do think there is high
level of precaution to be taken when we
talk about this kind of stuff. And yes,
does anyone want to react or agree
or disagree violently? Because I just
attacked the common creeds.
Not sure I perceived an attack perhaps
from what I understood of what you said.
Basically you have information geometry,
it formalizes a belief space in a sort
of geometric manifold.
The points represent possible belief
systems that an agent can have and
the distance between the points in the
space can be interpreted as a measure of
how different two belief systems are.
And this is necessarily tugged
by the priors given by the environment
which also push the agent to act in
a certain way given the type of thing
that it is, in order to maintain itself,
given the actions that it knows it has
available. And this
becomes normative because of the
strength of the
attractors within the belief space which
become the geometric landscape,
basically. So we can sort of model
the attraction through the curvature of
the space around the attractor. And so a
high curvature means a strong normative
force which pulls the agent to adopt a
certain, I like to say social scripts
because that's what I've worked on but
any sort of policy and or phenomenology
norm. And so in this context,
the agent's agency is kind of
complicated because it's both the
ability to sort of navigate the
landscape to move closer or further away
from the attractors. And so the degree
to which an agent has agency is a degree
to which it doesn't go necessarily
directly towards the attractor, but has
some degree of reflexivity over its own
action space in order to navigate the
different kinds of factors that
may be available to it. So we could see
that the momentum would be affected by
personal experiences, education, innate
tendencies or even the tendency
to resist or yield to
social pressures. I could go on, but I
know that a you have your hand up. So
why don't you go?
OK, I guess Avel could answer
before I talk a bit. So I was just
trying to have my hand raised before
talking. So if Avel wants to answer you
and afterwards I can talk, I'm OK.
I don't have anything specific to okay,
okay. So you talked about the dual
aspect of statistical organization of
complex agents and you said that it was
a core contribution of active influence
to social sciences. Can you
dig a bit on that and
just articulate it a bit more so we
could grasp it better and
then I could ask questions.
Do I still share my screen? Yes.
So basically what we have in here is
a formalism that deals from
very basic dynamics like just web
space and there is stuff that pensive
space. Zero level physical
representation of literally anything can
go there. And from there we
build a model of first self
organization, not quite that
agentive self organization. Let us say
something that can build a specific
stable ecology and maintain itself in
this ecology. That is what we have here.
And then given the lack of coupling
between active and tone states, we can
build sensitively, more complex stuff
that can implement higher order beliefs
about themselves and what they do and do
decision making that is conditioned on
information they have about themselves
and qualification under the form of
beliefs over their own action.
And as such, this is just math.
This says nothing about the world in and
of itself until we claim it corresponds
to things in the world. And we can claim
that this is a basic conceptual model
that maps well onto acculturation,
basically socialization engagement with
the cultural world. Because then we can
account of the human ability for very
wide open ended learning as
something that comes from there, as
something that allows us to infer things
about ourselves and then develop complex
policies and neck them blah blah, blah.
And because to my knowledge there is no
competing model that accounts for
anything near that competition,
I should not talk of competition, but
the odd models of cognitive
organization and culturation that exists
that are trying to ground themselves in
physics like an immigrant system. They
are just talking about dynamics. They
are specifically avoiding talking about
anything like content or semantics. So
they factor this piece of math as a
monopoly on building semantics from the
ground. And what it tells you is that
agency and identity and relativity is
all the same phenomenon. It's
conditioned by self belief basically
that is constructed in this specific
way.
How to say because this is the only way
that we can account for higher order
agency. Then at
least I would argue we should have a
strong priors for a series of agency,
either mechanical or conceptual that
vibe well with that picture. So this is
the claim I'm making. I guess I went
into too much detail, so I hope this is
enough. Okay,
so I have some, maybe not questions,
but some points to make now. Thank you.
So from what I see here,
we could put the active inference
paradigm into the individualistic
methodological individualism framework
in sociology. So the idea is that you
try to model an individual and then when
you have the good way to model the
individual, you can generalize to what
everyone is doing. So for instance,
if I'm working on something in
a certain way, then I could generalize
about that and say, okay,
sociologically I have this constraint to
work on this stuff. And then not
like everyone is doing that, but it
could go like that. But what is
interesting here is that it's not only
about one individual, but also that,
for instance, let's take the external
states. You could say that external
states here are other agents,
and also that,
okay, so you have the active states and
the internal states. So we could say
that your internal states are totally
influenced by another agent. So we could
do something like that with two
individuals, I guess. So one is
one of the agent here and the other
drives the internal states of the model
because they are really influential on
yourself. So there are some limitations
about this kind of way of thinking
because in general,
in sociology or in sociological
sciences, what you would like to say is
that there are some agents at a higher
level than only individuals such as you
and I. So the trick could be
to say that some states, for instance,
or some firms are agents foreign
by themselves. So you have agents which
are not individuals or persons.
I don't understand what you're trying to
say, Avel I was
just trying to react to your slide
because I don't see how it connects with
my own work here yet. Oh, I'm talking to
Mao. Okay, nice.
So yeah, if Mao, you have something to
say about what I just said, about how we
could have, let's say, two active agents
trying to talk together?
Yeah, we have such simulations
that already exist over various
kinds of scales. We have two agents
coordinating that are animals like birds
singing, and over time coordinating over
the song they're going to sing. We have
several models of leader follower,
where you have two
agents starting from relatively the same
point, but one agent developing more
confidence and therefore developing a
dynamic of leader follower with the
other agent. This is work that's
possibly going to be followed by
Francesco Balzan, who is working on
models of education and how maybe the
teacher and student dynamic may be cast
under these terms. I've done work with
Axel Constant and Maxwell Ramstead in
terms of active inference in social
scripts. That's what Ava was mentioning.
And this notion that through the
cues of the environment, your own model
is shaped both by the environment which
includes other people, and the way in
which you self evidence within this
environment. So for instance,
there's two ways we can understand your
question. First, we can say that
minimizing free energy is
basically an agent that has a form of
autonomy and it's constantly updating
its model to align with the environment.
So by virtue of doing this, it's not
fundamentally individual, but each
agent has its own model of the world.
Each agent reflects a perspective, a
very unique moment in spacetime that
will incur some errors relative to
others. So it's not that they
necessarily interpreted things wrong,
although they might have, but because
their perspective is slightly off from
somebody else. There's necessarily a
degree of incommunicability in this
sense. So here, self evidencing really
entails that identity.
You create a sort of identity here
through the fact that you may have
different preferred states from somebody
else based on your values, belief, your
social conditioning. But again, these
beliefs and values and social
conditioning have been shaped.
Again, we're talking about these trove
of attractors by other people.
And so we try more and more to challenge
this notion of individualism by
emphasizing the relational aspect of
identity, which means that identity is
not pre established but continuously
formed through the interactions with
other agents. And again, if we go back
to information geometry, the geometry of
the information space influences how
agents perceive their paths towards
minimizing free energy and affect their
choices, which again give you the
possibility to understand how agents
might be very strongly pushed by other
agents. Let's imagine an agent that has
more power than you and is trying to
influence you to do something, someone
that has very high charisma or someone
who has the power to say destroy your
life. You are more likely to shape your
beliefs to align with,
and therefore we can understand
individualism under a very different
light here. Avel, do you want to add
something? Colleen is waiting to speak
since moments. So let's hear. Colleen.
Hi, can you hear?
Okay, I just wanted to pick on
a couple of things that Maha was talking
about just now. And in her talk
it seems that you seem to be saying that
for social conditioning and the way in
which we are socialized, the importance
of social scripts appears to be greater
than the influence of individual upon
individual. And that's interesting
because it's not something that we would
tend to think as individuals that we are
integrating with scripts. In fact, the
whole idea of seeing a script as
something which is social was something
that I find that probably most people
would find a rather strange idea off
the top of our heads.
Is that a fair assessment of what you're
trying to say? And the other thing I
wanted to ask about was a few times
in talks recently and here today, I've
heard people talking about identity and
the active inference view of
identity. I'm not sure that I really
understand what identity means within an
active inference framework as distinct
from just our internal model of who we
are. Is there another idea that
we're thinking of here? And more
particularly, the word identity has a
lot of baggage and usage in current
contemporary society. Are we using it in
a different way? And if so,
how is it different? And potentially,
how does that give us insight and the
ability to engage with the ongoing
discussions in society in a potentially
fruitful way.
So I think I lost you for the last part
of your question, which seemed to be
about the difference between our
conception of identity and the
conception generally used. If that's
correct.
You'Re muted Colin.
Sorry. Yeah, I was referring to the
concept of identity as used in society.
Right. So, I mean, I'm not going to
speak to every use of the term identity
because it's a very useful term that's
used in law, that's used in physics,
it's used in sociology and psychology.
So it's used a lot. All I can do is
explain roughly how we consider identity
formation and then if you have a
specific definition in mind for a
specific field, we can maybe tackle that
one. Does that sound okay?
Yeah. To be clear, I was thinking
specifically about identity as
determined by group membership in
sociology. Okay.
So I'm going to tackle social scripts
first. Yeah,
I'm going to tackle social scripts first
and then I'm going to come back to
identity because I think it fits plea.
I've worked on that as well. I know that
Daniel and Avel have some work that
relates to this as but so your first
question was on the importance of social
scripts and what it means for cognition,
if I understood correctly. So from an
internalist perspective,
social scripts are cognitive structures.
They guide behaviors, they're acting
like brackets. We use the word
constraints a lot.
It's not a perfect guide because no
semantic marker is a perfect guide.
Everything is up for some degree of
interpretation. It's just that there are
some interpretations that are so
strongly linked to some degree of
embodiment that they sort of anchor the
rest of our semantics. So, for instance,
I can't stop breathing if I wanted to.
I can't. I will stop, but eventually my
body will restart on its own. And so
there's such kinds of natural laws here
that create these
bottom layer guidelines that can then be
sort of derived to infer other things.
And social scripts are just
representational,
social extensions of these constraints
given a historical context. So they
model and.
Did Mal drop or did I drop?
I guess it's they're given to you. Like
somebody will actually tell you what to
do and show it to you. And sometimes
they won't be. Sometimes they're just
things you observe. Sometimes there's
things you infer because you made a
connection between a weak script and
another weak script. So if you see
something that resembles a chair in a
room, you infer that, you have the
affordance to sit on it. So that's a
form of script. And then you see other
people doing the same and the script
sort of cements. And so now you
associate this to another part of a
sequence, and this becomes something
that allows you to temporalize and
basically leverage your B matrix in
order to exist in the world in a way
that doesn't cause friction with other
people. This also gives you action
triggers. There are things you see in
the world that now tell you this is the
thing you should do now. So there's this
sort of recursive loop that's very
inactive, that pulls you in a direction.
So the attractor isn't just a state,
it's a path. You're going to go down a
path. So for now, does that answer the
first question? Yes.
Thanks. It's helpful. Okay,
go ahead. Thank you. To get back on
the like, you talked about an active
loop, and I think that's a critical
thing to underline, which is that the
engagement with the world is a cyclic
process, a circular process. It
construct its own conditions.
There is no measure of power of
structure versus power of agents because
the structure is embedded in the agents
and the agents are embedded in the
structure. So I'd like to share my
screen again to give some detail over
what this entails.
Good window. You should see a PDF with a
tiny man personal montaigne
and loops. Is it
okay? Yes. I see.
Yes. So this is a presentation I did
recently about the Unification Church,
which is like when you want to be
published, you say new religious
movement, but you can say cult. It
works, which originated, I think, in
Japan and is now spread between Korea,
Japan, and it says mostly we don't have
numbers, but it seems to be the places
where it's most implanted. And it
was very remarked because of the
personality cult around the Reverend
Moon, the founder, and the very overt
exorcist practices of the cult, like
asking you for the equivalent of ten
years of salary at the time to
take your ancestors from hell and put
them in paradise by giving money to
Reverend Moon specifically. And they
were the topic of very aggressive
and excessive anticult movement in the
they are becoming a bit noticed again by
vice, not only vice,
but notably vice, because you have very
strange things like mass MAGA weddings
with people waving rifle and that is
very strange organization. And at the
time you had very moral
panic, we say now, around the cult.
You had basically a model of influence
that was that evil people would
brainwash you and then you were
commanded by the cult and or Soviet
secret agents from afar, and they could
say to you, horse. And this triggered
homocydal mania in which you blah,
blah, blah. So things that are
unnaturalistic, I will say, and notably
in reaction to the immoral panic, you
had a movement biologists of religion
that would try to understand how exactly
the cult worked. And the most famous
sociologist to do that was Aileen
Barker, if I remember, was she warned
the money she was coming. So you can
question her methodology, but she seems
to have done the most thorough and well
received analysis of them. So it's quite
important thing and she questions that
there is such a thing as brainwashing.
There is construction of a specific
social context that you have to comply
to if you want to come, but they can
force you, they do not have the
capability to torture you and make you
into RC radio community thing that does
not work. And so I forgot the name of
the so David Frank Taylor explains
the influence of the church in terms of
choreography of total participation. So
basically you have a very huge, very
emotionally investing ritual that you
just have to take part in to be a member
of the community. And if you are a
member of your community, you will be
helped, you will be loved, you will be
supported, you will be constantly
encouraged in a slightly coercive way to
invest more of your time and money and
whatever in the organization. And if
you don't, then all the support just
leaves because you're a traitor. You
have treason of the
true parents who was kindly out of
this own arts trying to save you like
Jesus did, but better because Jesus
failed by not having children. That is
very dramatic thing to say and that is
what they said. And because of the way
the organization is set up, you cannot
possibly question that. Questioning is
not accepted. There is no private time
in which you can privately question
yourself. You are always engaged with
people who are either formally or
informally depending on your seniority
watching you. And so you have basically
a context that makes it very easy to
align with the cult values and
it just happens that those values they
entail self sacrifice for the
organization but also for new members
and total deference to the cult and
its leadership and anything they tell
you to do. So it's not
kidnapping, but it's also not exactly
free consent to a specific context.
And from a purely, I don't
know what to say mechanical perspective
they can make you agree when you are
there, but they cannot make you go
there. So a question is how precisely
they can elicit compliance away
from the direct context of the
choreography of participation. And there
is like simple answer in my sense,
which is that we have a coherent
sense of identity. We can hardly think
of ourselves as a good money 1 minute
and then step out of the meeting and not
think of ourselves as a good money.
That doesn't make sense. Either we are
or we are not. At least most people tend
to have one integrated sense of
themselves as someone who is embedded in
a specific social context and has
specific norms and they are in such way.
And so the coherence of self identity,
it provides a key coupling between your
public and your private beliefs, what
you are expected to do in social context
and what you will effectively do and
perceive the world as privately. And
this I would say in the example
of the Munis, but in other rhetorical
examples like the emergence of
nationalism. It is a very
straightforward confirmation that indeed
coherence of self identity, like the
coherence between what you do and what
you think of yourself as doing,
is a very important process in
the structure of societies, generally
speaking, at least contemporary
societies. Maybe it was not the same
before. And so I do not think the
context in which it's mobilized, of
course it changes, but the mechanism, I
don't think it's new. And I'd like to
get back on Alex's point that sorry,
a's point that the approach we have is
individualistic. I do not think it is
the case because if we are correct,
there is a landscape of sociocultural
affordencies constraints, things world
out there and we engage with it. And
there are mechanism that makes this
landscape not necessarily identical but
very coherent between individuals. And
those mechanism are language and the
material symbolism developing ritual,
which is also symbolism, also
meaningful, but maybe less than
language. I don't know. I just mean that
the mechanism is the same and the
interculturally robust practice of role
taking and shared essentialities of
trying to do stuff together given
a specific model of the
attribution of tasks within the shared
goal and so these are human invariants
and all would be pretty good candidate
to force the integration of a common
model of material and cultural niche.
And so I think that there is
a pretty coherent, social material
niche, and I think that we all engage
with it and we all modify it, and we
maybe do not perceive it as the same,
but there is still a strong enough
constraints on the coherence of this
landscape between individuals for it to
make sense as a specific entity. And
then the proper explanatory scale of
what we do is not the individual minds,
it is landscape that we happen to
experience because of our individual
minds. So by the plateau
academia of Stanford on Holism basically
Holism is a theory where you agree that
there are explanations that are not
mediated by individual states. And I say
there are explanation that are not
inherited by individual states. And not
only that, but I can point to
organization that control people while
being absolutely not worried about
individual states only creating a
circumstance and then allowing them to
engage with it. And that would
be compelling, in my opinion, to say
that the model we have is maybe not
Holist, maybe a secret third thing that
is multiscale but certainly not
individualist, at least in the sense
that you are mobilizing. Thank you.
I talked more than I wanted. So Mao,
you were raising your hands. I am, but I
think Lorena wants to go. I will go
after Lorena.
Hey, guys. Yeah, I think that goes
directly into the idea that coming
back a little bit to the point that
identity they were talking before. And
if you think about the model that we
have, we have the external states and
different agents, they are always
actually very local and situated in
the same local constraint local
environment. Right. So your external
agent is going to be part other agents
are going to be part of your external
states and you are part of theirs.
Right. So the idea of laying down a path
and creating a specific type of dynamic
that react to the same type
of input that you are receiving and
driving this dynamic will generate
this sort of embeddedness right.
Because you do have the same.
Or. No, it's not necessarily the same,
but they're very close to each other,
they're very approximate. Right. So the
idea of a dynamic here, if you think
about describing that in terms of
like, in terms of the dynamics, you do
have very different Lawrence
butterflies, for instance. Each one goes
through the same type of route.
However, they're not identical, but they
are very similar. They are doing
something very similar and that
similarity sort of constrains, again the
construction of that environment. So if
you think about symbols and roles and
types of environment that you find,
they're going to be as concrete as
something else that you find in your
environment. Constraining and pushing
you towards the same direction or at
least a very similar you can describe
dynamically in a very similar type of
geometry if you like, or this
attractor will drive the very similar
type of path. Will describe this similar
type of path which
goes exactly to the Avel. Can you go
back to that?
The other figure that you have, the one
with the environment as well made
by yeah, that one. So exactly.
That creates a dynamic that they can be
then forgotten in a way that
will be described through a specific
mark of blank that will develop agents
together. We push them constraining,
they're going to be constrained together
and they're going to have a constructive
kind of role
in this very embedded normativity.
But yeah, you go.
Thanks. Yeah. So I think there's a nice
way to tie all this as well to the
internal nature that we seem to be
dispelling, but we're not. We have to
talk about specifically in what ways
internality is cast here. And I
like to think of the effect of self
esteem here. Self esteem to me is the
degree of fitness relative to your
perception of how well you're managing
to exist within these constraints and
interpret them in a way that gets other
people to validate and minimize the
friction that you're getting from other
people. So it aligns
with the concept of sociometer theory.
It taps into this notion of cultness.
So if you consider that there's
effective states that enable an
individual to track and respond to
discrepancies between self perception
and social expectation through these
effective states such as anxiety or
positive affect, we can see that there's
a dynamic nature and self organization
of self esteem which is continually
shaped and reshaped by experiences and
interactions. And so under
active inference. We can formalize this
by saying that a model that is more
precise effectively captures the
hierarchical structure of the moment to
moment variation of more stable traits,
such as what we consider to be selfish.
And so basically we
can see that identity and group
membership here are fundamentally
related to the effective experience of
being fit for the group membership. And
so once you're there, you can grow in
social cohesion and this will lead you
to potentially try to maintain the
group. It will lead you to try to
justify the beliefs of the group such
that you have a form of confirmation
bias, but also you maintain the
epistemic reality of this group, the
symbolic reality of this group, which
would be more costly to destroy than to
actually support. It's also integrated
into your self esteem. Therefore,
destroying the group would mean
admitting that you are potentially not
fit for the environment, that you are
potentially some degree of wrong. And so
this leads us to the possibility that if
someone has low self esteem, what do
they do? They can either stay in this
group and accept that they are unfit for
the group, and they would try to remove
themselves to some extent from the group
to avoid all that friction. Or they can
try to join a different group, one which
will support your beliefs about the
world if your beliefs are too far from
where the group you're supposed to
belong to currently is. And this is
where we get to these subclusters
forming these little subgroups that
potentially can even become sometimes
violent and sometimes really not.
Sometimes it's just some tumblr group,
but it has power because it gives
the individual this feeling, this
valence of now being fit to a group that
supports their model.
So I wanted to give a space to
talk. Yes, thank you.
So I would like to go back a bit on
what I said about individualism.
So, yeah, I agree that I was
wrong about associating active
inference with individualism, because
what is interesting here is that there
is an individuality through active
inference which emerge from the
collective, and you can justify or
describe individual actions,
or else through
the landscape, as you did just now, and
then go the other way around. So here
we seem to grasp the interaction between
the individual and the group and vice
versa, which is what I found interesting
here.
Okay. Moreover, there is what
the individual adds to a group.
I see that here. It seems to be captured
as we take the individual as how
to say that a unique perspective.
This is what you said before now, that
each person is a perspective,
a unique one. And yeah,
it's not all what I wanted to say.
Also, Lorena, you talked about the
beliefs that exist, and I think this is
one interesting thing also in active
inference. It's that we take belief as a
material thing that influences us
and that we can also influence or create
in a way even
independently of if it's right, wrong or
whatever we judge it is like what
we talked about with the Moon sect and
the Unification Church. So there are
people with crowns and we say that they
are the big boss and we have to deal
with it or to go away from the
landscape. From the landscape. And yeah,
it was like that in the social world,
indifferently of if the person is really
like the chief of the cults or not
because they said they were and people
were just following them. So in the end
it happened to create a landscape in
which one person is the
person who has power.
I don't know what to say more about all
of this. I guess I agree with what you
said just before,
that's it.
So maybe we should move to challenges
and opportunities of active inference.
So two
points, I think I just put them out
there. You can react.
I think that one ActInf inference may
give us computational models or even
thorough grounded conceptual models of
social organization, specifically the
semantic dimension to social life.
And I also think that in its current
formulation, within the Mikhail system
theory, it is inept to represent parent
evolution because Mikhail system entail
the formulation of a set of states that
do not change through time and a mikol
flow that does not either change flu
time. So there are opportunities to
apply the model to the
framework to grounded,
meaningful, semantically complete models
of revolution. But this model,
if they are conformed evolution, they
will not really vibe well with the math
that we invoke to say our computational
model are meaningful and that's like
rise and array of questions, I guess.
So does anyone want to react to these
two statements?
Could I go sorry, could I make a
comment?
More specifically, I'm interested in the
ways in which the ideas of active
inference impact on the way we think
about society and the way society works.
And I can see from my reading and from
listening to the discussion that there's
a very rich due lexicon in vocabulary
set of concepts for the thinking within
active inference thought. And as
we just commented, it's quite heavily
mathematical. So the barrier to entry
for the full active inference worldview,
over time these ideas will permeate out
into the mainstream and they will change
the way people think and talk about
society. I'm interested in the ways
people who've studied a bit more than I
have see potentially how this will
change the way society works or the way
that we have discussions or
envisage society more widely than just
an academic discussion. Obviously,
maybe the questions are a bit too big.
I think everyone is just waiting for the
other to talk first. Mao talked first.
So I think I want to tackle a
little bit what you said about the
open ended nature, the open ended
evolution in of
state spaces. Basically,
I think under the path formulation,
this open endedness is actually just a
perceived open endedness. It's just
a function of the timescale being
considered and the motion along that
timescale.
I think we can go a little bit more into
depth about this. I think
it's a very large topic.
Effectively, if we go into quantum
formulations, there's some degree of
irreducibility, and anything above that
is historically contingent. So obviously
some Markov blankets will dissolve and
reform and dissolve and reform. And
through this dissolution and
reformation, you get a new potential for
mapping of observation to states. So
there's always that possibility.
But I think some challenges for
active inference that are coming is,
for instance, the complexity of
social behavior.
We can extend active inference to
capture the nuances of social
interactions. But effectively, active
inference is about abductions. So it's
the best guess for now.
And it requires for us to put
into the models what we think
are useful variables, what we think are
the right variables. And it's possible
that we're always going to fall
just a little bit short. We can
either throw a bunch of data at a
problem and be like, well, okay, well,
just remove the noise, only pick up the
signal, and figure out what's happening.
But that's no better than big data and
deep learning. So we have to figure out
a way to move forward and understand the
variables of interest and do this across
scales. So identify the priors that take
over at a given moment, but they won't
take over even if they're higher in the
hierarchy at another moment, because in
this hierarchy, you've actually switched
states like you've moved. And this is
only predictable once you've understood
the effect of those priors. And you
can't just consider that you have the
priors to begin with.
So, yeah, as far as integration
with existing theories, I think we have
a nice opportunity ahead of us. It's
basically what you said, Colin.
I think we're going to be able to more
and more, through the alignment of
certain kinds of language and the
formalism under that language, we're
going to be able to pull more and more
theories and find what's at the core of
the connection between these theories.
Active inference is supposed to be scale
free, so it describes or it
is possible to help us describe the
phenomena basically from sociology
and literature to biology.
So if we understand this, we understand
that there's a possible touch point, a
convergence of all these fields that are
tapping into the same ideas or into some
connecting points that allow us to
understand how we maybe do away
with these different fields, remove the
silos, and come back together with
something that feels more integrative.
But then again, we're back to the
computational limits, obviously. Like,
if I want to compute the prediction for
an entire country, what is the
granularity level at which I should
compute the right variables and if we
understand that individuals are formed
by the group, et cetera, do I just do a
mean field over the entire group? In
which case am I losing out on some of
the variables that may actually impact
the outcomes? I think these are the key
questions that remain to be answered to
some extent.
So I agree with what you said. Now.
I agree that we can't represent
things and not somehow not cut anything
relevant to the thing when we model or
we represent. The point of it is to have
a more compressed way to engage with the
thing, with our knowledge of the thing,
than the actual thing. So we will just
cut information. That is the point of
modeling or representing. And maybe in
a very simple system such like just
say perfect gas model in physics, there
is information we can cut and lose
nothing. We can cut information about
which particle is where, because the
different particles of the same atom as
at this scale, the same properties. So
we don't really care what atom does
what. But in the case of human
societies, we have patterns of
engagement and the specific information
that is accessed by a specific agent is
important. And whatever we choose to cut
for a model, it will be relevant at some
point. At least it will probably be if
the information we cut is not
specific to a bunch of agent that will
die of car accidents or something. If
any kind of information, any type of
information we may want to abstract out
will be relevant somewhere at some
point. So yeah, we are dealing with
complex systems. We are not going to
model everything. But it
is a huge deal that active inference is
capable to fill in the semantic content
from dynamics, either from the
dynamics of component systems, say
neural dynamics and biological dynamics,
or dynamics of a social context with the
modeling of axe inference agent as
things that navigate the world and make
inference and stuff. And to my
knowledge, we do not have any other
theory that makes the bridge between
just dynamics and semantics.
We have other neurological cognitive
neuroscience people who talk about
dynamics a lot and how we can bring back
the activity of cognitive systems to
dynamics. But usually it is in a way
that insists that we should just look at
the dynamics. We don't really need to
worry about the semantics or if we need
to worry about the semantics, they
somehow reduce to the dynamics. The
dynamics is what exists and is important
and what we should worry about. And so
another framework that is relevant to
just study evolution of norms or
presentation or mental content in a
context, I cannot think of one, one that
is thoroughly grounded at least that
attempts to thoroughly ground itself in
mathematics, mathematical physics,
there isn't another one. And so that is
a huge deal. But there is a very
important problem, which is what I
said and you said, and we're grown,
which is that the periness in the
path integral formulation, in earlier
formulation in the FEP, it is illusory,
it is about like it.
So maybe to give a bit of context, the
path integral formulation of the FEP is
just when you do the FEP. So the bit of
math we make a huge deal about and
we apply it not to the dynamics of
a particle per se, like how it affects
the particle at point T, but how it
affects pathes of a particle for
mathematic reasons. Reframing a problem
in path integral formulation is a huge
deal. It is what makes the difference
between a Newtonian, you push something
and it moves. And full fledged quantum
gorge theories that underwrite all of
contemporary physics. So yes, path
integral formulation is a huge deal.
But to write it, you still need to write
an emulator space, like to make the list
of all things that are possible. And if
you think that this is a correct model
of the world and a complete model of the
world, and this is everything there is,
you have to agree either that cause do
not exist or that there is a place in
the primoldo wave function that existed
before universe did, before time did.
There is a place where cones lies and
I think cause exists and I do not think
cause are basic properties of quantum
mechanics. So cos must have happened
along the way somehow. And to represent
that mean to represent open endedness.
So we need open endedness in math and
the FEP is not one ended. And
structurally it's very hard to account
for open ended evolution. And at a more
prosaic level, when we look at
engagement with social dynamics, with
the social world, we look at open
endedness because there is always
integration of norms, there is always a
loss of information, but also that is
constructive of new norms. There is no,
like, writing happen at some point. And
then we did things differently, changed
the structure of cities, it enabled
administration to exist as a non trivial
power society that actually mattered
its organization. And yeah, so new
things happen. And if we want to look at
social engagement, it is critical to
look at how new things happen. And
currently the FEP doesn't do that in
active inference. I don't think it does
that. Maybe it can at a computational
level without grand from all pretension.
Maybe, but I did not see it. And that's
a big challenge that we have ahead of
us. And by we I mean everyone, not just
ActInf in front of people, everyone
should tackle that at some point.
Daniel, you were raising your hand.
I'll add just a few notes to Colin's
question. Certainly it's something that
we all ask ourselves and many viewers
and participants in the ecosystem ask
like, so what then? What does it really
mean for active inference to be applied
to or by or in the social sciences. So I
think that's a big open question,
certainly one that's not only
addressable by one perspective or even
with words alone, but I think there's a
few key pieces especially that
differentiate it from just the broader
or adjacent project of quantitative
social science or formal social science.
The question we should seek after is
what does active inference bring in?
And again, probably many ways to say it,
but we know for an active inference
agent, as a scale free statement,
free energy can be bounded by changing
the world or changing the mind. So
having continuity of social systems with
all other systems, spatial, temporal,
arbitrary, material and so on, gives a
continuity and an interoperability that
without a scale free first principles
approach, is essentially not even on the
radar. So that's one massive piece. And
then I think where that begins to bear
or modify fruit is essentially
the scientific and professional
development of cognitive engineering.
Understanding that the cognitive
constraints and scaffolds scripts, all
of these tasks implicitly and
then more recently, explicitly and most
recently quantitatively, informally,
are examples of cognitive engineering.
So whether it's a stop sign and what
that comes to mean in different social
locations or language as a complex
phenomena, these are examples of
cognitive engineering in the same way
that building a stack of rocks is both
an example of material engineering and
cognitive engineering through semiotics.
And now when the scientific process,
the professional process, enters into
this reflexive and relational posture
through active inference, that is
kind of a saddle point into a different
dynamic, I believe. Lorena.
Lorena unmute and then go for it.
Yeah, I just make one comment upon what
is that? Keep in mind that active
inference can understand beliefs and
signs and this kind of semiotics
as material and concrete because
constraints, they constrain the
evolution of the system, like how the
system complexifies, right. And the
constraints has this material effect
on the dynamics. You cannot really
believe that. Of course belief is
materialized as a table. Of course not.
But for the system in terms of
constraining and understanding how
things scale up and how they complexify,
they have that kind of role.
And that helps to understand a little
bit what Velvet was bringing about how
you can bring new values
and parameters for the dynamics that are
being described by the mathematics of
external and internal free energy
principle updating.
And that is a way of tackling this
novelty for this
kind of thinking over time. But you
don't have a proper account on how to
predict what is going to constrain
the system next. Right?
Yeah. Mao, go for it. And then we'll all
kind of give a closing round.
Thoughts?
Okay, well, there was a question in
the chat at one point. I just wanted to
potentially address the question if
that's okay.
So the question was, so would the
generative process of modeling the
social system enclose multiple agents on
one Markov blanket or I assume inside
or under one Markov blanket. So we
like to think of active inference as
nested in hierarchical. That's one thing
that Maxwell Ramstead definitely
pioneered, where each agent has its
own mark of blankets, but there is a
higher level Markov blanket that
encloses the social system in play.
So individual agents can interact with
each other and the environment, but the
social system as a whole also interacts
with the broader environment. And this
is where semantics and semiotics come
into play and the narratives around
certain groups start shaping how they
can interact with the other groups which
have a perception of these narratives.
So there's in group and out group
dynamics.
So it's a little bit akin to how cells
within an organism have their own
boundaries but are also part of a larger
organism.
So, yeah, I think that does that answer
the question from the person who asked?
That.
Does. Nice. So perhaps
A and Colin, feel free to give in your
marks and then we'll pass around the
instructors.
It can be as long or as short as you
like. Okay. May I go first?
So I would
like to say that the
key issue we are trying
to grasp is that effective in France
has social and political implications
due to its scale free structure and
how we can apply it to the social world.
Then there is the self referential
question that happens, which is what
is the structure of active inference as
a social construction itself and a
political construction itself? And what
are our own like,
our own what is our own political
power and social power in this social
and political world? And this is the
factor like thing that is going on
because afterwards, what is my own
social and political implication in this
thing? And the more you get your own
agency and the agency of active
inference, the more it becomes like a
lot to process and the more you
grasp your own agency and
the power you have and the
responsibility you have. I guess
this is one of the key points we are
trying to get here.
Yeah, I guess that's the point I wanted
to make. And to finish with that,
the game we are trying to play is to try
to found our own blind spots in this
game. Like what is the limit of the
model and does it have a
self referential limit or not?
That's it.
Yeah, I would endorse that
and I feel the same way. I found that
my reading just in the last year or so
of active inference ideas, I found it
very empowering. The ideas of active
inference in relation to the individual
mind are quite well developed.
And it's very empowering to
be able to look at yourself through the
active inference paradigm and understand
the thought processes that is you. It's
a very empowering thing. And as I
was saying just recently, starting to
look at the idea that we can incorporate
an active inference concept of the way
the social world around us is
structured, which is part of that
paradigm too, I think is potentially
more empowering. But it's early days
yet, but I look forward very much to a
more developed world where people have
discussions with each other, not just
about what I'm thinking and how I think,
but how I think about society and how we
think about society together. And it's
embedded within that paradigm. I feel
that's potentially something which is
very empowering and I look forward to
it. And thank the speakers all for their
contributions to this series of talks.
Thank you, Colin. So,
with the exception of Ben,
whose lecture and contribution kicked
off this course and were excellent,
also we have the others of the
instructors here. So how
do each of you want to kind of conclude
this chapter?
Yeah. Mao, then. Lorena? Raphael?
Yes. I think of
entities which are the capability of
interacting to maximize the information
they gather from the environment such
that as a whole, they can self evidence
to maintain the phenotypes they believe
to be similar to their own. And
therefore themselves and how this leads
to over time, the sedimentation of
norms and activities and eventually
the reference to these norms and
activities through the semantics and the
scripts. And effectively how this leads
us to all the complexities of language
and how we may now be at the point where
we have simulacra that represents
nothing, we just have these shells
of representations and these shells of
semantics which potentially have lost
their anchoring in reality. So I think
that was the through line of the course.
I hope we made a good case for it and
how active inference allows us to model
this entire path not only across scale,
but across time as well. So, yeah,
that's how I think I'm going to close.
Yeah, I think this is me now. Yeah, I
really like the story as well that we
are building throughout the whole
course, starting with a very general
idea of what is active inference with
Ben and then trying to build up
this collective notion how
we contain information in a certain way
that it's always synchronized. So this
is always sort of meaningful that can be
described in certain ways by the
mathematics of active inference. And
then understanding these questions, the
hard questions that we're asking now,
like how we can bring new variables,
how can bring novelty into the system,
which is something that we don't have an
answer yet. But I find that it's really
cool that we don't hold back in asking
that because I think that's the next
step for active, like understanding how
complexification comes about. How can we
describe that? Yeah, and thanks,
Avel and Daniel, for putting this
together. It was pretty cool and I hope
you guys also have enjoyed.
Thank you, Lorena AFO.
So thank you, Lorena. You're welcome.
I think I put finger
on something quite deep as
usual, which is that if we want to have
a coherent theory of nature that is not
based on just here are the things that
can be and we will draw dynamics on that
that is compatible with operating
evolution. We need to address self
referentiality, we need to address
recursion and the possibility for
recursive individuation of physical
beings. And that's tough and that's
very tough because the basis of
representation is just I list array of
things I want to represent and I
represent that. But if things can just
happen that are new and that are by
definition not in the field of
possibilities that preexisted, then we
are fucked. There is no way we can
represent that. And there
is a family of approach in quantum
information theory that tries to tackle
that how to draw physics without being
rolling in a specific set space and just
I'd like to explain the history of that.
So the math it draws from algebraic
topology, so we study surfaces, but not
by studying surfaces, by studying
transformation within those surfaces,
but then we remove those surfaces and we
keep only the transformation over what,
I don't know, but somehow we can, I
guess reconstruct coherent mathematical
entity from that. And I'd like us to
take a look at how this look, what the
math look like? So can we
see the screen? Okay, so this is the
structure of the quantum information
formulation of the FEP. These are
dimension of interaction between system
A and system B. What defines
the scope and the mode of this
interaction? I don't know. And this is a
cocon diagram that represents an agent
together with the representation that he
develops. And I could tell you the
words that correspond to the thing
within this diagram, but I do not know
what they mean. So it would be a hard
thing to do. And the math
that is capable to tackle the self
versatility like maybe because I do not
see any proof that it actually does. In
fact, it's not tractable for
humans and I exclude mathematical
physicists from humans there because of
the sheer abstractness of what is going
on and because of the lack of any abuse
reference that from anything we
intuitively understand in this. And the
work that we have to do if we want this
to move forward and to have a self
coherent theory of social evolution is
to somehow entangle from that concrete
meaning things that apply to the world
and conversely, use the way that we can
think of it as concrete interaction in
the world to further specify the
mathematics and prove that it is
actually self coherent and applies to
stuff. And this is a big
work in fact and this is
kind of exciting. I guess what
I wanted to say is ActInf in France is
dead. Long live active inference.
Great. Well, it was a fun course,
and this closing section and slide kind
of brought this unity between Chris
Fields's quantum work
and this social science, which in the
disciplinary paradigm are seen as
distant or with different systems of
interest. And you can't get there from
here, but in a scale free first
principles paradigm. It's not even just
that we can hold them side by side,
it's that they are more than juxtaposed.
So it's been awesome and its own great
experience to work with all of the
instructors who shared their amazing
and youthful and energetic perspectives.
And we explored new format in a new
way. We're going to process the
proceedings of the lectures and the
discussions, plus any
final submitted question and answers
through the Syllabus website. Bring that
together into an open access publication
of some kind. So for people who are
interested in that kind of editorial or
curatorial work, the active inference
journal is for them. And then in 2024
and beyond, let's see where active
inference is, see where social sciences
are, and hopefully,
as people are interested in Take it from
there. We threw in many fun ideas,
but I guess we'll leave it till then
to find out. You all
right? Thank you, everybody.