Hello. All right. Hello and welcome,
everyone. It is July 11,
2023. We are in active inference
for the social sciences, and today is
going to be a lecture by Ben White on
basics of active inference, the active
inference agent. So, Ben, thank you for
the lecture. Off to you, and we're
looking forward to it. Thank you very
much. Yeah, me too. Very happy to be
a part of this, to be kicking things off
with the first module on this course.
I'm going to be talking about the active
inference agent and trying to cover some
of the basics. I won't take too long
introducing myself. Ava gave a very
thorough introduction in his talk
recently, but I'm a second year PhD
student in philosophy at the University
of Sussex, and I work with Andy Clark
and with Avel and some other people
using active inference to try and find
things out about our relationship with
technology and within the context of
well being and mental health. The aims
for today I'm going to try and provide
quite a wide ranging overview of how
active inference has connected with
areas of philosophical interest, and
particularly how they relate to the
individual agent and the experience of
the agent and how the agent finds
themselves in the world. So I've split
this up to look at several different
defined topics. So I'm going to move
quite quickly through mind, agency,
emotion, and phenomenology, and I'm
going to say a little bit about the self
as well. And then there's going to be a
case study at the end that I'm going to
move through if we have time. So one of
the other aims that I have is to lay out
very clearly some of the core concepts
and core mechanisms like precision,
weighting, and prediction error enactive
models. I'm not going to go into any
technical details whatsoever. This is
all going to be fairly abstract. My
background and my interest in these
frameworks is philosophical, so it's
quite abstract in terms of how
everything fits together. And I'm going
to try and bring some of these threads
together to build up a layered picture
of what the active inference agent is
like, because this course is kind of
aimed towards seeing how active
inference applies to larger scales,
collective behavior, social norms,
sociocultural landscapes. And I think in
order to do justice to those things, we
need to first have a good idea of the
individual in active inference. So we've
got our work cut out for us. So I'll get
started. So before I dive
in, I wanted to just say a little bit
about how these frameworks hang
together. So active inference is
based on Karl Friston's free energy
principle. I think most of us are
familiar with that. But the free energy
principle just states that in order to
persist through time, biological
organisms must occupy only those states
that it would expect to occupy, given
the type of thing that it is so free
energy is essentially a measure of the
disatunment between a system and its
environment. And I'm going to say a
little bit more about attunement and how
that gets cashed out in various ways as
we go on. Active inference is a process
theory that essentially explains how
embodied organisms actually go about
remaining in those expected states. So
how we actually go about minimizing free
energy. And the idea is that all
adaptive behavior is explained by agents
garnering evidence to confirm their own
expectations. Predictive processing.
For the purposes of the lecture today,
I'm going to treat these as synonymous
because most of the work that I kind of
came up through as I was learning about
this was predictive processing. And all
of the papers that we're using today
that refer to predictive processing
refer to a predictive processing that I
take to be more or less synonymous with
active inference. So that's a very
embodied, inactive flavor of predictive
processing. I think generally the
difference is that predictive processing
can be a much broader term and
predictive processing can also apply to
passive models of perception. But we're
not going to concern ourselves with
that. Okay,
so some key concepts of active
inference, predictive processing then.
So the framework says that agents embody
or agents have we won't concern
ourselves with the nuance there, but
they have a generative model, which is
essentially a kind of understanding
or a model of the regularities that
underpin the dynamics between the agent
and the environment. So another way to
think about this in very rough terms is
a kind of mental model of the
regularities in the world and how the
agent exists in the world. And using
that model, the agent can generate
predictions about its own sensory
states. So given the model, what kinds
of sensory states would it expect to
find itself in in a particular set of
circumstances? And so where those
predictions don't actually match the
sensory inputs. So where there's a
discrepancy between the actual incoming
sense data and the prediction,
prediction errors are generated and
prediction errors are going to flow
upwards through the hierarchy. So the
generative model is said to be a
hierarchical model and predictions flow
downwards and prediction errors flow
upwards. And the sole imperative of the
brain body system, according to this
framework is to minimize those
prediction errors.
So a good way to kind of get a
little handle on this is to think about
just the example of perception. So
perception traditionally so I'm talking
about visual perception here. It's
traditionally been understood as a
bottom up process. And what that means
is that the brain waits for incoming
sensory signals and then it processes
them as they come in and it combines
them in kind of increasingly abstract
ways. And what we see is some
combination of those sensory signals
that have come in and been processed and
combined. So if you think about me
leaving my apartment in the morning and
stepping out onto the street and seeing
some cars. What's happening there is
some sensory information is hitting my
retina and it's being processed first
with very basic features like light
shade, edges and so on and so forth.
And then it's being combined with my
understanding of what a car is or what a
bus stop is. And that gives me my kind
of visual field.
Predictive processing, famously at this
point, flips this picture upside down on
its head. So visual perception under
predictive processing is a top down
affair. So the Generative model is going
to encode multilevel expectations about
the likely scene. So, just to be very
clear, when we talk about multilevel and
hierarchical, the higher up levels are
going to be tracking longer timescales
and higher levels of abstraction, and
the lower levels are going to be much
faster and much more concrete. So a
changeable scene, so there's going to be
some variation in what I see when I
leave my apartment every day is going to
mean that there's always going to be
some error in that picture. So it's
never going to be the same two days in a
row or it's extremely unlikely to be.
So no matter how well I can predict what
I'm going to see when I leave my house,
it's always going to be cleaned up by
some prediction errors. So essentially,
when I step outside and I step into the
street, my brain is already anticipating
what it's going to see out there. So I
know where particular cars are going to
be parked, I know where the bus stop is,
so on and so forth. And the perceptual
experience that we have is a
construction. We actually experience the
expectation that has been kind of
cleaned up post prediction error.
There's a little bit of debate there
about exactly what it is that we
experience. But for our purposes today,
we can say that visual perception is
essentially a construction.
So on the face of it, prediction errors
can be minimized using one of two
strategies, and this is going to be
really important.
So we have what I just described there,
which is perceptual inference. That's
where we revise our predictions to
better fit the evidence. So essentially
we update our model to better reflect
the regularities in the environment. Or
we can engage in active inference,
which is where the framework gets its
name from, which is where we essentially
make the evidence fit the model. So
that's where we in some sense update the
world so it conforms to the original
prediction. And active inference agents
bring about those expected states by
sampling the world in a bias way, so
they have certain expectations and then
we sample the world to confirm the
predictions. And I put perceptual
inference there in scare quotes because
perceptual inference on kind of readings
of most readings of active inference
just becomes a kind of action readiness.
Or as Ramstead and colleagues put it, a
state estimation. So it's just
perception and action are just wrapped
up in this continuous loop. But it's
really all about the action. It's really
all about bringing about those expected
states, and perception is just kind of
in service of that process. And so
Bruineberg and colleagues refer to the
enactive inference agent as a crooked
scientist, which is something I really
like. I think that's a very charming
image. So we are scientists that are
engaging in some very dodgy behavior
because we're not really interested in
having an accurate model. We're more
interested in confirming our original
predictions. Okay, so that
was a very rapid overview of some of the
core concepts and mechanisms, but
they're going to crop up continuously.
So I think we're going to get a much
better grasp on them as we go on. In
this section, I'm going to start to
expand on some of those things that
we've just put on the table, and I'm
going to begin to flesh them out in
terms of thinking about how active
inference agents actually exist in the
world. So I should say I
put this here to remind me. So those of
you who are taking part in the course,
I'm going to make available a document
with all of the readings that I firstly,
all of the readings that I've used to
make these slides, and then a bunch of
other readings as well that I think are
going to be very relevant. And
obviously, they're going to be organized
in terms of the structure of this
presentation as well. So this is just
I've put a little sample up on these
slides, but there's going to be much
more in the document. So I think it's
always good to start with some guiding
questions. So I've thrown up three here.
The first is how does enactive inference
characterize cognition? So we've just
looked at predictions and prediction
errors, but we're going to expand on
that a little bit. And we're going to
ask what kinds of processes does
cognition involve? How is cognition
related to the material environment?
This is going to be something how
cognition relates to the environment is
going to be very important in subsequent
weeks. And we're going to ask quite
briefly what kinds of vehicles might
realize cognitive processing.
So here's a couple of whales.
Whales are going to be a recurring theme
in this lecture, but I wanted to take a
step back and ask about Attunement
because this is one of those concepts
that gets thrown around a lot, and I
think once it's grasped, it becomes very
clear and very easy to use. But I think
prior to it being grasped, it can be a
little bit opaque and a bit slippery.
So on the left we have a humpback whale
that was found dead in the Amazon
rainforest, allegedly. I don't know if
this was true. And on the right we have
a whale in its natural environment. And
I think clearly the intuition here is
that in one case the whale is very well
attuned to its environment and in the
other case it's not. And I think that we
can start by asking what is it about the
ocean that allows the whale to be well
attuned? And what I want to say here is
that the particular dynamics between the
ocean and the whale allow the whale to
do certain things that it can't do when
it's in the Amazon. So in other words,
we might say that the ocean affords
certain things to the whale,
specifically filter feeding, being able
to move its vast weight around with
ease, things that, unfortunately, a
whale in the Amazon can't do. So
affordances are opportunities for
action. They are things,
roughly speaking, in the environment
that the agent can act upon. And there's
some debate about the proper way to
really characterize affordances, but I
like to think of them as relational
properties emerging from an
environmental feature and some skilled
embodied ability of the agent. So the
same thing in the environment will not
afford the same thing to different
organisms. So for example,
soil to a human agent might afford
walking on or laying down on, but to an
Earthworm it affords very different
things. And also, even amongst the same
organisms with humans, especially,
different surfaces and features of the
environment will afford different things
depending on your particular skill set.
And agents are going to go about
minimizing their uncertainty, so
minimizing prediction errors, staying
attuned to their environment through an
engagement with affordances. And this is
going to be something that is going to
drift away slightly as we move through
some sections and then it's going to
come back very heavily at the end. And I
should say that the idea of affordances,
to my knowledge, it first emerges in the
work of James Gibson the Ecological
Approach to Visual Perception. I think
it's chapter eight in that book that
really lays out a theory of affordances.
So this idea that systems or
organisms maintain their organization
through ongoing action means that
active inference has been labeled as
quintessentially inactive by Karl
Friston's. And I think that this is a
nice inactivism is an older framework
from theoretical cognitive science and I
think it's a nice way to understand some
of the key features of active inference.
But it does come with a little bit of
historical philosophical baggage. And
I'm going to try and unpack that really
quickly because I want to unpack exactly
what it is that we're committing
ourselves to when we think about
cognition in activist terms.
So inactivism comes in various strands
very, very quickly and roughly, you have
autopoietic inactivism, which commits
itself to what's known as the mind life
continuity thesis. This is essentially
that the structures that give a ground
to life itself are the same structures
that instantiate cognitive processes.
Sensing on this view is teleological
because it's oriented around supporting
vital systems. So things in the
environment have intrinsic meaning to
the organism because they support the
vital functioning of the organism in
some way. Sensory motor in activism
emphasizes how mobile and embodied
agents essentially enact the grounds
and conditions for their own sensory
engagements with the world. So the world
is not a kind of neutral static given
that we're parachuted into actually the
conditions through which we sense the
world are the conditions that we
can move and kind of interact with the
world in various ways and then there's
radical enactivism. And this is the
view that cognition is purely grounded
in these agent environment dynamics.
It's a purely dynamicist account of
cognition and there's no role whatsoever
for internal representations. So
certainly in certain brands of sensory
motor in enactivism there remains a role
for internal manipulation of
representations. And mental
representations are just mental states
that are about something in the world.
So some mental state is reconstructing
some feature of the world. And this all
harks back to kind of old debates in
philosophy of cognitive science between
internalist notions of cognition and
more embodied, embedded, extended and
we'll take more of a look at that in a
second. But the question here is what
are we committing ourselves to with
active inference? And I need to be a
little bit careful because I think that
people are going to disagree with this
to certain extents.
But I think we're certainly committing
ourselves to sensory motor in activism.
I think that's fairly uncontroversial.
And I would say as well that the
underpinning of active inference by the
free energy principle by my lights also
commits us or it certainly chimes very
deeply with the core tenets of
autopoetic inactivism. But I think
what's really interesting in trying to
understand cognition in the active
inference agent is to understand what
role, if any, there are for
representations. So if you
have any familiarity with the literature
on active inference, you'll know that
active inference people are always
banging on about models, prediction
errors, various other computationally
sounding things. And so the worry here
is at least for well, it's not
necessarily a worry, but the thought
would be are we committing ourselves to
a form of cognitivism? And again,
cognitivism is this it's generally
considered to be an old fashioned notion
of cognition as like computation over
symbolic representations in the brain
according to some syntactic set of rules
or something. And typically over the
last couple of decades in cognitive
science people have been moving away
from that view. So it would be
interesting if we were committing
ourselves to something that we'd already
moved away from and some people think
that we are making that commitment. So
Jakob Hohwy, for example, has argued in
various places that essentially
predictive processing or enactive
inference commits us to these very rich
reconstructive notions of
representation. And even Andy Clark,
Jakob Howie's foil in many places
has said himself that he thinks that
representations play a role here as
well. So in a talk in 2016, Clark said
it's internal representation. I think it
is. These are representation using
stories, but it's not internal
representation in quite the way that we
originally thought about it. So there's
some differences, perhaps major
differences between Howie and Clark
there, but others have pushed back. So
there's a paper by Maxwell Ramstead and
colleagues from 2020, I think it's the
tale of two densities paper where they
say that
a proper understanding of the generative
models in active inference suggests that
there's no role for representations. So
this is the kind of anti Howie view.
So I really like this paper from
Avel Constant and Andy Clark and Karl
Friston's which essentially tries to
broker some kind of peace in a debate
that in some form or another has been
raging for decades. So it'd be quite
nice to finally put this to bed.
So they argue that we can find, in the
formalisms of active inference, we can
find grounds for an armistice here.
So they argue that the formalisms of
active inference show that, quote
representational and non
representational cognitive processes can
be implemented by the brain under active
inference. And they do this by showing
that active inference accommodates a
dual architecture. So they show that on
the one hand, in some sense the
brain has to represent because under
active inference action selection
policies are happening over extended
timescales and so the agent has to
engage in some kind of counterfactual
thinking. So if I do X, what happens?
If I do, y what happens? And so on. And
the argument, very roughly speaking, is
that that is going to entail some kind
of representational, some use of
representations. But on the other hand,
they argue that what they call deontic
actions are processed through different
mappings in the generative model and
they're directly triggered by sensory
input. So a deontic action is an action
that is ingrained by our sense of the
expectations of others. So the example
that the authors use is stopping at some
red traffic lights in the middle of the
night when there's nobody else around.
So in a sense the claim is that through
a kind of social conditioning we know
what other people would expect us to do
in those circumstances and that allows
for this kind of dynamic reflexive
action policy setting.
And in those cases there's no room for
representative or there's no need for
representations there. I would
definitely suggest people interested in
this go and read this paper because you
might already have thought of some
potential objections here to the claim
that representations aren't needed for
deontic action and they do go into some
detail in talking about potential
objections there.
So that's the kind of status of the role
of representations. It's a live debate,
not everybody agrees. But it certainly
looks as though active inference has the
formal tools to accommodate both sides
of the debate. And it might turn out
that that's a good thing because we can
make everybody happy or it might turn
out to be a bad thing because you might
think, well, we've not really settled
anything one way or another. I wanted to
take some time, though, to mention
extended active inference. So I've been
talking about inactivism and I've
mentioned this debate between
cognitiveism and older ways of thinking
about sorry, cognitiveism and newer ways
of thinking about cognition as embodied
or embedded. And these are part of
what's known as the four E paradigm.
And clearly I think we are talking about
inactive cognition and you get embodied
and embedded kind of for free with this.
So the only one left on the table is the
extended mind. And this is just the
claim that under some conditions the
system that's realizing
cognitive processing can literally
extend outwards from the mind. So I'll
put some nice read ins for this up if
anybody's unfamiliar and interested.
But it's usually the most controversial
of the four E's. And Andy Clark,
who is one of the original authors of
the extended mind paper, really thinks
that active inference accommodates the
extended mind theory. And it's not just
that it accommodates it, but it actually
solves some old problems in the extended
mind about knowing how and why the brain
knows when and where to recruit certain
extra neural resources. And part of
the argument for this, what really sits
at the core is Clark develops this
argument based on the fact that the
generative models in active inference
are always in this, always making a
trade off between accuracy and
complexity. So you want your model of
the world to be accurate enough that you
can act effectively on the world, but
you also want to minimize the metabolic
costs of having models that are overly
complex. And so Clark utilizes this
insight to make the case that this
explains that in some cases as agents we
make use of these extra neural kind of
props and tools and things. And he says
that the imperative to reduce
uncertainty provides a location neutral
cost function that's always been missing
from the older arguments around extended
mind. So the upshot to
this, I think, is that you end up with a
view of agents as deeply coupled with
their environments. So under active
inference it's just nonsensical to try
and think about agents as decoupled from
their environment. The generative models
themselves are of the dynamics between
the agent and the environment. So these
two things can't be decoupled
perception, action loops. So remember I
said that perceptual and active
inference are essentially the same
thing. They're part of this circular
causality and they see the agent
constantly producing their own worlds.
They occupy the states that they're
expecting to through action.
And we might think, based on the
literature that I've gone through, that
there's some role here for
representations. So we're not committing
ourselves. The active inference agent
is not one that fits with very radical
interpretations of inactivism.
And active inference agents are porous.
They're open to recruiting external
material features of the environment to
reduce complexity and therefore minimize
the metabolic costs of realizing those
expected states.
Okay,
so that was a bit of active inference
set against the backdrop of some older
questions in philosophy of mind
theoretical cognitive science. But I'm
going to jump straight into agency and
motivation now because there's a lot to
get through here. I'm going to start
with a dark room problem. This is a
canonical philosophical worry in active
inference. So a lot of people, I think,
will be familiar with this. And in
really brief terms, it's really easy to
state. The challenge here is to say,
if it's all about minimizing prediction
error, why don't we just find the most
predictable environments possible and
stay there and live a nice error free
life? So Andy Clark paints a picture of
a dark room, and you can just be
strapped up to an intravenous drip,
feeding you the nutrients you need, and
you can just be really happy. But
clearly, we don't do that. Active
inference sorry. Agents in the world,
us, we generally typically sometimes we
do enjoy dark rooms, but most of the
time we don't for any extended period of
time. And so there's a challenge here
about how active inference can account
for what appear to be motivated agential
actions that necessarily mean we're
confronted with some degree of
uncertainty. And I'm going to set
active inference up in a kind of
dialectic with folk psychology here,
because folk psychology faces no such
concerns. So, to be very clear, folk
psychology is just the kind of
propositional linguistic framework that
the folk use to talk about and describe
motivated action. So it's a language we
typically use every day to describe the
reasons people are doing things. So folk
psychology has this belief, desire,
intention, schema, where, if I want to
explain, my friend going to grab a beer.
I would say, my friend believes there's
beer in the fridge. My friend desires
beer. And so those are combined to form
the intention to go and get beer. So
folk psychology doesn't have these kinds
of problems. So just
a little bit more on the dark room
problem and another whale. So the
dark room problem invites more than one
answer. We're going to see more than one
answer to it as we go along. One
response is to talk about what drives
curiosity and play and exploration, and
we are going to see more of that. But
the first response offered by Friston
Thornton and Clark is to highlight the
fact that organisms have basic needs to
eat, drink, and reproduce what you might
call evolutionarily ingrained needs,
and that those needs are going to
necessitate some form of exploratory
behavior. So staying in the dark room
will inevitably, under most
circumstances, going to lead to physical
dissipation.
So the question is, are these kinds of
appeals enough? And I
wanted to pull up a paper by Colin Klein
2018 that I think is like a really nice
articulation of these challenges.
Ultimately, I think he's wrong and it
falls flat, but I think it's a strong
articulation. So Klein argues that
predictions alone simply can't account
for the motivational character of these
needs. So Klein says, look, it's fine
that you've got these needs. Nobody's
going to deny that, but you just have
this one primitive to describe how
those needs motivate you, and prediction
is just not going to do it. So
prediction alone, as your sole primitive
is not going to be able it's like
predicting is not the same thing as
being motivated by something.
And Klein is really not happy with
appeals to these phenotypic needs.
And he construes these in the relevance
of the evolutionary history of the
organism and goes into a little bit of
detail. So he says, look, these
expectations are either going to be
about states, possible states, so the
state of being fed or clothed or warm,
or they're going to be about state
transitions, about what the appropriate
action is in one state to move to
another state. And he says expectations
about states themselves aren't going to
work because you have this problem of
accounting for novelty. So it might be
the case that in my evolutionary past,
all of my ancestors have had the same
expectations about which states they're
going to occupy. But there are lots of
states in my life that I could be
motivated to occupy that there's simply
no evolutionary history to account for.
And he says there's a very similar or
similarly difficult problem with state
transitions where essentially what we're
talking about with state transitions are
the most appropriate actions. So I have
expectations about the actions that are
going to fill foot that I need to take
under certain circumstances that are
going to get me to a particular expected
state. And Klein's worry is that there's
just going to be too many possible
actions in any given situation. So
there's just a kind of explosion
that's just going to be unaccountable
for. There's just going to be too many
different ways of getting to an expected
state that we won't be able to
account for in our past. So it's fairly
robust, thorough challenge built on the
dark room problem. And I think actually
it's a worry with two faces. So I think
the first is about how active inference
can describe agential behavior with its
austere, purely doxastic landscape. So
if you imagine somebody looking at their
house burning down, it seems like you
need more than beliefs to explain any
course of action they take. So there has
to be desire in there somewhere. So this
is an example Andy Clark uses in one of
his papers. And he know
the desire to run in and rescue some
item that you want from the house or the
desire to claim on the insurance is the
thing that's. Going to dictate how you
explain the person's behavior. So that's
the first problem. We need to look at
how folk psychology tessellates with
prediction. And the other problem is
maybe a little bit deeper, and that's to
ask, how does active inference actually
account for agential behavior? So can we
even tell some story using just
predictions and prediction error about
what really moves agents to act?
So firstly, thinking about folk
psychology, there's a couple of ways to
go here and I think ultimately we can
answer this worry. So Ryan Smith and
colleagues in 2022 in their paper
active inference models do not
contradict folk psychology. They argue
that the formalisms of active inference
can accommodate a belief desire
distinction. Now, I'll admit that it's a
very math heavy paper and it's a little
bit beyond my capabilities, but the
claim here is simply that there's no
contradiction. That actually the worry
that the important thing we have in folk
psychology is desire. And we're not
getting that in active inference. This
is just an unfounded worry. But there's
another strategy as well. So Joe
Dewhurst, in his 2017 paper, he employs
a different strategy and he says, look,
what are we even doing with folk
psychology? Let's not kind of be too
hasty and we need to think about what
are we doing when we talk about these
propositional kind of states.
So he says the first option is to say,
well, we're just being realists here.
So when I say that X desires Y, I'm
actually positing the real existence as
a fine grained mental state in X's head.
And he thinks that this is actually the
wrong way to think about things. He
thinks that folk psychology actually
it's an instrumentalist tool. It's a
kind of framework that we use just for
picking out coarse grained behavioral
patterns in some useful way. So if we
agree with Duhurst here and we just
become instrumentalists about folk
psychology again, it looks as though
there's different we're not forced to
kind of worry that there's some kind of
empirical problem here where the
mechanisms of enactive inference are in
some sense incommensurable with real
properties that we're positing the
existence of. Because we're just going
to say that those things don't really
exist in the way that we've typically
assumed that they might. So either
way, whichever route you go down here,
it looks like active inference agents
have beliefs and that we're going to be
fine in describing motivated action.
So what about the second problem?
So Andy Clark in 2020 authored a direct
response decline. So Clark wants
to argue that actually using predictions
and prediction errors and precision
weighting, which I'll explain in a
second, we can get a picture of agential
action.
So the first thing Clark does is to
outline the fact that under active
inference we have a very nice, well worn
account of embodied action. So, in other
words, what it takes to actually move
the body to perform different actions is
perfectly folded into active inference
under the same kind of computational
flow of prediction error minimization.
Just in a nutshell, for me to move my
arm, what I'm doing is making a
prediction that my arm is in someplace
and then minimizing the prediction
error. So once that's on
the table, Clark says, OK, that's fine,
we have this account of action, but
that's not really what Klein means. So
the move Clark makes is to appeal to the
hierarchical nested structure of the
generative model and to say that higher
level beliefs, which are about
temporarily extended future states,
these are going to perform a really
important role as a kind of controller
for lower level actions. So the idea is
that if I have a high level,
temporarily extended expectation to
attain a PhD, what happens is that high
level belief becomes unpacked at lower
levels in the hierarchy, and what you
get are more fine grained, faster action
policies that the system expects to help
support that higher level expectation.
And there's a mechanism in play here
called precision weighting, which
applies to prediction error signals,
because obviously not
all of the predictions we make about the
environment are going to be equally
important. We're not going to have equal
confidence in all of our actions to
bring about an expected state. And so
what precision weighting does is
essentially communicate how much
confidence we have in a particular
action policy to move us into that
expected state under perceptual
inference. Precision weighting just
signals how newsworthy prediction errors
are, so how important they are for the
system. So precision weighting drives
attention, for example, when we're
talking about predictive processing.
But in this case, Clark's claim is that
when you have this kind of nested
hierarchy of expectations, so you have
temporarily extended expectations at the
high level, unpacked into a kind of web
of lower level action policies. And
precision waiting is kind of modulating
the system's expectations about which of
those policies are most likely to bring
about the expected states. You get
something that looks a lot like
motivated directed action. And agency
is kind of inherent in this model
because the system rather
has to model itself as a cause of
those expected states. So if I have
these high level expectations, I, in a
very inherent way, have to model my own
causal efficacy to bring about those
states. So on a very low level, the
system has to model some form of agent
because I can be the cause of change to
my own sensory states, so I can cover my
own eyes and so on and so forth. So kind
of on this view, agency is a
latent variable in these systems when
it's making these predictions, so it
just kind of turns up. And Clark
argues that you essentially end up with
something that looks very much like
agents under folk psychology. But he
thinks this is a better view because we
end up with a, quote, different and
arguably much more unified internal
architecture trading in a single
currency. So Clark thinks, look, okay,
Klein's worry is we have this one
primitive. We have just prediction. And
the concern is that we're not going to
be able to explain agential action. But
actually there are ways that we can
appeal to the hierarchical structure of
the model and precision weighting. And
it turns out that this is a much more
elegant picture as well. But Klein
might press the worry, and anybody
listening might kind of think, well,
we've kind of done some work there, but
why do we expect the things that we
expect in the first place? So why
is my long term expectation to attain a
PhD and not to join the French Foreign
Legion, for example? What means that I
expect one thing rather than another?
And here Clark just bites a bullet and
says, nobody can explain that. We've
kind of shifted to talking about
questions, know, spookier questions
about free will. And Clark says, look,
if this is what you want, if this is
what you're demanding, then you have to
recognize that simply appealing to folks
psychology doesn't get you that,
know, people with these kinds
of worries need to be careful in how
much they demand from the active
inference agent. And I think the real
answer to that question actually, this
is more speculative, but the real answer
to a deeper answer to these kinds of
questions will lie in the kinds of
things that we're going to look at in
subsequent weeks. So, for example, the
reason I have the expectation to attain
a PhD rather than join the French
Foreign Legion is because I exist in a
particular kind of sociocultural
landscape with specific norms, and a lot
of my actions and beliefs are tempered
and shaped by the expectations of people
around me. So this is
just an overview. We went over the dark
room problem. Why do we do anything at
all if it's all about certainty and
prediction error minimization this
worry? I said you can kind of highlight
two aspects of this worry. One is an
actual account of agency under active
inference, which we have. We have this
Andy Clark model of agency to do with
hierarchical nested, unfolding action
policies over time and different
precision mappings. And then we have
this worry about the relationship with
folk psychology. So how do we describe
agential behavior and motivated
behavior? How do we describe the
behavior of agents if we only have
recourse to prediction?
And as we saw, there's one
argument here is that actually active
inference, the formalisms can
accommodate this belief desire
distinction. And the other move that I
really like is to just say, look, folk
psychology is just this instrumental
tool. It is, in effect, it's part of the
sociocultural landscape that we use to
shape each other's expectations by
putting these labels to explain our
actions. This kind of form of active
inference itself. So there's this kind
of philosophically interesting debate
about folk psychology, but it
turns out that everything's okay and
active inference agents are in fact
agents with beliefs, desires and hopes
and dreams and so on.
Okay? That's agency. We're making
good time.
Okay. So in this section I'm going to
introduce quite a lot of stuff,
but it's going to be all tied together
hopefully rather neatly in the case
study. At the end, I'm going to talk
about allostatis and emotion. I'm going
to say very briefly a little bit about
the self as well.
Here's some examples of some of the core
readings I've used. Again, these are all
going to be up in the document as well,
which will be made available. And I
thoroughly advise you to just have a
browse through these. There's some
really interesting stuff there. I'm not
going to talk about psychedelics or
meditation or depersonalization, but
there is some really cool active
inference literature on those topics as
well, particularly papers on
psychedelics and ego dissolution by
George Dean. A new paper just came out
by inezito Jonas Mago
and Robert Carhartt harris and I think
Fernando Rosas as well. I think I might
be mistaken on the authors there, but
it's a very new paper. Okay?
So the thing that is going to underpin a
lot of what I'm now going to go on to
say is going to be this notion of
allostatis. And this
plays a major role in a lot of work
on emotion and the self in active
inference. Lisa Feldman Barrett, whose
theory of emotion we're going to look at
in a second, has argued that the brain's
fundamental purpose, what it evolved to
do through that imperative to minimize
prediction error, is to manage the
body's metabolic budget. So the first
prior is kind of our most expected
state. The first prior in the sense of
our strongest prior probability, our
highest expectation is to have good
allostatic control. But I'm getting
ahead of myself there. All that means is
that we're balancing our body's
metabolic budget, our energy budget, in
an effective way. So error
signals, like I said before, that are
highly precise are those that are
weighted very highly. So prediction
error signals that have high precision
weighting are the synaptic gain on those
error signals is going to be increased
and that's going to drive learning,
which means in future our expectations
around those kinds of error signals is
going to be we're going to pay more
attention to those. And the most
highly weighted error signals that we're
going to get are to do with our own
homeostatic set points within our own
body. So if my temperature
started to rise rapidly, my body
temperature started to rise or drop
rapidly, that prediction error signal,
the violation of those expectations is
really going to grab my attention and
I'm going to do something about it. And
one way that we maintain these
homeostatic states is through the body's
own autonomic reactions. So were I to
start getting very cold, I would
probably start to shiver. And so the
body is trying to kind of rectify those
deviations from homeostatic set points.
But another thing that organisms engage
in, and humans do this to really
remarkable degrees. And again, this is
going to be something that I suspect is
going to come out in the subsequent
weeks, is that we engage in quite
complex and sophisticated anticipatory
actions to maintain homeostasis.
And this is something called allostasis.
So allostatic control, which I mentioned
earlier as this first prior,
is essentially the regulation of
homeostasis through action. So it's
actions that I can take to ensure that
I stay within those important bounds.
So shivering is good, but living
in a house with central heating is
better. Having a warm bed and
living in a community where we've had
these people of kind of engineers have
worked to create a kind of material
environment that acts as a kind of
background support to a lot of these
needs. Something that's another
important concept here is allostatic
load. So this is essentially the result
of not having good allostatic control.
So again, allostatic control is just
engaging effectively in actions that are
maintaining those set points, whereas
allostatic load is the physiological
costs to the agent of losing that
control. So there's so many studies
here that have just shown the immense
physiological costs of operating beyond
those set points and not having good
control. So allostatis load has been
linked with reduced cardiac health,
sleep problems, gut issues,
mental health issues, depression,
basically everything. It's really bad
and so good allostatic control is very
important and as we're going to see, it
underpins quite a few very important
things.
So really we could
dedicate a whole hour to looking at
emotion, but I'm going to blast through
it very quickly right now. And this
slide, I should say one of the core
readings on the document and the reading
that I'm basing this on is Lisa Feldman
Barrett's 2017 paper, the Theory of
Constructed Emotion.
The main idea here is this is one of
those theories that on the face of it,
it seems quite simple, but actually
there's quite a lot of subtlety and
nuance to it. Allostatis control
means inferring the causes of changes to
the body's internal state. So in other
words, if I want to keep good allostatic
control, I need to know not just what's
going on out there, but I need to know
what's going on inside me as well.
Okay? So if there's some crucial change
happening, I need to be on top of it.
And this happens through exactly the
same process as the same enactive,
error, minimization process that I'm
engaging with with the outside world.
So the brain is making predictions about
its own internal states and then it's
going to engage in some kind of action
to minimize any prediction errors. And
these prediction errors are going to be
very highly weighted. They're very
important. But here's an interesting
thing. So there was a very unethical
experiment done by Shaktor and Singer,
I think in the 60s, who they were
emotion researchers and they conducted
an experiment where they injected
subjects without the subject's
knowledge. I think they injected them
with adrenaline and then they exposed
the subjects to different stimuli.
So some subjects were exposed to one
type of stimulus and some subjects were
exposed to another. And even though the
subjects had essentially been they'd
been pushed to have the same, to
experience the same physiological
changes in their body, they reported
different emotional like different kinds
of feelings depending on the stimulus
that they'd been exposed to. So this
highlights something really important.
And again, I feel compelled to say that
I am moving through this incredibly
quickly. There's so much to say here.
But the nub of it is this in
order to keep good allostatic control,
in order to know what to do, the brain
needs to contextualize those changes in
the body because there's not a one to
one mapping between changes in the body
and an external stimulus. So sometimes
changes, physiological changes in our
body are about something in the world,
they're a response to something. And
it's very, very important that the brain
is kind of taking a confluence of those
inputs to try and contextualize, okay,
what's actually happening and what do I
need to do? So an example of this is if
you imagine running into a bear while
you're hiking in Wyoming, which is
something that's actually happened to
me, I've experienced it, it's
terrifying. And you imagine going on a
scary or a date that you're really
nervous about. The physiological
changes that are happening in the body
are, give or take, more or less the
same. So perspiration, elevated heart
rate, breathing changes.
So the underlying physiological
footprint is very similar. But what you
need to do to manage that situation,
that apt action is very, very different.
And so the claim here, the kind of
revolutionary claim in a way is that
emotions, the things we experience
subjectively are constructions, just
like percepts are. So just like my
experience of the car when I step
outside my flat is a construction that
explains away the prediction error and
gives me a cleaned up picture of the
world. Emotions are essentially doing
the same thing. They're explaining away
these prediction errors and telling me
this is the best explanation of these
changes within your body contextualized
against this external stimulus. So in
the case of the date, apt action is to
chill out and be normal to a certain
extent. And in the case of the bear,
you get the hell out of that. Although
interestingly, you don't. Running away
from a bear is a terrible idea. You
should not turn your back and run away
but you get the idea that it's going to
be what you should do in each situation
is completely different.
So that's emotion for the active
inference agent and something I
don't want to lose here is what you get
with this is really kind of cool because
it turns out emotions and subject we're
kind of moving into subjectivity here.
It turns out emotions are really they're
just part of the same cognitive
architecture. So there's no difference
here. There's no dualism between here's
thinking and here's emotion. And emotion
is this kind of fuzzy stuff that we're
not really interested in. Actually
emotion, subjective embodied feeling is
core. It's absolutely vital to
understanding how we maintain this
allostatic control and how we engage in
adaptive behaviors and how we remain
gripped to our affordances in the
environment. And the notion of grip is
going to be something that comes up
again very soon.
So very briefly, because this is
something that I've really already
talked about, but I want to put a
slightly different spin on it right now.
I've already said that allostatic
control for humans can involve very
temporarily extended scales. And we saw
this with Andy's model of agency. So if
you think about something like saving
into a retirement fund, for example,
we're doing something that the idea is
that maybe decades from now is going to
kind of minor spikes in prediction error
or the disappointment of not having as
much money right now is going to pay off
later. These are the kind of things that
humans engage in. And our generative
models have to be temporally thick. So
George Ben white that the levels of
temporal extension are hierarchically
interlocked. So shorter scales inform
expectations of what the agent can do
over longer scales. So these different
levels of the hierarchy are in a kind of
dialogue with each other telling you
what kinds of things are possible and
what kinds of things you should expect.
And when we were talking about agency,
we talked about the way that agency is
kind of baked into active inference.
Because in order for any of this to
work, the system has to have as a
hypothesis, I can do things okay?
And this is more or less taken to
be the same thing that underpins
the sense of self under active
inference. So the system implicitly
infers its own ability to bring about
intended sensory consequences. And so
Dean writes here, quote in Pristine it
is in this sense that implicit
in a model of sampling is a
representation or sense of agency.
So a minimal sense of self,
it's kind of like the flip side of
agency comes baked in here. So one
has to model oneself as
a potential cause of sensory inputs.
So George Dean and colleagues, I think
George Deane, Mark Miller and Sam
Wilkinson propose a model of the self
under active inference called the
allostatic control model.
And the move they make here is that we
have to recognize that it's not just our
self efficacy that has to be modeled.
We also have to have some kind of idea
in there of how we're actually doing.
So we have to model our own capabilities
in order to set precision weighting on
future action. So we don't simply infer
that we can be the cause of sensory
states, but also infer our own
capabilities to successfully bring about
expected states at longer timescales.
So the phrasing that they use is
tracking the performance or fitness of
the model over time. So part
of that tracking is going to be
affective and emotional. And so there
are strong links. We're kind of really
digging our hooks into subjectivity at
this point.
But the claim with the Allostatic
Control model is you get this rather
than just a minimal self, you actually
get a longer term phenomenological self
emerge from these interlocking
timescales, which are modeling not only
the agent's own causal efficacy, but
also modeling how good your own model is
at doing what you need it to do. And
like I said, I said when I was talking
about the reading and I want to flag
this again because I'm really not doing
justice to this in the way that I
should. But this has formed the basis
for a lot of really interesting work on
phenomena like depersonalization on the
role of psychedelics and the potential
for psychedelics in therapy and in
meditation, ego dissolution and kind of
that kind of stuff in meditative
settings. So anybody with any interest
in the self or in those kinds of
practices should definitely go and give
a closer look to these readings that
I'll make sure in a document.
Okay, so quick overview here. So active
inference agents maintain homeostasis
through anticipatory action, and this is
something we call Allostatic Control.
To do this, the system must engage in
interceptive prediction over its own
internal states. And actually, I think
I've got time to do this, so I'll just
deviate slightly. The topic of
interceptive inference is really
interesting in the context of active
inference. So I want to flag work by
Sarah Garfinkel, who I believe is at
UCL, who used to be at Sussex. And
Professor Garfinkel's work looks at the
central importance of interceptive
predictions in various psychopathologies
especially, I think she's looked very
closely at PTSD and anxiety disorders.
And it turns out that an
agent's accuracy in their interoceptive
predictions is a good indicator as to
the kinds of symptoms that they're going
to like, the strength and severity of
their symptoms in these kinds of
disorders. And what she's shown is that
if you can increase the accuracy of
interceptive predictions, this forms the
basis of treatment for these symptoms.
So in short, the better you are at
interceptive predicting. I think one of
the measures that they use there in
herlab is how well people can track
their own heartbeats without feeling
their pulse. So if you just sit there
and try and say like, my heart's
beating like this, then the more
accurate you are and the more any
training you can be given to be more
accurate. It forms the basis of
effective treatments for these kinds of
symptoms. So I just wanted to flag that
because the world of research in
enactive inference large,
diverse, vibrant, super interesting and
very much worth our time. Okay,
where was I? Here. Okay. So to maintain
allostatis control, the system has to
engage in interceptive prediction over
its internal states. And then to best
explain changes in those internal
states, the system has to contextualize
those changes against some extraceptive
input and that emotion categories serve
that role. So just to be very clear, on
this view, emotions are constructions.
There are some important deviations from
other theories of emotion here,
particularly what Barrett calls the
basic theory of emotion. So on her
view, emotions themselves have no
underlying kind of essence or neural
footprint. And there's an ongoing live
debate there as well between these
theories.
And also just at the end,
the good allostatic control in human
agents is this very temporally thick
phenomena. So we engage in very long
term planning that involves a lot of the
kinds of counterfactual representations
that we talked about with the Axel
Constant paper. And this is hypothesized
to form the basis of our
phenomenological sense of so,
okay, we're up to an hour. Good. We're
running on time. This is the final
section and it's probably going to be
probably going to be the longest
section. What I want to do here is I
want to try and pull together some of
the things I've been talking about
because it's been very fast and very
abstract and I want to try and pull some
of these things together in a slightly
more concrete example. So the case study
I'm going to use is addiction. So
there's a particular account of
addiction in the predictive process in
literature that I think in a very
succinct, sharp way highlights a lot
of the things I've been talking about
and puts them within a context that is
quite stark and easy to understand.
But in order to do that, I'm going to
have to introduce a new,
slightly more difficult to understand
mechanism within the framework that
crops up in a lot of the predictive
processing literature. And what this is
going to do, hopefully as well, is give
us a direct bridge to phenomenology.
So when we talk about things like
neurocomputational phenomenology,
the things I'm going to be talking about
here have underpinned a lot of the work
in that area. So these are some of the
readings we're going to look at some
work by mostly a lot of the
papers. We're going to look at first
author, Mark Miller, or Mark Miller's
been second or third author. And I bring
that up because in the discussion
section on the 25th, when we have an
hour to kind of unpack and answer
people's questions, we're actually going
to be joined by Mark Miller. So if
anybody has any specific questions about
the things I'm going to talk about. Now
in this section, he's going to be the
man to answer those,
but also I'm going to put a lot of
secondary readings up again in the
document so you'd be able to find them
all there. Okay?
So let's suppose switch gears
slightly. I want to
keep the focus on feelings,
although what I'm going to be talking
about here are not what might be called
like full blooded emotion states. But I
want to talk about something a little
bit more subtle. So one thing that might
seem really obvious, kind of so obvious
that we often overlook it when things
are going okay, is that it generally
feels like something to be an agent. So
when we're going about whatever business
we have in the world, we always
feel like something, and it's not
entirely clear how best to characterize
that. So I want to draw on some work in
phenomenology that some active inference
theorists have also drawn on and made
use of. Because I think this is a really
good grounding for some of the things
I'm going to go on to say. Certainly
proved to be a good grounding for some
of the work that I'm going to highlight.
So these are two books by Matthew
Ratcliffe, who I think is at the
University of York and has done really
cool work in kind of really getting to
grips with the what it's likeness to
live in certain conditions. And
Ratcliffe, he argues that he's
identified this certain area, this space
of feelings that have been largely
neglected in the wider literature, and
he describes these as existential
feelings. So he says existential
feelings are, quote, they are not
intentional states directed at however
many objects, and they are not feelings
of the body or some part of it.
Instead, they amount to a felt sense of
belonging in the world. So the main
difference between a full blooded
emotion state and an existential feeling
is that the emotion state is about
something. Okay? So if I'm disgusted,
I'm typically all the time I'm disgusted
about something in the world. So
emotions are intentional in that way.
Radcliffe elaborates on existential
feelings by I'm going to quote this at
length because I quite like it. He says
people sometimes talk of feeling alive,
dead, distant, detached, dislodged,
estranged, isolated, otherworldly,
indifferent to everything, overwhelmed,
suffocated, cut off, lost,
disconnected, out of sorts, not oneself,
out of touch with things, out of it,
not quite with it, separate, in harmony
with things, at peace with things.
There are reference to feelings of
unreality, heightened existence,
surreality, familiarity,
unfamiliarity, strangeness, isolation,
emptiness, belonging, being at home in
the world, being at one with things,
significance, insignificance, and the
list goes on. So this
is really cool work, and I recommend
everybody to go and read Matthew
Ratcliffe. But some of the work I really
like in Predictive Processing and Active
Inference has taken this idea of. An
existential feeling. And what they've
recognized is that these kinds of
feelings are really about how we are
orientated in regards to the world and
the affordances in it. So they're
background bodily states of action
readiness. So how are we relating to
how do we find ourselves in relation to
the world? So we're talking about the
general structuring that's present in
our everyday phenomenology. So I really
want to make that clear that what this
work is doing is building a bridge
between computational models and
the way even the underpinnings of those
models in neurobiology and
phenomenological experience.
So the thing that I need to introduce,
and this can be, it's fairly
straightforward, but it can be a little
bit tricky at times, is this notion
error dynamics. This is really
important. So like I just said,
aerodynamics is going to provide this
conceptual bridge between different
levels of analysis and it elaborates on
how systems are sensitive to the success
or failure of their own action policies
unfolding across multiple timescales.
So the recognition here is that we talk
a lot about action policies and expected
states, but the reality is that we have
a multitude of goals and action policies
and expected states that are
interlocking, overlapping, constantly
shifting. The picture is messy. And so I
like this quote from the 2019 paper
that says the roller coaster of
continual increases and decreases of
errors that accompany life become
expected and are folded into our
expectations. For such a system it
becomes important not only to track the
constantly fluctuating instantaneous
errors, but also to pay attention to the
dynamics of error reduction over longer
timescales. So the systems, the upshot
of this is that these authors believe,
building on some other work in
computational modeling, that systems
must track the rate of change in overall
error reduction relative to the system's
expectations. So this is the kind of
global upwards or downwards trend in
prediction error. That's what the system
is sensitive to, how that relates to the
expectations.
So the idea here is that aerodynamics
provide a system with a much broader
ongoing sense of how they're doing to
their multitude of goals over time.
So a big step here is that
those changes in the rate of reduction
feed back into the system. So they're
folded back within the system and they
serve the role of modulating precision
on action policies. So let's say I'm
engaged in some task. I have a
particular expectation about how I'm
going to do at that task. And when I
actually engage with the task, I do
slightly worse than expected. The idea
there is that that rate of change,
so the rate of error reduction is going
to decrease until I'm reducing error
worse than my expectations. And in a
typical healthily functioning system,
that rate of change, the sensitivity to
that rate of change is going to feed
back and reset the precision weighting
on those actions. So it's going to
reduce my confidence in that particular
action policy such that I might try a
different strategy, I might try a
different tactic, or I might just throw
whatever it is that I'm doing away and
go and do something else. So we're
starting to see this picture of through
expectations, sensitivity to change and
feedback onto precision waiting. It's
starting to dictate how I manage my
action policies. So there's this ongoing
reciprocal relationship between
aerodynamics and my future expectations.
Now, crucially, the claim here is that
on the subject level, all of this
manifests as these existential feelings
of some kind. So the way that I feel on
a kind of day to day basis is a
reflection of how I'm doing in terms of
these sensitivity to aerodynamics. So
when I fail at the task and precision
weighting is down regulated on that
particular action policy, the thing that
actually kind of oomph that moves me
to go and do something else are my
embodied feelings of frustration that I
experience. So as conscious agents,
those embodied feelings are what are
tuning us towards acting more
effectively. So optimal behavior
on this account is characterized as a
feeling of grip towards a shifting field
of affordances. So I'm going to unpack
this quickly. But the feeling of grip in
a nutshell is just this feeling that
we're engaging with our affordances in
the best way that we can and that we're
either meeting or exceeding our
expectations for prediction, error,
minimization what they mean by a field
of affordances. And this is again really
important. A landscape of affordances is
just the total opportunities in my
niche. So my landscape of affordances
right now is Brighton. It's not really
going to change very quickly unless I
get on a plane and fly somewhere else.
But affordances aren't neutral in that
way. They don't just exist there.
The affordances that stand out to me as
relevant or attractive is going to
change quite rapidly depending on what
it is I'm doing, on my internal state,
on the context and so on. So right now
my water bottle stands out as
attractive, a couple of keys on my
keyboard stand out as attractive. But
that's going to shift quite rapidly once
this lecture is over and I turn to do
something else. So the idea of grip is
that we exhibit a stability in
our attunement such that we can remain
attuned as that field changes. And this
is part of the skilled intentionality
framework which I won't get into because
I don't want theoretical overload, but
I've put some papers up on this slide as
references and of course the reading
will be in the document. But skilled
intentionality refers to the enactive,
openness and responsiveness to multiple
relevant affordances in a concrete
situation. So it's just this recognition
that things change quickly for multiple
reasons and we really need to exhibit a
kind of flexibility and stability in
those engagements. And aerodynamics
has been applied in lots of very, very
cool ways. I can't recommend this work
highly enough. So aerodynamics, I won't
run through how everything has been
explained just for time reasons, but you
can kind of take a look at this
yourself. But aerodynamics has been
proposed as a more complete answer to
the dark room problem that we were
talking about earlier, because it can
explain the drive for exploration and
curiosity, because it literally feels
good to minimize prediction errors
better than expected. So again, that
rate of change manifests as embodied
feeling. So we're always looking for
opportunities to do better than
expected. And kind of this has been
suggested to account for feelings of
boredom, prompting us to go out and find
new things to do. And similarly,
aerodynamics has provided a
computational account of play, which for
a while has remained a kind of mystery
because it's on the face of it like,
why would we engage in play when it's
metabolically costly and we need that
energy for other things? Like Lisa
Feldman, barrett says managing energy is
super important. So why do baby animals
burn? It all engaging in playful
behavior. Aerodynamics has a story for
us there. And there are also
aerodynamics based accounts of happiness
and wellbeing and depression as well.
So I won't go into the details there.
But it turns out that aerodynamics and
this connection to phenomenology is this
super malleable, flexible kind of
feature of the framework that really
underpins a lot of what we experience
and do as active inference agents.
Okay,
so I'm going to talk a little bit about
addiction. Got some time
here. Things are going well,
so I take so
I had some options here because I wanted
to use a case study that really brought
out some of the things I was talking
about. And as I've just said,
aerodynamics has been applied in a bunch
of different areas and it's all very
much worth talking about. But I chose
addiction because,
well, as you'll see, as I kind of make
clear, I think it also brings out not
just the way that all of this fits
together, but also why it's good and why
seeing people as active inference agents
and broader structures as active
inference structures is actually a
worthwhile thing to do. So addiction
was once viewed as a moral failing. So
the kind of Victorian addict is too
rotten to make the right choice, too
self indulgent. I say Victorian unless
you're Peter Hitchens and then you still
subscribe to this view. But that's the
old fashioned view. There was something
wrong with the addict, some moral or
spiritual failing, and gradually that
changed to what the dominant view is
today, which is the disease model. And
the idea here is that addiction is a
disease and that disease is
characterized by changes in the brain,
which changes to brain structures,
which mean the addict can't help but
act in a certain way when confronted
with a certain stimulus. So it's this
loss of control that's engendered
through these brain structures. And this
is the idea of it being a disease.
The work that I'm going to describe now,
I won't go into too much detail here,
but it's kind of founded on this thought
that this disease model, it can't be
quite right because these changes in
brain structure, essentially that's what
the brain does. It's just learning.
This is what we do all the time.
Essentially, me completing my PhD is a
process of me undergoing changes to my
brain such that I'm kind of
disposed to act in certain ways.
I think it's mark Lewis in his book 2018
The Biology of Desire, argues,
look, addiction is more of just a
dysfunction in learning. It's not really
a disease. So we need to think about it
a little bit differently. And this work
by Miller and colleagues, 2020,
that's where it picks up. Okay? So the
idea is that those brain changes
engendered through exposure to a
stimulus. In this case we're going to
talk about a drug. We're going to leave
behavioral addiction aside for a second
that clearly plays a critical role. So
nobody's going to deny the kind
of chemical, the importance of the
biology here that's going on in the
brain. And of course, different drugs
have different chemical profiles in that
regard. But on this view we're going to
kind of shift focus from that slightly
and we're going to have a much more
active picture where we view addiction
as a self organizing process of whole
agent environment systems. Okay, so I
have this extract here it is in the
dynamic interaction between the agent
and its environment that addiction is
born and endures. So the harm of
addiction emerges from a breakdown in
the broader stable dynamics that
typically underpin a flourishing life
work, family, friends, health, and so
on. So a typically flourishing life has
a broad kind of bush of concerns over
different timescales in different areas.
And what we're going to see is that the
harm of addiction is in a narrowing of
those concerns.
So what happens is when somebody takes
a drug to some people who are exposed to
drugs, that drug is going to, through
direct action on some neural mechanisms,
is going to signal to the agent that
they've done better than expected at
reducing prediction error. Of course
this is a losery. They haven't really
done better than expected in anything
that matters. But the signal they get
is, wow, like we have just reduced
prediction error at this insane rate and
repeated use through this aerodynamics
mechanism, repeated use is going to tune
our expectations about the kinds of
prediction error slopes, the kind of
slopes of prediction error that are
available to us in the environment. And
we're going to start to expect those
vertiginous slopes of error reduction if
we continue to engage with the drug.
And once those expectations become
deeply ingrained, anything else we do is
going to start to feel like failure.
Okay? So if I get used to taking cocaine
all the time and then I have to sit
through a family meal where I don't have
any drugs and I have to kind of sit
still and there's no dopamine available,
I don't have my phone. I'm going to
experience that as feelings of
frustration and as if I'm being
prevented from doing something I want to
do. And I'm going to experience that as
doing worse than expected. So I've
learnt these expectations for prediction
error minimization and I'm not getting
them unless I engage with the drug. And
of course it's worth noting that in many
cases these drugs are going to have
chemical withdrawal effects that
compound that as well, especially things
like nicotine. And alcohol in particular
is very nasty. So alcohol can kill you
if you try and withdraw from it too
quickly. So they really do pull the
agent into a grip. So what happens here
is the agent develops a kind of
suboptimal grip. So you start to enact
a new world, a new identity. So instead
of doing all the things you once cared
about, like different hobbies, you start
to hang out with different people, you
start to frequent different places like
a dealer's house or wherever, and very
slowly you start to carve out
essentially a niche. The addict enacts a
particular niche through their actions
and they have quite a good grip on that
niche. It's just that it doesn't speak
to a broader array of concerns.
So what's really important
is that this pushes back against
the disease model because on this view,
the active inference agent, well, the
system is doing essentially what it was
evolved to do. So there's another
quote from the paper here that I like
that says their habits allow them to
remain well attuned and keep prediction
errors under tight control so long as
they remain within the narrow confines
of such a that. And this is
important because it shows that
allostatic control and prediction error
minimization are not the same thing.
They come apart. And this really speaks
to a question that was asked after
Avel's session recently about what does
prediction error actually look like?
Well, in this case you have a system
that has learned that engagement with
certain affordances gives it's an
illusion, but it has this feedback that
says this is the state you expect to
occupy, or this is the state that the
agent has learned to expect to occupy.
And it's carved out a niche of
affordances that means it's very likely
to occupy that state. So it actually has
a really good grip on the situation.
It's just that that niche is
very narrow and it's constricted,
meaning it's simply those
habits and that web of habitual action
policies are just not well suited to
maintain good allostatic control.
So everything else in the addict's life
starts to suffer. So we can kind of
think of this as a form of niche
construction gone wrong. And I think
we're going to look at niche
construction in the coming weeks as
well. So why is this whole agent
well, so I should say just to back up a
second. So what I like about this
account of addiction is that it's
thoroughly an enactive account of
addiction. It really brings out the kind
of inactive core of active inference.
So the addict is addiction becomes
an identity. It becomes a world that the
person actually produces through their
actions. So rather than the disease
model where you have a person and a
stimulus and exposure, whenever they're
exposed to that stimulus, they're going
to have problems because of these brain
changes. What this does justice to is
actually the activity of the agent. So
they're not accidentally bumping into
this stimulus in the environment and
they're not just seeking it out, but
they're deliberately restructuring their
environment to make this state more and
more likely over time. So it really does
justice to the efficacy and the agency
of the agent rather than giving that
agency a more backseat role that it
takes in the disease model. But the
other thing that it does, because it's
this inactive picture, is that it also
does justice to the environmental
features. So it
kind of speaks to the fact that
addiction is not just all in the head.
Actually, some of the problems
of addiction come with the fact that it
is this procedural,
constructive process. And one of my
favorite experiments of all time is I
don't know if people are familiar with
the Rat City experiments. This is why
I've got the image up here. And this was
a very cool experiment where originally
it was found that if you exposed rats to
a drug laced stimulus in the
environment, I think it was heroin
laced water or it might have been
cocaine. But the original experiments
found that nearly all the rats would
kill themselves with the drug, so they
would just keep at the drug until
they died. And it was a very high
percentage of the rats would engage in
that destructive behavior until the
experiments were rerun sometime later.
And instead of having the rat just in a
boring cage on its own, it had the rats
in Rat Park, which was a very social,
exciting, brightly colored environment
with lots of different affordances. And
what they found was that given the same
choice, a vastly reduced proportion of
the rats would choose to engage with the
drug. Okay, so it's capturing the
importance of niche construction that I
think is really nice here. And it also
speaks to the role played by embodied
affect in phenomenology. There's
something that it's like to be an addict
and that really matters. It really
matters that the addict has these
embodied experiences when they're
engaging with particular sets of
affordances.
So that's really summed up in the
overview that I've put here. So these
were the things that I wanted to
emphasize. Active inference agents are
embodied. They're embedded in a
landscape. That landscape is constituted
by particular affordances. And we can
distinguish between a landscape of
affordances and a field of affordances.
And that distinction really speaks to
the inherent affectivity and normativity
of affordances, which affordances stand
out to us at a particular time, which
exert a pull over us and enactive
inference. Agents enact their worlds
through action. And this is nowhere
starker than in the case of addiction.
Active inference agents are effective.
So emotion plays this super crucial
role, keeping us tuned, keeping us
in that grip with our affordances, and
helping us contextualize those important
physiological changes. Active inference
agents are agents, okay? So we do have
a way to describe behavior as agential
and motivated, and we do have these
cognitive architectures that can make
sense of agential action. And active
inference agents have this inbuilt sense
of self that comes with agency as well.
So that's pretty much it. This final
slide just goes over some of the things
that we can expect. So what I've done
today, I hope, has laid a good
groundwork and has installed some higher
level expectations to learn more about
active inference. And what we're going
to do in the subsequent weeks is now
scale this up to see how, when you have
more than one active inference agent
together, how the expectations of some
can impact the expectations of others
and individuals. And I look forward to
learning more about that. But as for me,
that's it.
Amazing. Ben, awesome work. What can
people look forward to next week or in
two weeks if they join the discussions
section? Like, what's it going to be
like? Or who would you encourage to
join? Definitely, I mean, the more
people that come along, I think the
better it's going to be. I'm really
looking forward to it. I'm kind of just
in the first place, intrigued to see we
covered so much ground. I'm just
interested to see where people want to
go with this and see where people's
interests lie. I assume that people
are going to have questions, and I think
maybe the best way to do it would be to
explore some of people's questions
during the discussion. We can use them
to kick things off and keep things
going, but I think it's likely that
we have a whole hour, so we've certainly
got time to really dig into things in
some detail. And like I said before,
we're going to have Mark Miller with us.
And Mark is just awesome in discussion.
It's very, very passionate and
enthusiastic about his work, and he can
do a much better job than I can in
explaining it. So just to have the
opportunity to speak with Mark about his
work, I would say definitely come along.
All right. Anything else? Otherwise,
again, awesome job. No, I think that's
it. Thanks for listening, I guess.
Well, thanks. It was a pleasure. It was
ambitious. To what you did elegantly
with no equations or getting snagged
on any of the potentially infinite
philosophical and technical and
normative and all these different layers
of challenge and divergence. So to
really cut a path there is great. Yeah.
I think it just speaks to there's so
much good philosophical work in these
areas in enactive inference and
predictive processing. And I should say,
again, we didn't really do
justice to any of the work I talked
about. So the final thing I would say is
definitely the document is there with
the reading, and please go and actually
look at the work of these people,
because some of it's really good. All
right. Till next time. Cool. Thank you
very much.