hello everyone
welcome to active inference live stream
number
6.1 it is october 13th 2020.
whether you're a first-time listener or
not welcome to
teamcom teamcom is an experiment in
online team communication and learning
related to active inference
you can find us on twitter at
inferenceactive
at our gmail address our key base team
that's public
or our youtube channel this is a
recorded and an archived live stream
so please provide us feedback so that we
can improve our work
also all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome here and
in service of that remember your video
etiquette
mute if there's sound in the background
and raise your hands so that we'll be
able to hear from everyone
here we are in acting stream 6.1
and today's stream is gonna go like this
we're gonna start out with a warm-up
section
where we introduce some of ourselves
especially our newer
participants and just have a quick
check-in then we'll turn to the
discussion of the paper
today we'll try to cover the goal of the
paper
the road map how they get from a to z go
through the abstract which is how the
authors represent their work in the most
distilled form
and then look at some of the figures see
where they're going to be going with the
figures what they're going to be showing
and then
next week in 6.2 we're going to have a
lot more time for
further discussion on this paper and
also to dive into some of the technical
details of the figures
so please save and submit your questions
all right here we are in the intros and
check-ins
for the introduction section please
introduce yourself
and your location just say a quick hello
anything else
you'd like to add and then feel free to
pass it to someone else
so i'm daniel i'm in davis california
and i'll pass it to one of our first
time participants
matthias
it's actually mathis mathis pink
i'm a master student in germany
in at the university of osnabruck which
is in
lower saxony so it's uh afternoon
where i am i guess it's in the morning
where you are
um yeah i'm excited about
participating thanks for having me
i will i don't know is there another
person who's new here
uh lee alex maybe
let's go to lee our other new yeah
yeah hiya um yeah i'm lee i'm based in
london but i'm actually studying at the
university of york uh studying embodied
cognition
and yeah look really looking forward to
this
i will pass on to alejandro
hello everyone
i'm again at mexico kind of tired
um last week
was very hard but
um yeah nice to be here again with you
all
and um and pass it to
alex
hello everybody i'm alex i am
an engineer basically and now
also a researcher and i am stated in
moscow russia
and related to this system management
school
so i'm passing to klip
hi i'm john cliff i'm uh in uh
cambridge mass with the mit media lab
and actually doing this at
in northern new hampshire at my farm um
and i'm very pleased to be part of this
and i'm here
to learn
let's go to alex kiefer and i'll pass it
off
to maxwell
okay hi everyone uh so i was here a
couple weeks ago um
i'm a philosopher i guess and sometimes
computational
modeler at monash university and right
now i'm in new york city
um and i've been involved in this debate
that's that's explored in this paper for
a while so i thought i would join it
and i will pass it to who's left um
shannon
hi i'm shannon crooks um i'm part of the
sensory motor neuroscience lab at the
university of california in merced
but currently i'm in south dakota
um so i'll pass it to
sasha
hi everybody i'm sasha i'm based out of
davis california and i'm affiliated with
university of california davis
and also i'm just very excited to learn
and unpack some of these topics
um it's been a really great uh past
six or so streams so
i will pass it on to stephen
uh hello yeah i've been involved in this
for the last few sessions as well find
it very very helpful and very
interesting i'm
doing a practice based phd into some
processes to explore social topographies
and at country christ church university
at the solomon school of applied
psychology
with the help of the professional
development institute
and i'll pass that to
maxwell i suppose is it i believe i'm
the last one
um yes oh uh i'm maxwell ramstead
uh i'm based in montreal where i'm
talking to you
from at mcgill university and
i'm also the first author on the paper
that we'll be discussing today
so i'm quite excited to discuss it with
you
thanks alex kiefer by the way for
showing up alex and i have had a
sustained
uh series of discussions around these
papers that have led to
follow-up papers and i think to a really
robust and fun friendship
uh through these discussions so i'm
looking forward to discussing all these
issues with you
uh thanks uh thanks for the continued
following of our work awesome
you know we bring the ideas together
sometimes through the people and the
friendships
and i guess i'm not gonna pass it to
anyone since since everyone else is
uh spoken right yep i think that
is everyone so cool let's go to
our warm-up questions and anyone who
likes to
speak can uh feel free to raise their
hand or jump in if there's no one
speaking yet
so the first question is what drew you
to this paper or topic
and while people are raising their hand
i'll start i think what was
exciting about this paper was about just
combining two
different schools of thought and
bringing them in together in a
constructive
way that was really super additive
rather than just choosing
sides what about you maxwell
um well so the motivation for writing
the paper in part
um was that i don't think
that at least at the time i didn't think
that what the generative
model business uh you know under the
free energy principle
is all about really i don't think that
was well understood
at the time that we wrote this so i i
alluded to this i think a few
weeks ago this paper uh the answering
schrodinger's question
paper and physics of life reviews and
the paper that we discussed the last
few weeks multi-scale integration were
all originally the same paper
it was all one big thing and we ended up
splitting it
into uh different papers to address
different things
uh so you know the multi-scale stuff
that we've been uh discussing
to address like the the scale-free and
multi-level formulation of the fep
and the the aim here was really to
connect uh the fep to other pragmatist
approaches uh the center act the center
on action
um and also to clarify uh
the nature of the generative models that
are at play here uh
which aren't just kind of brain bound
statistical models but turn out to be
something like the phenotype
of the organism
cool anyone else have thoughts on that
uh alex kiefer yeah thanks um
so i guess well i was drawn into the
debate because um
um uh some of my work with jakob hovi
was
among the uh the sort of target um the
critical target of the article
although maxwell and company were very
nice to us
and they didn't say we were wrong they
just said this doesn't exactly
generalize to the free energy principle
um so that's how i got drawn into this
and i continue to be interested in it
because i think it
i mean i think we've we've converged on
more of an agreement than
maybe existed at this time this paper
came out but oh yeah 100
i think i think we basically converge to
one coherent story at this point
but this is two years in the making so
yeah but but i mean the issues raised
here are still interesting to think
about
you know and i continue to learn more by
thinking about them so
awesome all right the second warm-up
question
is going to be what would be something
that you'd like to have resolved by the
end of today's discussion
so that could be a specific question
about how to apply something to a system
yeah lee go ahead
go ahead lee ah sorry i was just turning
my sound up
um so so yeah essentially um i
i guess i was drawn to this topic
because
um my journey towards active inference
has been via cognitive linguistics
so i started off looking into
relationships between language and
perception and particularly metaphor
so i think i've got quite a different
understanding of
what's meant by model uh probably
something more kind of
phenomenological and uh maybe epistemic
um and and i really starting to
understand that that's not what really
what is meant by
active inference so i've taken a good
look through this paper and i'm
hoping to build some kind of bridge from
uh where i'm at to more of an
understanding of what's implied by
generative model in active influence
cool well great because that's one of
the main topics of the paper
and stephen
actually just so just bouncing off what
was just said there
in some ways when you take metaphors if
you bring metaphors into
embodiment and has been embodied in
space
and around us actually then suddenly
that whole metaphor work becomes
actually almost
very close to what might be a generative
model
in a funny way even though it's
different so
there might be some way i'm actually so
in some ways i'm kind of interested how
this sort of becomes full circle
and can come back to these kind of um
kind of human ways of knowing
even though we've accessing it through
maybe kind of abstracted models
interesting and i think we'll return to
some of these
ideas if anyone else wants to chime in
on what they'd like to have resolved but
very interesting to hear about metaphor
as cognition and
how we can humanize our understanding of
some of these technical
or conceptual issues all right well if
there are no
hands remaining i'll move on to the next
slide so today we're going to be talking
about a tale of two densities
active inference is an active inference
which is a
article in adaptive behavior in 2020
by maxwell ramstead kirchoff and fristen
and in this paper they lay out their
goal
really clearly which i always love to
see in a paper
they write at the very beginning the aim
of this article is to clarify how best
to interpret some of the central
constructs that underwrite the free
energy principle or fep
and its corollary active inference in
theoretical neuroscience and biology
namely the role that generative models
and recognition densities play in this
theory
aiming to unify life and mind
so what are the two densities they're
going to be the generative models
and the recognition densities and we're
going to learn more about them and hear
about how they're related and discuss
different perspectives on
how the densities are linked and
specifically
the question is what is the tail of
these two densities it's alluded to
in the title and it's awesome that we
have maxwell
and alex and so many other voices here
to to make that
synthesis and that tale that we're all
telling together
realized so um in the
acting stream 6.0 i provided a little
bit of context just from
my perspective on some of these issues
if people want to learn more
about uh some of the background ideas
but for now
we're gonna just jump into the abstract
and at any point people can just
raise their hand and i'll just pause
right there and we'll take
a comment or a thought in the abstract
they begin
by rehearsing what i had just read that
they're looking to clarify how to best
interpret some of the constructs
underwriting the free energy principle
and those two constructs are the
generative models and the variational
densities
so those are the two densities and the
tail is going to link them
we argue that these constructs
generative models and variational
densities
have been systematically misrepresented
in the literature
because of the conflation between the
fep and active inference on one hand
and distinct albeit closely related
bayesian formulations centered on the
brain
variously known as predictive processing
predictive coding or the prediction
error
minimization framework
more specifically we examine two
contrasting
interpretations of these active
inference type models
a structural representationalist
interpretation and an inactive
interpretation
so we're setting up the two sort of sub
stories these are the tension between
these two perspectives that we're going
to be
looking to resolve under the fep through
active inference
we argue that the structural
representationalist interpretation of
generative and recognition models
does not do justice to the role that
these constructs play in active
inference under the fep
we propose an inactive interpretation of
active inference
what might be called an active inference
in active inference under the fep
the generative and recognition models
are best cast
as realizing inference and control the
self-organizing
belief guided selection of action
policies and
do not have the properties ascribed by
structural representationalists
so for this next slide i'll really
appreciate anyone's um
perspective or linking it back to things
they've seen before because i just
put it up there as a visual and uh just
a starting place
on the left side here we have the
bayesian
structural representationalist
perspective that we're just trying to
highlight the
features that are going to be most
simple to carry forward
and the bayesian structural
representationalist story is about how
data and another type of data which are
often called hyper parameters
are linked through a recognition model
that
takes data like sensory data and
recognizes it
and then going the other direction you
have the hyper parameters
that are generating sensory data and we
can also talk about why it's important
to have this generative step
and the outcome of this bayesian
computationalist scheme
is that there's a statistical
convergence of a multi-level model
that represents structures of the world
through something like expectation
maximization or em models
and we can contrast that with the
inactive paradigm
and the inactive paradigm is about how
agents and the world are related through
perception and action
and the outcome of the inactivist
perspective is an embodied
ecological action sequence really from
an embedded agent
who is enacting behavior and so this is
always the school of thought where we
see all the ease
encultured and embedded in all these
things and
they're um seemingly at least at the
first pass
up to two quite different explanatory
uh outcomes they seem to be talking
about somewhat different
aspects about the world and they
definitely link them through
different ways so i'm just curious
maxwell or anyone else like
what led to these two models being the
two
cities the two densities that were
chosen how does one
come down to just two why is there not
one or three cities and then
how did the bayesian structural
representationalist and the inactive
viewpoint
rise up as like the two kind of uh tier
one theories that we wanted to
find a synthesis between well so when i
got into
this literature um
especially from the the vantage point of
philosophy
what i noticed was the very very little
of it was technically rigorous
in the sense that you know a lot of it
was telling uh
like a story about how you know the
brain roughly performs bayesian
inference and then
uh you know kind of saying well there's
like a family of different
theories that do this in various ways
and grouping the free energy principle
under that i say uh you know uh
there was like a lack of technical rigor
i i want to emphasize that alex's papers
with jakub are probably the exception to
that
when i consulted alex's papers
in 2018 i thought well here's you know
some wonderful work
that is really taking the time to drill
down
on the formalisms as they're used to
study the brain
i thought that was great but i've i
spent a lot of time really drilling into
the
formalism of the free energy principle
per se and one of the things that i was
sort of surprised
to find out as i was learning the
formalism was that
although everyone is talking about the
generative model uh there are really two
models at play
um so those are the generative and the
recognition models or densities
equivalently
um i mean so first of all we say model
by model we just mean a probability
density right so
uh a probability distribution over a
bunch of
variables uh that are of interest to us
um and so yeah the the two models in
question
uh under the free energy principle
function slightly differently than they
do
in more traditional brain-based
uh so to step back a bit in
in machine learning and in statistics
a recognition model basically tells you
the probability
of some state given a bunch of other
things it's a
it's not a joint probability
distribution
um and it's it's used essentially to
recognize what's causing your data so
you're using it basically to
invert uh your mapping
i mean uh alex also if i'm saying
anything uh
inaccurate here just uh please uh jump
in and let me know
uh but yeah so there's basically in
traditional uh
kind of you know bayesian brain machine
learning architectures
the generative and the recognition
models are basically just the inverse of
one another so
uh the kind of top uh the kind of
bottom-up
pass uh is a recognition
uh pass it's a recognition model in the
sense that it's starting from the data
and then kind of passing through uh the
network you're able to infer what
must have caused your data and uh the
generative model is the inverse past
where you're starting from your beliefs
about states
and you can generate fictive data you
know based on
uh on this model and at least in alex
this paper is the way that
this uh well the this is how it was
described
as applying to uh the free energy
formulation as well
and my point in this paper was that well
this is a very technically rigorous
and accurate description of what's going
on in the bayesian brain
but these constructs have a slightly
different meaning under active inference
uh and to bring it back to i'm almost
done uh just give me one one more minute
uh to bring it back to uh these
schemas basically the so the recognition
density
is sort of like your best guess right
now you can think about it sort of like
as your posterior and your prior
so your recognition density is a density
defined over all of your states and your
parameters
and it basically tells you what do i
believe is the most probable value of
these states and parameters now
you know given uh my prior beliefs and
my evidence
your generative model to the contrary is
the point of reference
uh you know for the generation of free
energy gradients
so it's not your posterior it's your
prior it's sort of like it harnesses
all of the priors um especially the
priors about
your preferred data distributions
relative to which the free energy and
therefore the dynamics are defined so
you know you write
uh inference and control i think you
discussed
uh in 6.0 dan yeah the
so the recognition model is responsible
for inference and the generative model
is responsible for control you might say
so i'll stop there cool alex
keeper and then we'll go to anyone else
with a raised hand
yeah thanks so i i stopped myself from
jumping in i mean that was that was a
good summary um the only thing
the point at which i wanted to jump in
was to say well so the recognition model
isn't uh as con construed in these
bayesian brain theories is
an approximate inversion of the
generative model so my
my um if i have any complaint about this
paper it's that i think that there's a
a closer sort of conceptual connection
between the
generative and recognition densities
than then maybe the paper suggests
um and that i don't think you can
cleanly separate these things so
uh well anyway i don't want to launch
into this yet what i wanted to do
first was just address the the question
was sort of how did these two
visions sort of arise and my sense is
that what carl fristen did he did
a lot of great stuff but the main thing
he did that distinguished his approach
from the existing stuff in machine
learning
a lot of which was based on free energy
minimization uh
which i think he came to around the same
time as people like jeff hinton
but anyway he you know he added action
into the picture and he
pointed out that you can act so as to
reduce the surprisal
or the free energy cosplay or sensory
states uh instead of just revising your
gender degenerative distribution um
anyway so i think i'll hold off on on
arguing for the moment
awesome i i just want to say i agree
with you now uh
these two things do do not really come
together uh come apart sorry um
i mean it's really just an
implementation of variational inference
from that point of view and variational
inference and this is why it's a tale of
two densities
is that to do this variational inference
thing you need both
you need a kind of point of reference
that's going to give you the free energy
gradients
and then you need a sort of what is my
best guess as i am performing gradient
descent on my free energy
and yeah like i i don't want i don't
want to say that the two come apart
and indeed i mean i think you know in in
a newer paper that i've written
on this uh i basically just straight up
say that you were correct initially
uh it with respect to the recognition
density so the recognition
density it's fair to say that it's a
representation in the structural
representationalist sense that
you've been uh articulating in in the
series of really
awesome papers which you should all read
by the way i think
uh yeah where is the the the the one
point of disagreement that i think we've
clarified now is the status of these
generative models
and uh yeah yeah i'll stop there too
nice we'll go to steven and then anyone
else with a raised hand before the
roadmap
now one question i've got is in terms of
if
if these um kind of hyper
parameters that they use in machine
learning are
using a free energy is it that
they're they're just minimizing the kind
of energy expenditure
and the entropy internally and
and they're not using shannon entropy i
they're not looking at
how entropy is inferred or transmitted
sort of in a second order process from
interacting in the world they're just
minimizing it within
the kind of data that's being kind of
accrued
which kind of in some ways seems to
happen easily when you look at like
vision data but may not be so
easy to pass when you sort of look at
the whole body
but that that question of entropy is it
that they use entropy in a different way
and they're not really using
entropy in the kind of um external
entropy of interaction but kind of just
the entropy
within the um calculations
in terms of there are two kinds of
entropy at play
in general right uh so entropy
in the thermodynamic sense is a measure
of how many macro states are com
compatible with a given
uh value of a macro state right so i
don't know your temperature is 36
degrees celsius
how many different macro state
configurations are compatible with that
so that form of entropy is one special
case of the broader
kind of entropy which is more or less a
measure of how flat your probability
distribution is
uh over your states so if you have a
perfectly flat distribution your entropy
is optimal
and um so the the entropy that we're
concerned with
is really the second type it's the
information theoretic entropy
but uh it's it's transpired over the
last few years that
uh variational free energy is also a
thermodynamic free energy you just have
to multiply by boltzmann's constant
so essentially yeah it's always
information theoretic measures but when
this is realized in actual physical
systems
it is also a thermodynamic uh free
energy but you know
the variational free energy it sounds
kind of spooky and esoteric but
it's really simple really is that you
have a preferred data distribution
and you have an actual data distribution
and the free energy is just a way to
quantify the difference between the two
um yeah awesome we'll go to alex
and then back to stephen
but yeah i was just going to briefly say
in in the you know the earlier machine
learning literature
the free energy definitely wasn't
supposed to be anything
thermodynamic or maybe that was
maybe that was an open possibility but
it was just a it was just a measure
as you were saying i think steven
between two internal
internally determined distributions it
was the top down
generative uh posterior versus the
approximate posterior
and um any connections to thermodynamics
are really cool but i think that's an
additional like very substantive um
question slash
thesis stephen and then anyone else who
raises their hand
yeah i think this is this is quite a
useful distinction
because i think that's where a lot of
the mixing gets
sort of caught up at the moment because
a lot of stuff has
been referred to in like the last 15
years around bayesian
optimization and bayesian stuff and then
where it's all pretty much as if it's in
contained in the data in the brain
and then now it's like try
it's like a reconceptualizing of that so
i think it is a big
big challenge for people to like forget
about what they've learned before
really agreed with that stephen and um
that's really what this conversation and
synthesis
is about is about bringing those
qualitative often
insights from inactivism and saying well
wait a minute
perception isn't simply the reverse of
action you know there's not
photons coming out of your eye so what
is different between perception and
action
but also recognizing that the world and
the agent have this sort of symmetry
and that they are linked so again anyone
can raise their hand but we're gonna
turn to the roadmap
and ask how the authors set up the
discussion between the bayesian and the
inactivist approached
and then ultimately converge towards
somewhat of a synthesis
and on the right side is just the title
page of the dickens
work tale of two cities so first there's
an introduction
sequence and then they talk about
statistical models as
representations and specifically they
talk about
generative models and recognition models
in bayesian cognitive science
as well as generative models as
structural representations so that's the
bayesian
structural and the representational
components
then they talk about generative models
and action policies which is sort of
opening the door
to this potential inadequacy of the
purely bayesian approach which is that
it's not action oriented
in the third section they discuss the
active inference framework
first they start by talking about how
phenotypes are conceptualized under
active inference
and about markov blankets and there's a
figure one which we've seen before and
we will see again
about how markov blankets and active
inference are linked
they then discuss surprise entropy and
variational free energy which are all
terms uh perhaps not surprised but the
other two that we've
brought up in this discussion and in the
paper they really go into detail
a bit more about how these topics are
linked there's then a discussion about
how active inference
specifically links the variational free
energy with the inferential models
in section four a tale of two densities
they talk about how the generative model
and the recognition density are to be
conceptualized
under the fep and specifically they talk
about the generative model and the
generative process
in active inference in figure 2 they
depict a generative model
and represent it as a bayesian network
in figure 3
they talk about the same generative
model in active inference represented as
a forney factor graph
and the similarities and differences
between figure two and three
were probably going to go into next week
in 6.2
there's then a section on variational
inference and recognition dynamics under
the fep
in the fifth section they turn to purely
inactive inference
and they say first the claim that the
generative models
are control systems and so this sort of
borrows
on and builds on the generative model
idea which is a bit of a
computationalist perspective
as well as this control systems
perspective which implicitly
means action orientation because control
of action
not just control of theoretical
parameters
they then take the fighting words
section
generative models are not structural
representations i always like it when we
can
get down to specific claims and
negatable state
statements and uh just really being
specific because sometimes these
abstractions get pretty far out
there's then the final figure four which
depicts the action
perception cycle in active inference as
a generative modal
and a process and last they conclude
with some remarks
and the remarks also conclude with
towards multidisciplinary research
heuristics for cognitive science
and i know we have a lot of awesome
cognitive scientists and other
perspectives in this room and so
this is sort of our springboard where we
can take the ideas that we're talking
about here
and ask well how does this impact how
we're going to do the cognitive science
research what kind of explanations what
kind of predictions
what kind of experiments are we going to
do differently
how will our research paradigm be
different if we take
this approach that is synthesizing the
inactive and the bayesian approach
so especially cognitive scientists um
would be awesome to hear any thoughts
and while people are sort of collecting
their thoughts about
anything on the roadmap or prior in the
uh last 20 minutes here we'll have good
time to go through the figures and ask
about how they relate
to this big topic how are the two cities
linked
what is the highway that connects the
two cities or what is the
broader collaborative network that links
these two
any thoughts here on the roadmap
you you definitely laid out the
reasoning in the paper very well so
thank you good and uh these papers are
uh straightforward to layout because
they really
of almost a uh additive
way of laying out the topics first you
lay out the strongest version
of the other approach and actually it's
the
professionality and the clarity and not
misrepresenting another viewpoint just
to throw it under the bus or
to make a straw man argument it's it's
laying out the strongest form
of the um prior literature is what
allows us to build
another level of strength on top of the
literature rather than just cutting out
the pillars from underneath us so i
always well and i have to say you know
we started off with this
a much stronger position than we ended
up with
and it's it's by engaging seriously
with the arguments that alex and jacob
had uh prepared
uh you know with a few other people
paolo godzillski and so on
had been uh arguing for this kind of
stuff but
i mean thank you for saying that about
the professionalism i really think that
there is something to
that argument and the whole point is to
keep the baby you know
uh with while getting rid of the
bathwater
uh and you know the baby is this sort of
idea that there is
something like uh representations of the
external world that you know carry
semantic content and so on like
uh it's just that it's not the
generative models uh it's it's the
recognition densities that's
that was sort of the tweak that we
wanted to bring to the table but
cool alex and then anyone else who
raises their hands
yeah so um yeah like like maxwell says
we've
had a lot of interesting questions about
this um i guess the point
the point on which i remain not
convinced yet is that i think i still
think of the generative model
even in the fep as a representation so
we can we can maybe talk about that
um i think to me what this brings to the
table and
this is like transformed how i see this
stuff is the importance of understanding
the generative model as a control system
um i just think you can do that in a way
that
also grants that it's a structural
representation and that's what i've been
that's still the framework in which i
work um so i think
there's another question raised here
about whether the generative model is
sort of encoded
and um i do understand where where the
authors are coming from
um on that question and i think it's not
so straightforward at
in the fep as it would be in some
earlier models like the helmholtz
machine
um so i don't know i'm curious to see if
maxwell and i still disagree i have the
sense that
i maybe still want to call the
generative model a representation
um more than maxwell does but we can get
to that can i
ask um alex and again anyone can raise
their hand and have a thought here too
is
what is the advantage of wanting
something to be a representation or
what is the alternative to something
being structural right
so i mean so i don't think in those
terms in terms of the advantage of it i
just think
is it a representation or not i think it
is based on what i
our representation is and how this thing
functions in this model so
i know oftentimes people talk about like
what's the explanatory value of
talking in terms of representations um
but i mean to answer more directly um
what's
so what's the alternative to it being
structural that's another good question
um in my view this structural
representationalist paradigm really
isn't anything new it's kind of just
like
the core notion of representation that's
been at work in serious cognitive
science since like turing
so like if you go back to um you know
papers uh
like um there's a paper from 1980
by uh alan newell on um
sort of uh foundations of cognitive
science and and
he described how um what makes a
particular symbolic um physical symbol
system
um able to uh
get what gives it its universal
universal computational capacity
is its capacity to simulate other
systems so i really think this notion of
simulation is at the heart of
what representation is supposed to be in
cognitive science and that that
that really just is structural
representation and if you go back last i
won't go on forever
if you go to um cummins's early work on
on structural representationalism um the
s representation
can also be read as simulation um so
it's not that i think that you
need to call it a gen uh degenerative
model a structural representation i just
think once you understand how it
functions
um i would say even under the fep that's
like what it is
but there's still a question about how
it's encoded or whether it's encoded i
think that's a separate question
awesome thanks for that response we'll
go to lee and then anyone else that can
raise their hand
okay so um so excuse me i was just
trying to make sure that um
i i was understanding terms in the same
way that they were being used but
alex you just talked about the uh the
notion of representation of
simulation and um
you know one of the ways i've kind of
arrived at active inferences is via the
work of
barcelona and perceptual symbol theory
and simulation
does that is is that overlapping with
what you're meaning by simulation or
does it have a different
um meaning if you're familiar with this
work at all
probably i'm not i'm not as familiar
with that work um
as with um the the newer paper that i
just
that i mentioned i am and it is just a
yeah
great idea no just kidding i want to
read it um
okay i'll accept that i'll i'll take my
word for it yeah i mean essentially uh
especially these deep generative models
or they allow you to
entertain um well i mean
the there's a sense in which the like
the bar salute
you know idea of metaphor is just what
the generative models do uh you know if
we're talking about a kind of
loose associative structure that
redeploys
inferences about one domain in another
i mean uh this is the kind of thing that
you would expect a generative model
would be able to do
uh so these things are definitely i
think strongly aligned
uh in effect uh i mean didn't steven
suggest something similar
i think uh like the yeah metaphors are
generative models in a strong sense cool
notion will go to alex kiefer and then
anyone else
yeah so um that's interesting i don't
know what to say about metaphors
but um i i think the way i see
the way i see this now is that um i
don't think what maxwell at all are
saying is at all
of course um maybe not of course i don't
think it's at all wrong but i just think
that
our the sort of the structural
representationalist reading
my view is that it doesn't quite say
enough but not that not that it's wrong
in any particular respect as applied to
the fep
like so so after further conversations
with maxwell and also with um
with michael and the other authors on
this um
it seems to me that you still have
there's still a need for a
sort of neuronally realized generative
model
uh in addition to considering the entire
phenotype
to be a generative model so if you have
a fancy organism that can do
you know deep temporal kind of modeling
and plan for the future and things like
that
i think there's still a need for
something that looks like a structural
um in the brain that that is the
generative model can be construed that
way
as well as there's this sort of larger
more encompassing system and maybe this
could be some somewhat hashed out
appealing to the multi-level
active infant stuff um but last piece of
this um
in discussions with with um michael
kirkoff i hope i'm saying his name
correctly
we've never said it out loud to each
other um
it it seems as though he at least he is
thinking of top-down
sort of propagation of signals as a form
of action
so the stuff that we were saying about
um
top-down generative models might just be
sort of a special case of
the sort of action that this paper is
talking about
ooh before we go to stephen and then lee
it really reminds me about alejandra's
point one or two weeks ago about
what are the similarities and the
differences between the systems that
can at least appear to do these deep
simulations
the counterfactuals like the brain
versus a
embodied phenotype the cell perimeter is
not simulating other cell perimeters
that's a little bit different than the
way that the brain might be able to do
something
strategic so um we'll go to stephen
and then anyone else can raise their
hand
[Music]
yeah one one thing i always look at when
you think of rep
we talk about representation also in
performance um
it's to think of like re-presentation
like is there another presentation
in the brain which often people start
thinking as a projection and then you
start getting into this
very visually dominated view of what
our knowing is you know so whereas it's
a bit different to reenacting or
reimagining
so like if i was to re-imagine as an
engineer
um a model and then i manipulate it
in my brain well am i manipulating in my
brain or have i reimagined it
in my peri-personal space and am i now
manipulating it
actively in my peri-personal space
and that is what i'm actually
thinking of as a representation but it's
not actually my brain at all
it's just a re-enactment in space
for me to then start to work with or if
i do it on paper
i think the mechanism for that is this
is not quite clear but this sort of
opens up that question
cool lee uh
stephen i think i understand what you're
talking about but i
are you just kind of um mixing up the
phenomenological
with the underlying ontological
level so if you have a representation in
the brain and you simulate it that it
that it manifests in experiential space
or perceptual space is that what you
mean
well to to manifest it in the uh
phenomenological space
is to enact is what i'm saying so
it's not like it's in the brain then i
project it into space
it's like it's not in the brain it might
be encoded
like place cells grid cells all of that
stuff with all the other
stuff but it might be encoded in a way
that can re-enact
it but once it's re-enacted so with the
work with
clean language and micro phenomenology
looks at like re
embodying concepts in
space around them so my kind of feeling
is that a metaphor
is kind of like our reading
on our kind of affect
and our kind of thinking our beliefs
recreated in a kind of a physicalized
way
you know so we actually do like we
i feel like i'm stuck behind the wall
like i start you can actually ask people
well where's the wall
and they will they'll know where the
wall is and what's it like to be stuck
and where so suddenly actually find that
they've actually got
like a model but they never had that
model before they kind of created it so
the question
becomes is it a reenactment a
reimaginization
and how much of that was already i
suppose is the question was that already
sitting in the brain
ready to go or did it only come about
through the act of reimagining cool
um in our last 10 minutes it would be
awesome to hear from anyone who hasn't
spoken as well as just to flip through
the figures so that we can see where
we're going to be
headed to do some technical unpacking
especially
next week so anyone can feel free to
raise their hand if they have a related
or unrelated point but in these last
few minutes let's just try to look at
the figures and hear some
closing thoughts so in figure 1 we have
the markov blanket and active inference
and we've returned to this figure many
times it's used across papers and it's
really
nice to see it again and again because
the context is always different
and the part that i underlined in red
was um
in graph theoretic terms the markov
blanket per se
is defined as the set of nodes that
isolates internal nodes from the
influence of external ones and in in
this capacity it's really good that we
had the discussion
about integrating internalism and
externalism
because those are also sort of like two
ideas that have this tension between
them
and the beyond internalism and
externalism paper
was about building on top of those about
taking the strengths of those two
ideas and then asking how they're
integrated under act imp
and today what we're doing and in this
paper is about
taking interpretations of internalism
and externalism
specifically this bayesian more
computational perspective
and this inactive embodied perspective
and building on
those strengths so it almost reads like
a recipe
for how active inference can be used for
synthesis which is by identifying
areas of tension in the literature or
previously unrecognized harmonies
between different ideas and then just
asking how we can build strength on
strength
rather than attack strength to weakness
or just
um you know contrast weaknesses and i'm
just going to continue just to
show the other figures but i'll pause
anytime someone raises their hand
on figure 2 oh alejandra go ahead
uh actually yeah and that figure um
i can take again uh the question
uh you mentioned um
i'm still confused in terms of these
generative models and their recognition
density
um in which temporal and and
spatial scale um
of course in each individual
cell of the brain this this process
is occurring and then in
i don't know in a layer of the cortex
and then in
the the hierarchy
of of the cortical layers
and then in the whole brain and then
blah blah blah but um so
um belief updating is happening in
each cell um
i don't know if um
if i'm i'm i'm getting to to
to to the to the point but um
the cells have to maintain actually this
blanket
contains also some beliefs that never
can change right um
so in order to to continue being
the cell it is um
um so um i don't know uh
this this process of of the densities
is is occurring
in i don't know how many scales and
yeah that's all of that i mean uh we'll
we'll end up
hopefully discussing this next week if
it's if it's unclear i mean i have to
say
i don't think the figures are super
useful in this paper uh they're mostly
there to illustrate
a few things what's really important is
the equations um so i mean
for next week dan i'll show you which
ones in particular so that we can put
them up
uh yeah so uh alejandro what you were
saying is exactly right
all of these things are performing a
belief updating and when we talk about
behavior or dynamics or whatever
it is all belief updating and belief
updating just means changing the
physical value of the recognition
density at a moment
so basically in this paper like the big
kind of conceptual contribution that i
tried to make to this
literature is to say well uh with active
inference we can rethink what we mean by
embodiment and enactment
so embodiment means encoding a
recognition density
uh so your physical body is a guess
about the it's a posterior probability
uh that you're you're constantly
updating through this process of belief
updating
aka dynamics aka adaptive behavior like
you've got this you we literally embody
this this density uh the physical states
of our body
encode the parameters of probability
densities
this is like the this is the idea um
and then basically the the generative
model is just the point of reference for
the dynamics that exists
in the dynamics the way i like to think
about it is sort of like dominoes
falling over
where the recognition density is the
dominoes
right each of these dominoes is like a
posterior estimate
you know and they kind of accumulate but
the wave
is the generative model you see like the
domino wave
itself that that the generative model
exists in the same sense as uh
the wave kind of you know making all the
the dominoes fall
and the recognition model exists in the
sense of the the
physical dominoes that are kind of
encoding the the process as it kind of
flows over uh but this will be i think
hopefully clearer next week
mathematically it's it's actually pretty
simple it's that the generative model is
the joint
probability density over all of your
variables
and this this density doesn't exist in
the brain
it's not anywhere uh what exists is the
the factorization of this density so you
know
you always see this in all these active
inference papers it's like p
of all of your variables so the data mu
and all the parameters etc equals and
then this long
factorized which is basically uh it's a
product of
likelihoods and priors so this product
of likelihood
and priors is the recognition density
that's constantly updated
right and that's what exists in the
brain
but joint density only exists as a
function of the dynamics it's like
all of these part partial uh like
carving
ups of this density right this
factorization they all move together and
in their dynamics together they realize
this joint density
sorry i just i i do have to end it at
the
59 as we discussed but this is the
perfect excitement to build
for our follow-up discussion next week
we're definitely going to go
into this question we'll just pick up
right here we'll literally just hit play
on the video
and uh go into detail on the
technicality and let's even have some
dominoes
on the screen so again just thanks
everybody for
understanding about the timing i've
provided
a follow-up form to the live
participants in the chat
and we welcome any other feedback
suggestions or
questions and please just uh stay in
touch
stay engaged if this was interesting or
exciting we
welcome all participants and it would be
awesome to have
you on this stream asking the questions
and also learning by doing with us
so thanks everyone for the awesome and
energizing discussion
and i'm really looking forward to next
week when we can go another level
detail into all of this so thanks so
much