You. Hello everyone.
We're in our first discussion of chapter
seven in cohort three.
So let's head over to chapter
seven and we will come to
the questions. But let's just
start with anyone who wants to
do you want to just give a general
comment or any reflection or thought on
seven or anything up to this point?
Ali and then anyone else?
Yes. So chapter seven is basically the
application of the first half of chapter
four in terms of modeling discrete
time situations. And it
goes through a number of case studies
in order to show how the matrices A-B-C
and D can be constructed in various
situations and the
challenges or rather the concerns
we may have when constructing such
matrices in order to have a viable
discrete time model for each situation.
So, yeah, that's basically the
premise of chapter seven.
Awesome, thank you. Totally agree. Just
like chapters two and three with low
road and the high road, we're kind of
like a pair. Chapters seven and eight
are kind of like a pair because seven is
going to go into discrete time modeling.
Chapter eight is on continuous time and
hybrid modeling. Does anyone else want
to make any just overall reflection or
comment on chapter seven?
All right,
I'm checking if there's any okay.
Does anyone have any question at all?
Otherwise we'll turn first to these
questions, start with
the written questions we have and
then just approach it from there. Does
anyone have anything else that they want
to consider first though?
Okay,
I'm putting in the chat, that's the
social sciences link, but here's
the chapter seven link in the chat and
so you can follow along there. Also
please upvote the questions that are
interesting to you because the questions
that have a bunch of upvoted points
we're going to make the short videos
for.
Okay, so we'll just go to the
I'm going to unvote all the questions
from my own you can still vote for them,
but I'm just going to unvote them so
that once we get to them, I'll vote for
them.
Okay. All right, first question
here's, chapter seven. Chapter seven
begins with a quotation. What I cannot
create, I do not understand. Richard
Feigman, what do you think this means in
the context of active inference?
Specifically,
I can't remember exactly who added this
in a previous cohort,
but they gave a mild and a stronger
answer. The mild answer is
you have to learn by doing. You actually
have to build the generative model to
understand active inference.
And then the stronger answer goes even
beyond that. And it's not just that you
have to build the generative model, you
actually have to have something that
escapes your hands and does something
interesting to really test the method
and understand it.
Anyone else want to add a comment on
this?
Okay, kind of a warm up question,
but anyone else want to add anything on
this? What I cannot create, I do not
understand. Otherwise we'll come into
the more specifics of the chapter seven
now.
Okay, so in that case, I'm just going to
go with the most upvoted questions.
Okay.
All right. This is on page 130, the
textbook they wrote. This choice, which
we're going to look to the textbook in a
second, speaks to the classical
exploration exploitation dilemma and
psychology, a dilemma that is resolved
under active inference. What do you
think about this? Okay,
so the setting that's
being considered is decision making
under uncertain payoff or reward
structure. So you think there's two slot
machines, one of them pays out 50% of
the time. You don't know how much the
other one pays out. So you could
continue to get 50% that would be
exploit, or you could explore,
and it might be better than 50%, it
might be worse than 50%. And so that is
sometimes called the exploration
exploitation dilemma. Does anyone
want to give a comment or a related
question on how is active inference
going to be approaching Explore exploit?
Michael yeah, I just
wanted to both affirm that I found the
mathematical representation of these two
ideas, that it's a trade off very
interesting. But to describe them as
resolved is something
that I find might be a little more
overdescribed, if you will.
Maybe the word is this formula
describes the trade off or as a way of
representing it, but resolution is a
much more open topic. So just thought I
would give a response, give feedback and
say, well.
Yeah, that's it. Yes,
maybe resolve in the sense of like a
high resolution image, like we can see
it. We've resolved the dilemma by
perceiving it not we have explained it
away or said that there is no trade off.
I believe this was Eric Sounds
previously, who kind of contested
the idea that Explore exploit is a
dilemma. It's not a dilemma.
There's not two options that are
intrinsically opposed. There's just one
integrated behavioral choice.
All of this being said, let's look at
how Explore exploit our approach
differently in active
inference. One more remark
might be that in a different sense
making context where the
explore versus exploit issue arose
continuously, the word sharpening
visibility was a way of describing the
space that sometimes just your
resolution comment helps remind me of
that. That it was like boosting the
visibility of the space does not resolve
the problems that you're trying to
address, but it does improve your
ability to act on the space. And I guess
that's maybe a suggestion for
language boosting visibility versus
resolving that's. All yes.
Awesome.
Yeah. Just to briefly catch us up to how
we get to this claim, chapter seven,
like Ollie mentioned, is going to be
concerned with a series of examples of
building discrete time generative
models. So these are models where time
clicks like one step at a time.
Figure 7.1 is showing just the
perceptual or the downstairs component
of a generative model. So D is the
prior, S are the hidden states, b are
how the hidden states change through
time. A is the matrix that maps hidden
states to observations. So this is just
the temperature in the room changing
through time outputting. A thermometer
reading at every time point. This is
hidden Markov model. Not a Markov
decision process, just a hidden Markov
model. Hmm.
They then write the A and the B matrix
as well as the D for a musical setting.
So there's four notes. The A matrix is
basically saying you hear the correct
note 70% of the time,
and then the B is the transition matrix.
So this is just playing four notes that
transition to each other 97% of the time
in this order. And it always
starts on the first note. So with just
those three matrices defined A,
B, and D, you have fully defined the
generative model for this. Hmm. There's
no decision making yet, but that's all
you need to define this. Hmm.
And then in Figure 7.2, there's an
example where actually there turns
out in this simulation that
the third observation, it should be
here, but it's actually here. So that's
what's heard because there's such a
prior that that's what should be heard.
Okay, now we get into action,
which is where the explore and exploit
are going to come back into play. So if
it's just a purely passive inference,
then the kind of dilemma or unavoidable
trade off is like over and under fitting
perceptually, making something that's
over compressed or under compressed with
your beliefs. But action
has a different set of challenges
because it's related to selection of
causal intervention in the world and it
changes sequences of future observations
and all of this. And as we know from the
expected free energy, the imperative for
action is to have both epistemic
value, like to gain information, and to
have pragmatic value, to have alignment
between your observations, your
preferences. Here's figure 7.3.
This is kind of the classic generative
model in discrete time. So we
see that same downstairs component, the
exact same. Plus there's the upstairs
decision making component, pi policy
intervening into how states change their
time, expected free energy g updating
policy decisions, updating them based
upon their expected free energy.
Michael? Yeah, sorry. Yeah, please. I'm
jumping back 60 seconds, but right
before you described that diagram, you
said how you compress the I can't
remember, but you use the word
compression. And I wondered, why is he
using compression as the verb to
describe what's happening? And are you
suggesting that in the same way that
let's say when you compress
data onto to
save more storage space, you do an
abstraction, reduce it, and it's a
compression of what the data is.
That is what's happening. There is a I'm
sorry to be wordsmithing here. I'm just
trying to make sure I'm tracking what
you were saying when you said okay.
It is very closely related to this.
There's two ways to think about it. One
is like we're, we're fitting some
gaussian, let's just say some bell curve
over some uncertainty. So we could think
about like, do we want over compressing
it in terms of tightening the variance?
That would be like overfitting versus
like if it's loose, then it's like
under. So that's a little bit like a
loose sense of compression, really.
It's just a variance estimation. Or you
can think about complexity minus
accuracy as being like optimal zip
compression. Like obviously if you
wanted a lossless compression you wanted
perfect accuracy, then you're opening
the door to an infinitely complex model.
On the other hand, if you're willing to
find a trade off between complexity and
accuracy, which is summarized by
variational free energy in the moment,
then you would end up with at the point
of diminishing returns, like the kind of
the Pareto optimal compression point.
Thank you. Sorry to no, it's all good.
So now to study this action setting,
which is where explore exploit comes
into play, we're going to switch from
the music listening example,
which was just kind of familiarizing us
with the A, B and the D. And now we're
going to bring in action, which is going
to require talking about Pi policy
and C our preferences.
Okay, so it's a T maze task.
There's an aversive stimulus in one arm,
an attractive stimulus in the other arm,
and a Q that indicates the location of
the two stimuli in the bottom of the T.
So the organism can either pick
one of the arms left or right,
maybe quickly get to the reward, but
maybe get the aversive stimulus. Or it
could choose to seek out this
informative cue and then having reduced
its uncertainty about the location of
the reward, then just
walk over to the reward. So that's going
to be one, two, three steps instead
of just going straight to one of the
arms, but you
then have higher accuracy with getting
to one of the arms. So how
do you get flexible and rapid
and adaptive switching between pragmatic
oriented behavior and epistemic oriented
behavior especially? How can that happen
as new information are rolling in
without necessarily retraining the
model? That is
what is going to be explored here.
Anyone else want to just add a comment
or thought or how
they see it at this point?
Yeah, have a general question in terms
of if you do an experiment with
different animals, for example, or
different observers, and you want to
model different balance between this
epistemic and pragmatic behavior,
where in the ABCD matrices
would that be? Yeah,
very good question. One place that
this plays out is in the amplitude
of C. So let's
just say that left and right are the two
directions on the teammates and
we don't have a habit for either one of
them if we prefer the
sugar over the aversive. So now we're
going to talk about the C matrix, if
it's one and zero so aversive we
don't really care about, then we give a
value of one for the reward versus
if the C was a million and negative a
million, then the pragmatic value term
would basically just be like scaled
larger. So the amplitude
on C is commonly used to
weight the Pragmatic value relative to
the epistemic value. Because just
framing things like this does not
guarantee that your parameterization is
going to be at this adaptive point that
actually does flexibly trade off between
epistemic and Pragmatic behavior.
Because if C is very small and washed
out so utility seeking has
shapes behavior a little bit, then
you're going to end up with a mainly
epistemic agent. And if C is vast
relative to the epistemic value, then
you're going to end up with mainly
reward seeking, just like
we see in the in figure Two six,
where if we totally discard the
pragmatic term we end up with purely
epistemic behavior. And if we totally
discard the epistemic term we end up
with purely pragmatic behavior. But also
if this term is just really small,
you can imagine it doesn't play that
large of a role and vice versa.
So in an empirical setting, you have
to parameterize the
value, for example, of C, so that you do
get goal reward oriented
behavior, but not just
like one track mind,
um, Ali and then anyone
else.
Yeah, well, actually this C parameter C
matrix here in the formulation of
expected free energy is a relatively
recent addition to active inference
formulation because in some earlier
literature or even some recent
literature, this parameter c is
not explicitly expressed in the
formulation, they just express
it as P of observation.
Because you see,
this is a crucial step actually in
active inference because if
we want to derive this expected
free energy as a parallel to variation
of free energy, then here
instead of C, we should have only Pi,
right? But replacing Pi
with C denotes the kind of inaccuracy
in terms of our policy selection. In
other words, it doesn't necessarily
entail, I mean,
undertaking the policy we've selected,
we have a preference matrix for
undertaking some actions, but it doesn't
necessarily imply that we only take
those specific actions per se. So we
somehow approximate our preferences
without restricting ourselves to
the actual policies that's been
undertaken in the situation.
So that allows us to even
formulate or at least describe some
counterfactual examples as well as well
as the actual behavior we
observe for the agent. So that's,
I think, one of the crucial
steps in terms of allowing
for a broader behavior of the agents
and somehow broadening the possibility
spaces of the agents, not just the
actualized trajectories of the internal
states versus the external states.
Yeah,
it allows us to articulate what is the
action possibility space and
separate that from the outcome
preference so we don't
have our finger on the scale directly,
can't control observations directly.
That's the kind of perceptual control
theory insight. You want your
preferences to be about observations,
but you don't want to be able to
directly control observations. So what
are the two channels that we have to
reduce expected free energy, change our
mind, change the world? How much to
balance those two? That was Olivier's
question. And that is the question is
how do you balance those two? But those
are the two things that you want to have
from a first principles being balanced
off in terms of your imperative for
action selection. You want your action
selection to be an epistemically
informative path and a pragmatically
useful path. Epistemic value,
expected information gain under a policy
pragmatic value how well it aligns with
your preferences expectations.
So this is how exploitative and
explorative behavior are again going to
be resolved. Not to say addressed away,
but how it's approached. If we were in a
reward setting, then exploitative
behavior needs no secondary explanation.
It's like there's money on the ground.
If it's about getting money, then just
pick it up. So exploitative behavior
under reward centric paradigm does not
need a secondary explanation.
Exploratory behavior on the other hand,
eventually needs to navigate into the
currency of utilitarian value in
a reward centric path. And so an
exploratory path might be highly valued
because for example, there might be a
reward. So if there's a 10% chance of a
$1,000, then that policy
would have that expected reward. And so
that might be more preferable than for
sure one dollars or 10% of $1,000
in the reward centric approach. So then
that's how you get explore and exploit
balancing. You have exploratory
trajectories being evaluated in terms of
their expected returns in reward and
then you can have everything compared on
the common currency of expected
pragmatic value in reward learning.
Okay, so how are we going to approach it
differently in active inference?
Different trajectories of action
are going to be compared again in a
common currency. But rather than that
common currency being expected reward,
the common currency is going to be
expected free energy. Expected free
energy is going to have two components
expected information gain and expected
pragmatic value.
As stated before, balancing those two
terms into an adaptive zone is
a fine tuning question. But this is how
we approach the question in a first
principles way by making a unified
imperative that one includes perception
and action. That's the integration of
perception action loop. We see like
observations and we see actions.
They're just all there in the same
equation and it unifies epistemic
and pragmatic value. Instead of coercing
epistemic actions into their expected
reward and then comparing everything on
the reward meter stick, we just
have a single unified imperative,
expected free energy that contains an
epistemic and a pragmatic loading.
Michael. Great stuff.
That's all.
Yeah, equation 2.6 gets revisited again
and again and just different ways of
seeing expected free energy so now we're
going to continue seeing the teammates.
So here the matrices are shown
for this teammate. So, yeah, there's the
mouse aversive and beneficial
outcome. Olivier yeah,
sorry. No, it was just a bit like it's
behind on the last equation 7.4
for you. I find your last explanation
really great and very enlightening.
And in a basic context of reinforcement
learning, you will have somehow the
first term within the second, is that
what you're saying?
It wouldn't
be nested within the second strictly,
but yes. Basically policies,
one slot machine is giving you the 50%
reward and then you don't know the other
one. But a policy might be entertained
and even selected because it has a
high expected value. That is expected
value based decision making because you
say, well, I think slot machine, this
slot machine might have a high value,
so I'm going to take an exploratory
action to kind of explore that,
but not because of the information gain
it gives me, but because
of the expected reward. So it's kind of
like converting everything to a
pragmatic currency and then comparing
the expected utility or the expected
reward. And so you get utility
discounting, you get time preference,
all this stuff, but those are all
correction factors within pragmatic
value. Yeah. Okay, yeah. Thank you.
Sorry for the interruptions. This is one
of the key topics and this
is how policies are selected.
And that is the empirical challenge,
is being able to parameterize everything
so that it doesn't just behave trivially
like a novelty seeking agent over here,
or like a utility seeking agent over
here. We want to have some training in
the middle here's
where the matrices are shown for these
two settings. Here the block is on the
right and here the white is on the
right. And it just shows what the
matrices look like. So it's helpful to
see what the actual matrices look like
in the generative model, because
remember, this is the generative model.
So if you define A, B and D, just like
we saw in the music example, they're
just specific matrices of whatever
dimensionality it is that you're
studying. If there was four notes, then
D had four in a vector, a was a four
by four, b was a four x four matrix
in the music example. Now when you add
in policy,
policy has a dimensionality of however
many policies you can take. So if
there's four options policy has,
there's four options in the pi vector
and then there's going to be a slice of
B for each of the dimensionality
of pi. So if
there were four options for what you
could do, then there would be four
slices in B. And it's kind of like,
okay, if you choose action three, then B
three third slice in b is going to be
the one that we use to
update S. So once you define
this very limited, very interpretable
set, of parameters. You will have stated
the generative model and then you're
ready to engage with standard methods
for training and updating this
generative model. And so that's why in
active inference we spend a lot of time
think about chapter six setting up our
understanding of the problem because
once you can describe the dimensionality
and the parameters of the generative
model that was the work,
then you just update this as a
statistical model using standard
methods. So there's a lot of work in
understanding the problem and in framing
it and understanding what is the system
of interest and all these other things,
what form of degenerative model is
appropriate but then you don't need
to engage hopefully but actually in
secondary engineering concerns
for reasonable projects. I'm sure at
some very large scale these things do
come back into into play. But that's
kind of the cool thing about active
inference. We understand what all these
variables are and then when we want
to model our own setting we just specify
the generative model and kind of hit
play.
More matrices being shown.
Here's the C vector and so plus
six for the attractive stimulus and
negative six for the aversive stimulus.
Now if this were zero zero six
and negative six so the amplitude of
C were just smaller so the relative
preferences would stay the same but
the pragmatic term would just be
smaller. So then the agent would behave
more epistemically. Whereas if this were
6 trillion and negative 6 trillion then
the pragmatic term would come to
dominate.
So again, what is the approach of the
resolution? It's putting different
trajectories of behavior, action
selection on a common footing, expected
free energy which unifies
the epistemic and the pragmatic value of
different actions. We don't say
epistemic and pragmatic value are the
same thing. In fact they're different
but they're complementary. And so having
a unified imperative helps us adaptively
approach this question of the actual
trade offs between courses of action
that have known consequence and
those that are providing new
information.
Anyone want to have a thought? Yeah, go
for it. I'm a
babe out of water in so many levels.
But in my original field of training in
economics we had this phrase we used
often called Satiris paribus which was a
way of kind of saying that's an
extradinality to our models and we're
just going to keep going with the way we
do things, which is close enough. And
the consequences of this kind of poor
treatment of dilemmas was that things
like pollution and other externalities
were they might not fit in the
representational model and therefore
were kind of underweighted and
trivialized. And what I'm hearing you
make a case for, in a different
discipline, in a different way is
changing the math to handle what is
otherwise trivialized as external,
too inconsequential to be attended to,
is embracing the tension and
thus making it a part of what then can
be the sense making model of the
discipline overall. Which seems
something we can learn from you all.
Building not even one layer and
connecting that to kind of good hearts.
Paradox like a metric becomes Gamified.
Do we care about the levels of lead
in the measurement or do we care about
the hidden unobserved levels of lead in
the soil? And so in our systems model
that hopefully everyone will be able to
come to the table on, we could say,
well really there's both.
They're just different things. There's
the true underlying distribution which
we're never going to measure at every
little grain of sand and then there's
the sensor fusion that we have to do
with observations. So let's not try to
game the observations, but rather
come to the table with a more holistic
understanding of the relationship
between hidden states and observations
and how hidden states are changed and
how our actions influence the hidden
state distribution, but how that emits
observations, just articulate the
problem, break it down into the
components. And then the amazing thing
is these natural components of the
situation again prior beliefs about
hidden state underlying hidden states
that are unobserved emission of
observations, how the world changes
through time, actions that influence how
the world changes through time, our
strategy of deciding on action,
those are our naturally separable
aspects of thinking about a situation.
And in a way it's kind of amazing that
all you have to do is just like smash
the matrices together and the math does
kind of work out again in a way that we
would want it to.
Yeah, it's Chill 7.4
is going to go into a little bit more
detail on this epistemic value of
policies. So there's a few different
breakdowns here. They're all equal but
this is a few different representations
of just how we can think about the
informational gain associated with a
given policy. So, whereas the pragmatic
value for a policy is fairly
straightforwardly identified with how
close the expected observations
are to the preferences. So the most
pragmatically valuable trajectory is the
one where the body temperature is right
in the middle of the temperature
distribution. The least pragmatic one
would be the further away. But here's
where we see this I of Pi. So there's a
few more descriptions on I of Pi. And so
it turns out in this case with this
teamase, initially the action
that the mouse selects is to it
takes an epistemic action to reduce
uncertainty because it's like, okay,
there might be some pragmatic value,
but also it's a risky decision up here,
but going down is going to
be a policy selection that gives me a
lot of information. Now this
isn't the whole iguana as they brought
up in the beginning of the book. Like
how does the mouse come to know that the
aboutness of the queue is this setting?
So this isn't like from the
big bang to the mouse making the
decision, the total model, there's
always stuff that's structurally encoded
in the model how does it mouse come to
know that the aversive stimulus is
negative and so on. So these are levels
that you can add in but this is just
showing basically again in this simple
example it's just showing what it looks
like when the mouse undertakes
an epistemic action. And in the Pymdp
model stream 7.2, where there's
a very similar example to this it's not
in a Tmaze but it is with a mouse that
gets some information and then makes a
decision. So it's very similar to this.
You could play around in the script and
you can see what happens when you change
the preference vector to like a super
high or super low value.
Okay, little bit of boxed
discussion on precision
and entropy. The h is associated
with entropy but
let's just continue on. That just
relates to the over underfitting of the
expected the expected sharpness or
blurriness of a distribution.
They move on to another of the settings
that's been very well repeatedly
studied in active inference which is the
eye cicade setting the
motion of the eyes. And so one reason
why this has been studied a lot is that
the fovea of the vision, the area that
we have high resolution color vision is
actually very, very small relative to
the visual field. And that's why
multiple times per second the eye is
making these policy selections to move
around. And those policy selections,
although we might look at something
that's beautiful or rewarding and have
that fix our gaze, to a first
approximation, the imperative of the eye
circade is informational. It's gaining
information about the visual field
and so that is why the epistemic
visual search is a really
useful intangible setting.
Again, it's not like gambling.
You're kind of setting up a situation
towards pragmatic value but rather
this is one where there's going to be an
emphasis on the epistemic. And so this
is like based upon the ambiguity of
stimuli and about how
epistemic attraction occurs. When
there's information to learn. Where
something where there's no information
to learn doesn't that moving there does
not have epistemic value.
Kind of this is a little bit of a
formalization of the streetlight story
from every culture. Where did, where,
you know, where are you looking for your
keys? Under the streetlight. Oh, did you
lose them there? No, this is just where
I could look clearly. So that is
about looking where there's light and
searching where you can not
necessarily because you have a high
prior that the information is there but
just because it's easily resolvable
under the streetlight best place to find
high quality unambiguous uncertainty
resolving information.
So the ambiguous poorly lit square is
ignored reproducing in silico
streetlight effect. If you're not going
to get resolvable information it's not
of epistemic value to go there but if it
is going to be high quality uncertainty
reducing information that is like
epistemically valuable 75
Learning and Novelty so in.
Figure four, three in
seven, where we, where we revisit it in
73. There's no learning in
this model as written,
there's updating of the hidden states by
moving it through the B matrix.
But the A, B and D themselves do
not change. So now
they're going to talk about how learning
can come into play. So in other words,
like the A matrix is fixed in this
setting. But you might be interested in
a situation where the A matrix can
change through time. Like maybe the
mapping between hidden states and
observations changes. The way
that learning is generally approached
in Bayesian inference settings is
you make a prior distribution
on the variable of interest.
So for example,
lowercase A is going to be a hyper prior
or just a prior distribution on A.
So instead of just saying A is seven one
one like we saw in the
Music example, you can have a
distribution over what
A looks like that is going to help
with learning. In the extreme case
where learning rate converges to zero,
that's like a super sharp distribution
around what you think A is going to be
like so that you have very strong prior
on A. So new information is only going
to move that sharp distribution a tiny
amount. Conversely, if you were having
a lot of learning on A, you'd have a
very flat prior on what A could be
so that new observations would update
your beliefs about A a lot.
But this is just an example of the
composability of this framework in that
the base model doesn't have learning
attention, all these different
relatively sophisticated cognitive
phenomena. But this is
like the little firmware nugget or
kernel which by understanding the
compositionality relationships of then
we can start to bring in learning on
different parameters. And of course
learning is awesome and it sounds
awesome, it is. But if you also think
about it from a statistical perspective,
that doesn't mean that every parameter
should be learnable because sometimes
you're just increasing the computational
challenge of your problem vastly more
information on learning.
Here we see another difference
with learning between active inference
and many other machine learning
approaches. And this is the
embedding of action in the inference
process. We actively think about
how much information are we going to
get. Like when people are training an
image recognition, it just here's a
thousand images in the training set just
plug and chug. But what if you had an
agent that was like which image should I
look in of these thousands?
Then it would become of primary
importance which sequence
of learning observations the agents
took within those thousand labeled data
points. So that's what G helps
us understand some
new terms salience,
novelty, different decompositions
of G.
One final example, again, more just like
referenced because it's in other papers
but not really explained with the
matrices. Here we have a maze
exploration agent which is like another
kind of classic setting so it
has gray in the likelihood, which is
like 50 50 between white and black. But
it starts off, it takes these three
steps and it's like, okay, it's
updating, now it moves. Here updates
that. Okay, that's a white square,
that's a white square, that's a block
square, that's a block square. So this
is like somebody looking over a maze
visually seeking a path
to solve the maze.
7.3 is a little bit of a summary
of a pretty advanced topic which
is Bayesian model reduction and
structure learning which is treating the
question of what structure
should the generative model have?
Treating that question as a parametric
inference problem. So should
the model be one, two or three time
steps deep and then say, okay, well
we're going to have some time horizon
parameter and then we're going to test
whether one, two or three is the better
model. So like we're going to learn the
structure of a model as part of
reducing down from a portfolio of models
but they just sort of briefly note it
and there's more citations
and then as and then any
other just thoughts or questions. Seven
kind of has a lot of little short
vignettes.
Okay, just briefly, just so that we
touch it all, then next time we can have
voted and added a lot of questions and
everything. 712 is a two level model.
It's a nested or a hierarchical model.
Both the higher and the lower level,
one and two are discrete time.
You can tell because they all have the s
t minus one t t plus one. So later we'll
see a hierarchical model where the lower
level is continuous time and the top
level is discrete time. But in this
setting both nested levels are discrete
time. So this could be every hour and
this is 60 minutes within an hour,
every day, 24 hours within a day.
Here's a multi scale updating generative
model that's related
to sentence reading and
they've done a lot of simulation studies
of multilevel inference in reading,
like where the eyes are moving to
resolve uncertainty about the letter.
Order of letters is sought out to reduce
uncertainty about words. Order of words
in a sentence is sought out to reduce
uncertainty about semantics. Semantics
are operated on for pragmatic value.
So that's chapter seven. It's a
fairly loosely
connected sequence of discrete
time models. Several examples, starting
from the musical example, which is just
a passive inference hidden Markov model
bringing us back to the discrete
time generative model that we saw in
Figure 4.3 that's shown again in 7.3 and
then several decompositions. Of expected
free energy focusing on the Epistemic
value, especially in terms of how
getting Epistemic and Pragmatic value
unified under this G functional
allows us to approach the adaptive
finessing of exploratory and
exploitative behavior.
And again, the work is in understanding
and designing the generative models.
That's not work about work. That's
really the task itself is the systems
modeling and systems understanding,
because essentially, by saying what
these variables are, what shape these
variables are, you will have
prepared your model to run. And until
these models are defined in terms of
their dimensionality, it's not ready to
run.
Any kind of closing
thoughts, Michael? It looks like
Martin might have had to do the math
class after all.
There's so many. I mean. As will I.
There'd be so many. And and again,
like, let's try to let's explore how the
let's see how the the AI explanations
did for chapter seven math
explanations. Why would a high schooler
be interested?
Let's look at it for one of the
epistemic ones.
People can evaluate and add comments or
change the text,
but for those who are learning, and
ultimately we all are, I doubt
there are few, if any, people for
whom this equation doesn't require
contextualization and clarification and
deeper breathing. Yeah, these lines are
not it's not like, divide by two and
then do this.
It's like these are multi step
derivations. And so
going back to the accuracy minus
compression, that's the challenge of
writing a textbook accuracy minus
compression of what they had to share.
So our work is to kind of refine
that balance for ourselves.
Some of these look helpful. Some of them
don't look helpful. In terms of the AI
answers, I. Would use the word scary.
I got to run, by the way. Great. Thank
you. Yeah. Any other comments?
All right, great. Well, next time,
second discussion on chapter seven. So
we'll return and look at what questions
have been upvoted or asked. So thank you
all. Farewell. Bye.
Thank you.