Alright, hello everyone. It is week
eleven and we're in
chapter five, part two of the
active textbook group first cohort.
We'll be now turning to some of the more
direct questions on chapter five after
having more of an overview last week.
We'll also be
concluding our regular chapter
discussions for the first part of this
book. And in the coming two weeks,
we'll be having some review and
synthesis and connecting some dots,
asking overarching questions, returning
to questions that were based in a
specific chapter and hopefully people
like on their own or wherever else
they're seeing as relevant or requesting
new pages if they see something that
they want. Providing some synthesis on
this first half of the textbook, which
is the epistemic half. And then for
people who want to continue in the
textbook group, go to the onboarding
page and there's two columns
there's. Yes, for part two of cohort
one, chapter six through ten. So check
that box if you want to be included in
starting in September going through
chapters six through ten, which has like
the recipe for active models and that's
when we're going to be getting more
hands on with modeling.
Also, everyone is welcome to join
for part one, chapters one through five,
cohort two also starting in September.
So it could be a fun experience just to
get another coat of paint on the
material, play a more active role,
ask another set of questions informed by
what you've seen in the first cohort so
feel free to check those boxes and
then also keep incubating
as we head into chapter six
and beyond. In the second half of the
textbook, like the project ideas,
several of the project ideas like
related to what Mike and Noah have
added, we've started to address and
explore in the active block, for
instance, meetings on Wednesday,
especially related to cyber, physical
systems, simulations, taxonomies for
governance, these kinds of ideas.
Brock's added some great notes about
what is the ramp that gets someone to
the low road or the high road. And then
I've recorded the first chapter and the
first segments as an audiobook.
The first chapter doesn't have any
equations so it's straightforward to
read, but the subsequent chapters do
have equations, which is motivating
having the natural language
representations of the equations. So
there's still a ton of discourse
questions that can be asked why things
are one way, why things are a different
way. If it can be placed into the
equation itself, that's great. If it
needs to be somewhere else, hopefully
the space exists and people can request,
if not, but for example, when reading
the textbook, the equations can be read
this way. So those are just some of the
projects that people can look
forward to and the affordances to
continue on, which is again going to
the onboarding and participating in
first five chapters. Again cohort two or
going to continue? On with
chapters six through ten starting in
September for both of these so that we
can complete one pass of the book by the
end of the year and also probably make a
lot of progress on different project
ideas and project ideas arising as
we start to see and build templates for
the models. And also Ali has
some nice interactive notebooks, so
there will be a lot of great things
coming together. If anyone wants to
raise their hand, of course, just go for
it. Otherwise we will be continuing
with the questions
asked about Chapter Five.
Before we go to the questions, is there
any general comment that somebody wants
to add about Chapter Five?
Their reading of it, their rereading of
it, listening to the video from last
week? How is chapter Five
hitting them today's?
To kind of maybe bring that one step
closer to a specific question.
I'm not going to read this whole quote,
but this question says in the preface
they wrote in Chapter Five, we will move
from formal treatments to biological
implications of active inference.
This AIDS in mapping the abstract
computational principles of active
inference to specific neural
computations that can be executed by
physiological substrates. This is
important in forming hypotheses under
this framework and ensures that these
are answerable to measure data. In other
words, Chapter Five sets out the process
theory associated with active inference.
Is this how people saw chapter five?
Do they feel like it did something
different? Did it succeed at
making the abstract computational
principles linked or mapped to specific
neural computations executed by
physiological substrates?
Yes. Eric, first of all, I have to
apologize. Only watched half of last
week's discussion, so I may
be talking about ground that's been
covered before.
It just seems to me that I've seen many,
many papers
trying to map theories onto brain
circuitry and physiology, and I'm
not well enough. I'm only loosely
associated with neuroscience and don't
follow it very closely. So it's hard for
me to cite specific instances along the
way. I know you mentioned no Menta,
which is one of the more recent ones.
It's trying to say these are what the
layers are doing. So this
chapter to me didn't seem any
very qualitatively different from
anybody else's very hand wavy way to say
here's what the computations are all
about and here's how they map to what
brain circuitry could map to what brain
circuitry might be doing. It's all quite
hand wavy, I find, and I
guess plausible, but it's certainly
not definitive, nothing close to that.
Maybe one other comment I would
say is, again, in this chapter,
they use this word prediction in a way
that conforms to the theory. But to say
that what's happening in,
say, motor control,
where top down signals from the cortex
go down to the ganglia in the spinal
cord in order to invoke motor patterns.
To call that a prediction is, to me, a
kind of well, that's taking extreme
measures to map the concepts of the
theory onto what neurons are doing and
if the theory works out to be very
useful in some way and that's what you
have to do to make that happen.
Okay, I guess I can use that language,
but Operaria just does not seem like the
right language to use to say, yeah,
we're trying to set up some motor
patterns, set up some context and
situations for what we want the local
reflexes to be doing.
But to cast that as a prediction just
seems a little unnatural to me. So those
are my two reactions to this chapter.
Thank you.
Anyone else with a raised hand?
This is a really good point about what
the linkage or mapping is between
without going into, like, you know, is
anything physical or, et cetera, like
physical brains in their niche and any
type of equations. Would a well fitting
linear model say that the brain is a
linear model? Does a well fitting Bayes
graph imply that the brain is a Bayes
graph? Does a well fitting Bayes graph
plus a philosophical belief that we're
just making a map, we're not describing
the territory equate to what beyond
a linear model or a verbal model.
Rohan. Yeah. Building on
the previous point right. I'm still
unsure about what Active inference is,
considering a signal, there's no
effective well, there's no noise model
or it doesn't specify that here's,
because if you say that I'm predicting
something, right. So there must be
something that is substantially
different, statistically different from
some noise distribution that you can
differentiate. Right. So it's basically
trying to estimate some hidden
probabilities, which is not really a
signal. Does that make sense?
Because even the internal states,
unless they're actually instantiated
prior, like when we set up the model,
we say, okay, these are the only states
that you can actually traverse.
You still have to infer the states from
your measurements of reality.
Thank you.
Jacob? Yeah. I just want
to ask if the noise isn't kind of
implied in the
POMDP formalism,
like, I think in Figure 5.4,
where it shows the direct and indirect
pathways of message passing,
it describes Active and the basic
ganglia as a POMDP generative
model. So it's partially observable.
Doesn't that imply some kind of noise?
My counter to this would be that is
missing information that needs to be
filled out. That's not really noise.
Right. So noise would be something let's
not use this. So we have
returns of a stock, and looking at
the distribution of the prior returns,
we know what the spread is, and in case
we want to measure whether your
portfolio is substantially different
from this distribution, that's where we
would have some sort of, like, sharp
ratio or a signal noise ratio. Noise
ratio being the complete set of
distributions that are possible, the set
of ranges that are possible.
That is not really here, because that is
missing information. So we can only
observe the fact that
we have only partial observations does
not excuse the fact that we don't have
even noise models of the sensors. So how
good are the sensors, for example? Do we
have some idea of that?
Yes. Yaku, but then I'll add a point
about the Espasian terminology.
Yeah.
What's the practical difference between
partial observation where the noise
implies some kind of information that is
missing, versus a distribution that's
added to full observation that adds
noise to the sensory processing?
Great.
So if I use an actual physical sensor,
right, it would be something like
what are the ranges of values that it
can go up to? Because we've designed the
sensor, so we basically know what the
bias is, what the variance of the sensor
is under different conditions.
There are actual physical processes
implied in that measurement. So in the
case of ultrasonic sensor,
it's probably like some current value or
some voltage value that's being measured
by some circuitry somewhere. So there
are ranges for that. So there's no
missing information there. So you
basically know it's already a prior
in this system, right. So you know what
the ranges of values are going to be.
And from there you need to infer the sum
state in the world. So is there an
obstacle in the way or is there?
Okay, let me just make a comment about
some basing terminology then. Jessica
and Brock so let's look at figure 4.3.
This is the partially observable Markov
decision process that Jacob talked
about. But we're going to be just
talking about the perceptive part, not
the action intervention into how things
are changing, yet just focusing on this
motif on the left, like step by step
guide uses. So you mentioned
about the bias related to measurements.
So if the measurables are the observable
sense states, then the bias and the
covariance and the variance about how
the reading on the thermometer relates
to the underlying variable, the hidden
state, the temperature of the room,
it's embodied in the a matrix because
that is actually the learned or fixed
variable that is playing
a role of a noise model.
Then you mentioned when talking about
returns on stocks, testing whether
there's like a substantial difference
from some null expectation, like is
there a signal that's different from the
noise? This is like a frequentist
approach. It's based upon determining
whether there's some statistically
significant level. Doesn't have to be,
it's not the only way to do it, but one
can do like a p value on whether a given
signal is statistically different from
given a noise model, different from
noise. And then like, the sharp ratio
and other types of things are like
summary statistics. They're like
descriptive statistics.
Noisy measurements are addressed
in the context of the POMDP by
having an a matrix that accommodates
some of the features of denoising a
signal and then precision variables
and those precisions can again be
learned or fixed. But like the
functional aspects
of what is being referred to as noisy
measurements are accommodated within
this kind of Bayesian approach. Which is
why common filtering, generalized
Bayesian filtering, why these techniques
are used because we can have a Bayesian
update scheme implemented with
variational approaches, message passing,
sampling, all these things that does
denoise signal, and it does embody a
noise model and a signal model. And
that's all part of the generative model
of the cognitive entity. So it just
isn't being addressed from a frequentist
statistics or.
Yeah, I shouldn't have brought up the
Sharp ratio. Maybe that's not the best.
But the Sharp ratio is
effectively some way to say that some
portfolio choice is different from
others. Or in communication systems you
would use something like EB over N zero.
That's the signal to noise ratio for
any sort of communication system,
but they're not necessarily only
frequentist. Right. So there are patient
ways to estimate these things. In fact,
that's pretty much how we do it in
practice, is we don't assume that we
know the complete distribution. We
update priors in each of these cases.
Coming back to your point that the A
matrix does address this. The A matrix
would be something that you
said it would denoise and filter out
some stray observations. But okay,
the question still remains is when
you're saying prediction, is it
prediction of the signal over here?
As in what is the future state of the
sensor? But I think there, it seems
seem to indicate that the prediction
relates to the free energy minimization
itself. Right. So you choose policies
that would minimize your free energy and
keep yourself into some set point,
which means that there should be some
sort of an idea of what
ranges are there for this value or how
far can these go before you're
not in that set point anymore? So even
if you, if you do want to make that
prediction, it's, it's not just the
signal value. So signal values
effectively through the Marco blanket,
they affect some internal state. And I'm
assuming that's what we are trying to
predict, that the trajectory of. The
future internal states actually the
expectation that's being minimized
is over outcome observations, not about
internal states. Okay? Yeah. I'm sorry.
Even then,
the signals may have well defined
precision and bias, but the entire
system itself doesn't have any sort of
well, it doesn't know how wrong it can
go. It doesn't have any error estimate.
So there's no noise model. As such,
we would have to assume that there is
some distribution of states and then
then use something like lee squares or
some other optimization routine to
actually bring this in practice.
Great. Totally possible. It would be
interesting to sketch out a Bayes graph
for what you believe a signal to noise
or some type of noise model would embody
and maybe we will see some analogies
or some mappings. Jessica and then
Brock.
Hi. I think someone like what I was
going to say probably already been
covered by both you and Rohan in the new
comments. But I was going to say that
with this filtering and a lot of the
biases and things, I kind of made sense
of it.
I think it was like chapter two or
something like that. So the why is this
quote unquote thing
that we can observe from the hidden
state or the process of something that
we don't know for everybody.
We can see the same thing, but how we
process it internally is going to vary.
It's going to be very subjective. So the
why is going to look different for
Daniel than it's going to look for me
based on all this filtering. And so the
blanket states, I imagine, sort of like
what have those filters that encode the
biases and other things that allow us to
process things differently than our
generative model. It's going to be
updated differently, also encoded, I
think in the general model will be a lot
of cures and things like that that
embody, I think, probably a lot of
biases and things of how we understand
things which also influence how we
interpret what we observe.
So for me, it's like a lot of these
things are there in terms of statistics.
I don't know how much, but that's how
conceptually, I understood
a lot of these things. Basically, in the
blanket days of the Marco blanket, it
would have a lot of disfaltering.
Yes. If you're going to try
to, let's say you observe something
that's different than what you predicted
in your model, then you would take
action and to forage and find
information and to figure it out, okay,
what am I missing? Why did I make this
mistake or like this error in my
prediction so that I can have more
information and update the model so that
it aligns more closely? So then you will
basically take action to the noise and
basically get closer to the
reality that's out there. Yeah. I don't
know if this official lightning, but
that's how it kind of makes sense to me.
Thanks, Jessica Brock.
Yeah, I just wanted
to, I guess, speak to this sensor
noise model in
practice. In reality, when we're talking
about sensors, like in a physical
system, like, like a digital signal
processing kind of context, like, the
sensors are tested under some conditions
for things like jitter and spurious
kind of noise conditions and stuff
like that. But they're tested under some
conditions, meaning that
there's never ever going to be a
time when you have an actual model.
You're just going to have an
approximation whether that's expressed
in a frequentness or Bayesian way.
There's going to be some uncertainty in
the model and especially if you start
connecting it up to a larger system
doing the same. Kind of like is the
jitter in that sensor the same when
it's completely isolated as it is when
it's on a six x nine PCB board
with 12 volts
on one side and an oscillator next to
that.
Is it the same thing? You have to
do these sort of electromagnetic
compatibility resonance sort of testing
on it.
In practice it's Bayesian like you're
doing the same sort of bounding and
belief testing and
finding your errors and correcting them.
Even in practice.
I don't see how you could possibly have,
even physically a system that could
exist where you had a noise model that
you could write down that was actually
the noise model under all conditions or
yeah,
it doesn't seem like a approachable. I
don't know. It's not even not tractable,
but just a wrong thing to do.
Thanks, Brock. In the
case of engineering and designing
models, it's up to the designer or the
engineering team to understand what is
adequate or not. And for natural systems
outside of their bounds, natural
selection sweeps them off the table. So
some of the adequacy questions are
either based upon specified or
implicit human standards or the
failure to resist dissipation and
therefore the failure to realize
repeated measurement of oneself or from
the external. And then that system is no
longer let's just continue to move
through some of the questions. Yes,
Rohan. Go for it.
Yeah, I completely agree with what Brock
said. Right. But my point was,
when you say that you're predicting
something, it means that you either know
the quantity that you're trying to
predict and
it corresponds to so in this case, some
action results in some reward. I guess
you could predict the reward, but
without knowing how wrong you're going
to be in the future. So where exactly
any living system would have to be aware
of its own bounds. Right? That's what I
meant by noise model. So it has to know
that it has to stay within some bounds
and as it starts coming closer to one of
the upper or lower bounds, there should
be something like pulling it back down
or some feedback mechanism. But that is
not very clear from what I've read so
far on active inferences, how exactly
it would estimate that. You can just say
free energy minimization. But what
is a minimum in this case that would be
different for different systems? It
should have some idea of where the
surface is of whichever local surface
it's lying on. That was my point. So for
sure it's different for different
systems. It's different as every single
generative model is. And then you
mentioned like a pullback attractor.
And so this has been treated extensively
in the context of physiological
measurements and then again where those
priors on the physiological measurements
are, the Tolerable range are either
provided by the human engineering team
or through evolution by natural
selection and then the quantity.
Another related topic would be
expectation maximization models, which
is what is happening essentially in the
dialectic between the observation and
the hidden state update is an
expectation maximization like process
where it's like given the hyper priors
or we can just simplify, given the
priors on S, what are the most likely or
the distribution of observables. And
then given the observables, what should
be updated about the hidden state
priors. And when those are at
convergence, the model is stationary and
then as things change, either from the
top via learning or context shift or
through changed measurements, the
expectation maximization algorithm is
just able to track those changes. And
that can, in the context of a fixed
prior, have the function of a pullback
attractor. Okay,
and that's even before getting into
action specifically. But yes,
definitely considering the role of
comparing future plans of action and
which plans of actions will have the
least expected free energy based upon
their pragmatic and Epistemic value.
Like the Epistemic just being clarity
around how it's going to be achieved and
the pragmatic value being that KL
divergence between the expectation slash
preferences and the expected
observations. So if we expect slash
preferred to be in homeostasis, the
pragmatic value is going to come or be
loaded onto policies that keep us in
homeostasis, even if some other one is
super informative. How that model gets
tuned is quite literally the details of
how the model is trained. Right.
My point was that active inference
doesn't help us find this. We have to
find this ourselves and then hopefully
once we have instantiated these bounds,
I think active inference works very well
to keep it within this. If you can't
discover this de novo, I can't
have what you'd say table or asset
type system, like a blank slate system,
go out in the world and discover your
bounds. That's not going to happen. But
this kind of method is what I was making
it out. Whereas taking something
equivalent without any so deep learning
is another method. Right? So you
just feed it a lot of data, it doesn't
have to know anything about the data.
Eventually it forms some opinion about
the data it's seen and then it's able to
do some classification depending on how
much data it's seen. So it's able to
build certain amount of bounds. Whether
that's generalizable is a different
question. But here the
learning part does not say much about
how exactly it goes about discovering
where its limits are. That's my point.
Sure. Thank you. Eric.
I would love to dive just a little bit
more into the thing you were just
talking about, how expectation
maximization is a
mathematical formulation for how
to infer belief states from
observations. Because you basically
go through this iterative process of
trying to find alignment between the
states of the belief and the observables
and then you contract that over time
between that concept and the concept of
message passing. When I think of message
passing, I think of some sort of a
distributed system where you have some
local computation and then it sends and
you have again either synchronous or
asynchronous process for communicating
between these kind of different centers
of belief state.
And then again, through message passing,
you have often an iterative process of
convergence. So those are not the same
thing. And I think message passing, to
my understanding, would be an Em
algorithm under certain types of
messages and states at each of the nodes
that you're sending the messages around.
But not all message passing is going to
be an Em algorithm. And similarly, when
I think of Em, I don't think about
message passing. I think about making an
arrays of belief
and matrices between mapping between
belief and observations and then trying
to compute an expectation for what my
predictions would be and then making
this iterative convergence. So I don't
think of that in terms of message
passing. So I just love to hear other
people's ideas about how to tie these
two ideas together.
Yeah, Brock, if your
hand is still raised. Okay,
sorry. Yeah, all good.
Does anyone have thoughts on this?
There's a lot to say about the
expectation maximization algorithms.
And just to kind of give a little
context, this is the step by step paper.
So this is the model stream one,
it's four parts. And this is like really
a quite relevant figure, which is not in
the textbook but helps a lot.
Like this is the essence of the
partially observable Bayesian inference.
There's a prior D and then there's an a
ambiguity matrix that is mapping in
a generative capacity between hidden
states s and observation measurements O.
This is the tail of two densities
because O through A
can give you the most likely S and S
through A can give you the most likely
O. And it turns out that by alternating
those procedures in a Bayesian update
context, that two stroke engine
is called expectation maximization.
Again, because given expectations on the
summary statistics of A distribution,
the expected sensory observations can be
generated and then given those
observations, a likelihood function can
be maximized that then updates the
hidden states. So this motif, this kind
of elbow motif is then extended
into a caterpillar with this be, which
is how the hidden state changes through
time. So importantly, note what's not
there, which is like the observations
being chained through time. So it's not
that the temperature reading at one
moment influences the temperature
reading at the next moment. The
temperature readings are continually
linked, synchronously like in one
time slice to their hidden states.
So then when action gets into the
picture, we've talked about like several
sources that's like the equation 2.5 to
equation 2.6 phase change, because
action brings in several kinds of
uncertainty. First off, you're reducing
your uncertainty about observations
which haven't happened yet. You're also
having the unknown consequences of your
actions. And in order to have action
selection that's relevant, one has to
have a preference distribution over
what kinds of observations they would
like to be seeing so that action can
guide it in that direction. Okay then.
So that's the expectation maximization
two stroke engine is basically
graphically proposed
here. D is just the initiating set of
parameters and then in a one shot way,
like you can have a folder with a
thousand images and do expectation
maximization on it, or you could have
something that's dynamical and do that
type of expectation maximization through
time.
Eric asked how is it related to message
passing on graphs? So I'm
not familiar with all the details of
this model, but you basically said
it, which was that certain message
passing systems implement Em.
But of course not all message passing
architectures implement Em. So message
passing is more general than Em. Also,
Em wouldn't have to be implemented
through message passing, but there's
like an area of intersection where the
Em algorithm can be seen as a type
of message passing under certain
compute rules in a factor graph.
And Em, at least from here, may be used
to break cycles in a factor graph.
So it's always like how close to the
kernel and the Platonic ideal of active
inference are we talking? And then how
many heuristics and just ways
of connecting things are possible.
So I
will now read the chat.
That'S from previous context. Okay,
thank you.
The statistical Parametric mapping
textbook and documentation. SPM has
a lot on Em variational inference
and a lot of the parts that bring one
to understand this a lot
better. SPM is like almost like it
doesn't include action that much because
it's a neuroimaging. So the observations
are neuroimaging, sensor fusion,
different error modalities, like the
whole monopoly. And then
SPM started to incorporate participant
actions in this partially observable
metabasian way and potentially
that is what led Friston and colleagues
towards a grander synthesis of inference
and action under a
statistically principled framework.
Let's just see if there's any other
these are all important questions and
there's a lot to get up to them and then
there's like a lot to go from the
question, but these are all important
things to raise if
anyone has a thought on this. How should
we think about redundancy in neural
systems in the context of active
inference? So redundancy would be like
if there's something that's playing a
functional role but its removal is
not damaging the function of the system.
There's ten pillars knocking out one of
them, the building stays up, so there's
redundancy in the pillars. What about
the cases where the same neural circuits
serve multiple functions?
So how do we deal with the fact that
there's like a many to many potentially
or a complex mapping between system
elements and system functions where
sometimes removing node one does
nothing, but removing node one and two
does a lot of things, but then removing
one, two and three and it's going back
to being fine. Jessica.
I guess my comment is more like a
question and maybe like ask Blue about
it because this is what I feel. But this
question made me think. About. It's not
only like that the brain has this
redundancy of things, but it's
like if you have some kind of damage to
your brain, another part of your brain
that maybe was not used for something
would develop that capacity and so
it would create that ability.
Neuroplasticity brand
new even though it was not a redundancy
to begin with. So I guess I'm more
curious to understand this. So other
people who know more like Blue and stuff
about this. Basically that's kind of
what this question made me think about
and kind of wanting to understand more.
Nice. Good question. Yeah. Blue wrote,
Depends on your age. Different
neuroplasticity mechanisms are
differentially available throughout life
for different organisms.
Just one thought on this would be like
the same neural circuits serving
multiple functions might be totally the
case. For example, and is
the function of the heart to provide one
pound of weight to the torso. It is a
function of the heart. So identifying
what function is being modeled is what's
being done here. So let's just go to the
example of figure five three. This
neuron modifying it
like a loss of function experiment or
having it injured might influence more
things than just the lower motor neuron
descending message. So that'd be a case
where it serves multiple functions.
This is just one statistical model of
this function, of this circuit. And that
returns to the earliest comments of Eric
with like, okay, this is like
Tantalizingly seeming like it's actually
going to be describing the neuroanatomy.
But then they say things like note the
absence of dot dot dot dot dot dot dot.
Note that there's a discrepancy between,
for example, the reality of the anatomy
and the base graph. This highlights that
the connections implied by message
passing schemes may not manifest as
single synapses.
So, okay,
there's kind of false positives and
false negatives. The Bayes graph isn't
just the anatomy. That's fine.
The linear regression between height and
weight isn't the actual relationship
between height and weight. And the
structural equation model of inequality
is not the generator of inequality.
So it's totally fair and shouldn't be
expected to be otherwise. That the Bayes
graph, the best fitting Bayes graph,
the most didactic bays graph, the
simplest Bayes graph, none of those
recapitulate the anatomy. And the Bayes
graph that recapitulates the anatomy
would not necessarily even be the best
fitting. It's map and territory.
And if somebody has a special equation
to break through that blanket,
everybody would love to see it.
However, sometimes it's easy to gloss
over that in
principle challenge of mapping
formalisms to biological systems.
Because we see the cell and then the
blanket is the membrane and we see the
brain and it's like vision and action.
And it seems like it maps onto the
physical or the anatomical structure of
the world or the causal structure of the
world, and it
doesn't. So I hope people can add more
thoughts about how we consider
redundancy because it's a great
question,
but we'll leave it there.
How are reflexes modeled in active
inference? Would they exist in an active
inference module that is distinct from
proprioception? Would they operate on
different timescales? If anybody wants
to add some
context on it,
a reflex arc relating to where
reflex is defined as a
function that is being relayed through
the spinal cord of a mammal and not
passing. Like you could have a nerve
block in the cervical vertebra and it
still is able to implement that's one
definition of reflex. Often it's also
used slightly more broadly to mean like
stimulus action, reproducible outcomes,
but not every reflex has a perfect
reproducibility, et cetera, et cetera.
So it's kind of a continuum. Yes,
it would involve proprioceptive input.
That proprioceptive input would be
combined or juxtaposed
with the descending prediction,
resulting in an error. And then that
directionality and magnitude of the
error in this model drives the reflex.
There can also be multiple timescales,
but we haven't seen any nested modeling
yet. This is just the one
layer model.
The schematic on the left in figure
five, one shows that layer five of
cortex projects to spinal parameter
neurons. And this can be interpreted as
a prediction. Okay,
so this is this one helpful
context, and it relates
to this earlier highlighted section,
which is like it's the interpretation,
the interpretive link between some
anatomical or biological feature
phenotype and some parametric
resonance with a model.
The validity of that ranges from pretty
clear, pretty uncontroversial, pretty
useful, pretty effective,
to none of the above.
And it's hard to know what given
interpretive links are doing.
Like saying that this edge on this base
graph can be interpreted as a descending
excitatory connection or that
might be used to generate specific
testable hypotheses. Like if we measured
it during a period of excitation the
activity of this neuron, we expect it to
be increased, whereas if it was a
descending inhibitory connection, et
cetera. That's a great example of
active inference being used in in a
proactive way to generate hypotheses
about biological systems that are going
to be, as they said in the preface,
answerable to measured data.
By grounding in a computational
model that is related to the
neuroanatomy but isn't trying to be like
a digital twin of the neuroanatomy. We
can generate predictions about gain,
loss of function, different measurements
to make if they don't already exist.
And then that can be used to increase
our confidence or reliability or falsify
even a specific generative model as
proposed. So there's so much
discourse like continuing to the present
day and surely beyond, as like all these
questions and recently posted in the
Discord about active
inference or free energy principle isn't
falsifiable. Now, the funny link is
it's not falsifiable. So it's been
falsified, it can't be falsified,
so it's incorrect. That's an interesting
connection that some people make. But a
linear model cannot be falsified. A base
graph cannot be falsified. Once any
given linear model is presented in a
context with constraints for a certain
data type, then it's an empirical
question of its accuracy and adequacy
relative to other models. But at
the abstract level of a neural network
or linear model or active inference,
falsification simply doesn't apply.
But there's a lot that could be
clarified about
what are the utilities and some of the
pitfalls of mapping
biological or cyberphysical systems to
active inference models. If it's a
purely digital system or potentially
even a cyberphysical system that's been
designed a really certain way, it might
be compatible with activ like
essentially by fiat or by design.
One could make an artificial creature
like an infer ant that is implementing
active inference. One could also
model an ant in the field using a linear
model or a levee flight or some other
model or an active inference model. But
those are two very different settings.
One in which sort of the rabbit was
placed into the hat and then we have a
rabbit analyzer and the other one being
like we don't know what's in the hat,
but we have a rabbit analyzer that we
think applies to what is in this hat.
Chapter five includes some evidence
presented on different
neurotransmitters. So it'd
be interesting to see like, what other
frameworks are able to be compatible
or even provide unique explanations,
predictions, et cetera, related to
neurochemistry. Have neural networks
ever been used to derive unique
predictions or found compatibility with
neurohormones neurochemicals?
And then again, they have a final figure
in chapter five that's like a graphical
overview of several of the systems that
are described in the chapter
specifically relating to the cortical
cognitive functions and then
the dialectic between habit and
free energy driven planning here
with Dopamine as a precision modulator
with extensive further modeling
presented in other papers. And this even
more basal motor selection mechanism
based upon reflex arcs and
proprioceptive error minimization and
all of that.
We raised these questions not to offer
any answers, but to highlight some of
the exciting avenues of future research
in theoretical neurobiology. So a lot of
the questions that are asked here
in this paragraph, but also above, at
the very beginning they said we're not
saying how it is, we're just giving like
the current process model understanding.
And then especially at the end, they
raise even more speculative questions.
So that
takes us to the end of chapter five.
That's the first half of the book.
That's the epistemic component of the
book. Well, a lot of it is epistemic,
but that's the first five chapters.
The second five chapters, which are
longer partially because of having
more figures and things like that. But
you can see there's more pages slightly
in the second part of the book, though
we've also read at least some of
the appendices.
That's where we're heading, which is
picking up on chapter six
in just a few weeks with a recipe for
designing active inference models. So
for those who stuck with the uncertainty
for the first five chapters and stay in
the game, more will become clear when
the recipe for the dish is seen. And
then more will be clarified when
the dish is prepared, and then when you
cut the vegetables, and then when you
design the dish and the recipe and all
of that. And that's like a journey that
we're all going to be on. The tools are
not finalized and the kitchen is not
completed, et cetera, et cetera, et
cetera. So it's
just a call for us to go to Onboarding
and indicate our interest in continuing
with one or the other cohort or sharing
with any colleagues who you think might
like to jump in to the second cohort of
part one. And then in the coming two
weeks, we'll be able to take a
step back, look over the chapter
questions, but also think about more
general questions that we're having.
Basic questions, meso questions,
advanced questions, research avenues,
and also turn to the project ideas where
multiple of these are already active and
there's spaces for people who want to
facilitate or catalyze some other
direction. So fun
meeting everyone's.
Welcome to stay on for
Tools or head up to a room above if they
just want to talk to other people about
anything else. So thanks again for
joining and see you in just a few
minutes for Tools.