All right, hello everyone. Welcome.
This is ActInf livestream number 51 one.
We are in the second discussion of this
paper, canonical Neural Networks perform
Active Inference. Welcome to the active
inference institute. We're a
participatory online institute that is
communication, learning and practicing
applied active inference. You can find
us on this slide and this is recorded
in an archived livestream. So please
provide us feedback so we can improve
our work. All backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome and we'll
follow good video etiquette for live
streams, head over active inference.org
to learn more about the institute and
how to participate in projects and
learning groups. All right,
we're in ActInf livestream number 51
one, and having our first
nonsolo discussion on this paper,
canonical Neural Networks perform active
inference and really appreciative that
you've joined today. It's going to be a
great discussion. We'll begin with
introductions. I'll say hello and then
please just jump in however you'd like.
And we can start by setting some
context. So I'm Daniel, I'm a researcher
in California, and I was interested in
this paper because we've been talking a
lot about active inference from a
variety of different perspectives, from
the more fundamental math and physics to
some applications, philosophy,
embodiment, all these really interesting
threads. And this paper seems to make a
really clear meaningful contribution and
connection by connecting active
inference entities and this approach of
modeling to neural networks which are in
daily use globally. So thought it was a
fascinating connection and really
appreciate that we can talk about this
today. So to you and welcome.
Go forward, Takuya, however you'd like
to introduce and say hello. Yeah.
Hi. I'm Tafia Isomura, neuroscientist in
Lique Brain Science Institute in Japan.
I'm particularly interested in universal
characterization of neural network and
brain using mathematical techniques. So
this work I believe important
as a link between active brain forest
aspect, Bayesian aspect of the brain,
and the dynamics system aspect of the
neural network. So I'm very happy to
join this discussion session. Thank you
for invitation. Nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you as well.
The first thing you added, the universal
characterization of neural networks.
What is the universal characterization
of neural networks? Why is it being
pursued in this area of research?
So, as a narrow sense,
my gain aim
of this paper is that so, you know,
people active inference lab
communication to characterize brain
activity, behavior, so on, so on,
but which would be different from
conventional neural network. So there is
a crossover program which is
associated with conventional neural
network and it is not very clear whether
all characterization of computational
neural network can be explained by
activity infrastructure principle or
not. So here universal characterization
means that characterization of every
aspect of conventional neural network
which is a kind of dynamics system
derived as association between
biological phenomena and simple
mathematics. Car formula using gift
card, using differential equations as
the broad sense. I think universal
characterization means that well,
it is a characterization of brain
intelligence, but it's a big picture and
the paper particular address is only one
aspect of the Bull picture.
All right? So it'll be great
to pull back to really understand what
synthesis is happening. So I'm going to
ask what makes a neural network model a
neural network model and what makes
active inference lab model an active
inference model? Is this synthesis and
connection you've made true? Because of
what?
Because basically what we
show is the mathematical
equivalence between the formulation of
canonical neural networks and the
formulation active inference lab in the
sense that we show that as possible
neural networks can be characterized by
minimization of some biological
plausible cost function. And we show
that that cost function can be least as
variational based on inference and a
particular cross of gentlemen model in
terms of well known partially observable
position process.
Alright, shall we perhaps
walk through some of the sections of
the paper? It would be awesome. Just for
each of these sections, maybe the
numbered and the lettered sections.
What does the section aim to show and
why was it there in the paper?
Briefly it's
over, right? So briefly.
So first we introduce
so the gain issue main program,
our interest, which is relationship.
We try to make a formal ring between
neural network and active reinforcements
that gain program background.
And then we first formulate
the equivalence, mathematical
equivalence, in a very Brea manner. So
in the first section in results,
we formulate the
relationship using complete
craft serum, which is well known
statistical theorem proposed very
long time ago. And using
that we link a
general form of neural network with a
general form of variational data
impress. But a problem is
that this characterization does not
address a specific generative model
which is crucial to characterize a
specific model, specific neural network
dynamics. So in the following sections,
we characterize the problem
using Pomodb or partially observable
Markosition process and link that
model with a particular class force
canonical neural network.
And then we simulated we
use the simulation to propagate
that property in terms of some major
tasks.
All right, thank you for this.
Could we talk about the complete class
theorem? So what is the scope of the
complete class theorem and why
was it the relevant set of the neural
networks to pursue or the right way to
frame it? Thank you for asking that.
So I like the slide you
showed last week's video.
So computer cross theorem basically
indicates the relationship between some
crossover decision rule and vision in
France. Here a crucial keyword
is admissible decision
rule, which is a rule which is
as good as other decision
rules or at least at
one point better than other
decision rules. So simply speaking,
adomissibility indicates in some sense
it is the best rule for some aspect.
And usually we characterize such a
goodness using cost function,
loss function or risk function.
And here what we did is we
established some association with this
type of loss function or risk function
with canonical
neural network which is we call cost
function or biotic roles Costa function
or neural network. So our assumption is
that neural network minimize cost
function. So if it active the
inclination and it is virusly
active some sort of optimality so we can
say it is adommissible with respect to
that cost function. So the
beauty of complete cross theorem is that
if we find some admissible decision
rule then automatically we can say that
it is based on inference in
terms of some Bayesian Costa function
with gentlemen model a priori beliefs.
So this computer chaos theorem is
crucial as abstract characterization
of the relationship between conventional
neural network architecture, dynamics
and variational. Beijing influence.
All right, thank you.
What does it mean when you said it was
biologically plausible of a loss
function? The term is a
little bit arbitrary because in this
paper we mean by probability
in the sense that this neural network
model can be derived from realistic
neural model through some approximation.
And so here barricade probability,
suggest means probability
as a neural model or synaptic processing
model. And if this cost
function loss function can derive such a
plausible algorithm, then we can say
that this cost function is barely
plausible.
So what is the distinction between those
neural and synaptic components in the
loss function or what equation to look
at? You mean distinction between
dynamics and synaptic? Yeah. What is the
distinction between them and how is it
represented in the equations?
Okay, basically neuropathivity
equation means differentiate equation
about a variable that represents firing
intensity or some sort of
variables associated with the firing.
On the other hand,
dusty equation means an update
rule about the synaptic weight or
synaptic strengths which is
a connection between two neurons.
And beauty of
this formulation proposed in this paper
is that we characterize both heuristic
equations synaptic procedure equations
in terms of gradient
descent on a same cost function,
common cost function. So we
can say that if we
consider the partial derivative of
some cost function with respect to new
activity, then it's derived by gradient
descent rule about if
we consider a partial derivative of
chaos function errors with respect to
synaptic weights, then we derive a
prosthesis rule.
Are those the only two aspects of a
neural network or why are those the two
key aspects?
It is a main, I think
it's the main body
of the neural activity. If we consider
some inference running or
action exhibit by neural networks
in the sense that neural activity
correspond to fast dynamics, fast
gradient dynamics mix and
scientific processes indicate through
dynamics that minimize least function
and cost function. But in general, we
can consider any aspects, any variables
associated with your method. For
example, at least what we show in the
paper is any free parameter which may be
associated with firing threshold or
although we don't discuss in this paper
it would be possible to add other
variables related to neural network.
For example, here we ignored
contribution of Griad factor but
it would be possible to add the Griar
factor in this correlation or any other
aspect of virus corporate neural
network.
That's very interesting and it
speaks also to a general separation
of time scales. For example in
different multi scale systems or in the
renormalization group where it's
describing some minimal multi
time scale system where the faster time
scale can be seen as perception like a
slower time scale can be seen as more
learning like. And then in some
hierarchical model what's learning of
one time scale can be perceptual for a
slower time scale? So it's a very nice
generalization.
Are there any examples of decision rules
that will help us think about the action
components of what the neural network is
doing? Because it may be more familiar
to think about digit characterization
and image classification, some kind of
classical tasks for neural networks.
But how does the decision rule play out
in the context of neural networks?
Okay, so in this paper
we basically assume a closed loop so
comprising a neural network part and
environmental part. So Neuron receives
sensor input from environment and
provide some feedback to the
environment.
Even with the example of classification,
we can say that output correspond to
classification output,
which is kind of generative model
relevant. Example would be, for example,
controlling agent like a robot control
or any kind of control errors.
Decision making tasks. For example,
when we encounter some
choice tasks, we need to advertise,
for example, left or right or something.
Any kind of such a decision can
be associated with the admissibility or
admissible decision.
So what would an example of an
inadmissible or admissible strategy
be in the decision making task?
Admissibility usually characterized
by loss function or risk function.
Here admissivity indicates that
there is another decision rule which is
at least one point better
than the forecast decision
rule. Simply speaking
in Adobe CBD indicates that decision
rule is not good
relatively. Let's just say our decision
rule is we always turn right. Is that an
example of a decision rule? Because
there might be settings where that is
strictly effective and the simplest rule
whereas there's other settings where
that's going to be tragic. So what does
it mean to be admissible for an agent in
light of different environmental
contexts? That's an interesting
point. So even with such
a too much simplified
rule it can be admissible
under some particular situation,
particular loss function. For example,
the rulers that always turn right maybe
the best under some situation,
right? So the
relationship of admissibility or enough
adommissibility depends on both agent
characteristics and environmental
characteristics.
What aspects of the environment.
For example? For example,
if that decision group matches
the structure architecture of
environment then maybe
that decision always downright active
the shortest past under some
situation, some environment.
How does this admissibility help us
think about like overfitting and how
does it help us think about the way that
different practices are used for neural
networks to prevent them from being over
fit in practice?
Well,
strictly admissivity is characterized
with the Bayesian risk.
We cannot observe a hidden states of
the environment, only we can observe is
a part of the entire universe.
So the question is an important
question is what is the best choice
under such a limited information?
Limited information?
So this Bayesian list adoissibility
or computer credit theorem tell
us that well
known, only the well known
Bayesian framework achieved
the adommissible
decision. Which means that in
this aspects Bayesian optimization give
us a least choice strategy, otherwise we
overfit or find
the suboptima evolution.
So it's a nice association, nice linkage
between the decision, but is a good
decision about the decision and more
established statistical inference.
Freedom work.
Thank you, that's very helpful.
So we're reducing our
uncertainty and risk about hidden
states in the environment. So in the
special case where the entire
environment is observable without errors
like a chess game, then there's
an equivalence between correlation of
risk or loss on observables or on
hidden states. But they're not really
hidden, but they are environmental
states. Whereas any amount
of uncertainty in the mapping
between observations and hidden states,
which is usually shown as a in the
partially observable Markov decision
process, any amount of uncertainty about
unobserved or partially observed
environmental states enables
you to fit your uncertainty optimally
about that hidden state and
fit that uncertainty simply with
the gradient descent. And by doing so,
you don't overfit a model of
observables,
which might be the fallacy or the issue
with simply doing descriptive statistics
you might get an infinitely small
variance with a frequentist estimate
because you have 1000 data points. So
the variance from a descriptive
statistics perspective might be very
small.
I think it speaks very much to why
neural networks are useful in practice
from training with limited data sets
because that's an empirical observation
that they don't entirely over fit. But
also I'm sure there's ways to construct
them that are overfit.
Yeah,
overfit will occur if we select
some optimal priorities. For example.
Well, I'm not sure if it
is overfit in the
sense what you mentioned because if
we select some priorities then the
Bayesian function itself changes and the
neural networks that try to fit to that
Costa function. So cost function
minimization will be achieved agent
such a situation. But that solution is
not good for our
original help us. That's the tricky
part. Yeah, that is reminiscent
of some discussions we've had discussing
like driving off a cliff or blowing up
is also reducing free energy. Like
dropping up a building reduces your
potential energy. And so there are
potentially decisionmaking or strategic
trajectories that do for some time
horizon minimize free energy,
perhaps even or maybe even guaranteed
better than some longer time horizon.
Because if the shortterm strategies were
somehow better than the longterm
horizon. It would be difficult to
imagine because the long term horizon
would be at least as good as a shortterm
strategy. So that speaks to the
challenges of planning in action.
So how is planning addressed in modern
neural networks and how does this work
help us think about that?
That's another very important aspect.
I have to say that this framework
addresses planning aspect,
but that planning is not necessarily
the optimal
solution in the sense that what we
interested in is optimization or
learning under limited structure.
The structure is characterized by here
Prosperia neural networks.
So yeah, planning occurred
by association between risk
in the future and our decision
in the past. Here we model that aspects
using delayed moderation
of scientific activity mediated
by some neuromodurator or
neurotransmitters. This is
the model.
This is model as the
risk factor and the heavy product
holding the neural
network.
All right, I'm going to ask a great
question from the chat and then we'll
look at the figures a little closer. So
ML Don wrote a question stuck in
my mind for a long time. Could you
please put it to rest? Do we need to
have knowledge about all states possible
actions and sensory inputs for active
inference?
Well,
you mean if you seek the exact
solution, exact optimal solution, then
maybe more information would help you
to find that. But under some
ideal assumptions then the
is not necessary to achieve the optimal
solution. I'm not sure if
I correctly answer your point.
So just to restate it.
Of course, knowing all the state's
possible actions and sensory inputs,
it's not a bad thing. Worst case,
there's some computational complexity,
trade offs, but the problem becomes
fully stateable. But I
think ML Dawn is asking about cases
where you don't know all of the state
spaces or potentially even the dimension
or the semantics of hidden
states, active states, sensory inputs
and why not even add cognitive states?
So in not just partially observed but
partially known state spaces,
how are these address in neural networks
and how does active inference help us
think about it?
Okay, I think the question
is about how can we separate
those states?
Like sensory function interface
entorhinal,
how can. We separate not just in
principle have these states be
separated, but deal with the fact that
some of these states we might have good
knowledge on and some states like the
hidden states we might not even know,
like we don't know the dimension of the
cause vector in the world. I see.
In terms of dimension,
there is a statistical technique to
estimate the dimensionality, for example
via information criteria like I
agent information criteria, based
information criteria, all them try to
info estimate plausible dimension
about the environmental hidden
states. There is an analogy with
those information criteria and version
of free energy minimization. So with
version of free energy inclination we
can identify the plausible model
structure which in principle involves
the dimension aspect.
But in terms of Neural network in
this paper we don't carefully consider
about the dimensionality optimization
because we first define the
number of neurons and don't change
during the training. But in principle
we can consider the
change in the number of neurons which is
associated with the neurogenesis
adult neurogenesis or development during
the developmental stage.
That would be an important expansion
of this direction.
That's very interesting.
Here's a remark.
Well, one note is equation
one summarizes a lot of what you've
been describing. There's a parallelism
or a concordance being drawn between the
loss function of Neural networks and the
variational free energy of the
parameterized model there.
So to come back to these processes
that influence learning which we could
think of as the Neural network becoming
more fit from a loss function
perspective or the variational Bayesian
partially Observable Markov decision
process entity generative model encoding
better at doing what it does. So there's
the firing rate on the Neural network
side, the synaptic plasticity at a
slower time scale which we discussed a
little earlier. And then now there's a
third time scale with the
birth and death of new cells and maybe
even new layers.
And that kind of multiscale
temporal structuring is
not intrinsic to the Bayes graph
to represent multiple nested timescales
in a Bayesian graph in the act of
inference literature it's more common to
make a hierarchically nested model,
right? And just say that the time
handling on one level is happening more
rapidly with respect to clock time than
deeper nested, slower models. Whereas
the Neural formulation allows
us to deal with multiple ongoing
active states without appealing to
hierarchical nesting,
which is a very important feature.
Well, both distinctions
will be possible. So without
hierarchical or with
higher car modeling so even with
hierarchical modeling, the optimization
of dimensionality should be
possible. It would be possible. But in
other distinctions we can consider
that a population of Neural models
so one has a single layer,
another has two layers,
three layers, four layers. And consider
the probability of network
architectures associated
with Costa
minimization and a particular
environment which is in principle have
the same computational architectures
with the hierarchy model.
Very interesting. Yes, perhaps I
over generalized or speculated because I
thought about how one could have a
100 timestep POMDP that
also performs multiscale behavior
potentially extremely wastefully, but at
least it could in principle. And
similarly, within a neuron there could
be another Neural network or
some other structure approximated by
that. So they almost both enable
hierarchical and non hierarchical model
modeling as you described, but in very
different ways that
lead to very different implementations.
Yes. I think this brings us
to the topic of forward and reverse
engineering. So you talked a lot about
reverse engineering.
What is reverse engineering and what is
forward engineering and what has
been done in these areas of engineering?
Okay, I'm not
an expert in this
process, but I believe that liver
here means your
characterization of the blueprint
of some device or machine
from data observable information like
activity or action behavior
of some agent. Goal is
identification of blueprint and
the crucially here blueprint correspond
to generative models because once we
define generative model, we can Deneve
evolution, anthropology algorithm,
running inference algorithm and any
behavior of the agent. So here
reverse means that we
first observe some activity of agent
and its mechanism is still unknown for
us, but we can estimate
its mechanism using that
activity by identifying the most
plausible guarantee
model which can minimize some
Costa function or risk
function when we feed
the data to the
model. So, on the other hand, for the
engineering would be more mainstream,
way fast defined model blueprint gently
model then drive everything
including parasite functional running
algorithms and behavior action
prediction algorithm.
So, by reverse engineering neural
networks, we're observing some
already parameterized neural network and
then fitting a POMDP to
it. To what extent
is it possible to take a given POMDP and
create a neural network that performs
that inference?
Okay, in this paper or
in the following paper, what we
consider is a strategy that we
first feed empirical data whether
force neural response data to BioScale
prosper neural network model
which is similar to a conventional model
fitting approach where we have
differential equation data and
differential equation to explain the
behavior with the minimum
prediction. So now,
a virtue of this framework we
established is that we
can naturally transform such neural
network architecture with the
very known partially observable markup
action process architecture.
Because for any kind of canonical neural
network there is a cost function.
So we Deneve cost function through
neuroactive decision which is opposite
with the conventional way we define cost
function derived algorithm and then we
use the formal equivalence
between neural network Costa function
and variant queen energy. So now
transform the journal architecture to
Beijing model architectures and once
we characterize vital energy,
there should be some
general that define
that informational energy functional.
So in
particular, in this example,
canon network nicely correspond to well
known across macquarlin
process. So, by using this
procedure, we identify a
plausible home DP architecture
which correspond
to observed activity data.
Well, let's stay on
this last point.
So, after all those transformations,
first the measurements of neurons
using that data to fit the neural
network and then by virtue of
the relationships unpacked in the paper,
transforming the neural network in
the left side of figure one into a
particular form of the P-O-M DP.
So first, what are the constraints on
that form of the P-O-M DP? Is this a
little corner of model space or what are
the space of acceptable P-O-M DPS?
That totally depends on what kind of
neural network model you are
considering. So for example,
in this paper we discussed about a
particular crossover from DP in
which each state takes either
zero or one. So it's very restricted
compared to the general form of homedp.
But we consider a factorization
so in the sense that although each
but we consider a vector of observation,
a vector of hidden states where each
element correspond to one
single one hot vector but as an entire
state it can represent
high dimension discrete state space.
And this architectures nicely correspond
to neural network architectures because
usually each neuron takes either zero
one or some value continuous
variable between zero and one.
So we use this association
to characterize a particular OMDP which
correspond to neural networks,
and this follows a
particular mini field approximation,
approximation or approximation in
generative model because we associate
posterior belief in this particular homo
DP with the neural activity,
which means that posterior of
action also has a factorization
architecture in the sense that we
don't fully consider about the second
order statistics between neurons
activity and activity, which is outside
of this poem. RASM.
So each
neuron activity correspond to posterior
expectation about a particular element
of the state and we don't consider the
joint posterior property of all state.
So although this is a implication,
we see this Asia
impress, but otherwise,
for example, we can consider any
recurrent network architectures which
correspond to state to transition
metrics and it would be
possible to extend this architecture to
higher call structure in the sense that
it is straightforward.
Consider a tree structure or any kind of
higher car structure by assumptions that
some neurons connect to other neuron but
not connect to other neurons.
So this is Lamme as considering the
higher car structure in general.
That's very interesting.
It's commonly remarked in the
base graphs that they represent
the connections amongst random variables
and there's a relationship between their
computability and their sparsity.
The sparsity structure as in which
variables do or do not influence each
other makes the problem tractable
through factorization and just kind of
conceptually like if every one of a
thousand variables or an unknown number
of large variables if it was all by all
the number of parameters to fit on that
connectivity matrix would be very high.
So statistical power would be very low
for any given edge. Whereas the more and
more constrained you make the
connectivity of the variables, the more
statistical power you have to resolve or
kind of spend on fitting those edges
like in a structural equation. But you
might be losing sight of the unknown
unknowns by constraining yourself to a
very limited or fallacious
topology of the variables. So there's
this kind of structure learning
statistical inference question in the
Bayes graphs then on
the neural side from the biological much
of neuroscience is about understanding
how the firing rate,
connectivity patterns and other factors
Hohwy the structure of those neural
systems and their function like form and
function enable adequate
inference and inference on action.
So it's like in both of those areas
or really like in neural network
artificial and neural networks
and in variational. DAGs the discussion
is about how the structure and the
fine tuning work together to
generate function and about some of the
statistical or biological challenges of
balancing different needs while also
constraining the cost in terms of
materials and biometabolism.
So it's a very rich interoception
that is being explored here.
If these models can really be moving
back and forth.
In the sense that back and forth.
Moving back and forth, like there's some
imprints of the model that is
implementation independent or like some
interlingua or some semantics or
compatibility, I don't really know. I
mean, that's something we can explore is
like what is it that is such that one
could forward engineer and then reverse
engineer and have like kind of
an expectation maximization between
these two areas. So what is it that's
being solved?
Yes,
important point,
for example, about you is
that we can use the knowledge of
Bayesian inference to explain your
activity dynamics, which is
crucial because people often say that
characterizing neurodynamics is no
straightforward,
we may obtain some solution on your net
dynamics, but the meaning of that
dynamics in terms of the functional
aspect is very unclear. We don't know
the meaning of connectivity strength
matrices and what is the learning of the
threshold factor, so on and so on those
de Vries from
the modern physiological phenomena.
But it is not necessary to have
clear linkage to functional exploration.
So explanation of function of the brain.
But once we transform translate
this dynamics into Bayesian inference,
then we can explain every functional
aspect of the neural network diagrams
architecture in terms of where
established Bayesian inference under a
particular crossover Bayesian model, in
this case palm DP model.
So now it turns out that
synaptic strength correspond to a matrix
B matrix, which are very established
culture meaning. So yeah,
this is useful to explain neuronsynatic
property in terms
of established statistics.
Also, for the people in active inference
lab site, it would be helpful to
understand the neuronounce master
straight about particular
active interface model model.
So I think it related to forward
modeling. But finally to discuss with
discuss about the border service rate
of that forward model, we need to
address the neural network architecture
service property. So in
that case, we can transform
a particular force DP invasion modeling
to a neural network architecture using
this relationship and then get
prediction about the substrate.
So if we have this based on model,
this particular quantity in this model
should be it
would be possible using.
Oh, it's all good. Can you just repeat
the last 20 seconds? Yes.
So in the last part I mentioned
about first we define
the Bayesian model and then can predict
what is the neural net substrates that
correspond to that particular
Beijing model. So this will be useful
to identify the biological
quantities that correspond to a
quantity in Beijing. Chaos.
There's a lot there.
It makes me think about the inference
of implementation and. Heuristics in the
computational setting, which is often in
the extreme disembodied, and the
biological setting, which is in the
extreme entirely embodied.
And for a given generative model,
the kinds of computational heuristics
that can be applied include a
whole host of different strategies
ranging from sampling to tree
exploration and branching to
paralyzing the data architectures
and all these other kinds of disparate
strategies and software
packages and implementations.
But on the biological side,
what is needed is something that's
very simple but also very
inscrutable, which is a given
pattern of interactions must
embody that calculation.
So that might mean that
it can add three digit numbers, but it
can't add two digit numbers under some
constraints. But what isn't
accessible to that kind of
morphological, biological or like form
and functional computing, what's not
accessible are the tree branching,
the database decentralization,
like they're a different set of
heuristics. Right. But they're both very
useful when we're thinking about making
sentience artifacts or benefiting
simply from the explainability across
both sides of this figure.
Yeah. So you now address an important
point. So Homistry, it is very
nontrivial whether there is a
corresponding valve car architecture
force any given Bayesian architectures.
I believe it is impossible to design
biography architectures to respond to
arbitrary Bayesian architectures.
So only a limited aspect of
region model can be implemented
in a vertical plausible manner. And that
point is crucial as capitalization of
biological network. Biological brain.
Yeah. Wow. Well, just to kind of
touch again on this forward in reverse
engineering.
For. A given POMDP if we're
willing to compose it within a certain
class, which might be quite general
still, but some class of PMDP,
as written. On the paper. We may
be able to have a neural network
architecture that would be very amenable
to deep learning, low energy computing,
pretraining various features.
And then on the other side, for a given
artificial neural network that we come
across in the wild or
a model of neural dynamics that
we fit using a neural network model.
So something in a neuroscience
laboratory that model
can have interpretability corresponding
to the variables of a given
POMDP. And just to kind of give one more
point on how that's going deeper than,
for example, statistical parametric
mapping SPM. So let's just
assume that the neural network we're
dealing with is fit from brain data
from some lucky Kant,
right? Now, what would be possible or
prior to this line of work or without
this line of work, one could fit
a neural dynamics model and then do
all kinds of analyses, like power
analyses on the different frequency
spectra and say, look at the average
firing rate or the correlation
coefficients of firing rate. So fit the
firing rates and the synaptic
Plasticities and store all that data.
And then we could just pick a POMDP
that we've seen in the literature
without any reference to the neural
network and optimize the POMDP.
And then we could say well, it turns out
that when the POMDP o is high there's
increased theta power in this firing
pattern. So it's like comparing the
descriptive statistics from the neural
model to the descriptive summary
statistics of the POMDP decision making
model. However, with this formal
connection there is actually an
interpretability to the unobserved
neural states which are what are being
inferred from the fMRI measurement,
from the EEG measurements and so on.
Those underlying variables have a
specific interpretability in
relationship to the structure of the
P-O-M DP.
Right? So yeah, that's also
very interesting important aspect.
So what
you said is I think more conventional
strategy and it is
also formally related to model
comparison aspect. So we usually think
various modeling and identify or select
what is the best model
to explain a given data.
And this reverse engineering idea
involves such a model comparison
aspect in the sense that we try
to find the model with the best
expandability which should we have
the identical functionality,
right directory
address, the exact same Costa
function architectures using the
information natural transformation. So
it should be up to explain
the neural data in the Bayesian sense.
Yeah, one can imagine how
that would transform the way that
current neuroimaging studies and
technologies describe what
it is about the measurement that
provides information about the cognition
model. So, to give another related
example, let's just say a person was
wearing an EEG headset and
a previous study had shown that
increased alphaband activity was
associated with this behavior.
That's comparing a descriptive statistic
of the observations of the sensor
and correlating the summarized
observable to some other
variable like anxiety or performance on
a behavior. In contrast,
an unobserved variable in this
setting the actual underlying
neural state is being correlated to
some semantic generative
models component.
So it's no longer necessarily that any
single frequency band would be
associated more or less with a given
outcome, but it's actually some hidden
state variability
which gains the interpretability across
this transformation. Which is a subtle
point, but it speaks to how broadly
the equivalents would reinterpret
empirical neuroimaging results as
well as a variety of artificial neural
network experiments and diagnostics
where people do lesion studies and
double knockouts on artificial neural
networks.
So anywhere where
somebody with awareness sees that a
neural network, artificial or
biological, is having summary features
described and correlated to something
that's more semantic in a quest
for meaning may now have a
different approach that involves
formalizing. The model explicitly in
terms of unobserved hidden states
with a cost function akin to
a variational free energy minimizing
risk bounding surprise on the
Unobservables. So even though the
unobservables were modeled in a
sense in the other conventional
strategy like neural activity is
a variable in fMRI
experiments, it's underlying the bold
signal. Yet this formalism
concordance is a more coherent
and powerful connection.
Lib sold. So you now
address this very important point.
So first to address
that so we need to clarify about
what is a program,
consider here. So this is a
program Socalled metabasian problem in
the sense that researchers try to infer
or estimate neuro activity or
brain activity which infer the
external world dynamics. Right. So
neuron or brain environment and we
research brain activity.
So there are two step processes.
So this sort of meta Bay is
quite tricky intractable because
sometimes London
variable becomes posterior about
other aspects. So I
think there is some established approach
about metabolism. But this
paper provides some alternative in the
sense that we separate two programs by
saying that here what we
import is simply neural
network dynamics which is shown in the
left hand side of this figure.
So we feed data to conventional
neural network model which is a simple
differential creation. But thanks to
this formal recovery between neural
network dynamics and home VP behavior,
then we can transform the resulting
neural network architectures or dynamics
into the page and in force
in some sense post Hog mana.
So we nicely avoid the
directory addressing the meta agent
program but obtain the same kind of
solution in that sense.
Yes, with combining with brain activity
recording Lieke de Boer imaging.
Yeah, we can estimate
a plausible neural network model in
the right hand side and we can transform
that to home DB in the right hand side.
Awesome. I'm going to show an image and
ask a question from Dave in the chat.
So, Dave made this image,
it's the right side of figure one that
we've just been looking at with the
variational Bayesian information and he
wrote the arc shown as impinging on the
S self arc. Is this
intentional? If so, it could represent
tuning or modulation of the feedback of
S into itself.
Do you have a thought on this? It's
attention? Yes. I think it's related
to the usual formulation of
home DP architecture and active
inference concept in the sense that
our decision or policy in
the usual setting modify the
state transition matrix b matrix.
Here, delta is an alternative of policy
of agent. So basically the
director indicates stated
transition metrics under a particular
decision which agent made.
In that sense, what the agent changes
is state transition metrics, not state
itself directly. That's why we use this
illustration.
Awesome. Very subtle
but important point, which is when we
look at the classical POMDP formulation.
So here we'll look at a version shown in
figure two. I'll just bring just figure
two in.
Could you describe what you just did
about the role of the B matrix in
influencing how hidden states change and
how that is where our policies have
impact? And also please, how do the
top and the bottom of figure two differ?
Okay, so in the usual correlation
under active inference
with palm DB structure. So we for us
to consider the
prior inference and depending
on the prior preference, we compute
the expect free energy and its
minimization provide the policy and
the policy moderate state
transition. So now in the
upper Brea, we instead use
the builder which is the
option of the agent.
So here option or decision was
made for each timestep
so that unlike the conventional
formation, we have a sequence
of delta and for each time
step delta moderates active states
cognition matrix B. So B is a matrix
that transformed hidden
state in the previous step to the
current time step and its moderation
indicate that under a specific decision
rule. For example,
if this F indicates our
cognition in the virtual environment
with the Gold decision move
forward. But if we choose the
no go decision, then it
unchanged. So such a moderation
of state transition was made by choosing
debuta and the lower part correspond
to Beijing inference made by Bayesian
agent. So basically there
is a symmetry between a third part and
roar part because we assume that
this Beijing agent has a plausible
guarantee model which nicely correspond
to given environment defined in
the above upper
part in this figure. But one
interesting thing
asymmetry is that to
model this particular canonical neural
network, we don't consider an
arrow or link from delta posteria
to S posteria which is
in the environment data
moderate S
in the next step through P matrix
moderation. In this particular Bay
jets which formally correspond to a
canonical neural network, we don't
consider that it is correspond to
an absence of the projection
from output layer to the
middle layer.
Okay.
This is from the 2020
paper, but it shows the neural network
architectures, the two layer
architectures. So could you restate
the top and the bottom of figure two in
the 22 paper and connect it to why it's
important that you're studying two layer
neural network models? I miss you.
Yeah, can you just connect the
asymmetry between the top and the
bottom on figure two with the
two layer neural network architectures?
You said that the asymmetry, there's no
direct link between.
This is another story. So in
the previous paper there
is only output or concept
layer because we basically consider a
single layer feedforward network. So my
apologies for some confusion about the
network architectures in the 2020
paper. So now upper part of
this network architectures correspond to
environmental generative process and
only a lower part correspond to single
foot feed for neural network
architectures. So now this
part is identical to
a map from O to S.
OSS area in the 2022 papers.
Okay, so on the top of figure two
is the actual generative process.
It's the true structure of causation in
the environment, which is to say that
actions delta actually
influence how states change through time
via B delta.
The generative process through the A
matrix emits observations,
sequences of observations.
And here on the bottom with
a mirrored structure
is the generative model of the entity.
So what's the relevance of the arrows
and the more force factor graph
structure on the bottom?
The arrow indicates active
inference.
So it's a flow of the information
in the sense that to calculate in
the step two, we use the information
of step two conversation and step
one's posterior expectation about hidden
states. So those two determine the
s two's expectation.
Usually in the following graph, we
consider retrospective arrow
so in the sense that s three also affect
the s two inference. But this
corresponds to Bayesian smoother in
the sense that we update every time step
simultaneously to better inference.
However, what we consider here is more
filtering approach in the sense that for
each step we compute the latest hidden
states and then we don't change any
other states in the past.
So that's why we don't consider the
arrow from future to the
past.
Awesome. Yeah. Just to highlight that in
the Bayesian smoothing approach, it's
kind of like fitting a spline because it
takes the whole time series and it fits
the smoothest possible line
or the line whose smoothness is on the
AIC BIC frontier.
But here on the bottom with the
almost pseudocode implementation
provided by the Force Factor graph,
which was demonstrated to be equivalent
with the Bayesian graph in the
2017 work with Friston, Par and de
Vries. This architectures is
reflecting a filtering scheme like a
common filter or just generalized
Bayesian filtering through time, where
estimates are being carried forward and
changed time point to time point,
such that the decision rules, or the
updates perhaps more accurately, are
defined between time points. And the
total time series does not have to be
loaded into memory or remembered at
once. And then the Bayesian filtering
approach has the asymmetry
with a different consideration of
action. So why again
is it that action is considered
differently in the Bayesian filtering
approach on the bottom of the generative
models than the consideration of action
in the generative process.
That correspond to lack
of cognition from Y to X
in the figure one?
Or probably a figure four
is helpful to that
relationship.
Four? Yeah. This is an example
network architecture comprising input
Brea, output Brea. What we
consider is information flow from
sensory to middle Brea and middle area
have a self connection, recurrent
connection and middle area project to
output layer. So there is no connection
from all output layer to middle
layer. Right.
So that's why we don't consider
the link from data
in the bottom layer of the figure to
posterior. So this
is different from true generative
process in the environment.
This is a kind of simplification.
So because our purpose is identifying
the plausible Bayesian
model which correspond to this type of
neural network canonical network.
So in other words, this neural
network uses approximation about that
point or use
limited form of palm
DP scheme.
Thanks. So could you describe W-V-K
and Gamma? Just what is the biological
or functional interpretation of those
variables? What brain regions
or what processes or pathologies do they
map to? Okay,
so basically, WVK,
synaptic strength is in the form of
matrix and active
inference.
They represent connection
in the different layer or different
architectures in the sense that W
means forward connectivity from sensory
Laje to middle Laje, k correspond to
recurrent network recurrent connectivity
and V correspond to projection
from middle Brea to output layer.
So in this paper, we don't discuss the
relation to brain anatomy in detail,
but what one
can consider analogy, for example,
say x corresponds to
several cortex activity and
Y, for example correspond to cerebral
wrong in the sense that it determines
the action. So it is considered that
in the cerebrum there is a signal that
represents choice. This is joined for
examples goal no go decision made
in cergram.
It's analogous to this
particular architectures. On the other
hand, in the several cortex
we compute the sensory
information to generate
some inference, prediction and planning
the way it is computer by
this recurrent network. In this
particular modeling, although we don't
separate brain region in detail,
but this recurrent network is sufficient
this graph of recurrent network is
sufficient to characterize any type
brain architecture in
the sense that we can design
any higher
car or mutually
connected architecture using a generic
crossover recurrent network by changing
weight.
Awesome. So the middle layer
we can think of as like the cognition
stuff. It's the internal states when we
talk about perception, cognition,
action in the active scheme
or even in the sandwich model of
cognition, perception, cognition action.
So W is describing
how those sensory inputs either in one
step or composably in multiple steps
become processed to these internal
representation of hidden external causes
inferred external states. And so these
are the states that have
that sigma relationship and
a generalized synchrony with external
states. The sigma and the generalized
synchrony are not discussed in your
paper, but it connects to other work and
the recurrent connections are
facilitating attention or
waiting of the stimuli.
This is the recurrent learning loop and
the relationship of the A between
observations and hidden state estimates.
And then a different kind of modulation
comes Hinton play between the hidden
state estimate of the internal states
state and the action selection. So what
is gamma corresponding to?
And why is the gamma modulation between
layers two and three differing
functionally from the k synaptic
modulation of one and two?
Yeah, so K matrix
basically formally correspond to B
matrix in the Bayesian information.
So we rotate the information about
the prediction, right, our narrator
or our expectation about the next
state based on the previous state.
On the other hand, Laurel gamma
is quite different from such a
computation. Gamma basically means
risk function, which is in
principle can we use arbitrary risk
function. So this is a part of
generative models we designed and the
rule of risk function in generative
model formulation is attention
form of generative models depending on
that value of gamma which
examples retrospective
moderation of evaluation of task
decisions given an
outcome in the future.
In terms of neural network, of course it
corresponds to some neural modulation.
For example, Dopaminergic moderation is
famous in the literature which moderates
the activity and fluxicity of various
brain vision. But we particularly focus
on Dopaminergic or any
kind of neuromoduration of cyanogic
prosthesis in the output trigger which
may correspond to Cergram.
So in the Serbram neural
activity or processes moderated by
Dopaminergic, input from is
used as the optimization
action rule,
decision rule or sometimes attention
help us.
Awesome. Very interesting because in
some previous papers and models that
we've looked at, attention is
dealt with as policy selection on
mental states. So internal action
selection, it's an action like
variable describing attention and
awareness and even metacognition.
And so that connects the role
of Dopamine in motor decision making
seen in many Dyskinesias
but also with the role of Dopamine in
seemingly nonmotor based
decisionmaking like gambling
or investing where it doesn't seem to
immediately translate to a
given motor sequence. Yet it has
analogous computational characteristics
and the comorbidities and the side
effects of different drugs that affect
the Dopamine neurophysiology are known
to have carryover in terms of
like the rigidity or excessivity of
motor and decision making aspects.
So it's like interesting that Dopamine
has long been understood to have that
parallel role in
attention as cognitive action and
motor action and that was
established empirically through
modifications of Dopamine signaling and
also had been modeled analogously with
computational neuroscience.
And this is providing again a slightly
different interpretation of
that very well studied Dofaminergic
modulation of attention and
policy.
Yes. In addition
to that, I believe another important
aspects is correlation of scientific
processing by document.
Do you want to show something or yeah.
Can you see this
paper? I sent
you a chat.
If you can't, I'll send you a PDF.
Okay, let me see. I'll look
at it up now.
All right. The paper is a critical
time window for Dopamine actions
on the structural plasticity of
dendritic spines from 2014 byagasha.
So what is interesting about this paper.
Yeah, it basically explained
conversation of plasticity by Dopamine,
which is common but crucial
point of this paper is that it shows
that it proved that Dopaminezic input
can moderate after
hebion prosthesis is established.
So this paper showed that they
add domain logic input for
about 2 seconds after or several seconds
after the Hebbian process
is established. But such a post hoc
moderation, post hoc introduction
of heterotopamagic Impetu is sufficient
to change the past capacity which
may be associated with the
Costa hoc evolution of
our past decisions. So by decision
making we of course changes the changes
the weight matrix by through trust 50.
But to evaluate the
goodness or badness of our decision, we
need to see observe the future outcome
which is propagated by for example,
Dopamine. And this paper nicely show
empirically that Dopamine
actually can change
the past evaluation,
maybe after such a psychic level,
very local level,
ecoscopic level.
So there's a
short term window,
the critical time window that they're
describing. But there's some window.
Yeah, some window by which
dopamine potentially unrelated to the
initial heavy and plasticity events,
right. Where secondary dopamine
signaling or not secondary
just after the initial fact,
potentially of a different valence or
the same valence can synergize
or cancel the
plasticity formed in the moment.
Exactly. And this is not limited
to Dopamine, but other neuro moderator
can also do this.
Well, on one hand, how does this change
our understanding of animal
neurophysiology? And then I guess, on
the other hand, how does this influence
how we would design sentient
artifacts.
For both animals and artificial
agent? One important
message I free with us.
So this tells us possible
simple architectures to make learning.
This is association between past
decision and future reward or
any risk factors, which is otherwise
computed by computing forward prediction
by iterating some computational,
this is a usual way to predict
the future event and then select the
option. But using this
property, biological property, which is
observed in experiment,
we can design, we can imagine other
simpler architecture to make a planning.
So for both animals and synthetic
Bayesian agent, it provides an
alternative explanation about the
association between our past decision
and the future risk and the optimization
of our decision to maximize,
reward or minimize risk.
Well, one interesting note is we spoke
earlier about the difference between the
Bayesian smoothing all at once approach
and the Bayesian filtering step by step
approach. Now, if one had infinite
knowledge and computational resources,
the Bayesian smoothing approach is the
way to go. Like, you don't want the
decision rule for investment. You want
to look at the whole time series past,
present and future, and know the best
moments to have made the trades. I mean,
there's no comparison. You're going to
do better with the Bayesian smoothing.
However, it's just implausible
computationally and because it requires
total memory of the past and knowledge
of the future. So that's what motivates
the development of Bayesian filtering
approaches, which are tractable and
calculable through time. Yet with
this time delayed modulation.
Part. Of the Bayesian smoothing strength
comma back into play. It doesn't
enable true anticipation
of future states, but that's what the
expected free energy does. However,
the delayed neuromodulation allows for
reconsideration of a window of past
states. And so in that way it
corresponds to like a
slightly deeper filter,
not just a filter of a time step of one,
but a filter of like a rolling window of
five or with some decay. And you don't
want that window to be too big because
if the window were ten minutes,
then too many contrasting
stimuli would get piled together.
The Dopamine level would just converge
to a mean field average. But there's
some time decay or time constant on
the post hoc modulation where that
neuromodulatory signal is
actually a parameter of interest.
And that's not an infinitely long or
infinitely short window, but it's some
niche dependent amount of time.
And that's a very interpretable and
first principles interpretation of
the computational role of
neuromodulators in a way
that is also consistent with all these
other concordances we've been exploring.
So it's quite an interesting connection
back, I guess, in our final
minutes of this discussion.
What are you? Well, maybe go
to the beginning at the end, which I
meant to ask earlier, but it's a good
way that we can sort of close today and
look forward, which is how did you come
to this line of research specifically
studying neural networks in this way
with Karl Friston and your colleagues?
So, yes,
so my interest was the
characterization of Barricade network.
So my first motivation is to make
biologically plausible artificial
intelligence. But to achieve that, we
need to know about biological brain or
biological neural networking.
In these several years, I collaborated
with the doctor professor
Californiston to study about
his salary principal after doing forest.
My question during that
period was the
priority principle, is everything
about the biological possible
neural network or is there another
aspect that can characterize the
virus car neural network? So it is
non trivial. It was non trivial.
So that's why I
tried to start from characterizing
the neural network first. So our
strategy is not
considering the way of implementing any
Bayesian algorithm as the brain
architectures, but my interest is
rather characterization of a given
vertical network in terms of some
other things. One possible way
is of course based on inference free
energy transplant reinforce. So that's
why I start from characterizing power's
network. But just
defining neural network architecture
is insufficient.
It is not tractable, it is far
beyond the computational tractability as
the mathematical analysis.
And we need some assumptions
or some trick to increase the
tractability. One day I came
up with an idea that
in which we consider that both
new activity and fastest follow the
same cost function gradient.
This is very much an allergy with
physical system like Lagrangian
information geometry, Hamiltonian
formation. So usually we consider some
energy landscape and design
plausible trajectory
as the evolution of some principle
of minimum action
or restruction. So we imagine
that what if we applied such idea to
computational neural network or
biological neural networks to
characterize their dynamics
in the first principle,
that's the first computational step to
come up with this framework.
And finally we noticed that
it is not easy to connect the Newtonian
dynamics with this type of neural
activity study because neural
activification not necessary to be a
second order differential
equation, but rather it is fast order
and considering many things.
Then we finally
use a Costa function
proposal in the papers,
which is not necessary to have a
former identity
with the so called lavalier in the
Newtonian physics, but it
is rather plausible as the rule
or underlying mechanism
of such type of network.
Awesome. Well,
it has been quite an interesting dot
one. I really appreciate everything
you've shared today. Is there anything
else you want to add at this point?
Otherwise we'll talk again.
Yeah, I already
speak a role. Thank you.
Alright, talk to you later. Bye.
Thank you very much for a nice