You. Hello and
welcome, everyone. It's October 18,
2023. We're in the course active
inference for the social sciences. And
today we're in the lecture by the course
co organizer, and that will kick off the
final leg of the course, which is Avel
Gwenin Carlos lecture, Social
Constraints and the Excess Central
Stance What Makes US Human.
So we'll be looking forward to a lecture
followed by a discussion. So if you have
any questions, please feel free to add
them in the live chat or submit to the
course syllabus. And also at the end,
we'll talk about how we're going to
conclude this course. So with that,
thank you to you, Avel.
Hello. So, do you see the slides
correctly? Everything is fine.
I will take Cyland as a yes.
So the role of this session is basically
to show you the inspiring intuition
behind the Evolve course and to show
very concretely well, very abstractly,
but in my mind, concretely why the
specific formalism of active inference
and social constraints is relevant to
understand the human species and the
cultural evolution of things that we do.
So we'll talk of social constraints, of
the existential stance, and of what
makes us human. Disclaimer this
presentation is closely aligned with the
upcoming paper, which, whose name is the
same, I think is tentative for now,
and whose co author, whose man on job is
a co author. So first,
let us ask basic questions about the
topic at hand. What is culture? By
psychologist Cecilia Hayes. Culture is
typically used in one of three ways.
Culture can be information or behavior
required socially. Like, if I am an ant
and I figure out that you need to go
somewhere because of pheromones,
this is culture. It can be socially
equipped behavior that is shared within
a group. So, for example, if I am an ape
and I figure out how to open nuts with a
stone thing and the group just everyone
does it the same way. This is culture
and it can be the adaptive evolution of
socially acquired behavior, which is
like, if I remember well, we have
evidence of it in the wild for
COVID and humans only.
So the question is,
we know that culture is the human
specific, like it is the case simply,
but depending on what we mean by
culture, it can describe behavior that
is very much shared with
other species. So a
question that needs to be answered is
how specific are the human cultural
mechanisms? So one
core thing to understand is that there
is no such thing as the cultural
mechanism. The mechanisms of social
learning in humans, they are culturally
transmitted. Whether you will listen to,
I don't know, elder rapper,
Scientist depends on the cultural norms
in which you exist. And the specific way
in which teacher student interaction are
supposed to go is again, culturally
embedded. And the type of information
that people will try to figure out is or
transmit is itself culturally embedded
so we can't just write the mechanism for
human social learning. This is like
empirically there is none and
conceptually I don't think the notion is
coherent to begin with.
So one core argument for this is we have
basically explicit linguistic rules
about who we should trust like listen
to your parents and those are
linguistic. And language varies from
culture to culture. So this changes from
culture to culture pretty
straightforward. And in general the
practice of cultural submission, of
intentional teaching they are varying
between cultures and I do not want to
get into it because I don't think I
would say something that is accurate
without notes. And we
can however take a look at a
behavior that is I think nearly
universal, which is storytelling. When
people tell story, they use
stories to transmit norms and in
the specific culture of the Agta
or Agta, I have misspelled it at least
once, I think it is Agta. You have
core role of storytelling in telling
people what to do and you have specific
tales that were studied and that were
stated to specific norms and
these are very important because here we
have laws that are written somewhere and
that people in blue will come and hit
you if you don't follow them. But this
is not something that is universal. So
in a context where you do not have
states, you typically have no really
other way to transmit norms than talk
about it.
From there, everything is culturally
embedded, like the way you transmit the
norms, the kind of norms can be
transmitted given this way, the way
specific cues will be understood, given
a specific niche, et cetera, et cetera.
So yes, all this to say there is no big
c culture, there is cultural
transmission, there is cultural
evolution but there is no specific
mechanism or actual type of
culture in humans.
But there are categories
of behavior that are very obviously
human specifics and that are very
obviously cultural as in direct
contribution to
culture. For example fire. It's
obviously majorly important to culture
because if you have fire you get a lot
of calories. If you get a lot of
calories you get a big brain like you
can afford big brain but fire unit
doesn't produce culture. That's not how
anything works. Things that do work
directly to produce culture are language
and role taking. So language, I think
you are familiar with it. You are using
it now on the receiving side,
it is practice that basically embeds
communicative intents into a specific
set of symbols that can be letters,
that can be words. Like orally it would
be phoneme, I guess. I don't know if the
phoneme or the word is a symbol, but you
have symbols and they embed meaning and
people use it. And what is critical is
that each of the symbol has a public
meaning, has a public like semantics and
pragmatics. If I tell you chair, maybe
we don't know precisely like what
specific thing enters in the chair
category maybe or perceptual
installation of chair will vary. But we
agree on the basics of the chair, we
agree on what we can do with chairs, we
agree with a lot of things implicitly by
the use of this word and we can use the
role of syntax to manipulate this unit
of meaning in a specific way. I sit on a
chair, I'm talking about an action that
is relative to a specific object that is
a chair and you understand what I mean.
If I was trying to mimic it, maybe I'll
get it through, maybe you would think
I'm saying I'm crouching over bed,
why not? So the language and
the fact that it has a publicly
instantiated meaning is critical in
keeping coordination in the specific
thing that people do and why they do it,
which is ambiguously cultural and you
have another more subtle mechanism
process, I don't know, phenomenon which
is shared intentionality. So by the work
of mainly Tomasello, we know that chimps
are not very social and
they can learn they are but as
intelligent as humans, well, at least
young humans, but they usually are not
really interested in what? Other teams
are doing and most importantly, they are
not interested in sharing goals trying
to figure out what is the end result
that some other chimp is upholding and
trying to mesh in this plan to
help him. While in human from a very
young age we are very stream motivated
and we are very motivated to figure out
what we whatever we are collectively
doing and figure out what one's
role is in that and do that. And this
is likely not bona fide cognitive
function that stands on its own but it's
behavior that is a cognitive process
that is endemic in humans very
aware if existing everywhere else and
that is core to most theory
of the transmission of culture. So these
two things we know are human specifics
up to maybe very small and important
details and we know are critically
embedded in what we call culture. And so
what I will do from now on is to
provide a specific theory of culture.
So the active inference of culture
landscapes that in my opinion basically
explains or at least meshes well with
why those two specific pheromones are
so important from the appalling of
culture. But it also means that culture
is not information Percy, it's something
that is more organic and that evolves
more like biological system themselves
evolve than population of genes. And
from these accounts we will go to figure
out what it means about collective
organization, figure out why we have
gods and taxes and from
there we will go to more physical and
peacemaker consideration and ask how
basically this theory can be written
within physics through the active
inference formalism. So let us go
first. I am just presenting the theory
of the active inference of clear
landscape and I am presenting a core
concept, the concept of stroke
constraints that derive from at least my
treatment of that. So active inference,
probably a lot of you know what this is
but this goes on YouTube, so I will re
explain. Active inference is a theory of
cognition where basically agents enact
expectation of the world. They have a
world model and they make predictions
over the world model and they strive
for those predictions to remain coherent
with what they actually observe. And
that means that the agent will update
beliefs that are false. If I hear
meow and I think there is no cat,
I will then think that it is more
likely. And on the other hand, I will
try to provoke to realize prediction
that I kind of need. So for example, if
I really want to hear meal, if I really
expect to hear meal and I expect this to
be like a basic step of my life, I will
maybe figure out how to get a cat that
works not well with cats but with
drinking or eating. Yeah, I expect to be
a thing that has water in it because
else I die. So when I'm thirsty I am
thirst by drinking. And you have this
basically duality of predictive normal,
what we call typically perception, just
trying to figure out what there is
outside and updating our belief when we
don't. So I said perception but is more
inference and there is active inference
which is like the realization of this
inference through action. And a core
argument of active inference is that
those two are same process. They are
the same process that is entailed by an
information geometry. So basically a
space of belief over which the dynamics
of an agent unfold. And a
core feature of this approach is the
dissolution of agency as we typically
understand it. We typically understand
agency. It will be like hey, I'm an
agent, I want to do this and I will
reason about what I want and I will
reason about how to get it. And we'll do
the thing that I reasoned about. Reason
is important. It's not the basic
cognitive function that analyze
everything we do. I do not think this
statement is controversial. And in
active inference the model we have is
that at multiple scale, in multiple
contexts, we produce prediction over our
sensor flow and then strive to realize
those prediction. So what that means is
that our action are not constrained by
will in a joke case, they are
constrained by what looks more like self
model, a model of oneself. And what
oneself would typically do in contexts
such as the one I'm exposed.
To.
Related concepts is the notion of skill
and intentionality. So this is this
skill intentionality thing is a theory
that stands at the interface between
active inference and ecological
psychology which I will absolutely not
get into. And the core argument of
skillet and shallity is that when you
are a skilled agent. So agents that
understand how to do things in the world
well, you do not experience the world as
represented space in 3D with 3D
models in it. And each object is well
defined and has a lot of properties that
are embedded in a world model that you
have in a video game. What you see is
a landscape of basic opportunities for
action. I will see a computer. I know I
can mash the keys.
I think you say keys. And I know I can
go to the Internet, and I know I can do
this or that. I see a door, I know I can
go through it if it's open, I can close
it. I can go through it if it's closed,
and I can open it. This is the basic
opportunities that the door presents.
And you don't say a logical consequence,
but very coherent entitlement
of active inference is that I will
see minimal model of things around me
that are based on the opportunities for
action that they present. I will orient
my attention minimally to grasp what I
can do with things and what the
field, the perceptive field that I live
in is a landscape of those affordances.
So the picture is an extract from
Fallout Novegas, which is the greatest
RPG. Please play it. This is important.
Only thing you need to keep in mind
about this course. And that shows you
like, radio in three D F
radio, and you have an action button
that tells you whether you want to
activate the radio. And you have HPS and
APS. I have no idea what AP is.
And this looks more like naive
feel than what you'd get into a really
realistic presentation of, like a
picture, photo picture of your
environments, because you have the
perception of the object. Like, you have
3D array represents your vision of
an object, but it's embedded in things
that tell you where you're looking at,
things that tell you what you can do
with things, things that tell you what
are your states, what are your basic
states when you're engaging with this
object? And this is,
I think, pretty nice illustration
of what we could mean by attemption and
the landscape for what is actually being
transmitted. You need less issues.
Sorry, Avel, could you repeat the last
30 seconds there? It was just like it
hung up. Okay, just repeat
the last 30 seconds. Thank you. So this
is a picture from Fallout Nivegas,
which is a good game. And I claim that
it is a pretty good illustration of what
we talk when we talk about action rated
perception, because you see the object
and with through the object, you also
see what opportunities for action it
presents. In this case, activate the
radio and you see it in the way it is
embedded with your physiological states.
So the HP and AP.
And a core feature of
that is that when I experience
affordances, I feel directly
through the perception whether the
affordance is good or bad. If I
see, I don't know, a cliff and all,
of a sudden I can fall off the cliff and
die. This will cause fair.
The perception of that possibility of
falling and dying will be negatively
loaded if I see, I don't know, a hot bed
in winter and I know I can now rest
after a day of work where I was cold. I
will be happy about it. I will perceive
the possibility in a positively balanced
way. And so this is the case for basic
physiological thing. But this is also
the case for cultural norms and values.
We come to experience the world as a
world of affordances and this is
the same for the social world. I will
feel bad or good depending on what
possibility for action I will experience
in a given context. And this
is a picture of forest path near
Arcological site that is studied by
the research group that funds me escape.
And from a pure direct perception kind.
Of way there is very complex
statistical feature that are embedded in
the picture but if you are a human, a
thing that walks what you will perceive
like feel directly, experience directly
is just a possibility to walk along the
path and follow it. And this
is something that you feel is a property
of the path. I think you see the path.
You think I can go through a path? You
don't think there is a 3d space? And in
this 3d space there is a set of
statistical feature, one of which being
a flat thing in the middle. And among
the enter space factions they have one
of them is to walk through the path like
just do this and this and this and this.
You just feel like you can go through
there. And the
way humans learn about each other,
the way humans gravitate and come to
expect things about each other, they
can. Develop, basically a sense of what
is culturally possible or not possible
in a given context. And this sensation,
this perception of cultural
possibilities, it is embedded in the
way we pay attention to things. We will
pay attention to. Different things
according to what is culturally relevant
in a given context, in a given
situation. And this is a core argument
of the thinking through the mind account
of cultural evolution which was
spearheaded by Maxwell, Ramstead and
Vesier. Forgot his first name.
And because of everything that we saw
before, because of the dissolved agency
that we have in the active in France the
patterns, cultural patterns in the flow
of attention they will not simply
be experienced. As abstract norms and
value that one could or could not
respect. They will effectively constrain
the thing. You can pay attention to the
outcome you expect in a way that will
drive your action towards specific
outcomes. And so this cultural landscape
of affordances, they embed
intentionality and normativity, as in
the patterns that are relevant to
explain normativity and intentionality,
they are in the landscape. They are not
like only at least in your brain cells.
And a core argument, I would
say, is that the engagement with
a cultural landscape, it is duel to
existence of social constraints where
social constraints are understood as
statistical patterns that will causally
act over what you do or cannot do.
So when I talk about circulatory
landscape forensics, I am implicitly
talking about a set of constraints that
acts over behavior. And this I've
demonstrated by talking about meditivity
and the like.
You have how to say you
have arid nuance in the notion of
constraints, which is that.
Avel sorry,
again,
Avel from your side. I'm not hearing any
audio.
Mao or Maria, do you hear him? No,
nothing. You can't write every over
collective behavior. So where is the
scale of one specification? Yes. All
right. Could you repeat the last 45
seconds? Can you hear me
now? Yeah. Okay,
so what I'm saying is that the
engagement with cultural landscape
forensics, it is dual to the existence
of social constraints which act over
individual behavior. Because when I
engage individually with the landscape
forensics that is a characteristic of my
local material and cultural
environments, the embedded
will drive my behavior, my intention,
my presentation in a specific way. And
instead of looking at how each
individual agent engaged with the
landscape, I can look at the constraints
that emerge from this collective
activity. So is that do you hear me now?
Okay. Yeah.
Okay, good.
So let us get back to the question of
what makes us human. We are told about
human specific mechanism phenomenon
that seemed to be involved in culture.
Those were language and role taking.
And those two phenomenons seem to be
pretty robust candidates to explain the
coherence of a shared cultural landscape
or set of circumstraints language. It
provides a space of public presentation
like representation in the classical
connectivity sense that you can
negotiate that are actually out there in
the literal sense. They are sensory
signals that are in the environment and
that structure and Asian behavior. So
when you talk to yourself, it will
constrain what you pay attention to
implicitly what you can and cannot do.
And when you talk with others, this will
influence what you say and what you want
to say and what you perceive to be riven
to say. And so it will constrain your
behavior and in a much stronger and more
robust way than you could have to
implicit intentionality inference and
role taking in a more subtle way brings
agent to think existentially, to not
ask. The question what I am supposed to
do in the situation but what an agent
that is embedded in the specific
cultural context where I embedded is
expected to do. And so this basically
forces you to have a synchronization
between what you experience as
possibilities for action and what you
expect are cultural expectation over
behavior. So these two mechanisms,
there would be very, very strong
mechanisms to enforce the coherence of
cognitive landscape between agents. And
it just so happens that there are things
that exist only in the one species that
has full fledged, cumulative, open ended
cultural evolution. So,
yes, I think this is interesting.
Okay, Avel,
you just unshared your screen.
Sorry? You unshared your screen, or is
that done? No, I did not unshare my
screen.
Could you just reshare it? Yeah. There
you go. All right. Looks great.
Continue. Thank you.
Nice. So, yes, the question is,
as I said, there is duality between each
agent engaging with a landscape for
dense and constraints that
exist over the landscape, that is
shared, that is straightforward, but in
the set of constraints that is
characteristic of a given landscape.
Basically, to account for perinetric
culture evolution, this must be a set of
constraints that changes to time, that
builds new constraints and new dymical
flow. And this is something that you
cannot get with a landscape in the
sense of system theory. That is not the
system theory does not deal with systems
that do open ended evolution. So the
question is, what relation can we make
between the dynamics of enculturation
according to which agent integrates
specific cultural expectation and the
dynamics of open ended cultural
evolution through which cultural
landscape and the constraints constructs
itself through time? And this is where
we get to the more holistic side,
where I think we can see why the
specific construct of constraints is
critical as compared to the simple
cultural landscape approach. Let us take
a look at this. There is a thing called
biological autonomy. It is quite recent
term in its formalization, the relevant
formalization that describes the ability
of a living system for self
construction, like maintaining one
structure and challenging it through
developmental and evolutionary time.
And the best formalization we have had
so far is from Montevil and Mossio, and
it's constraint closure. A constraint
is simply a relatively slow physical
process that shapes a faster process,
like canalized material or information
or energy flow without itself being
affected at the timescale of the
interaction. And for Monteville Mosio,
you get biological autonomy where you
get a set of constraints that
collectively produce itself. Each
constraint is produced by other
constraints in a set, and each
constraint produces other constraints in
the set. This is a very simple ID.
This is a very informal ID in the sense
that it doesn't have dynamics, doesn't
have a physics. It is just a formal
statement of what we mean by autonomy.
And this IV basically is
the best grounding we have to think
about what is living and what is an
agent, although in itself it does not
entail agency. And when
we look at social systems or any systems
as a set of constraints, what you can
see is that systems such as the brain
multiscale organized system, they can
be read as basically a set of nested
constraints like your DMN, the activity
of your default mode network, which is
the basal activity of the brain. In the
absence of stimulation, it basically
is constituted of chemical constraints
over what the composite tissues
do at a given point in time. And this
itself is a constraint over what
individual cells do full time, which
itself is a constraint over the
evolution law of an individual cell, et
cetera, et cetera, et cetera. So I can
always look at a multiscale system as a
set of nested constraints at nested
scales and in systems that are
autonomous, that are biological
cognitive agent. Not only the
smaller scale systems like cell.
They enable, they construct, and they
enact the constraints that are aeroscale
agents. But aeroscale agents can also
shape back the behavior of low scale
agent. Like of course, if I
do something which is something that I
as an agent do, this will constrain the
activity of my neural networks. This is
like heavy and learning, this is common
to all model of learning. Learning goes
through change in network structure and
so there is an opportunity to model
emerging agent from collective
network activity and to look at
the interaction between description at
nested scales of behavior and
this is applicable very
straightforwardly to the human species.
So this is sumerianity state and
something that you can look is that it
is very dense, it has very dense
building that are built in a specific
way. It is near a river which
enables the trade at great distance.
It has a bridge, so entry to the city is
constrained to a specific point and it
is essentially surrounded by several
fields very flatlands, that are rubble,
that are fertilized,
probably by water from the river.
And basically all of these feature are
enabled the production of first aid
societies, societies with a central
administration that does stuff. And
these societies will robustly produce
context, material context, that favorite
is their own survival. For example,
dance settlements it enable you to have
everyone together to tell them what to
do. Temples which give a matter of
grounding to the authority of the state,
bridges that allow you to move things
around and to control what gets in and
out and more cultural cereal fields that
allow you to take the food and bring it
back to the city. And the production
of such settlements and such material
environments by states is somewhat
robust intercultural phenomenon at
a more like ancient or
multicultural scale you
have a set of process that are critical
in the construction and action of norms
in humans and most likely
common ancestor to those processes is
dancing and singing. Dancing and
singing. They give you embodied
synchronization. And this is shown to
drive development of group identity.
And this gives you, basically,
emotional grounding of the norms that
are shared within society. Because those
norms, they are not abstract
expectation. They are embedded in your
specific emotions, in your specific
embodiment. While you do things that are
critical to your ecology and ritual
activity and storytelling. They allow
more complexity of the martivity by
using symbolism and the system of
tomativity. There are maybe less
embedded, embodied sorry, so less
embedded in the one's direct
experience but they allow a more
complexity in the nature of the norms
that are transmitted and enforced.
And these norms,
by the simple fact that they are
perceptible through metal symbolism and
through storytelling they become a
causal force in the cultural landscape
that is shared by a group member. So
they become things that are the power to
produce or constrain the framing in
which people will read specific
situation and therefore constrain and
produce social behavior.
And this is, like I've
said this already, so this looks like
repetition. But I want to hammer this
because if this is the case,
then we can be interested in what
complex tails sorry.
In agency that emerges from the
constraints embedded in complex tails so
we know that people can perceive non
material agents under certain
conditions. This is common in
schizophrenia. Like, you will hear
voices that tells you to do things and
that are not embedded in a specific
body. This is common in decade
Valentine's disorder because you will
have agents that basically share your
body while having and existing, while
not being tied to a specific body.
Sorry, I'm misspeaking. One specific
personality can exist while they are not
in control of your body. And so in a way
that is not contingent on the direct
material in action of what they want and
want not to do, and under a lot of
anthropologically described conditions
that are not considered pathological,
you can basically have regimes of
attention that produce enormous reagent
that you can talk with and that have
motivation and that have limited traits,
which are often called tulpas, which is
a term borrowed from Buddhist
literature. And so
this emergence of the material agent
how to say, if I consider an agent to be
something a closed set of constraints
and I consider things like tails
and ritual as mechanism that produce
constraints in behavior there is
basically no difficulty whatsoever at
conceptual level. There is no
unexpectedness or no complexity to say
that specific systems of constraint that
happen to be closed and that are
embellished in those tales and rituals,
they exist as biological agent.
So we kind of have basically a model of
gods, of non material agents which is a
better, less logical way to put it that
relies on systematic training of your
regime of attention. And of course,
when it's collective, it will like those
agents will be social agents. They will
be things that have power, that have the
ability to frame the debate around
specific things. If you and I think is
sorry. The painting that is on the right
of the screen is a painting by William
Blake that presents basically. A late
18th, I think notion of God, which is
not really Old Testament, which is a bit
more New Testament, but which is often
sensation of the clockmaker God
that was popular at the time and what
you see on the painting is resent. So
William Blake's version of God that is
in the sky like, very powerful, very
juice like imagery and that is using
this, his hand, to draw a compass, that
is considered a symbol of constructing
things of masonry like. The compass is
one of the Freemason symbol for the same
reason. It is a symbol of orderly
creation in William Blake's paintings.
And so if we share a belief that there
is a God somewhere and he built the
world as it is intentionally and this
God is benevolent or at least much too
powerful for us to fight with basically
European they bold on to following
the order because if you don't, god will
remove you from the order. And you don't
want that, do you? So even if you
don't have the existence of
a material institution of this God,
even if people don't really believe that
there is actually a guy with a bird that
does stuff, the shared ritualized
belief in an entity that has this
specific motivation and these specific
traits, it will shape heavily the
social landscape that is available to
everyone. And this is compatible
with although it
does not entail the existence of actual
agency that is tied to this specific
entity through the constraints that this
entity concretely is. And something that
I find again interesting is that
religion that are popular today so
Christianity, Islam, Buddhism, Hinduism
if you think of something as a religion,
it will likely fall under this
handle are typically what White House
call? Doctrinal religion which are
religion that are where basically you
sit down and you look at rituals and
there is priesthood that is trained
to do the ritual in a specific way that
is supposed to mean specific things.
And this is basically optimal to build
very robust notions of what gods
are, what they want from you, what they
do, what they're motivated by, et
cetera, et cetera. So I
must insist that this is with question
mark. But in principle,
the Schoenstrains model, it can
produce a touristic theory of gods and
non material agent sorry, as socially
embedded non material agent that are
computed collectively through engagement
with a specific cultural landscape where
ritual and doctrinal elaboration
are important components.
And I can say with exclamation mark that
this model, it enables naturalistic
theory of social agency that is not tied
specifically to individual bodies.
If I consider a social system, actual
organization to be autonomous, that is
closed system of constraints, zane
agency or maybe non trivial agency, it
simply reduces to the power to shape
this landscape and
you can have emergent social things do
that. You can have states which follow
specific rules. So social constraints
and specific norms. So against
constraints that have autonomy and that
are able to shape the landscape. But in
all of this, this part in my opinion
shows that circle
constraints specifically are relevant to
study these social worlds, that they
correspond to relevant
social processes in human order, agents
that are institutions and maybe again
question mark, no matter agents, sorry,
material agents into institution. So
gods. The question that needs to be
asked is how we can model the portion of
constraints. Because all of these rely
on the idea that somehow in the
landscape that whispers, there is such a
thing as constraints and they are well
defined thing that exist over a
collective behavior and that they have
the property to construct itself and
for reason we'll very shortly see. To
frame this mathematically in a coherent
way is insanely hard. I don't know how
to do it, no one knows how to do it. We
have leads, but they are leads, nothing
else. And so we'll turn to the question
of whether active inference frames a
gauge theory for enculturation. You
should know what this is by now, gauge
theory, we will see that soon.
So to explain Gold's theory, I need
to explain explanation, which is fun,
but mostly symmetries in physics. In
physics we frame physical problem around
symmetries symmetry. It is algebraic.
So something that has composition like
plus groups of transformation over the
space of possibilities, which are
irrelevant from the perspective of the
same dynamics. This is very abstract.
So let's look at symmetries. This is the
ceiling of the Lotfola Mosque, and it's
found what you can see is a symmetry
under the C 32 symmetry group. If you
shift this picture by one over 32
full turn, it does not change. This is
what we mean by a symmetry. This is a
transformation, a set of transformation
that is closed and that does
not change. Well, not a picture of
course in the context of physics, but
the dynamics of the relevant system we
are studying. And for formal reasons
I will not absolutely not get into here
explanation. In physics it usually
derives from the statement of symmetry.
For example, when I state that energy is
conserved, this is the same formally as
stating that my system is symmetric in
time. When I state that momentum is
conserved, that reduce formally to
stating that my system is asymmetric in
space. Okay? So most things in
physics can be framed as simply
symmetries over system dynamics.
And a Gold theory is simply elaborate
instance of this core ID. So if
your symmetry has two properties first,
it is continuous. So not like a
set of small rotation, but like the set
of all possible rotation that you can
take around a circle and local. So you
can apply the symmetry transformation to
every single point in space. Your
problem basically can be framed with
realm degree of freedom. So because the
symmetry does not change your system,
whether your system where your stem is
in the, for example, clockwork rotation.
It is not important. It does not change
the dynamics. So this redundant degree
of freedom we call a gauge parameter.
The core feature of gauge theory is to
take the geometry of that problem and
make it into a physical force. So when
I say gorgeous parameter, so this is you
should see in the screen nontrivial
z over two z possible bundle of a
circle, which means basically that you
have a circle, it has two stages, and
when you are over it, you can be either
on top or down, and you can't know
where it is. So this is not quite
the graph freedom because you have only
two choices. To get to the graph
freedom, you have to get a continuous
space of choices. But this is basically
what we mean by gold parameter. It is a
geometric property of your system that
you know mathematically exists, but that
cannot possibly be observed or how
to say corresponds to a choice in how
you observe your system. So this is why
we talk of GOJ, because this is a choice
in how we inspire the system. But I will
not get into the details of this here.
And the thing is that because of its
redundancy, the Goch parameter does not
have to be the same in a specific
trajectory at any given point in space.
And from that you get curvature.
And curvature if you are anywhere near
physics and, you know.
Avil okay, last thing
we heard was if you're anywhere. In
physics about relativity theory, you
will know that curve to the naive
embedding space. So if you know vaguely
about relativity. Theory yes,
sorry, just if you're anywhere in
physics and then continue from there.
Yes. So if you are vaguely familiar
with relativity theory, you know that
curvature in a space, it corresponds to
forces. So in relativity theory, the
curvature of spacetime, it corresponds
to the gravity force. And generally in
physics, the curvature in other weirder
gauge spaces, it translates in the other
fundamental forces. So weak force,
strong force and electromagnetism.
So, yes, just stating that there is a
space which has a gorge parameter in it
and this space has a curvature. It
entails that you have a force that
emerges over the, let us say, natural
framing of the problem.
And this speaks very closely
to active inference. So active inference
can be framed as a consequence of a
formal result that is called the frenzy
principle. Let us write a
dimmical system stochastic which means
that it has noise in it and which can be
partitioned between an agent A
environment B and boundary sorry, an
environment E and a boundary B such that
the distribution of the agent and the
environment are independent from each
other given the distribution of the
boundary B, which kind of means that an
information in E that is relevant
in A and vice versa has to be in B. But
doesn't quite mean that. But it's very
close. Then you have an information
geometry which is like
geometrical construct where each point
in the agent corresponds to its position
of belief over the
space of external states.
And because of this information
geometry, each possible internal
state of the agent, it entails
implicitly a belief over external
states. So this means that given the
condition of partitionability,
I can write Bayesian belief over my
environment as a simple geometrical
property of the space we are working
in. And as I just said, when you have
a geometry and it's curved, you get
forces. And so the FEP
can straightforwardly be framed
as gauge theory where
the symmetries in sensor entropy
technically. But let us say the space of
belief I am evolving in directly
constrain my action in a specific manner
to constrain biasian coherence between
what I expect to be the case and what I
experience to be the case. And so
straightforwardly this grounds active
inference because like what I just said
is what I said to explain active
inference up to some technical words
that were added in. But yes, this result
entails predictive processing and
predictive control of behavior of the
agent and to some extent
improves the possibility of this
existing in bare dymical system theory.
But I do not think that the FEP can
possibly represent enculturation. So
when I talk of a dynamical system, this
is a system with dynamics in it. You
are, I think you understand that.
I do not think you necessarily
understand the formalism that we imply
by it. A mixture system is a
flow function phi, a time parameter t
and a state space x. So what that
means is that to frame an ecosystem, I
have to write a space, let us say, I
don't know, just the Euclidean space
with three dimension. I have to specify
time, which is like naturally in the
occurrence space what we think of as
time. And I have to specify a specific
way in which my system will move in
space in a given step of time. So fear
gives from any position and any time
slot where the system will be if it
starts from this position after the
specific time duration. This is
what a unimical system is. But if you
have noticed this,
this entails that I define preemptively
all other space of possibilities of my
system. If I have a system that is
open ended system of constraints, that
can build new stuff, that can build
language, that can build accounting,
whatever new states this doesn't go,
maybe you say we could reconstruct a
minimal notion of new stuff happening by
working.
Sorry, I'll ask him again,
Avel again repeat the last
30 seconds,
but your audio is still not there. It's
like a 30 to 42nd period where
your audio just doesn't transmit. None
of us can hear it. But the Internet is
fine. Working over the dynamics
of the system per se, learning the
mechanical system theory. So you can do
that either. Fine. Yeah. Continue.
Yes, continue. Okay.
So the mixture system can be written as
a flow function phi over a state space x
and a time parameter t.
When you specify x you specify the total
space of possibility of the system. So
if you have a system that has opened any
evolution in it well, you cannot work
with a fixed space. You could maybe
circumvent the issue by implicitly
having new things happen from a change
in the dynamics of the system. But in
Mikel system theory the dynamics are
pregiven through the flow function
phiical system
theory. System is a specific
deterministic flow. So you can't change
the flow through time so you can't model
the construction of new constraints and
you can't model the emergence of new
parameters that affect causality of
system. So the FEP in of itself cannot
present the creative evolution of either
cognitive kinds such as money shares or
constraints. And this
is where we have to get in weirder
spaces formally to get something that
looks like it could model open end
evolution although I cannot say
definitively it can because we didn't
yet by construction. When we work with
set theory which is the basic theory of
mathematics which is about specific
objects that are predefined we can't
have what Kaufman calls adjacent
possible which correspond to new
evolutionary possibilities that are
brought about by the evolution upon an
evolution of evolutionary system like
living systems.
Simply, set theory forces you to define
all of the possibilities at step one of
the modeling process so can't have your
system that builds new possibilities
through its activity. This is not a
coherent concept in set theory.
However. What we can do is to look at,
rather than set theory at a category
theory which is, let us say, another
approach to mathematic which looks not
at specific objects and their
relationship to functions but at
specific spaces and their relationships
to functions. And this change in
approach basically does not entail, at
least not a priory that when you write a
system you have to write all of the
possibilities that are within the system
preemptively. You can write a space and
then look at the relationship between
the space and other adjacent spaces that
could correspond to adjacent possibles.
And one thing that is related to
that, at least in spirit is I
won't get into detail but formal
approaches that allow you to build
quantum state spaces from the property
of quantum observation rather than the
opposite. So simply speaking, we can
look at the problem of how cognition
brings about new possible not as a space
of possibilities in which there is a
flow but as a set of spaces
in which specific events such as
observation, such as enculturation,
such as invention of new concepts can
bring about new spaces. And when we
rewrite active inference in the language
of category theory we get things that
do not quite say the same thing as
immaculate system theory like actual
active inference, actual frenzy
principle but we get things that are
very very complicated. So the diagram
that you see on the bottom left of the
screen is a conecocone diagram. I could
tell you what a concoction is but I
don't know. So I could not explain that
is meant to represent the alignment in
reference frame or the mutual active
inference between two subsystem.
So again, formally we have no reason to
believe this can't model upon evolution.
But also given the level of effectness
of the math, we have very very few grip
with which to understand what we're
looking at and how this relate to
specific cognitive and cultural
processes. So there is a lot of progress
to be made in that direction before we
have a self standing theory of open
ending cultural evolution and the
basic handle of social constraints I
think is a good bridge between the very
concrete, very simple the immigrant
system theory and the very abstract
problem of many evolution. So let us
wrap this up here and try to take out
a few snippets of actionable information
that was included in the talk.
First, agents by nature they
engage with the world with their world
as a cognitive landscape that is defined
by the modalities by which they perceive
the world, that is defined by the
intrinsic themativity that the agent
experience and that is.
Again sorry, just go back 22
seconds but
still the audio is not ready yet. But
it's okay, we'll breathe before we jump
into the conclusion.
It okay.
Still don't hear you.
No,
we can do the slide game where someone
else presents the slide. Any volunteers?
Okay. Yeah, I heard that. Okay,
cool. Can you please continue? No.
Okay, we'll try to go fast because this
is not agreeable. So one,
agents engage with the world as a
cognitive landscape which is defined by
affordencies so minimal representation
of the action that are possible in the
landscape and the normativity that's
embedded in the possibility of the
action. Two, the fact that humans
collectively enact relatively coherent
circular landscape. It entails that we
have social constraints over collective
behavior and the existence of those
social constraints they enable or
thought do not necessitate the emergence
of higher scale agencies such as
institution, organization and maybe
godlike beings.
And last, the dynamics of constraints,
they entail a duality between the
creation of meaning. So the way we
humans create a way to understand the
world and the conception of physicals
in the sense specific, concrete,
causally relevant possibilities that
characterize specific social cultural
organizations and maybe like physical
version paratuses but just don't worry
about it. And all of it is embedded
in this diagram the engagement and the
duality with a system of constraints
that produce itself in a pen in manner.
So a claim that I'm making on the record
here is that if we understand correctly
every arrow in this diagram. We
understand culture evolution, we
understand what human are, and we
understand opening evolution in the
cultural world. And here I'll go through
the slides in case someone needs a
reference and has the time to go through
the video to find the reference. So,
thank you. And sorry about the audio
thing.
Did this go well?
Yes, it gave some much needed silences,
so it was all good. Cool.
Well, first, Mao or Maria,
if you would like to give any comments
or reflections. Otherwise we can go
to a few topics and then talk about how
we want to conclude with the course.
But first, Mao or Maria, do you want to
say or ask anything?
No. I mean, this was a great summary.
I think you covered a lot of grounds. I
think, ideally, I would have liked to
see how
much we can do with gauge theory and
how this can potentially link us
to understandings
of would be that would be
interesting.
Cool. Thank you, Maria. All right.
See you, Maria. Okay. Anyone in live
chat can ask a question or let's
first address the course question while
people are writing questions. Live chat.
So what do you see for the coming weeks
as we kind of conclude this first round?
So you're asking me right.
So, for a reason I do not understand,
and Daniel understands, no one came up
at the Mao discussion session. So I
thought it would be interesting to push
a presentation for the last session to
have everyone saying that things have
feedback and I have a current thing
to move on from. The question is whether
you feel there is a need for a
discussion that is specific for the
session we have had just now, because
lots of things were covered, lots of
audio problems were existing.
And basically the two options are either
next session is everyone presents, we
give you feedback ciao, or we have a
discussion session. So at the time that
was initially planned for the
conclusion, and then we have yet another
session that will be the conclusion
where you will make a presentation and
you will get the feedback. So we'd like
to know which is your preference,
because both are very possible in my
book, but doesn't show anything to me.
So what you want is goals.
Yeah. Mao also open to your thoughts.
And of course, we're sharing it so that
people can write in live chat or let us
know in the coming days what they
prefer. I'm down for a discussion
of what we covered here. The slides
being linked and going into some of
these next steps, and then a form based
registration for a presentation only
session so that we'll then know exactly
who wants to present what. And then we
can ask how many minutes they want to
do, or something like that. But mao?
Yeah, I think it would be good to get
people who are interested in getting
more active to come and make
a small presentation, explain what they
understood, describe the highlights
for them, and potentially link it to
some topic in social sciences we may not
have covered here, but that they
now see through a different lens. I
think that would be interesting.
Okay. All right. I will look
through the live chat while avoid
getting some water, and then we'll ask
any questions that people come up with.
Is there ever symmetric information
between or among social entities?
Or maybe from the scripts perspective,
mao or from the or however you see
in relation with the constraints? I
mean, what about asymmetric constraints?
I'm not sure I understand the question.
Can the person give a little more detail
in terms of in the questions? Okay,
evil is back. But there was a question
in the chat about can information ever
be symmetric? You talked about
symmetries. So are those symmetries in
the information that two social entities
have, or are they in the constraints
that entities experience? But what are
the symmetries and what are the breaks?
I would say that depending which space
you model the problem information, it
entails symmetry because it
has to be readable. So you have to be a
conservation between context or time of
something that is considered to be the
content of the information bearing
thing. But also it is a symmetry
breaking because if you take any
presentation format, let's say binary,
a random string means nothing, and you
have to break the symmetry of the
uniform expression to say something. So
it depends very heavily on how
specifically you are modeling the
problem. But for fundamental reasons,
any mathematical representation, it
depends on the implicit model of the
symmetries of the system because you
won't present things that do not matter,
but you have to present things that do
matter, and then you have a very
uncomfortable amount of freedom over how
you want to present any single thing.
Certainly this comes up in learning
active inference and in talking about it
like what you described, how many ways
there are to model a given thing which
is related to which symmetries are
preserved, as you mentioned. So how do
we reckon with that space and with the
different ways of representing the
same social setting?
So a reason why I'm not quite
comfortable with the notion of
information is that in all
possible settings where I define quantum
information theory as not possible
because very few people overall think
about it, information will be a
probability distribution. It will be
like functional over probability
submission that is minus to the
logarithm of the probability. That is
what self information is. And this
is defined over a probability
distribution. Distribution is defined
over state space. So implicitly
information entails differential state
space. So if you want to work over
things that are prior to state spaces,
you cannot work with information in any
coherent definition.
Basically, the one thing you
could do that is vaguely inspired from
work in quantum information theory,
mainly by Christopher first is to not
look at the probability, but at the
sorry, not to look at the information.
I'm using that term in a colloquial way
now because I have to switch meaning
information not as a property of the
dispersion but as a property of quantum
operator that corresponds to observation
and that embeds. Basically, we could say
again, in a very, very colloquial sense,
something akin to an expectation or a
measurement or a synchronization event
in the active inference model. And this
for a specific type of operator,
for a specific type of spaces, you can
get basically the space that flows from
the operator rather than the other way
around. And then information is like
it's not colmogo rough complexity, it's
not shaman information, it's not a
variant of entropy. It is basically what
is hypothesized by these specific
operators that you use to interact with
matter and with cultural and material
environments. And maybe there is a big
maybe here, I should say maybe one more
time. Maybe this can adapt it in some
way to account for the process
of ankuration, where basically
the process angulation is considered as
the integration of specific reference
frames, like expectation colloquially.
And this entail
the evolution of the cognitive landscape
and our social constraints either
defined over the cognitive landscape or
defined as a self standing mathematical
object, I do not know. But if we have
that, and if we have a decent
level of understanding of what
constraints the evolution of neurofence
frames, we have a selfcending theory of
the unfolding of creative landscapes and
of open ended culture evolution. This is
a sufficient condition, I am sure of
that. But it is very hard to reach.
There are so many threads by which you
could take it and each one is like the
level of postdoc in mathematics. And I'm
not talking about 19th century
mathematics, but talking about algebraic
topology. I'm talking about weird
category thing that people only figured
out how to define 30 years ago. So yeah,
I'm not confident I will give you an
answer to that within five years. I'm
not confident.
Wow, very interesting there. All right,
some questions from the chat. So, first
upcycle, Club wrote do you think
ritualized storytelling is driven by
social constraints? Everything is driven
by circumstraints. We just define
circumstraints as the contrast that
exist over behavior. If we
expect that every night we have to go
around the fire and listen to someone
tell a story, then yeah, this will
happen. If we expect that we have to go
on YouTube and listen to talks about
abstract things such as inference, this
will happen. So in this sense,
everything, every single activity you
have is embedded in landscape or
cultural expectation. And this is why
it's pretty hard to talk about basic
mechanism of cultural transmission
because whichever cognitive mechanism
you are looking at is encultured and
could in principle and likely has been a
few times changed by cultural evolution.
Yes. Cool.
And that takes me back to the scripts
discussion in papers, the strong script
at exactly this time here's the script
that we're all going to read from on
through the spaces of weaker scripts
like we tend to meet here or there
happens to be a path here. Okay. So then
some comments from M. Lenin. One,
thank you. I don't know if making a
presentation to explain what one
understood is an attractive invitation.
Still, two places I did not track as
well as I hope was. One, dissolution of
agency as we know it and two,
the informational geometry among agent,
environment and boundary went over my
head. Thank you.
So dissolution of agency and agent,
environment, boundary. Yes. I will
get back to the slides. Are you
seeing the window?
Yeah, I'll bring it in. That's fine.
Thank you. Okay.
So the dissolution of agency is
basically the idea that when
we think about agents, people like we
think as a system that has a body and
that has a brain and that has the
ability for discursion, like
deliberating over what you do and not
do. And we place agency at the level of
discursive beliefs. So if I say I
want to grab the water and I grab the
water, I grab the water out of my
agency, if I inadvertently, I don't
know, bump into something and make it
fall or grab without thinking about it,
is it attentive? Most people
would say yes. But that's actually not
entailed by the most used model of
agency. Legally speaking,
you are held as not responsible
or less responsible of things that you
did not have the opportunity to debate
over. But from a purely cognitive
perspective and if the active inference
model is correct, the bulk of the
intentionality of your ability to direct
your own flow that you have does not
come from reasoning and deliberation and
central executive system like cognitive
function that we associate with
reasoning and agency. It comes from
the basic expectation you have yourself
and the world because your expectation
over the world constraint heavily
implicate the opportunities for action
that you perceive and your beliefs over
yourself constrain just as heavily the
options that you will end up pursuing.
And so the agency, your ability
to decide of stuff, it mostly
reduces to predictive process over your
self model and your world model. And
this is while not like I don't
see any problem formally or empirically
with that picture as I understand it,
that comes very well for the
neuropsychiatric and psychological
literature and sociological literature.
Like this is good, this works
scientifically, but this is
counterintuitive because again, most
people will expect you to have reasoning
and then to decide of stuff and then to
execute all the stuff you decide. Which
again, I don't think this happens.
So harder question is the information
geometry, I kind of glossed over it
because yeah.
So the. Information geometry is a
geometry that is defined within his
incode system, equipped with a
partition, blah, blah, blah. And so by a
geometry, I mean basically a space of
curvature that exists over your bezel
space. This is basically the same thing
that I'm presenting in the bottom left
of the screen. Here you have a space
that is your normal space, where you see
stuff happen, which is represented here
by the line. And you have a curvature
that is defined by some of the things
that are defined over the space and by
the Frenzy principle. When you have this
partition condition that is verified,
then each
state in the agent internal states,
like each specific point, it can be
corresponds to a belief distribution
over the states of the environment.
And so this is in this sense that we
have an information geometry like we
have a geometry. So curvature over
space, where the space is the internal
state of the agent, and the geometry is
belief over ethical states. And
furthermore, this matters because the
agent isn't actually constrained by the
image. The agent is
effectively constrained by the geometry
in such a way that its internal flow
optimizes the bias and coherence of the
belief that exists according to the
geometry. So this is highly
math, this is straightforward, but lots
of words, lots of section. No real
visual aid, put it. So this is more
something to read about and something to
hear about, which is why I glossed over
it. But I hope going over it again
brings a bit more of clarity.
How would you connect what you just said
to the differences with written and oral
culture? Like, what is hearable? What is
seeable? How does writing in
the printed or etched or digitized form
relate to how you discussed culture
today?
I see you as frozen. Danielle, can you
hear me? I can hear
you. Mao. Okay, so do
answer, or do Mao answer? Mao, if you
want to. Yeah, please. I can give a
little bit of an idea, but effectively,
we're talking about precision and
temporality, right? So writing and
discourse, the discourse has to relate
to pragmatics, and the discourse
is likely to be interpreted because it
has lower precision than, say, writing
has over time. So here you're talking
about the ways in which the information
geometry will be bent and shifted
through the precision of the embedded of
the embedded normativity that is given
rise to through
these markers that you can point to over
and over and over with high precision.
I think that's the link.
Basically. So when I talked about role
taking and language, I claim that the
core reason why this matter is because
this enforce coherence between the
cognitive landscape experienced by
agents and writing changes massively the
scale at which it is possible. And it
changes massively the level of emotional
embeddedness of language.
It is much lower in speech than sorry,
much higher in speech than it is in
writing, especially if you account for
singing as a form of speech. So
historically writing very clearly
and very ambiguously powered the rise of
administration. So states so
organization that do a lot of accounting
and bookkeeping like book is literally
in the word and that enable the
centralization of resource management.
This is explained in detail in the logic
of writing by Goody Goody.
And yeah,
basically this writing is a core
cultural innovation that enables
centralized policies, city states,
things like that.
Yeah, that's very interesting.
So one topic Avel that we've discussed
and maybe you could unpack a little bit
here is thinking of culture and
these cognitive ecosystems leads to
consideration of the cognitive security
or of different information risk
aspects. So where does that come into
play with the formalism or what
you discussed here?
So, from a cognitive security aspect,
one thing you can read in the formalism
quite directly is that if you control
the environment as in the cognitive
landscape experienced by agent, you
control what the agent do directly.
So there are two things that are
very stereotypically associated with
cognitive security. This is Russian
propaganda, not quite propaganda.
Cognitive warfare campaigns pretty much
around the world more generally the
propaganda that is used by authoritarian
regimes to get stuff going and the
cults that historically are tied
to the worry of brain control by evil
cults that can control you from afar
like you had a telecommand. And so
in both cases actually,
let us get back a bit. When you are a
state that does propaganda and when
you are a state you can do a lot of
material engineering so producing the
environmental states in which people
live in. And for example,
if you look at the city of Brazilia,
which is one of the very few
specifically built capital city that
exists in the world, there is like one
in there is Brazilian and there is like
maybe four others. And those cities are
basically very big, glorified
administrative centers. And Brazilian in
particular, it has neighborhoods
for work, neighborhoods for leisure,
neighborhoods for habitation.
It is extremely divided and because of
this dividedness you basically don't get
to do stuff that are not work or hang
out with your family. That is not a
possibility. And of course this changed
massively the way people experience
their life and this change massively the
topology of this network that can
emerge. But when you are doing cognitive
warfare in the sense that NATO defines
so you are state or state organization
and you are trying to fuck with another
state or state organization you don't
get to just build cities that are bad
but it's not possibility that you have.
So what the Russians do in a systematic
way is to try to basically create dots
over what information is reliable so
that people feel paralyzed. The target,
I must insist critically is not the
information that is available. It shows
that people can have the actionability
that the people can give to the
information. And so they tend to
propagate a lot of conspiracy theory
nonsense because it occupies a lot of
space and it prevents the possibility
for public debates to occur. And another
strategy they use is to manipulate the
personal identity that are embedded
often in ethnicity or in the case of
the US advanced countries
where political life is mostly decoupled
from ethnicity. And I understand the
irony to say that this is the case in
the US. But you don't have ethnically
specific parties or armed forces, so
this is less the case than elsewhere.
So in these countries they will use
political identity, so they will use
republican identity or leftist
identity, but mostly republican identity
to just push complete nonsense and
get people to act in a way that overall
destabilizes the grip of the US over
their own population. And so this is the
basic way
that we do connective warfare. And you
can understand this in terms of social
constraints because again, the target
is not like information in of itself.
It's the possibility that is afforded by
the social context in which we evolve at
an instant. The goal is to create doubts
and noise in the public setting. It's
rate constraints that are not compatible
with efficient collective organization.
And a way where you do it
is when you see it being done in a much
more systematic and efficient way is of
course with intra state influence where
state administrators and state
institutions, they try to create grip
over a population. And if you look
at the birth of nationalism like we have
the notion today that nations are
somewhat coherent political groups that
let us say the French hang out together
and take decision together. This notion,
it's not quite recent, strictly
speaking, but the fact that it's
dominant, that it is just a standard
expectation, is very recent. And it
derives from the French that
somehow where a group of administrators
somehow managed to convince everyone
that they shared identity and they
shared mutual obligation,
responsibility in virtue of this
identity. And the way in which
this happens is they sent instituters in
villages and they sent soldiers and the
children had to listen to the
instituters explain to them that they
were French and they needed to do French
things like going to war for France.
And if you did not let the children do
that, you went to prison. And no one
wants to go to prison. Of course,
I'm doing a very huge caricature here.
There is not a shadowy set of influence
that sense. This is an
overspecification. But what happened is
that the French state managed to create
a social niche up in a very very foreign
villages where French
hood became a basic condition of
existence. Most of your social thing,
the fact that you were legally
recognized as existing, the activities
or activities that you had lot of those
were embedded in your perception of
being French. And so when this is the
case and when you see that
administration tends to be on top of
things, administration tells you you
have to go to war in virtue of your
freshness, then you go to war. You don't
fight against the administration. You
fight against whoever administration
tells you fact that you have agreed
implicitly that you are French
beforehand makes this lot harder to
resist basically than if the state just
sent soldier at you and kidnapped you
and gave you a swear until you fight.
This is not how you make things
efficient. Army Ras this way are
unorganized. They are unmotivated, they
are not good. And if you want people to
have stakes, you need to give them power
or you need to give them the impression
they have power because they are French.
And here. French Governs things.
And whether you are in the set of French
that actually direct things or not,
bad question to ask. Just go to the
trenches. And this type of
things we would not think as cognitive
warfare because we would not think as
between. Implicitly, when we talk about
warfare, we talk about between states or
between nation conflict. And this is
within a nation, within a social group.
But you can look at cults and
how they create social influence. You
can look at, for example, one of the
most famous cults that existed, which is
the Munis or the Unification Church.
They were widely accused to make
brainwashing. They were accused to
somehow control people and make them do
things they don't want to do. That is
not a possibility. You have an
organization like you cannot kidnap
people and hope that it will be okay.
You will get killed by police if you do
that. Most likely in the US. In this
specific space where the education
church evolved. What you can do is to
create a context where you have a huge
grip over what people can and cannot
say, what they can and cannot think
about themselves. You can tell them that
your leader is the coming of Jesus that
is going to bring everyone in paradise.
And you can make people go to work
sessions, talk about it and you can just
physically cling to those people all the
time until you are quite confident that
they feel that whatever you are doing is
important. And you can have very big
emotional ritual where everyone cries
and become extremely embedded in the
group membership. And you can be
extremely supportive of group members
while being extremely aggressive to
anything that go away from group
identity. And when you process this
environment and people and goats in this
environment for a long time, they tend
to develop this group identity. So when
you tell them the big leader tells you
to give us 20,000
for your ancestors not to go to hell,
that seems reasonable. That seems like a
reasonable ask, which it would not
unless you had a very tight control over
the social environment of someone
because then it's not just giving money
in exchange for a good. This is about
upholding your self identity as someone
who follows and believes the culture.
And yet again, this is something that is
formalized directly in terms of
constraints because this is about what
you can and cannot do in a given social
context. This is not about abstract
beliefs, it's not about brain control.
It's not about anything but what you can
and cannot do in a given social context.
All right, there was a ton there. Let me
kind of retrace a few of the pieces that
I heard there. So towards framing
cognitive security under this cognitive
constraint framework that you're
discussing, for which active inference
under the free energy principle is the
process theory that gets it done. First
you described how modern states have a
lot of administrative capacity and
affordances, especially through writing
and especially again in the last decades
and centuries of information environment
changes. And then you pointed to two
kind of patterns or genres or motifs of
influence or cognitive warfare,
propaganda and cults discussed.
One example of them surely could have
gone into more detail, or there's other
examples and perspectives and so on.
And as Mao alluded
to earlier, precision modulation is a
key aspect of constraint. I mean,
precision modulation of how tightly
you're holding the baseball bat, the
movement, its precision in wobble is
going to be related to the grasp. And so
increasing uncertainty can lead to
anxiety and doubt. All of that's very
wrapped up in a narrative setting. Then
you discussed how there's a ratcheting
of thinking and acting like a state
breaking symmetries like states do, and
getting grasp over the subject,
over the citizen. That's a complex
topic, but that's what you went and then
there are asymmetries around control
of the environment, the information
environment, ability to read, write,
edit in the information environment.
And that leads to these engineered
distributions of what is important or
what means what, which justifies or even
writes the blank check for requests of
funds, whatever the narrative is around
those funds. But more fundamentally,
those strategies can threaten sense
making, which is to say the inbound
perceptual component of active
inference, and then also decision making
and action selection, which is the
fundamental complement the outbound
aspect of active inference.
I'll read another comment from the Live.
Oh yeah? Do you want to add anything
else on? Like, I'd like to point out a
very specific example that is
contemporary, which is the
campaign by Israel to remove people from
the Gaza band. So just I
don't know when people will watch it.
So on the 7 October, 11 days ago,
Hamas, which is a terrorist
organization, Islamist organization that
is dominant in the Gazaban, attacked
Israeli and slaughtered IRA settlers
that were nearby and slaughtered
tourists that were nearby and attacked
military bases. They made, I think,
2000 deaths.
The state of Israel that is
currently led by very far right parties,
things that we would not have equivalent
of in Europe or the US has decided to
answer by blaming each individual
Palestinian for this and trying to
deport them like
this is not itself. What I'm trying to
comment about what I'm trying to comment
about is that every single comment
you will see about it on Twitter makes
the confusion between Hamas and
Palestinian on one side and Netanyahu
and the Israeli on the other side. And
so this produces a framing that says
basically people
are trying to decide whether the AMAs
action are justified or not. And
implicitly in this debate, they create a
context.
Wherever group
lose the GMAC debate gets to be killed
to the last. And so you
produce very, very basically that
produce a framing that makes the only
possibility in the conflict
extermination, because each side this
is not two side dynamic. There is no
Palestinian and there is the Israeli and
there is the I will
not make all the relation but by this
framing. Like the framing that either
the Arabs or the Jew must prevail and
kill the other. You give a lot of power
for groups to just make this a genocidal
war and justify things like cutting
water to 1 million people because like,
200 of them committed massacre.
And I do not know if there is a single
actor that tried to get this. I do not
think this is the case. But this is a
very powerful instance of how procrang
that does not need to target what you
believe, but it does need to target how
you frame problems.
Yeah. Lot to say on that.
Any last pieces you
want to discuss?
No, it is good. I have talked a lot.
I'd like to stop talking you.
Okay, well, thank you. We will
send out updates to people about the
coming weeks, so thank
you. All right, bye.
Ciao. Thanks for your attention.