You. Hello. Thanks for all joining.
It's active textbook group cohort one
meeting 22,
chapter nine on October 28.
Okay, we're in the second discussion
on chapter nine,
model based data analysis.
Would anyone like to add anything they
want or mention how the
generative model discussion from the
previous 1 hour relates
to model based data analysis? How does
chapter four relate to chapter nine?
What does chapter nine address?
What do chapters six and nine address
that chapter four doesn't?
Um, I mean, six is about
thinking about applying it in,
like, incredibly kind of simplified
step by step kind of way.
And nine is very specifically about
answering scientific questions with it
and doing that with.
This metabasian. It's like almost
nested.
Sort of schema of active inference.
So, I mean, that's the
through line, I guess, but I'm
not sure more. Than that what to say.
That's really insightful. Thank you,
Ali.
Yeah, actually, I would compare it to a
kind of learning how to solve
problems in, I don't know, mathematics
or other physics or other areas.
For example, in chapter four,
we acquired some necessary knowledge or
prerequisite about how
to think about the phenomena or the
problem we're dealing with. Chapter six
kind of outlines a roadmap a
roadmap about how exactly
we should proceed to solve that problem
in a kind of formulaic way.
And chapter nine, actually,
in chapter nine, we get our hands dirty
and try to solve some
of the actual or empirical problems with
the tools or techniques we had learned
in chapter four and six. So in
this case, I somehow
think of chapter nine as a kind of case
of study well,
kind of case of studies or a kind of
solved problem section of this
textbook. And, yeah,
I don't know how much that captures
their nature. That's great.
Wow. Great thoughts. I totally
agree.
Let's look at the table of contents.
Chapter one, special overview.
Chapter mirror symmetry.
Same, but different with ten.
So now in the middle eight chapters,
two chapters on the low road
and the high road, helping two different
approaches which can be developed,
like in a lot more detail,
to approach active inference from two
fascinating and non controversial
starting points Bayesian inference from
the low road free energy principle
and the repeated measurement persistence
imperative.
Chapter four is the first chapter on
active inference. Active inference is
about the generative models that are
being specified and how they're being
computed. After just
one chapter on active inference, it goes
to the area where the most research
and modeling has been done in active
inference, which is computational
manalian neuroanatomy.
One chapter on active,
one chapter on the primary domain.
First half of the book,
second half of the book. This is the
part where you're going to be in
parallel, perhaps on your first, but
perhaps not on your first reading.
You're going to be doing playing through
these applied
aspects of modeling.
First is the recipe for designing active
inference models. In Chapter Six, as
both of you have, very nicely
set.
Then the Figure
4.3 Dialectic discrete Continuous
Time is revisited in two chapters
because it probably it's one
key difference. It's a minimum of two.
So it prevents, like any like, oh,
well, it has to be a PMDP. It's like,
well, obviously not.
So it keeps the space of generative
modeling open and it allows for
discussion of the very interesting topic
of hybrid active
inference nested models with continuous
actuators, for example, but discrete
decision making apparatus.
So it just is like wanting to cover
these two key types of models in a bit
more detail than was addressed in
Chapter Four. But this was the first
possible moment to address it after 4.3.
Just kidding. Maybe not.
Then Chapter Nine, yeah,
where we are now, which is just, okay,
you've built your pure discrete time
pure continuous time or hybrid
generative model. If it's a toy model,
you can just generate data and just do
whatever you want. Or you
might have data from sensors or real
world or however that's in the data
format that your generative model
expected to receive, which was part of
your design process, you could have
determined what structure literally the
data is going to be in. Is it going to
be like, yes, data can be reshaped, but
just broadly, is it like 256
sensors in a row of one? Or is it like
eight by eight? Just those kinds of
questions. So that when the data start
coming in for the experiment, whether
you generated the data from the
generative model or whether you're using
it in a purely recognition model
capacity on real world
data, what does it look like to
do statistical modeling with
these statistical models that we've been
using?
And then chapter ten is a review.
It restates what each chapter does,
provides some further thoughts,
and just summarizes the unifying
capacity of active inference modeling.
Then there are the appendices Ali.
Also one in my opinion, very interesting
section of Chapter Nine is the section
on models of false inference,
section 9.7, in which there's an
interesting definition of
the disorders, I mean the
mental disorders, and how we
can actually computationally model those
different disorders.
Sorry. It says that here the
disorder does not necessarily imply that
the inferential mechanism is flawed. In
most of the studies, the inferential
mechanism operates normally but based on
a flawed generative model. So that's
basically what we had learned about how
we can somehow
update our beliefs or correct our
perceptions based on either refining
our generative model or modifying our
generative model. Or somehow,
sometimes we can just well,
act upon those errors and try to reduce
our uncertainties. But in this case,
it's a very interesting point on the
case of computational pathologies
because oftentimes people ask,
well, what does active inference
actually explain? So I think this is
a very good example of its very
meaningful and significant application
in any sense of the word. So if we
can somehow computationally model
these kind of disorders, we'll most
probably have a much better
understanding of its origin and
the way to probable
treatments of those disorders and many
other applications can comes
to mind. But yeah, I think this part
of the chapter nine is something
that was not addressed quite explicitly
in the previous chapters and in my
opinion is the most interesting part of
this one. Great.
Awesome. Yeah. It reminds me of the
table in chapter four, or sorry,
chapter five with the neurotransmitters.
So they were still at the organ systems
level in chapter five. But five
is very much related to nine, I guess in
that sense as well, because it's
like, here's what dopamine does, here's
what acetylcholine does just at
the computational model level. And then
here it's like that computational model
was fit, like between the phenomena,
like attention or policy precision or
however phenomena to a molecule
in chapter five. Here, the phenomena
is being connected to a real human
clinical application.
So it's not that we're saying or anyone
is saying or anything like that, that
the molecule is being directly linked
to this paper,
even if it's mentioned. The direct
linkage approach is people in group
X have more molecule,
have less molecule,
and even the neuroimaging approach can
be seen as a variant of that, which is
people in group X have more brain
activation pattern.
In computational pathology, those kinds
of biochemical measurements and
neuroimaging measurements can, and they
are used. However,
this type of computational modeling is
referring to parametric modeling,
where the parameters are related to
the pathology.
So it's not an a priori classification
of those with and without. And then
descriptive statistics showing that a
biochemical or a brain imaging pattern
are differentially expressed.
That's descriptive statistics. It's not
computational pathology. It might be
precision pathology,
but it could still be precision or big
data or however, with just like purely
doing data summaries, doing a random
forest model to diagnose. These models
have a cognitive structural hypothesis
about the nature of these phenomena,
like the ocular motor syndromes. Again,
it's not just people with the diagnosis
and without. It's a neurocognitive model
of eye behavior.
And then explanations
can be made from clinical data by
rendering various aspects of the
generative model conditionally
independent of others, ocular motor
syndrome, such as intranuclear
optipomilegias, may be induced.
So if you just were diagnosing these as
different conditions, maybe they have
similar ideologies how the condition
arises, maybe they have different,
maybe they have multiple.
But these two conditions computationally
can be understood as parametric
modulating in a
computational model of ocular motor
behavior.
This isn't people with internuclear
opto, DA, DA, DA have higher glucose or
lower glucose or this brain region or
this aspect of them, those are
all absolutely valid approaches.
That's like scientific methodological
pluralism, which is like, it's okay that
people want to do different approaches.
Everybody's contributing to a common
people who care about this and are
creating high quality reproducible data,
their data will always be useful and
their perspectives are valid and we
don't want to have a discourse space on
inter nuclear optipomygia that's
saying that one model is like simply the
only correct model.
This paper makes a positive contribution
and points to some new ways of
thinking about various
pathologies and
thinking beyond the ways that they've
been worked on before,
where one can imagine that before 2000
and so on, you had what health records.
And you have some double blind
experiments. And so you might do a meta
analysis to find correlations with
features of people and all of those
things that we've been describing. But
it was not plausible to
actually implement computational models
of these phenomena. Now,
interestingly, that's something that can
be worked on by researchers directly,
and then somebody can a doctor could
download Ocular motor syndromes
programming,
whatever it is, but this can be
developed in a pure research context.
And the Generative Model is like the
interface for the
kind of information that might not be
available to the person developing the
Generative Model because
it relates to a lot of problems and
issues about data availability.
That's one kind of just side note, but
dilly. Thanks for raising that point
that I just wanted to emphasize and
unpack, which is that this table,
which is taking up two and a half pages
of a pretty short book is describing.
These are like the cases that can be
brought up, which they're providing in a
helpful table for what active inference
describes. So if the principle of least
action, gauge theory, et cetera,
sophistication does not interest one,
these are more pragmatic value.
Now that will probably move the goalpost
to show me where the computational
modeling helped somebody with delusions
and that's a fine place to want to go.
But it's also a standard and an approach
that it's not related
to the substance of the theoretical
development.
I mean, I think you could probably the
response to that question might be.
Something like the difficulty of
implementing that model in a way that
provides actionable
real time affordances
to address the aberrant
priors in a way that's causally.
It's going to actually affect that
system. We need
either more compute or a particular kind
of algorithmic medicine that doesn't
exist yet or et cetera. But that's not
a problem with the particular approach,
it's just an insufficiency of ability
to enact it, I guess.
But I wanted to ask a question about
specifically this aberrant prior
beliefs. It says ultimately the
pathology is a consequence of aberrant
prior beliefs. It's not the Generative
Model, it's aberrant prior beliefs.
I think this is like Ellie's point and
everything that you just went through is
correct that this is kind of where the
rubber really meets the road for its
value in demonstrating or whatever. But
I'm wondering also.
To me that there's like an easy
confusion thing there about beliefs and
priors. If they just believed the
right thing. Then they wouldn't have
these that's not.
Really what that means though, right?
Is another way of saying this, like in
the Ocular motor.
Disorder case, like a kind
of neurobiological bias
in some kinds of cells or whatever,
right. That's pathologically
different than normal or whatever,
like some receptor
for a particular chemical or
whatever, is that a kind of thing?
That the way of saying that differently
in that particular case that is.
More. Commensurate with what they're
actually saying there. Or like not more
commensurate, but just not relying
on jargon and or
domain knowledge specific for what they
mean by beliefs and priors or is
that not right?
Yeah, well, there's a lot there. Are you
talking about the comparison of the
terms beliefs and priors in relationship
to the way people might naturally
interpret such beliefs to
be, and they may indeed be people's
beliefs about the world in the
conversational sense?
Like some beliefs are just your retinal
states but other states of the world,
as if or really are your states on other
things. Right?
Yeah, I guess I'm asking if beliefs
is in some cases
it is beliefs, but it's also another way
of stating if another way of stating
that is a structural
systemic bias for one thing or another
or whatever in that context, is that
physical or informational kind of non
folk psychology? Is that commensurate
with what they mean by beliefs there?
Okay, let's try to yeah, Ali, please,
first, sorry.
I'm sorry, but you mean the statistical
use of the word belief? Because in
statistics and in folk psychology,
as far as I know, this term is used in
quite different ways. So I
guess that what you're talking about is
the statistical sense of the word
belief. And if it maps onto the folk
psychological sense of this
term or am I missing something here?
Well, let's just take two steps back for
a second. And just in the text it says
at the bottom of page 185 here at
the top of that yeah, it says the
infertile mechanism operates normally
but based on a flawed generative model.
This means that ultimately pathology is
a consequence of aberrant prior beliefs.
Yeah. And I'm asking a
kind of just to explicate different
whatever right
there in. The context of psychological
disorders, which is not necessarily
pathology. But I'm just you know, if you
tell somebody, oh, yeah, it helps with
or is the impetus or whatever for this
whole thing was to think about
specifically like schizophrenia and
other but that.
Immediately kind of puts it in that.
Category or that context of definitions.
And so just to kind
of. Nuance the
term their beliefs a little bit.
Yeah. Is it commensurate with the rest
of the text to say in
the case of this specifically of this
oculine motor disorder category,
like you're saying beliefs in the retina
or something that is like
cones, like being sensitive to
something. Well, it's just what they are
sensitive to and in this particular
person they're just
sensitive to or whatever the relevant
structure is there. But it's sensitive
to something. Right. And that's
its belief in some sense.
I'm not looking for what's the
statistical definition or anything like
that, but just is that completely off
track or is. That I have a thought, but
Ali, if you want to make a response
please.
Yeah. I think that this term
belief and its different meanings in
different contexts actually sort
of bleed into each other and there
cannot possibly be separated cleanly
from each other. So in this particular
case I believe that the word belief
partly is this folk
psychological sense of the word and
partly it's based on the kind
of philosophical epistemological sense
of this word. Because especially in
epistemology when philosophers talk
about belief, usually they don't mean
just the folk psychological sense of
this term, although it relates to that
concept, but it's much more nuanced than
that. So in the case of Oculomotor
pathology well, I believe that the word
belief somehow can be
interpreted in a little more abstract
philosophical sense of or
epistemological sense of this word than
our folks psychological sense of
it. But again,
I think it also has some overlappings
with the folk psychological sense of it
as well.
Great thought just to kind of restate
that then say what I was planning to
before. So here it's situational where
people talk commonly about don't talk
about beliefs like the eye, like where
it believes it should be looking,
people don't talk about that. But there
might be another cognitive model that
does align very well with an expressed
felt cognitive belief and
everything in between and bundles that
are mixed like people who believe that
they're accurate on a task but actually
are low accuracy. So it's going to be
very model specific, I think how it maps
to different people's understanding.
But that was what Ali's response
kind of made me think about and that's
why I didn't choose an example like
Delusions to focus on because that is
related to a felt or experienced or
reported phenomena.
Okay, so beliefs
and priors and this question of
disorders of inference which as Brock
mentioned was like part of the early
impetus in relating to studying for
example, schizophrenia and fristin's
earlier and continued work.
Maybe there's a part of missing and
maybe it's not the right context or way,
but I think first
we can narrowly interpret what they use
to mean disorder and then have a more
broad perspective. So I
read this does not necessarily imply the
inferential mechanisms flawed. Like the
CPU has the right number of cycles,
the machinery are not flawed, the car is
operating at normal burning temperature.
Given its generative model as specified
hashtag chapter four it
is doing appropriate variational,
message passing, belief propagation,
approximate Bayesian computation,
Bayesian brain however you want to see
it. Given what this person has
experienced and their parameterization,
it's not the case that they're making a
fallacious estimate.
Now that's sort of in their situation
where it's like, yeah, okay, but you're
going to say that for whatever they do
do. But that's kind of that tautology.
It's like, right, that's our best
estimate of the system as it is is just
how it is in most
of the studies reviewed in Table 9.1,
which is to say the pathologies
that are identified in Table 9.1,
the inferential mechanism operates
normally as per the previous meaning,
but based upon a flawed generative
model. And it's literally like there's
the rub. Aberrant prior beliefs is like,
what? And so that is where I would say
there's two ways to zoom out from that
and contextualize that statement. The
first is aberrant. Prior beliefs are not
intrinsically aberrant, whether they're
subconsciously or consciously held.
Belief in itself is not aberrant.
But there's the niche and especially
just the human cultural when we're
talking about these felt beliefs. So in
the niche, it's like there is ant
colonies that were high foraging and low
foraging. Those are not aberrances of
foraging behavior. That's variation in
foraging behavior with respect to
variation in weather. And there was
probably decades where one was better
than the other. And that's why
there's evolution. So it's
like, what's the purpose? Okay, so level
one of aberrant is in a niche context
and then especially for these
expressively human experienced
settings, that's where I think there's
an opportunity, again, not saying that
this paragraph is the right place in
this textbook, but that's where it's
important to also bring in.
I'm not expert in this area, but like
Foucault social descriptions of
mental illness diagnosis.
Are only crazy if majority of people.
This book, which I've mentioned on live
streams before. If I could just describe
why I bring it. Up and, like, how I
think it's relevant to chapter nine is
just like she's saying there's different
methods and there's different
theoretical interpretations and it's
very clear and it's very
pluralist. And though guided,
everybody will also, I think, see like
deeper aspects too. But just I studied
with Helen in Stanford and
she was just very like it was very
interesting to see that coming from
philosophy because in the scientific
domains it's like not framed that way.
We could have a generative model for
these conditions and scenarios
that integrates different types of
information in a situational
way with the sparse model and we could
all work on that and then different
people could have different data sets or
different public or private data sets.
But that requires not just sort of like
operational coordination and
ontology driven design and other
features, but it also requires basically
personally held commitment to pluralism,
at least in practice because there's too
many methods and methods are too last
mile to dictate
models of phenomena. These are not
measurements, but they're generated
alongside and with and from
measurements.
And so that's not descriptive statistics
per se and that's a major difference
in what you can do with the tail of two
densities approaches
these situations differently
than one might see in a health
journal showing the
population level factors associated with
a disease.
This is a different kind of study but it
could be done in a population context
which has been done extensively in SPM
and Neuroimaging.
So you can still bring in features of
the people and understand how different
features of people are quite literally
associated with the diagnosis.
And that is seen as
a label on a neurocognitive
model, a generative model. Now what's
the generative model? Chapter Four
chapter Six and then it's like, okay,
we're just going to say that all of the
people's ocular motor circuitry are
structurally the same and we're going to
explore how the two groups differ in the
parameter estimates of these different
features. Or you could say I'm studying
a situation where this region has been
severed. So the hypothesis I'm testing
is actually whether this connectivity
versus this connectivity is going to
have this observable difference that's
testing a structural hypothesis. So you
could test parametric hypotheses within
a generative model and or structural
hypotheses across. But to kind of return
to this point those are these two ways
that the model can be quote in in their,
you know, way aberrant or flawed.
Quite literally it could be a parametric
estimate that's aberrant which
as discussed does not mean intrinsically
bad number 4.2 or three 7.3 is
not bad. It's about its relationship
within a niche and a fitness context and
like all of that. So it could be a
parametric aberrance with
respect to a state estimator like an
expectation on a variable or precision.
So that's the LaPlace approximation.
It's the hierarchical predictive
processing approximation structure,
expectation variance, mean variance,
mode variance, center of the path,
width of the path those are
the two. Gaussian distribution takes two
parameters. LaPlace approximation takes
two parameters. Hierarchical message
passing has these kinds of
variables or it can
be structural differences which is quite
open ended.
How is this useful?
An example is provided here,
potentially. For example, let's just say
that there's people who do and do not
have a certain situation.
Some moths go towards the light and some
don't. Is that because of
differences in their behavior where
the statistical variance gets loaded
onto differences in their realized
preference vector or their habit
e? So there could be a behavioral
setup that would do the fibonacci
pattern of variability or just whatever
it happened to be which is extensively
described in SPM how to time different
behavioral stimuli,
some natural observational setting or
controlled behavioral setting both of
which have pros and cons. Both quote
controlled conditions in the lab and
natural observation. They have pros and
cons. But the idea in model based
analysis is that those can be the
observables and you may or may not
control the observations, but at least
you know what they are. And then you can
explore whether differences in behavior
end up being reflected in statistically
differentiable parameter estimates for
prior preference or for prior d or
for the fixed form term e.
Ali.
Yes. For what it's worth, I also put a
quote from this recent paper by Car
Pristen from a couple of months ago,
which is, by the way, is a great
overview of this whole field of
computation psychiatry through the lens
of active inference. And here
it provides a clear and explicit
definition of the term belief used in
this area. So I thought
that might be helpful here. The kind of
beliefs here are Bayesian beliefs. And
then it goes on to describe what
Bayesian beliefs mean.
Awesome.
Um cool. That was super
clarifying. I think it
makes a lot of sense.
Maybe. I don't know if the
answer was already given exactly,
or I'll just ask it a different,
slightly different way about.
The separation between the generative
model and the priors. Here in this
toy frog jumping example are
the aberrant priors, the frog apple
distribution on that belief beforehand,
and.
The. Observation, the updating, all of
that being the generative model is
working as intended. But it's just
that the priors were
so out of whack that when
the generative model
kind of observes and steps through or
whatever, that it
just ends up in the wrong state and or
is the likelihood model I'm not sure.
I guess in the toy example there. How
you could have how it would be. I guess
the part that's missing there is the
context, maybe. But yeah, like if I had
a prior belief that was different than
your prior belief, but we didn't
have a disorder or whatever, I would
imagine our priors wouldn't be the same,
but they would still kind of converge.
So I'm not sure how you get there
without an outside prior
belief. Or something about the
environment that's totally wrong,
right? Or something
else about the environment or the
likelihood model is somehow really
wrong. Yeah,
thanks. Great question. Those are
exactly the two greetings. Welcome back.
Ali those are exactly like the two. Let
me unpack that in the pathology example.
So society expects us and or
we actually die or have consequences
with when the frog when it's a frog,
you're not supposed to eat it. Apples
are okay to eat.
Now, if you turn down too many apples,
you starve. If you eat too many frogs,
you die. So you have to balance your
type one and type two false positive and
false negative error rates in this
eat, do not eat, jump, does not jump
observation setting. Because these
are idle classifiers here. But we can
imagine these as more action oriented
classifiers. Apples are for eating.
Frogs are for throwing.
Now, society and or the niche defines
aberrant behavior as
one that does not conform to
expectations or to
a thriving state in the niche while
recognizing that all parameter values
that are actually observed are at least
there. Now, that doesn't mean you want
them to be there, they want them. But
also then that's a belief an agent has
about another system that also exists.
So there would be many ways to
see that aberrant behavior. So if
you like speaking to the person who
discards too many apples, maybe they
believe that they have a strong prior on
frogs 0.5 or
their likelihood, which is also a
parametric belief, is different.
They have a different action mapping.
Now that here's the question. Now you
put them in the lab and you have jumping
and non jumping frogs and apples.
And then you can use those experimental
techniques on
a computational model narrowly to
determine do they simply expect frogs
to appear but they know what frogs and
apples do?
Or do they have an
appropriate belief about the likelihood
a priori of frogs and apples but they
have an incorrect action mapping?
I hope I said it correctly, but I think
you get the picture. The point is you
could then use experiments to determine
whether groups of people who had
effective or ineffective behavior and
then if somebody, for example, had an
overestimate of frogs, then the message
to pass is frogs are not as common as
you think. Whereas if
there was somebody with a variance
interpretable variance here
in the likelihood model difference with
some other preference again, keeping in
mind that that's still like it's like
outlier detection and attracting
which isn't even necessarily a
preferable thing. But just pointing out,
just statistically, this person's model
would be updated by saying it's not
known that apples can jump, but actually
they can. It's possible that apples
jump, so next time something jumps,
don't just throw it away.
And those are very different points
to convey and
this is a very simple example,
but it's helpful to think about because
those are the kinds of parameter if this
was your model of schizophrenia, those
would be your levers or your knobs.
If you had a more complex model and the
models are more complex, then there's a
lot more associated challenge.
Yeah, Brock. Oh, no, I was just going to
say that was really helpful.
I don't even know, it seems good.
Obviously I know next to nothing, I
guess, about psychiatry.
I don't know how you do it though,
without something like this.
I guess they were doing something kind
of like this approximately informally to
some degree, in some cases, but it would
seem like just guessing almost,
I don't know. Yeah, well, I could infer
about schizophrenia without something
like this. Well,
to simplify a complex area, there was
studies that associated either a
biomolecule or a genetic variant, but
especially biomolecules in brain imaging
directly to a diagnosis which from a
health record perspective exactly makes
sense. It's the data you have. However,
this is an unobserved model
of. The phenomena itself that can
incorporate measurements, including
health records, and that allows the
development of an actual understanding
of the ethiology and the causation and
therefore could be used to justify
traditionally understood interventions
or suggest different behavior
and interventions like maybe you don't
just, oh, you're low on this, just take
this thing that raises it. It's like
maybe that's not exactly the. Move,
but just more precise affordance
to do that. Yeah, including the
counterfactuals, like in a clinical
setting that is going to be quite
interesting. All right, let's just in
the last minutes look to Ten Minsky
active inference as a unified theory of
sentient behavior. If anybody
wants to do a little like Twitter thread
recap on the sentient the
sentience discourse over the last few
weeks, I'm sure we can find some funny
tweets, but with the sentient pong
playing neurons and just wave after wave
of semantic discussion about the
term sentient. In this chapter
we wrap up active inference main
theoretical points from the first part
of the book, chapter one through five,
and its practical implementations from
the second part six through ten. Then we
connect the dots. We abstract away from
the specific active inference models
discussed in previous chapters to focus
on integrative aspects of the framework
benefits of activ.
Summary of the book 10.2, chapter one,
chapter two, chapter three, chapter 4567
and eight, no love chapter
nine. You just read it. Go read it
again. Connecting the dots.
The integrative perspective on active
inference,
interestingly framed in terms of some
early dennett work.
A call to model the whole iguana a
complete cognitive creature, perhaps a
simple one, and an environmental niche
for it to cope with rather than
single dimensional analyses
and measurements on a complex system
just too much like a Whirlwind to
just measure and oh, well,
brain regions correlated with this and
this region is correlated with that.
Those kinds of structural and
behavioral, morphological any given
measurement does not
ever get at the underlying causal
structure unless you specifically model
it that way.
Active inference helps with that issue
by offering a first principle account of
the ways in which organisms solve their
adaptive problems. So by framing
attention, memory, anticipation under
common computational
framings and a unified imperative
it's possible to integrate different
kinds of phenomena. Memory attention
can be thought of as optimizing the same
objective.
Ten four predictive brains, predictive
minds and predictive processing.
Kind of a provocative selection.
Active inference creatures, or their
brains are probabilistic inference
machines connecting to the kind of
focus of predictive mind, predictive
brain, predictive processing, coding
area, which is like the real time and
anticipatory, especially real. Time
unfolding anticipation self evidencing
prediction predictive
processing specifically Livestream 43
perception section 10.5 helmholtz
perception is unconscious inference then
how that was implemented in Bayesian
brain Bayesian brain the
inactive turn the pragmatic turn action
control bringing action in
end of Livestream. 43 End of paper. 43
Idea motor, cybernetic, some other
ontologies that are kind of like easily
functionally equated with parts of
active idea motor theory, cybernetics,
optimal control theory, utility,
decision making, Bayesian decision,
reinforcement, learning, planning as
inference, behavior and bounded
rationality. And then, specifically,
what free energy brings into bounded
rationality, valence, emotion,
motivation, homeostasis alistasis and
terraceptive processing, attention,
salience, epistemic dynamics, rural
learning, causal inference, fast
generalization and next
steps social machine
learning and robotics. Summary.
Lord of the Rings, we are confident that
you will continue to pursue active
inference in some form.
So it's a quite long chap. There's a lot
in it. We'll talk about it
next time. Thank you, fellas.