Hello and welcome. It's July 29,
2023, and we're here in session
three discussion of the
course physics's Information Processing
at the Active Inference Institute.
We're having a follow up discussion on
Chris Fields's third lecture on quantum
reference frames, and we're looking
forward to your participation. So if
you're watching along live and you've
been invited to the calendar event,
it's not too late to jump in. If you're
watching on YouTube, you can write any
questions or comments in the live chat
with Dean And. Ander here we're going to
be looking at some of the key points and
taking it in a few different directions,
sharing our reference frames, making a
shared one. So, Andrew, would be awesome
to have you zoom in a little bit on the
slide and then feel free to
take us through some of the key points
so that we can see a little bit how
you're seeing it. Thank you. That looks
good. Yes. Okay, so let's start by
reviewing the last lecture from
a couple of weeks ago, and then we can
open up the discussions. If there's any
questions that appear in the live chat,
we can address those. All right. So
lecture two, Chris introduced this idea
of the information processing
between system A and B, where they
interact via qubits on a boundary, and
they have reference frames that
give meaning to this communication. You
want to think of information processing
as a communication channel, the way
Shannon thought about it. So that was in
lecture two. And lecture three a couple
weeks ago tried to
make this more explicit by emphasizing
the idea that this has to be physically
embodied somewhere. Okay. And I
think that because we are so used to
information being fungible in
no small part because of the Internet
and everything, it's a little hard
to understand at first when the claim is
made that you have a QRF that it's non
fungible or you have a piece of quantum
information that's non fungible or
things like the no Cloning theorem.
We're so used to information being
fungible, to it being zeros and ones
that it's a bit of a
change in mindset at first, but that's
exactly what lecture three introduced.
This was all stuff, right? Could you
maybe just unpack that a little bit?
What would it mean for information to be
fungible? Or what's that stance like?
And then, what does it mean for
information to be non fungible? And what
is that stance like? Yeah, I'm out
to get there. So let me scroll down the
slides, because that's addressed here.
So maybe I should have kept this in the
beginning, but anyways, session two
talked about how information theory
makes this simple and obvious. Okay.
And in session three, we talk about
reference frames and mechanistically,
how all of this works.
So, yeah, let's address that question of
the difference between
hold on 1 second. Let me use my mouse to
scroll down here.
Okay, so that's a little faster. Right.
Okay. Can you restate
your question, Daniel? Yeah. What would
it mean for information to be fungible
or non fungible? People might be
familiar with that in the economic
setting with non fungible tokens and all
of that, but what are we talking about
with informational fungibility? I think
it basically comes down to whether
you can replicate. I mean, it's
basically the difference between
classical and quantum information. As
far as I know, fungible information
is everything that you can basically
turn into a message of zeros and ones.
How you transmit it may be different,
the channel, the physical hardware and
so on. But at the end of the day,
it's something that you can write on a
boundary and something that you can
transmit at zeros and ones. Whereas
quantum information,
you literally have to send the hardware,
the piece of hardware, the QRF. At least
that's how I understand it. So a simple
answer might be that
it's information encoded in a piece of
software versus a piece of hardware.
But I don't think that analogy is
perfect. Yeah. Dean, what do you
think? Here's what I'm curious about.
And again, you guys can help me with
this. As opposed to reference frames, I
oftentimes default to
frame of reference. And I know that in
one of the live streams, what I tried to
bring out was the idea that there was an
ice cream cone looking at an ice cream
truck. And the question was always
whether or not which one of those two
entities, one is in the foreground and
one is in the background. And in this
slide that Ander has up the question is,
is the non fungibility because only
A and B can decide whether the
VA as seen by B, the A is deeper
into that image based on our frame
of reference. And the B is closer or is
the B the one that's actually deeper and
the A is the one that's in the
foreground? And I was wondering whether
the idea of non copyability is because
of that depth of field aspect that
cannot be determined unless it's
literally handed over the way that Chris
was describing it. I think that's
basically think I'm
not sure that I can answer your
question, but I think I have the feeling
that Chris well, Chris said this in the
lecture, that at the end of the day,
the KrF is somewhere
in your nervous system.
And here whether you bring
up a good point. Right. It looks like
this slide is a bit of an optical
illusion. Whether you see A or B deeper,
I guess it depends on something going on
inside your head. This picture is so
symmetrical that if you focus enough on
it, you can change your opinion.
Just to even connect that to what we're
talking about. The classical fungible
information on the Holographic screen,
on the blanket, and then the quantum
cognitive rotation is those two images
are on the screen identical. And then
whether it gets a quantum rotation such
that the three points of the axes are
closer to us than the intersection on
that kind of tetrahedron or the other
way around, whether the ballerina is
rotating one way or the other, that's
not on the boundary. So the information
about the depth of field is part of
the QRF or part of the enactment of the
QRF, and it's not written on the
boundary.
And that goes back to the preparation
question and not just the measuring.
Yeah. Like if the preparation if your
whole enculturation or the last five
minutes it was entrained, or you were
holding an object, that predisposed you
to think that the vertex of the
intersection was further away, that's
the preparation sets your prior so that
when you get this ambiguous artifact,
you rotate it into the most natural
position. Cognitively.
And that's the preparation that sets you
up for a measurement. No measurement can
happen without a preparation. What do
you think, Andrew? Sure.
Yeah. Everything you said makes sense.
So perhaps let
me recall what was that around the
slides in this
whole spirit or philosophy of making,
emphasizing that information is
physical, it concubine this whole thing.
One of the glaring omissions in
physics was the embodiment of
the reference frame, which was treated
as an abstraction in classical
physics, such as by Galileo, but maybe
even Einstein, even if he my hunch, is
that he did have more of this instinct
know, particularly in all those thought
experiments of trying to chase the
library. You are chasing the library.
Right. So at the end of the I mean,
this is the whole process of making the
observer and the reference frame more
and more explicit and more and more
physical. Because at the end of the day,
it has to right. If you start
with this assumption, that solipsistic
assumption almost, that all you
see is part of the same
material ether that you are,
then you are part of the universe
and you're observing something that is
out there. So you need to include a
theory of what it means for you to be
observing that. Right. And at the end of
the day, the observer has to be
physical. That's what was emphasized by
Chris at the beginning of this lecture.
So this jump from treating the reference
frame as an abstraction to a real
physical entity,
these people have talked a lot
about in these papers that are quoted
there. But I should also remark, if
folks want to see this, it's coming up
in high energy theory. Also in
recent work of Saskind and others,
where they talk about quantum reference
frames very explicitly. So I don't
have the citations off the button, but
it's definitely becoming an important
thing in the last 20 years, this attempt
to really explicitly treat the reference
frame and the observer as a quantum
entity, as a physical entity.
Okay, so that's
what I just said the jump from treating
things reference rims as abstractions to
physical objects go.
And because
we cannot make a perfect copy of quantum
information, we say that these are
unique and clonable and unfungible. So
in order to recreate an experiment
perfectly, this is addressed as a part
of fungibility or not. Right. Can Alice,
if you have some sort of quantum
experiment and Alice and, you know,
it's the usual DPR thought
experiment or whatever, alice and Bob
are separated by light years.
Is it enough, if they want to recreate
the same, exact same experiment for
Alice to send string of zeros and ones?
Well, if you had an experiment where
that's enough, then you can recreate it
with fungible information. If not, then
you need to somehow send non fungible
information, which really implies
sending a piece of hardware.
Can I add another piece here on the
previous slide? So this
looks really technical and scientific,
but let's think about Alice's
laboratory. Is Alice's brain,
mind and Bob's analogously? Alice is
thinking about what to say and then says
it. And that information might be
written in a chat form. It might be said
verbally, it might be transmitted
through digital or analog signal. But at
some point it's going through this
classical informational interface. And
then Bob's laboratory is like perceiving
and unpacking it. And the question of
semantic alignment is such that if Alice
gives a shopping list of ten items,
if there's semantic alignment, bob would
be able to go to the store and then find
those ten items. And it made me think of
the dictionary definition of left and
right. So this gets back to our
discussion of whether the vertex on
these axes is coming towards us or away
from us. So I looked up the dictionary
definition of left on towards or
relating to the side of a human body or
of a thing that is to the west when the
person or that thing is facing north.
So that's, I guess, one attempt to
anchor what it means to be left. The
second definition is the left hand part
side or direction. And you could imagine
there's an analogous definition for
right. The point is you can't describe
verbally leftness and rightness or
chirality in general because its
reference is an embodied perspective.
And so if Alice said, okay, you're going
to go down the street and then turn left
at the stop sign, how would Alice
communicate to Bob what leftness meant
at that stop sign versus rightness?
And that's this question of flipping.
And the way that the quantum formalism
accommodates that is through the WIC
rotation and the quantum cognitive event
where the fungible transmittable
holographic information gets rotated
into the imaginary axis with the
formalisms that enable it to be rotated
at all. But that means you could rotate
it left quote or rotate it right.
Yeah, I think that's a very good
explanation. I don't know if I have much
to add. Dean you wanted to say.
Can'T. I don't know the answer to this,
but to take what Daniel just said, to
take the basic concept of being able
to take something that,
for all intents and purposes, can appear
one way or another and then turn that
into how Chris closed the last lecture
with we are seeing ourselves as both
being entangled and also being
separatable. How did we go literally
from a three dimension vertex to
we're both entangled and we're not
living in a paradox. That's just the way
it is. We're also removing
ourselves or separating ourselves at the
same time. That's what I would like to
know, because somewhere between three
arbitrary lines and complexity is
not a paradox. Something has to be
happening, and I'm not exactly sure how
that transition plays out.
Anybody want to enlighten me? Can you
repeat your question, please? Well, how
do we go at this point of the
reference frame description of saying,
you can't copy it, all you can do is
pass it? Because we
think things could be flipped based on
internal reference frames, internal
meanings and internal models. The thing
we choose for context. Yada yada yada
yada goes all the way out to the
conclusion of Chris's conversation
with us in number three, where he said,
bottom line is that it's not a paradox
that as things become more and more
complex, then it
wants to get to a place of entanglement,
alignment, a sense of agreement,
and at the same time wants to remain
separate. So between those two things,
a whole lot has happened. And I
don't think we've skipped over it, but
we certainly haven't opened it up and
really looked at it closely. And I'm
just curious what's in between those two
scales. I agree. I think we're
going to cover that towards the end of
the talk, but I agree. I don't know how
you see this related to QRS or the stuff
we just talked about, but I think it's
the big question in this lecture,
right, that was like, where does this
tension between increasing complexity
and wanting to predict
what the environment is doing? One
requires entanglement and the other one
requires separability, at least
colloquially speaking, I think this
tension is basically
what the free energy principle comes
down to. Right. Daniel, what do you
think? You have the free energy and you
have the E minus TS. One is prediction
error. I mean, not exactly E minus TS.
Right? That would be thermodynamics but
you know what I mean. One is prediction
error and the other one is what was?
I can remember.
I'll definitely look forward to the
technical unpacking that you'll get to
soon, but I was reminded of the William
Blake quotation, do what you will. This
life's a fiction and is made up of
contradiction. So let's modify
that project what you will,
rotate what you will, spacetime's a
fiction. Not that it's false, but that
it's a projected fictionalization that
it doesn't have the ontological primacy
that the topology of communication does
and is made up of contradiction. Yes.
And it's made up of this tension between
fitting and not overfitting, between
aligning and the principle of unitarity
and differentiating and becoming through
others. We become ourselves and that
type of articulation and recognizing
that two complementary forces like
convex and concave come into existence
at once. Like a zero to two jump is
not an issue or a stumbling block.
It's that we wouldn't have it any other
way. Couldn't have it any other way.
Yeah, sure, we'll get that. Towards the
end, you can almost even call it a
duality. It's not far fetched. I mean,
it's the sort of thing that I think most
people will be happy to take for
granted. Such supersymmetry like you
have two kinds of particles, but the
same amount of them, and dualities that
are all over the place. So I think it's
not unreasonable to just accept that
there is a tension between increasing
complexity, which you want A and
B to be separable for, and accuracy
prediction. Now, how this is related to
emergent space and these
QRS stuff, I don't want to make very far
fetched claims. We'll talk about
emergent space later on the course. But
for now, let's say a few more words
about QRFs and then we'll get to the
complexity stuff towards the end.
QRFs are almost building blocks, if you
want, for information processing
here, it's very useful to recall
definition that I feel I think we have
mentioned before of information as being
differences that make a difference.
That's probably the best colloquial
definition of information I've heard.
And I think it does a lot of work. I
mean, it's almost mathematical, but
anyways, we need to unpack it a little
more and see. So for a difference to
make a difference, what do you want out
of QRF? Right. Unsurprisingly, I mean,
not surprisingly, but reassuringly, I
think would be the word.
You need a QRF to have sensory action
and a default state,
right? This is sort of like where your
Bayesian prior distribution is encoded.
These three things will give you a
building block for any information
processing. And that ties
together with all the work in the free
energy literature and perception action
loops and whatnot.
So before we see mathematically how
a TRF is defined, I think it's more
illustrative. And I think Chris went
exactly on the right order when he
presented this a couple weeks ago,
seeing examples from h.
These are actual pieces of hardware that
are effectively QRX, and it's remarkable
how they map to well. I'll skip
ahead a little bit. But when you get to
the mathematical definition of a QRF as
a quantum system that you
can specify with this category theory
diagram, you have incoming arrows into a
node that then expands. Right? And this
roughly corresponds to measurement and
preparation degrees of not degrees of
freedom, degrees of freedom would be the
same, right, when you attach it to the
boundary. But measurement and
preparation stages, I guess, would be
the better word. But anyways,
let me go back to these examples,
right? And Daniel, you're the biologist
here, so correct me if I say anything
wrong here. You have a
cartoon picture of a bacteria, I think,
and this is a very simple sort
of thing, right? It navigates in the
direction of food and
that's it, right? So it is a very simple
rudimentary example of a cureb. You have
the sensory stage
here, I guess the degrees of freedom. I
guess the degrees of freedom. It's not
obvious here what the boundary is,
that's one thing. But it
is a good enough picture to see the
resemblance to here we have the
measurement which in this case you're
trying to measure concentration of food.
You have your node here,
C, which is your prior
distribution for concentration of food.
And finally you have the output, the
preparation stage, which is the
rest of this chemical network that will
control and steer this bacteria,
right? So there is here you want to call
it the action degrees of freedom that
will steer this bacteria in the
direction of food. And likewise with
cell division, this I understand even
less that the network appears more
complicated. But I think it's fair to
say that at the end of the day, all
these chemical networks that appear
super complicated somehow have
to be mapped to this category
theoretical diagram. That's all there is
to it. You're going to have the sensory
input and the action output and
you're going to have the default
chemical concentration which amounts to
this node over here.
You remember this from last lecture,
right, Daniel? Yeah. And the Cone Co
cone we explored also in live stream 17
on the Bayesian semantic information
flow. But I'll kind of add a point about
these biological systems in relationship
to artificially specified systems and
what that helps us understand about
perception, cognition, action. So the
cone COCONE diagram has this bow tie
architecture or this kind of like two
pyramids touching point to point where
there's a preparation and a measurement
which can be different dimensionalities
or different scopes. Like it could be
multi input, multi output or multi
input, single output, vice versa and so
on. But they come through this eye
of the needle with C prime here. Now,
contrast that kind of architecture
represented here abstractly, with what
we see in the bacterial process and in
the cell division process.
These have that kind of a bow tie
perception, cognition, action
architecture or measurement, cognitive
integration, preparation architecture.
In contrast, we see, for example, an
artificial neural network where the
input and the output layers are usually
lower dimensional, maybe an image coming
in with several hundred pixels and a
single output like a classifier coming
out the other end, but a dimensional
explosion in those internal cognitive
layers. But in biological systems.
It's actually exactly the opposite. For
example, many, many receptors on the
cell surface, on the holographic
boundary, the sensorium of the cell.
But then there are these common
secondary messengers that many pathways
converge upon. So that reflects
the kind of radically different
architecture that a QRF embodies,
as opposed to the approach taken by
disembodied intelligence frameworks
which use dimensional explosion
internally to try to categorize
and classify and find edge cases versus
this dimensional winnowing that is
reflective of these embodied
intelligences.
And if I may make a tangential comment
here also, I think the good thing about
these two examples is that they also
showcase the fact of how
the deep implications of scale free
biology, if you want to call it this
way. We tend to think of these sorts of
processes such as here only
happening at the level of the nervous
system in animals, or as you said,
neural networks. Right. We tend to
associate this with neural networks.
And perhaps evolution has tiered us in a
way that endowed us with nervous systems
to make these things. Maybe these are
higher up in the layers, but really
that's a bit of an arbitrary distinction
that we make. The processes going on at
the cellular level, even if they don't
appear to have anything to do with
nervous system. My understanding is that
there are some generic properties that
are the same and everything that has to
do with information processing, it
manifests maybe slightly different when
it comes to explicit neurons, but at the
end of the day, it's the same generic
process going on. Would you say? That's
right, Daniel?
The ontological claim is that it's the
same generic process happening, whereas
the more instrumentalist claim is that
we can model it with some shared
abstractions.
Yeah. Okay, so we can continue.
Right? So from,
you know, I don't have a whole lot to
say. Daniel said quite a bit about at
the end of the day, QRF,
you can visualize it as this diagram and
you can think of it as if you are more
familiar with the picture of a neural
network and ways on a neural network and
so on. That's the way to think about it.
Now, let's continue with explicit
embodiment, if you wish. So QRFs
in the formalism have to be attached to
a boundary boundary degrees of freedom.
And I should add another remark here,
and personally to me also, the hard part
about this quantum free
energy principle, formalism, if you
wish, is what you said at the beginning
is the fact that it's topological,
right? So very often it's not clear what
the boundary degrees of freedom are.
Right? Because we tend to think of
boundaries as geometrical
and certainly the classical FEP treats
them as geometrical. But that's not the
case here in the quantum free energy
formalism where we have emergent space
will be talked about in later sessions.
But that's just like one quick remark to
make at the end of the day, though,
even if it's topological, we're going to
have real degrees of freedom that this
URF is attaching to this cone cocoon
diagram. And you're going to have
measurement operators that yield
classical outcomes plus
and minus one.
And then you can think of this QRF
or more abstractly, this concoction
diagram as a neural network, if it was
acting on those Ander qubits and
then back propagating some sort of
action signal preparation.
Okay,
let's not forget that Lambdawer's
principle and so on requires
that we are mindful of energy
constraints on computation. And that
gives us the following picture.
Number one, we're going to have to use
energy from the environment to
fuel our computation, to fuel our
observation. That means that right away
you cannot use the entirety of your
boundary to gather information.
It necessitates an
allocation of resources. Right here,
E is the observed environment, and the
blue portion is A, thermodynamical
sector where you extract free
energy and dump heat in order
to run this computational process. And
then furthermore, you can have a memory
sector where you write things on a
boundary, and this takes up energy.
Also, writing information onto the
boundary by Landauer's Principle will
take up information. And Chris
called this the minimal interesting
observer because it has a memory
sector, and quite minimal
here implies that we have at least
minimal interesting implies that we have
more than one layer here. The process of
writing things into a memory sector
requires us to have a clock so that we
can label those memories in time.
Okay, so we do have time as part of this
formalism, just not space yet. Time has
to be internal to the observer.
Just one piece on that that Chris
mentioned. And as you
echoed, time here is an attribute
of some cognitive systems in
terms of their internal understanding
so that they can sort memories and
understand what came earlier or later.
It's not something that's a priori
defined externally, which is the case in
the kind of spacetime first. Now, how do
we fit communication into here? We flip
that we're talking about the topology of
communication as ontologically,
primal and now certain kinds of
sophisticated agents. This is not like
necessarily true of a rock or a
metronome or a particle of a gas, but
some kinds of cognitive systems are such
that they are able to generate an
internal clock concept. And that doesn't
have to be the same thing as what's
happening on the wall with Kronos. This
can reflect a purely internal time
kairos that enables observers or
interactors that have different clock
structures. And then Landauer's
principle helps us arbitrage or connect
the informational demands to the
energetic or the metabolic demands.
Dean so when I
first listened to the lecture, I thought
when the term or phrase trade off
was raised, I traditionally
have thought of trade off as kind of a
binary. If I'm picking this,
I'm trading off against all the other
things that I didn't pick. So one
or the other or others plural. But when
I saw this, and especially when I heard
it in the context of things like degrees
of freedom, I began to wonder whether it
is because it could sit on either side
of that boundary. It could be a priori
or it could be ad hoc or post hoc, a
trade off which prior to
this conversation, I just assumed that a
trade off was one or the other.
But essentially what this implies is.
It'S. Still a kind of a degree of how
much weight you put into it and then
you kind of cross a threshold and then
you've made your pick, you've completed
your trade off. Or again,
did I misinterpret what I was hearing?
If it's topological as opposed to
the more conventional spacetime
perspective,
can a trade off be both ad hoc and post
hoc, seemingly at the same time?
Very interesting question. Let us just
let it float and continue on enter. All
right. Because again,
I'll just say this. If it can be,
that would really move us out of the
classical realm that would essentially
say that anytime we've made a pick, we
really haven't made a pick. There's
still a whole bunch of other things that
are going to happen that
can change whatever that action
is that we thought we carried out or
enacted. If we're talking about an
internal, internality state,
which is what I think we want, I think
we want to be able to change our minds.
Let me take that one way. Dean.
The analytical equations of the Action
perception loop don't tell us in
implementation like if we're going to
write it in code, whether we should use
Action first procedurally
to update our observations,
or whether we enable our observations to
wag the dog and then select Action
at the end of the loop. So is it a
perception action loop or is it an
action perception loop? And those enable
a kind of seesaw where sometimes
we want what we learn to change what we
do and other times we want what we do to
change what we learn and having that
kind of a fulcrum or a pivot and
again to connect it to the vertex
popping in and out. The analytical
formalisms inscribed on the screen of
the FEP, like the textbooks,
they're ambiguous. Whether we lead with
action and have inference follow or
whether we lead with inference and have
action follow or lead with action have
inference follow whichever one of the
combinations there are,
and then that trade off
or runoff is broken by
specific embodied cognitive agents that
trade off about the procedural primacy
of perception or action can't be
broken. Generically, right?
MMM.
It certainly makes for a lot of waste
heat if you're not careful.
It'd be exhausting a lot anyway.
Okay.
I don't know if we can talk about intent
much with this formalism, but. We can
take a very descriptive approach to it
and go down here a little more actually
before I don't want to get ahead of
myself. What I mean by that is whether
we can put intent or not in this
hierarchy, I don't know if it
matters a whole lot, but at least we can
talk about it operationally and
descriptively and say just like when
you have a clock,
the clock is just there, right?
If you don't have the clock, you don't
have the memory and that's it, right?
And likewise here, if we don't have an
attention control compartment, we cannot
play with all these QRFs that are non
commutative at the same time.
So if there is no attention control
system to begin with, we cannot talk
about a system that has non commutative
cure apps. Meaning here, one presumably
goes to memory sectors, the other one
goes to environment sectors and so on.
So this is certainly a necessity of the
fact that we have different sectors
of the boundary being allocated to
different purposes, such as
environmental observation and memory and
so on, within the environment.
It's worth remarking that here, if you
think deeply about first principles and
what it means to observe an entity,
well, you still come down to these
differences that make a difference sort
of thing. Right. Which involves whenever
you're looking at the environment, if
you're going to identify a system, you
need sort of a background that tells you
that puts the system in context. Right.
So that you can identify the system as
something distinct. I think this,
again, is something that we have talked
about in previous discussions
where the easiest picture here is
something like the speed gauge in your
car, where P
is the gauge itself that tells you the
speed, but it's meaningless
without the reference system right,
outside of the thing that stays
invariant, right? The context, the
background that gauge moving means
nothing to you. So we come back to this
idea of if we think of information as
differences that make a difference in
terms of first principles, this
environment sector that we saw earlier
has to be further broken down into
pointer and reference estates.
Again, this is covered in depth in
Chris's papers. I'm thinking
particularly of free energy for
generating quantum systems.
And again, just to reiterate this
attention control staff compartment,
which is, by the way, very reminiscent
to the hierarchy that was earlier, with
the clock arising higher up in the
hierarchy, deeper into the layer.
Likewise, whenever you're writing
something into MMR, you need to have
that clock. Whenever you are deploying
noncommunicated gear apps, you're going
to need an attention control
compartment. And we just described this
operationally. If you didn't have it,
then the agent would not be what it is,
could not deploy those noncommutative
QRFs. So,
marching on,
we'll just end here with QRF alignment
and the free energy principle. Just a
few more words. This is possibly the
most interesting picture in this
presentation and just we can recall here
the possibilities for KrF alignment and
how free energy comes into play in
this formalism we
call a the trivial interaction. We call
this a thermal interaction.
And then you have a bunch of
possibilities, right? And depending on
each possibility, you're going to see
things as noise or
as in the paper says, non local hidden
variables. The last situation is
what we call alignment when we have QRFs
of the same size, perfectly aligned.
Recall, I think this
would be the situation where you have
noiseless classical computation,
right? You have A and B just
interacting. And also
this is the situation where, correct me
if I'm wrong, Daniel,
this is Entanglements, right?
Asymptotically once all the curves are
aligned, you have entanglement and now
we can tie it back maybe to Dean's
earlier. So these two slides conclude
the discussion basically and then we can
open it up. So given these possibilities
for how QRFs can be aligned, QRFs
deployed by AMD can be aligned, and how
in each situation you're going to get
noise or whatever,
then what does the free energy principle
say in this quantum setting?
Well.
Minimizing variational, free energy
leads you to entanglements.
So if theorem here,
if you are in the picture of B here
and the QRFs are aligned, a and
B are going to be intact.
Now, there is a tension between this
tendency towards alignment as free
energy principle will carry you and
observe reality, which is that we're not
just a Blob of Entangled particles.
There is separability and systems
are attention between maintaining
separability and at the
same time being correlated enough to the
environment so as to be able to predict
it. And now we can maybe go into a
more philosophical discussion about the
free energy principle. I should also say
in the last month, just like I talked
earlier, TRFs Lenny Suskin,
whose recent paper that talks about TRF
led me into a rabbit hole of looking
into his recent work and he's talked a
lot about complexity. I'm being very
speculative here, so if someone can call
me out, that would be good in the
comments. But just skimming through some
of his papers, I saw a monograph in 2018
where he talks about complexity and he
puts forward this second law for
complexity in quantum systems and
increased complexity. And it is very
reminiscent of what's going on here.
You have a tension between systems
tending to entanglement and the
other side of the free energy
functional, if you wish, where systems
increase in complexity and that
necessarily requires that A
and B are separate. So Daniel, do you
have any comments at this point?
Yeah, there's a lot to it. I like that
you showed the four possibilities
in the image above and said it was one
of the most interesting figures. I
agree. And how
to connect this to the classical FEP
and also how to see the quantum
FEP not as just a
second story built on top of the
classical FEP which would be kind of
like a historical chronological
understanding of the theoretical
apparatus. But it's almost like the
quantum FEP was like a basement we
didn't know about because it
gives a broader context. And though it
appeared conceptually several years
later in the timeline we understand that
doesn't give it a secondary status.
So what it really means for the
classical FEP to be kind
of like a
special case of this actually
more generic setting
there's just a lot I'm very.
I can wrap it up and then if Dean or you
want to say something, we can continue
with that. But let me conclude and this
is all I have to say for mean,
I'm sure Chris will explain this more in
coming sessions and lectures. But I
think the main key differences is in the
emergence of space. How it might emerge
from something more fundamental, maybe a
tensor network or who knows? But that's
the big difference, right? And I suppose
the quantum free energy principle
generalizes the classical free energy
principle because it doesn't have this
spatial embedding. Now,
this to me personally and also
to folks in the audience for asking
questions is probably the hardest part
to wrap your head around. And I
foresee interest in those discussions
and lectures that deal with the concept
of emergent space. Because every time
you try to and I've done this myself
I've been thinking about how you could
apply this formalism to better known
pictures or compared it, for instance,
with thermal equilibrium, with
relaxation, with thermal equilibrium.
And then you start thinking about,
okay, what is the boundary and so on.
It's far from obvious, right? Because,
again, you have to remind yourself that
the definition is topological. So in
that regard, I think it might be worth
talking about one of the questions that
came up that I thought was good and then
I can call it a day on this end.
So this question and I think it was the
first question asked since the. Last
lecture can you just read the full
question and then read the full answer?
Thank you. The answer, it's number 28
here. Can you guys see it? Should I zoom
in it a little bit? It's pretty small,
but reading it will be good. Okay. So
this question I think I've asked myself
this question too, maybe in
a different way. But basically it gets
to the point of what I was saying
earlier, right? That it would be
nice to see how we can use this
quantum free energy principle formalism
to recover maybe familiar settings such
as relaxation to thermal equilibrium via
the heat equation. But that's far from
obvious how you do it if your definition
is topological, right?
So the question says, what happens when
the agent becomes identical to the
environment? When the model has been
improved so much that it does not differ
from the environment. Is this a state
even possible? Would it be
thermodynamical equilibrium maximum
entanglement? Okay, so clearly it's not
thermodynamical equilibrium, but I think
what the person is asking if maybe if
I'm understanding this correctly,
they're wondering, okay, so if the free
energy principle drives A and B towards
entanglement, then it's fair to say that
any distinction between them has
dissolved, right? That they have merged
into the same thing.
That has to do with this whole
definition of philosophical debate of
thingness that Karl Prieston is a
proponent of, right? What it means for
two things to be separate. Okay,
so let's see what Chris said.
Kristen has pointed out that the limit
of the classical FEP, the limit of
perfect prediction, corresponds to
generalized synchrony between system and
environment. Each sends messages that
the other can perfectly predict.
Now, however, it's clear I'm
not reading anymore. I'm making a quick
remark here. I'll continue in a second.
In the classical FEP, it's clear that
A and B, even if they are in the perfect
limit of the FEP, they remain different
entities. Right? Because you have that,
if you wish, that extra layers
of differentiation coming from their
spatial embedding. Right? In the
classical FEP that is clear that they
haven't even if they are getting
synchronized, they have not lost their
separate identities. You can always say,
well, this is the one that was to the
left and this is the one that was to the
right. Pun intended with earlier
discussion, right? You have that extra
resource for separating them, if you
wish, by virtue of the special
embedding, right? The special embedding
is giving you this extra information
that allows you to keep track of amb
separately. So I'll continue. This
notion depends on the system and its
environment being separated and hence
distinguished somehow. In classical
formulations, they are separated in
ordinary 3D space, I e. They occupy
different locations. So they are
different because they occupy different
locations. Right. But if you don't have
that geometrical background, then how
you know that they're different, right?
Okay, so I continue. The quantum
formulation is background free, meaning
it assumes no spacetime embedding.
System and environment do not have
different locations, even though they
have different sets of degrees of
freedom in the overall Hilbert space.
Here the FPP. The limit of the FEP
is maximum entanglement. This does not
mean that the system and its environment
are identical. They are. And they have
different degrees of freedom. Okay, so
this is just addresses the question I
just posed. It means that the joint
state is not separable into
a system S and environment e. Their
states are no longer conditionally
independent. This is distinct from
thermal equilibrium, which means that
they have the same temperature while
remaining separable and that their
interaction can be characterized as the
change of thermal fluctuations I E
noise. So I
guess this is a nice warm up for things
that are to come. But I do think that
this whole idea of emergent
space is going to be possibly
one of the most important in the course,
and it's going to help the gap between
the class and quantum formulations, for
sure. Dean, what's your take
on this? What I saw was that when you
have that kind of alignment, that
perfect alignment, that was one that was
D in that diagram,
right? That was one state of a complex
state that included an A and a B and a C
and probably a whole bunch of other ways
that yeah, right.
So that one state where you've
got this kind of entanglement isn't into
perpetuity. Like you don't get there and
then stay there. And that's where, I
think, the question of separability and
complexity, it still works
because just because you've momentarily
gotten to a place that we define here as
D doesn't mean you stay there
indefinitely. You could be swapping
around to B and C and A in the next
instant. So at
least that holds the complexity piece
up. That moment for
however long that moment is. Where X A
and X B are aligned isn't permanent.
So it's not predictable in that sense.
Therefore it is complex. I still
don't know how we get, though, that the
closer we get to agreement, the more
complex things are. Unless we're
just talking about D in this array of
ABC and D that
goes back to that quantum reference
frame. I think, like I said, again,
maybe I'm interpreting this wrong, but
when I message pass the reason why,
I have to literally give it over to the
other person and let them have it. I
can't have them copy. What I'm doing is
because there has to be, I guess that
reinforces the separability piece of
this as well, the fact that I can't give
them a copy, that I can only give them
the information, and then they've got to
sort of unpack it in
their own way of taking it off the
boundary. But again,
I struggle with this. I'm guilty
as charged, but what I'm trying to do is
trying to come up with my own narrative,
so that what Chris is saying makes
sense to me, as opposed to make sense to
the world, which is what Chris is trying
to do. I'll try
with another speculative fiction. So
there's a screen between, let's just
say, the stage and the audience or
whatever. It's a holographic screen.
And on each side of the screen, there's
some embodied object.
So that means that it's a
volume enclosing object because points
and lines and planes are only
abstractions. Every real physical object
encloses volume. And now a light is
going to be coming from behind each
object facing the screen. And that's
this kind of cone that we're seeing from
each side. It's like the shadow cast by
the object. So if the object was a
sphere, then it would be projecting down
to a circle onto the screen.
If the shape were a cube, it could be
projecting down. And so where the light
is positioned is the perspective
that that cognitive entity is taking on
its QRF. Those lights could move.
So now we have the situation where the
two spotlights are moving. Maybe the
shapes are staying the same, maybe
they're changing too. And it's like two
search lights scanning across this B
oval and sometimes
they are perfectly locked or there could
be a situation where they're perfectly
aligned or there could be situations
where they're totally disjoint.
And each of those situations have
different implications for what
one entity sees when
it looks at the screen. Maybe like the
shadow is the only part where you can
see because the rest of it is too
blinding or something like that. And so
then if we're in case A here where
maybe B doesn't have a projection or
maybe B's projection is totally
somewhere else, then A is in this
solipsistic I'm the active agent
interacting within an inert world
setting. And D is
like potentially the
computer engineer's classical dream
or Asymptote, which is like all the data
going through the USB cable is just
being perfectly noiselessly received.
And then we also get these B and C
cases. But A is kind
of like the inert world. D is
like the perfect communication channel
and then to connect it just to Friston's
concept of generalized synchrony. As
we've talked about many times,
generalized synchrony doesn't mean
lockstep. Two agents could reduce their
uncertainty about each other, not by
doing the same thing at every time step,
but for example by turn taking. And I
think that points the way to how we get
reduction of variational free energy,
reduction of prediction error, surprise
and so on without especially
spatial temporal enmeshment, but not
necessarily even informational identity
enmeshment. Because you could have two
things that through their alignment
become actually differentiated and
that could increase the mutual
information between two metronomes. Not
just to have them going in the same
direction, but to have them going in
opposite directions. The mutual
information in those two settings is
going to be high. So it's not the case
that generalized synchrony means that
things are becoming blurred.
We could actually also have integrated
information through increased
articulation, not just decreased.
And then life finds a way or cognition
finds a way. On this trade off frontier
of in our pursuit of unitarity,
will we blur to unify
or will we differentiate to unify?
But those are the paths we have. We
don't have the backwards.
Yeah, yeah, makes sense.
Any other latter slides ender?
No, that's it. So Chris made a few more
remarks at the end about language
here, but he mentioned
that he's going to talk more about this
in the coming lecture. So we'll just
leave it up to him.
Yeah. There could be some very powerful
and interesting linguistic opportunities
for updating our
speaking to reflect what
we are learning here.
I don't know what those necessarily are,
whether it's a syntactic or a semantic
thing or whether it's a narrative thing,
but how to actually reenter some
of these formalisms into our focus
understanding could just be
immensely powerful and we
could have a lot of integrity between
the natural language way that
potentially were already showing up for
engagement and some of these
formalisms that get to
first principles about interacting
entities and boundary conditions and all
of that. Dean, any penultimate
thoughts? Not really. I'm going to go
back and listen to the I'm going to
listen to Chris's comments again about
this common cause and the fine tuning
assumption and whether that's sort of
metaphorically, a dialing in or what
he means exactly by the fine tuning. In
the context of this conversation today,
what you just kind of said about are we
dulling something here or are we
sculpting something to make it more
fittable? I'm going to go
now and go back and listen to what he
talks about in terms of fine tuning and
maybe update my priors around that.
And are there any last thoughts or maybe
scroll over to the schedule of the
course again just so we can close on
that? Yeah,
we're halfway through. We just completed
the third discussion section now, so
we've had three lectures and three
discussions. It's all downhill from
here. By the way, this was the first
midterm. You guys both did well.
We're going to head into session
four with these last three, how agents
use multiple communication channels and
that's going to get connected to the
quantum FEP, how spacetime emerges from
communication, which is something that
we've brought up a bunch. It's been in
the background, but making that explicit
is going to be exciting. And then
section six, I think, is just going to
be such a jumping off point because
the scope and the intensity of what
is transpiring is extreme.
So connecting it to biology, which is
to say life more fully, and where
we go in 23 and beyond,
that's going to be awesome. So, any last
words, Andrew? No,
I just echo what you said.
I would say it's going to be uphill in
terms of how interesting it's going to
get uphill in a good sense,
meaning that we're planning cool.
Well, I encourage people to check out
the course website and submit questions
that they'd like to see addressed by
Chris. Also to register and join these
participatory discussions. There'll be
three more of them, so if you want to
join, share your QRF,
be part of the public of all of these
works that we'll compile at the end and
just get your exoskeleton in the
game with what is happening here. It'd
be really awesome to hear more voices
and to have more on board.
Okay, thank you, Dean, and Ander till
next time.