Hello,
everybody. Welcome. It is September 26,
2023. We are here kicking off
a new stream series at the Active
Inference Institute. This is the morph.
Stream 1.1. Today we have David
Cappell and also this section and
streams facilitated by Sarah Ham. We're
going to have a overview, first
presented by Sarah. Then David
will share some work on neuromorphic
computing, and then we'll have some time
to discuss. So thank you both for
joining and Sarah, to you for the first
presentation and also to introduce
yourself, if you'd like. Yes, that's a
good idea. Thank you very much, Daniel.
So my name is Sarah. I'm a
neuroscientist specializing
intelligence, currently working in the
field of neuromorphic computing at
Sheffield Hallam in the UK. So I'm going
to give you a high level overview of
what neuromorphic computing is before we
hear David's exciting talk in the first
edition of this new series. Just to let
you know, if you're watching on Double
Time in the future, I talk quite fast,
so you might not want to watch me on
Double Time. So this QR code I put
here will take you to a paper which I
thought was a really nice introduction
to the field. But neuromorphic computing
can be defined as computing systems that
are designed to mimic the structure and
function of the nervous system. So this
doesn't have to be the human nervous
system. The field actually takes
inspiration from all sorts of animals
and insects, although the definitions
online don't necessarily acknowledge
that. So some people are quite open with
what constitutes neuromorphic, while
maybe others would prefer neuromorphic
was reserved for hardware instantiations
of biological like neurons, which are
sometimes referred to as non von Newman
computers. And I think that's what the
paper that that QR code refers to it as
their definition. So what I think is
really interesting is a little bit of
the context. So, like our current von
Newman computer architecture was also
inspired by neuroscience, particularly
the McCullough and Pitts 43. Neuromodel
inspired von Newman's first draft in
1945. So neuroscience has a long history
of inspiring computer science, and this
also includes reinforcement learning,
which is based on theories about
learning, decision making from
behavioral psychology based on rewards
and punishments, and also Hebian
learning principles of cells that fire
together, wire together from 49 became
foundational for unsupervised learning.
So, first of all, hang on 1 second.
So in order to understand the why of
neuromorphic computing, I really wanted
to explain what's so great about the
brain. So here's some inspiration for
light bulbs. So I'm going to ask you a
question. I just want you to think about
it for a second. In terms of light
bulbs, how much energy do you think the
brain uses? Do you think it's more or
less energy than the bulbs lighting the
room that you're in? If you're in the
future, by all means pause this. Pause
this. If you want to do some in depth
calculations. But I'm going to skip to
the answer. The answer is here,
in the pink circle. So it's 20 watts.
So that's the equivalent of one modern
day energy efficient light bulb. So
that's probably what's above me now,
basically in my room here. This QR code
should take you to quite an interesting
paper on power consumption in the brain,
if you're interested in that. So that
works out about four bananas a day to
power your brain. And this is
calculated, by the way, based on calorie
intake that the brain needs. So, for
context, the fastest supercomputer in
Europe, I think it's called lumi, in
Finland it's been called exceptionally
green, and its power consumption is 8.5
million watts. So that's around half a
million light bulbs, while your brain
uses just one. So then the question is,
well, what does your brain do with that
one light bulb or four bananas?
Apparently it does 1000 billion
calculations per second. So there's lots
of other massive estimates out there.
This wasn't even the largest by several
orders of magnitude. Estimates are
obviously very speculative, but they're
all massive and they all tend to be
based on the number of neurons, their
connections and firing rates. But I
think it's really important for the
context that supercomputers can't
actually yet match our complexity of
skills or the adaptability of the human
brain. So we actually excel way beyond
supercomputers when it comes to things
like complex decision making, learning
from experience. So how does
your brain compare to AI? So, I
mentioned that modern AI is already
brain inspired. However, artificial
neurons are highly simplified. They
don't capture the complexity of
biological neurons or networks, like,
not even close. Individual neurons are
actually more like networks themselves.
And research suggests that modeling one
biological neuron requires a five to
eight layer deep artificial neural
network made of around 1000 artificial
neurons. This QR code should take you to
the paper. For that.
You have 86 billion neurons in your
brain. They work together to form a
highly energy efficient, low latency
supercomputer that works just above room
temperature, off the equivalent of about
four bananas a day. So hopefully I've
given you a sense of how amazing your
brain is, as if you didn't know that
already, and how it's already been used
to inspire the, I guess, fairly basic AI
that we have now compared to human
intelligence. So, next I'm going to
explain how key features of the brain
are being implemented to catalyze our
next generation of AI and technology
through the field of neuromorphic
computing, which is why you're all here.
So, traditional volume and computers
have physically separate computing and
memory units, shown here on the left.
During computation, data must transfer
backwards and forwards, like really
fast. So there's a bottleneck,
essentially for speed and energy,
whereas in neuromorphic architectures,
which are shown here on the right, with
the help of Dali, computing and memory
occur in the same place. So they're said
to be colocated. Essentially,
individual neurons perform computation
while memory is represented by the
strength of the connections, the weights
between neurons. So the synapses. So
chips like this might be created with
components like Memoristas for example,
which can emulate synaptic weights. And
this architecture improves speed, it
reduces energy consumption. And what's
really interesting is it enables
massively parallel processing meaning
that multiple problems can be worked on
at the same time. So this is
particularly important, this
architecture, for various use cases,
but also because as we reach the end of
Moore's Law, which is the number of
transistors you were able to physically
make tinier and tinier to fit on a chip.
And it's also important because humanity
needs to massively reduce its energy
consumption against the backdrop drop of
creating ever more powerful AI.
So artificial neurons typically use
continuous activation shown on the left,
they're always on, while neuromorphic
neurons, they're said to be spiking, so
they're on or they're off, which is
shown here on the right. So similar to
sort of an action potential. So the
benefits for this are again power,
efficiency and also applications where
timing is important and this is given
that they're event driven. So
essentially they have the potential for
spatial and temporal dimensions which
then enables added spatiotemporal
encoding and processing of information.
You might be wondering a bit about GPUs
which also enable parallel processing.
Research suggests that GPUs are suitable
architectures for deploying spiking
neural networks which I think makes this
a really interesting time for the field
given how high end GPUs are becoming
ever more pervasive.
So the brain learns strength of synapses
between neurons. This is based on pre
and synaptic firing patterns. I think
David's Talk will talk a lot, we'll go
into a lot more depth on this. But there
are many different types and patterns of
this across the brain depending on the
types of synapses such as excitatory to
inhibitory, excitatory to excalitatory.
And the neuromorphic field is working to
leverage these rules because of benefits
for on chip learning and also
applications such as pattern recognition
and edge computing as well. Edge
computing being quite a huge use case
for neuromorphic computing because of
the sort of event driven nature and also
the low energy usage. And this QR code
should take you to quite an interesting
paper on STDP that I found.
So what neuromorphic solutions are
available? Now? You might just think
this is all theoretical, there are
actually many different solutions out
there which I'll just give you a really
high level overview of. So the Human
Brain Project has created several large
scale neuromorphic computers including
Spinnaker, which is this one at the
bottom, this board's, like maybe like
the size of my face or something. So
that runs in real time and it's
comprised of multiple general purpose
arm microprocessors and there was also
BrainScaleS which is an accelerated
analog architecture and it runs 1000
times real time. So the
board next to the blue one, that's an
actual credit card size version of
BrainScaleS, which they've recently
made, which I thought was pretty cool.
And then there's also some big players
in the space. So this blue one here is
Intel's Louihi chip. They're onto Luihi
two. Now, that's their Neuromorphic
chip, and they have an open source
software framework for that as well,
because they really want to catalyze the
open source community to get involved
with it. So neuromorphic sensors also
exist? So this little blue thing in the
middle is actually a Neuromorphic
camera. It's maybe like this big. So
they aim to recreate how our nervous
system senses stimuli, such as light.
So, for example, in a Neuromorphic
camera, which is the one here, each
pixel works independently with a
microsecond resolution. Hopefully, my
GIF will work. There we go. So you can
see each pixel working there, which is
pretty cool. So compared to traditional
digital cameras, they have improved
performance with motion and lower power
consumption. There was also a
Neuromorphic nose recently by intel,
which was pretty cool. So it could learn
the scent of a chemical after just one
exposure, and then it could identify
that scent even when it was masked by
others. And then finally, this is a
humanoid robot called an ICup. And what
you can do is you can actually integrate
Neuromorphic sensors, such as the
camera, and then Neuromorphic chips
maybe spinnaker or brain scales into a
humanoid device like this or other
devices like a drone. And then from
that, you can actually create embodied
neuromorphic systems. And this is
something that we work on at the Smart
Interactive Technologies Research Lab in
Sheffield in the UK.
This slide just highlights some of the
potential applications of Neuromorphic
computing, which I thought were quite
interesting when you think about it. So
the understanding of context, pattern
recognition, advanced sensing, fusot,
learning, generalizing across tasks,
complex decision making,
explainability, and brain interfaces.
So all these skills are really
beneficial when you're thinking about
human centered, real time applications
in dynamic environments. So things like
self driving cars, for example. And
personally, I think that neuromorphic
systems are also likely to be the future
substrate of brain computer interfaces.
Probably a bit biased because I'm a
neuroscientist, but they're low energy,
they're real time, and they also have
architectures which match our own
hardware. So I do think we'll soon see
the BCI field being catalyzed by
neuromorphic systems, particularly maybe
for hybrids of hardware and wetware. So
maybe even potentially containing
people's own brain cells, which you can
actually grow just from a hair cell.
And a particular focus of our work is
designing AI, which learns in a similar
way to a human. So it has an innate
sense of curiosity, and it learns
through interacting with the real world.
So in the 50s, Alan Turing said,
instead of trying to produce a program
to simulate the adult mind, why not
rather try to produce one which
simulates the child's brain. If this
were then subject to an appropriate
course of education, one would obtain
the adult brain. This is very much the
philosophy behind the neurodevelopmental
approach to AI and neuromorphic
computing, which I just wanted to
highlight. There are some
challenges in the field. These are very
high level, but I'll just give you a
little bit of an idea of it. So,
training spiking neural networks is more
complex than traditional neural
networks. Also designing hardware which
actually implements spiking neural
networks STDP on a large scale is said
to be fairly challenging. And then also
developing algorithms which can actually
effectively leverage all these
technologies. So the hardware, the STDP,
it's an ongoing active area of research.
So if you're here, you're probably
interested in active inference. So I
wanted to highlight this. Actually,
someone put on the discord today one of
these studies, which was pretty cool.
So a couple of recent studies have
combined neuromorphic computing with
principles of active inference. So
active inference comes from
neuroscience, and I would argue that it
lends itself very well to neuromorphic
architectures. In a recent paper on
embodied neuromorphic intelligence, so
it didn't really mention active
inference in it. The QR code on the top
right here, it was suggested that a real
breakthrough in neuromorphics will
happen if the whole system design is
based on biological computational
principles with a tight interplay
between the estimation of the
surroundings and the robot's own state
and decision making, planning and
action. So some of those themes might
sound quite familiar to people
interested in active inference, and I
would suggest that active inference is
well placed to meet these requirements.
And I just wanted to highlight a couple
of recent studies here. So this one on
the left, Gandalfiatal, recently
demonstrated plasticity and rapid
unsupervised learning in a neuromorphic
system using active inference
principles. The author suggested that
their experiments could be adopted to
implement brain like predictive
capabilities in neuromorphic robotic
systems. And then there was the Dish
brain paper, which some of you may be
familiar with by Kaganatal. So this was
a hybrid wetware hardware neuromorphic
system that the authors claimed was
embodied. The system showed rapid
apparent learning of the game of Pong
using the free energy principle for
learning. And the authors claimed that
the system exhibited synthetic
biological intelligence. So the field
implementing active inference principles
in neuromorphic systems is very nascent.
And the idea behind this more stream
series is to create a space and a
community to share knowledge, ideas and
expertise to catalyze the field. I think
some really exciting technological leaps
are probably going to come from this
area. So thank you for listening to my
quick run through Neuromorphic 101.
And next up, we're going to hear
from David. So David, over to you. If
you want to introduce yourself, please.
Thank you, Sarah.
I would share my screen.
Yeah.
Can you see now my screen,
the presentation yeah. Okay, perfect.
Okay. Hello. My name is David Kappel.
I'm a researcher and group leader at the
Institute for Moyo Informatics at the
Rural University Bohom. So I'm
leading the group on sustainable machine
learning and we have a very strong focus
on neuromorphic computing. That's why
I'm here today. And I'm going to start
with a very similar motivation than
Sarah did, which was really a great
inspiration for this talk, I think. So
probably most of you have seen this
interesting recent result, and I don't
mean Germany winning the basketball
championship, but this really big leap
in artificial intelligence that we have
seen in the last years, especially the
last two or three years. So this is a
picture generated from a prompt by a
Dali network and it's really amazing.
It was considered science fiction like
only two, three years ago. And this was
essentially made possible by a
neuromorphic approach, which is deep
neural networks. And these deep neural
networks have become huge now, but this
comes also with a caveat. So basically
the flip side is that among other
problems maybe these models may have,
they consume huge amounts of energy.
So models like Dali or Jet GPT,
as Sarah already mentioned, they would
consume energy budgets that are
comparable to houses or cars. So
training Chat GPT a single time is like
a gigawatt hour approximately. So that
would be 300 tons of CO2 emission
and many times, which comes down to many
times the lifespan of a typical car.
So this comes with two problems.
Obviously, this makes training these
models only accessible to a very small
number of very large players. So
essentially the big tech companies. And
secondly, and maybe even more
importantly, this is not compatible with
a planet with limited resources. So if
the growth rate of AI continues like it
did in the last years, it will consume
13% of the global energy consumption by
2030 and it will basically outrun
the transportation sector in another
five years or so. So this raises the
question, does sustainable machine
learning exist at all? And obviously,
since I'm working in the group of
sustainable machine learning, I believe
it does. And why I think it
does is because we know a system that is
very efficient and is still probably
better than these AI models, which is
the human brain, which consumes, as
Sarah mentioned, around 20 watts or
four bananas a day.
It's many orders of magnitude more
efficient than the AI models we have
today. But so far we don't
know essentially how these networks work
and especially how to train them. And
basically our goal is to transfer now
mechanisms from machine learning. We
have this nice picture here. Basically
we start from the machine learning side
where we already know our way around.
So we have these models that are
wonderful and that give us really
impressive results, but they are not
efficient and we want to transfer them
to a new efficient AI generation.
And our idea is to use inspiration from
neuroscience that make this
transfer faster and possible in the
first place. Okay?
Actually, biology is a great source of
inspiration and always comes around the
corner with very surprising results.
And one of these results that I stumbled
upon a couple of years ago is that
reliability of synapses in
the brain. So, as you probably know,
neurons in your brain are connected for
synapses. But if you look at
this is a paper from 2019, and they
could actually identify individual
synapses and they could trigger them to
make a synaptic release, like a single
transmission. But if you look at these
measurements, you see that this is
really covered in noise. So essentially,
if you basically average over this and
zoom this out, you see here these
typical synaptic traces, which is the
average white line here. But below that,
you see this huge jitter. So they really
like go several standard deviations up
and down. And this is actually very
surprising given that neurons are
probably the single most costly cell
type in your body in terms of energy
consumption. They are really in
comparison, they consume quite a bit
of energy in your body. So you would
expect that these transmissions that are
communicated between neurons, which are
very costly, should be highly reliable.
So this is very counterintuitive these
results and has been puzzling
neuroscientists for quite a while now.
And then there
is a second puzzling observation,
which is that the morphology
of neurons looks somewhat like this. So
this would be your typical pyramidal
neuron you have in your cortex.
But you see that this is actually, for a
cell, quite big and elongated.
So this can be up to a millimeter in the
human brain, which means that if a
synapse fires somewhere here, it has a
very hard time communicating with the
cell body, which is down here. So the
electrical signals that are produced
here may travel down here,
but the synapse up here has no way of
measuring the actual voltages at the
cell body. And this is actually the
interesting place because here are the
action potentials formed. So if the
synapse would really like to know about
what is going on in the cell body so
that it can make predictions about how
the neuron will behave and how it
interacts with the world. And this is
another very puzzling or
open problem in neuroscience, how this
communication actually works out in
single neurons between the cell body and
the SynOps. It is known that actually
the action potentials can travel back
up. So they see kind of this binary
variable when the neuron spikes,
but they cannot actually measure the
membrane potential down here. So only
the most prominent electrical signals
can actually back propagate through
this. And this suggests
that the synapse actually has very
sparse information about what's going on
in the cell body. And most
models of synaptic plasticity don't
cover this at all. And we were wondering
how does this interaction work? How can
the synapse produce useful
learning signals given this sparse
information about this important state
of the neuron? And our idea was that
essentially these two observations,
these high levels of noise and the
synapse and this large distance between
cell body and synapses which give these
high uncertainties, these are actually
the two sides of the same coin. So our
hypothesis was that actually we could
use the same models that
we know already from the behavioral
level, how an agent can
act and perform in an environment of
high uncertainty. And we just apply this
to every sign ups and there is an error.
So every sign up should utilize these
same models, basically.
And this model would immediately suggest
that actually synaptic transmissions
should be noisy and these levels of
noise would express uncertainty about
the environment. And then we can use
this model to derive learning rules and
we can compare them side by side to
biology. And this is the first thing I
want to show you. So I just give a very
quick introduction to the free energy
model, because some of you might not be
that familiar with it, but this is
essentially a model to describe
a situation like this. You have a person
that is interacting with some
environment and here I assumed very
simple. So this person tries to throw a
ball to some target. And we as humans,
we are good in solving such tasks. And
we are also good in solving such tasks
if there is high levels of uncertainty
in this. So if the person may receive
some visual feedback, but a lot of this
feedback may be hidden. So you can
imagine this going on behind some wall.
And the person now still might want to
predict what is the trajectory of this
ball flying towards the target so that
it can make an accurate action.
So we will assign some variables to
these states here. So we have
essentially this feedback that this
person can observe. And we have this
unobserved state of the ball flying
here, which we call U, where the person
doesn't have direct access to it, would
only see parts of it, for example, when
the ball is at the corners of the ball
appearing. And then to model
this essentially, or to describe this
behavior, the person would have
an internal description of this
trajectory. So an internal model of this
state, U. And this
model would then be updated to match the
observed feedback.
And this can be described very nicely in
this beautiful mathematical framework of
the free energy principle. So the idea
is that you would essentially establish
a model of your internal state, so
essentially how the internal
states and the state of the environment
interact. And you would have a model of
the feedback, so how the states and the
feedback you observe interact. And
essentially you can then write down a
loss function that measures the distance
between this model of the internal state
and this model of the feedback and the
external state.
And then by essentially
minimizing this distance between the
two, you can derive all sorts of
behaviorally relevant,
can solve behaviorally relevant
problems, for example, learning. But you
can also use this for other things,
like figuring out what are good actions,
for example. So making inference about
both the internal states and the
actions. For example, and this is in a
nutshell, the free energy principle.
And this object here happens to be what
is known as the variation of free
energy, which is also just coincides
with statistical physics. And this is
where this framework has its name from.
But you see that all is probabilistic
here. So essentially you have two
probability functions q for the internal
model and P for this interaction between
states and observations. And you have
here a distance measure between them
that you want to minimize. So now if we
look at the neuron and the synapse and
how they interact with each other, we
find a very similar picture. So single
SynOps, which we have here in green,
has an internal state which we,
for simplicity, model only as the
synaptic weight. Based on this, the
SynOps, when it's triggered by a
presynaptic spike, it would generate a
post synaptic current. This would then
propagate to the soma, which is our
external state, which we cannot directly
observe because it's too far away from
the synapse. But we can see a feedback,
which is this back propagating action
potential, which is this binary variable
that tells us whether the neuron has
spiked or not. So this is exactly the
same framework if we write it down like
that. And we can just use the same
mathematics to solve it.
So to solve it, we only have to come up
with a couple of we have to make a
couple of assumptions. So we have to
write down a model for this guy here.
So this model of how the feedback
and the external state interact. But we
have very good models for this. This has
been studied over many years. So here
you see how typically a model neuron
behaves. So you have here the membrane
potential of a leaky integrated fire
neuron. And you see that this is just
going up and down. So this neuron would
receive a lot of presynaptic input and
maybe also noise. And eventually at some
point it hits a threshold, it would
generate a spike. So that would be the
sets that travels to the downstream
neurons and also back to the SynOps.
And then it resets,
right?
So we can write this down mathematically
as a very simple differential equation.
But the neuron doesn't have access to
this state again. So it's again behind
this wall, it only sees these spike
events. But we can actually, for this
simple case of a leaky integrated fire
neuron, we can solve this analytically.
So we can write down what is the
posterior distribution of membrane
potentials given the spike times. And
what comes out of this is actually a so
called stochastic bridge model, or in
this case of a leak integrated in fire
neuron. It's an orange bridge model. So
this can be written down analytically.
It's not simple, but it's doable.
And we can then just use this directly.
So this model that we have to again
write down these free energy
functionals. So we make here an
assumption how the synapse actually
produces post synoptic currents and how
they are integrated in the neuron. But
that's also given by the leaky
integrated fire neuron and actually the
stochastic inputs that the synapse
generates. So for simplicity, we only
assume here basically Gaussian synapses
that would inject draw a Gaussian random
variable and inject this to a leaky
integrated fire neuron. And then all
these ingredients actually can be solved
in closed form and we can derive
learning rules that would minimize this
free energy functional. Now,
and if we do that,
this has a bunch of nice properties
because this Einstein Beck bridge is
completely determined by the back
propagating action potentials. So
basically the times of the post synaptic
spikes that arrive at the neuron,
this shape that we get here only depends
on two neighboring post synaptic spikes,
which means that we get here
automatically a learning rule that looks
like this. So a learning rule that only
depends on the difference between two
postal optic spikes, which we call here
delta t two, and the
difference between the post synoptic
spike and the actual input that is
triggered at some point on the
presynaptic side. And we can
basically make here this lookup table
and just compute what would be the
update that these sign ups would need to
make so that it learns optimally in
terms of this free energy principle.
And this is the shape that we get out.
You see that there is a strong
dependence on the post synoptic firing
rate, but there is also a dependence on
basically this typical STDP that Sarah
mentioned before, what is the relative
positioning of the pre and postsynoptic
spike. So in a nutshell, this model
can now be split into essentially two
pathways. So we have this ATOC response,
which basically just whenever there is a
presynaptic spike that triggers an
action in the synapse, we would draw
from this Gaussian distribution and
inject it into the neuron.
And then there is this postalk update
where the synapse would look up in this
onstain Woolenbeck bridge, what would
have been the optimal output that it
should have generated, so what would
have been the optimal action. And then
it compares the actual action with this
optimal action according to this free
energy principle and then generates a
delayed response which is an update of
the synaptic weight. Okay?
And importantly, this internal model is
only implicit. It's encoded, so to say,
into this spike time dependent.
Plasticity rule. So how
do these rules then look and how do they
compare to biology? And actually the fit
is quite nicely given that this is
derived really from first principles
without making any assumptions. So this
is the measurement in biology. This is
this B and Al rule, b and Pool,
very old work where they actually did
this in vitro studies where they
injected pre and post synaptic spikes
and then they measured what is the
weight change in the synopsis. And this
is the rule that is predicted by our
model. And you see that at least in a
first order approximation, it gives us
very similar shapes. And this also makes
sense because the
synapse wants to change the most when
it's close to
the pre and post synoptic spike times
because this is where or the post
synoptic spike times because this is
where it knows the most about the state
of the postynaptic neuron. The free
energy principle would actually suggest
these kind of cones with
almost no assumption essentially. But we
also get because we have not just the
first order spike time dependent
plasticity rule, but we also have this
dependency on the post not of the firing
rate. We can also compare this to other
results. And this here is this old work
by Kaupner and Brunel. So this is
actually a model, but that was very
detailed describing the
plasticity based on the pre and post
synoptic firing rate in the synapse.
And this is what our model predicts. So
if we inject render and pre and post
synaptic bossBack trains with different
rates, our model would predict this
shape, which again is not a perfect
match. But given that this is a very
idealistic model, it's actually the main
features that low firing rates on
the postynopstic side would lead to
depression and higher to potentiation
are reflected in this.
Okay, I assume I still have ten minutes,
right? Okay, so I would give
a quick intermediate summary and then I
want to show some other work where we
actually apply this now to
actual machine learning model.
So what we have seen here is that
synapses are actually are very
stochastic and this was a
big puzzle. And B suggests that actually
the synaptic noise is actually the
synapses way of reporting its own
uncertainty about the environment,
where the environment is actually the
post synaptic neuron and it really
interacts in this fashion of the free
energy principle with this post synaptic
neuron or that's a very nice way of
describing it. And if you're interested
more, there's a paper, a preprint out,
you can read up on all this.
Okay, so how does this now connect to
neuromorphics? And actually so we are
not actually doing neuromorphic
hardware, we are doing neuromorphic
algorithms. So we try to bring these
inspirations now into actual machine
learning models and we thought that this
might be a good attack angle to
solve a problem that is well known in
machine learning. So I just drew
here very simple convolutional neural
networks with various convolutional
layers and then maybe some dense layers
that you would have in your machine
learning algorithm. And the way this is
trained, as many of you know, I guess,
is through end to end errorback
propagation. So the idea is that you
have a training set which has inputs and
targets. So, for example, in a
classification task, this could be
pictures of cats and dogs. And you would
have targets which are class labels,
so to say. So there's actually
artificial neurons in there, and one of
these neuron may be active for cats and
1 may be active for dogs. And in your
training, that data, you have exactly
these labels that were generated by
humans, that were sitting down doing
this by hand. And then during training,
you show these examples to the network
by propagating these inputs all the way
from the input layer to the output
layer. Then the output is here compared
to these hand labeled targets. And then
the mismatch between the two is back
propagated through all these layers back
to the input. And all the weights or the
synoptic weights that are here in
between inside these layers would then
be updated accordingly, so that after
doing this many, many times, this
network becomes good in telling apart
Kelvin docs. So this has a problem,
this algorithm. It works great in
practice and it's the foundation of all
these models we have talked about, like
Dali or Jet GPT, but it is quite
inefficient. And the problem is what is
known in the literature as the locking
problem. So if you would split up this
network now into blocks, which I already
did before, but this is arbitrary, but
for implementing this efficiently in
terms of a software algorithm, it might
be interesting to do that. And now you
would want these blocks ideally to run
in parallel, so that you can basically
show the first example on this first
block and then already train it while
the second block is doing something
else. But this is not really possible
with end to end back propagation because
of this lock in problem, because the
activation of the second block depends
on the activation of the first block.
So you have to propagate it all the way
to the end. Then you compute this error
and you would then back propagate. And
only when this is done, you can start
the next epoch where you show a new
bunch of examples and
you see that during all this time,
here, the thread that would run this
first block maybe would be idle and has
to wait essentially all the time. And
this obviously makes them very
inefficient. And now our idea was that
we use basically what we had learned
from this earlier model on how synopsis
communicate over these long distances
through this free energy principle, and
also apply it just to a deep neural
network. And the idea is that you have
here, again, basically you have already
this generation of inputs to some
output. But what is missing to make it
applicable to the free energy principle
is this feedback that you always need.
The idea was that we put here a very
lightweight feedback network. So
essentially each of these blocks now in
this deep neural network would be
accompanied by a feedback block that
locally generates a target. So we used
here really in the simplest case, which
we have, so this is very recent work,
we only used linear blocks so far. So
these are single linear layers and we
would generate now these outputs here in
these feedback blocks and then use the
free energy principle to derive a
local loss. That allows us again to
minimize both these feedback weights
that we have here and also the weights
in the forward network. So it's
essentially the same idea. So we have
here these outputs which we interpret
now as parameters to a probability
function. So we can apply this
probabilistic framework, but now all the
rest basically rolls out the same way.
So we assume that these outputs are
essentially the internal states of this
model and we have these
observations given in the inputs and the
targets. And now we try to minimize
basically P would now be this feed
forward network and Q would be now a
function that contains features
of both the feedback and
the feed forward network. And the nice
thing is that if we I don't have time to
go into the details now, but if you
write this out, you see that this
actually decomposes, this lock term here
decomposes into local linear terms that
give you these local losses here. So
essentially that you can minimize here
block local between forward and the
corresponding feedback block, a loss
function. And you can then actually do
this in parallel because maybe the
picture is good to see here. So what you
have to do now you have a bit of
overhead because you have this feedback
block. So this would be the two
execution times of the feed forward
block and the feedback block. But in
principle they can run in parallel and
once the forward block is done, the next
forward block can start propagating
through this network, but simultaneously
already the forward block, because it
already received a target here, can
start updating the weights and when it's
done, it's free to operate on the next
epoch. So there is no locking anymore in
this framework. Okay, so I'm
pretty much done. I'm also out of time,
I think. So how does this perform? Of
course we changed the learning
algorithm. Now we have to also go back
and see if this is still giving
us the same performance.
As I said, this is the first results
we have here now and at least to mid
scale data sets like cipher
ten or so, this seems to actually
perform very well. So we attract it for
standard architectures, fashion MNIST
with ResNet 15 and ResNet 18. We worked
mostly so far for small data sets like
Fashion MNIST with applying free splits
to ResNet 50. We get basically the same
performance as standard backprop. As
networks get deeper, you see that our
problem that we have now is actually
overfitting because we have these local
targets. It seems that these smaller
blocks actually overfit to some extent.
This is not so severe for still up to
tasks like cipher ten. So we get quite
close already. But if you go now for
really large tasks, there's still
something missing for like
single splits. We are getting there,
but we are not reaching all the way up
to back propagation. But it's still
interesting to see that you can apply
this principle also to these standard
machine learning algorithms. Okay, this
is my second summary. So actually we
found that deep neural networks are
surprisingly good in generalizing over
probability spaces. This is how actually
this work started. And our
idea was to exploit this and to utilize
it to distribute learning in the same
fashion as in the first project I showed
you and to solve this credit assignment
problem by generating these feedback
networks.
Yeah, that's basically it. And then I
want to acknowledge my coworkers and my
students. So I have two very good PhD
students, carlisle and Cabrill, who is
now here in Bohom and works on this
topic. And the first project I showed
was work I did together when I was in
gettingham with Christian Tetlav. And
the second project is I worked closely
with Christian Meyer and Anand Sutomoni
and yeah, thank you.
Thank you very much, David. That was
absolutely fascinating. I think it's
incredible how closely the sort of model
matched biology. Like considering you
derived it from first principles, I
think that was really cool. I did have a
question just about the last sort of the
bit. You spoke about the Convolutional
network and you said traditionally it
has to go all the way end to end, which
is really inefficient. And then you
showed the results that you got. Did you
look at energy consumption with yours as
well? Not yet. So we are actually
currently working on it's
actually not so easy to implement these
things in standard machine learning
toolboxes. So Carlisle is currently
looking into this, the PhD student in
Jester, he has an implementation now,
and he's now evaluating how well
we can make use of this parallelization
in practice. But we are actually quite
confident that for
parallelizing it, it should be there.
The question is how much you save in
terms of energy. Because for these
smaller scale models that we use now,
ResNet 18, ResNet 50,
the effect might be not that huge. So
once we ramp this up to really larger
models, the effect should be bigger.
But yeah, this is ongoing work. Very
cool. Thank you. And then I was just
wondering as well, this local error back
propagation, is that something that
other people have tried with these
convolutional neural networks or is this
quite a new way of implementing it?
There is a bunch of approaches that do
this. For example, I mean, the closest I
guess is target propagation which has
been proposed, which essentially uses
random feedback weights to back
propagate here. So these guys would not
be trained.
And this
works nicely also for small scale
problems. But as far as I know, they
don't perform that well. Even for cipher
ten, it already starts breaking down
because these random feedback weights
are just too coarse an approximation, I
think. And this is the first okay,
maybe I have to be careful. I think this
is the first method that allows you to
train these feedback weights. That is
not a contrastive method. There is a
bunch of methods that use a contrastive
step. So you have
maybe seen this forward forward
algorithm and all these things,
but what they have to do always is they
send in the actual input data and then
they send an kind of anti input,
an anti input that is usually
generated artificially. So they do some
distortion to the input to make it and
then they have to use both information
locally to do the update. So the network
has to keep in memory the input and the
anti input and the responses. And this
makes these approaches a bit harder to
parallelize in this. And the nice thing
here is that we derive an
upper bound to this variational free
energy loss that can be spelled out
completely by forward propagation. And
that I think is new. So that is the new
bit of this. Very cool.
That's awesome.
Well, yeah, few comments, one piece that
kind of between the two of your talks.
That was at least a new distinction to
me, which was the difference between the
Neuromorphic hardware and the
Neuromorphic algorithms. So it's not
just about new hardware or Wetware,
though that would be great to see.
It's almost like there's this
intermediate or a bridge step with using
the algorithms on
the hardware we have today that
like Sarah mentioned, the Spiking neural
networks which are amenable to GPUs or
just using standardized CPU multicore
scheduling approaches. You can already
do more with what we have
using the Neuromorphic algorithms. So
it's not just a material science
topic, but also there's a lot
at the really micro scale that we can
learn related to noise processing
scheduling and then also even at higher
levels of abstraction, probably learning
from biomimicry and cognitive systems
more generally. But that was a
distinction for me.
Yeah. So maybe to add yeah. So I think
that the problem becomes really now more
pressing as these Neuromorphic devices
become so the hardware devices become
more mature and they usually cannot
really shine on these standard
machine learning algorithms because they
are really optimized for GPUs. So you
need to think a little bit. So you have
to take one step back and think again
about the algorithmic side to really
use them to full capacity. And as you
have seen now, we collaborate with
Professor Meyer, who is doing this
spinnaker chip in Dresden, but there's
also other approaches like the Louis
chip that Sarah mentioned from intel and
so on, and they are really looking
into this. Now, also from the
algorithmic side. I find
it really useful. It's kind of like a
mindset or a mental framework when I'm
thinking about computers or AI, and this
is probably because I'm a
neuroscientist, but I also have to
translate it to, well, how does the
brain work, how does the information
processing work, et cetera, in the
brain? And when I came to sort of
computer science and AI after
neuroscience, I found myself naturally
translating it. But I feel like the
framework is just a really useful way of
understanding computation at the end of
the day because our brains, as I said,
are just these massive supercomputers.
And I'm constantly reading papers on
computer science or whatever. And then
once you can conceptualize anything
really as well, how neuromorphic is
this? And then if you start thinking
about, well, how could you tweak it so
it's slightly more neuromorphic? And is
that then going to give you these gains
that we get with the brain? Is it going
to give you some extra parallel
computation or is it going to give you
some energy efficiency? So, yeah, I find
it the definitions when I was looking at
the definition is I think it really
depends who writes the definition. And
because it's such a dynamic area at the
moment as well, I think it has been
changing and it will be changing, but
for me, I feel like neuromorphic is more
of like a mental framework where I look
at things through conceptualize,
through yeah, I think it's. It'S also
not very well defined.
You also mentioned that actually
artificial neural networks are a
neuromorphic concept, if you want, and
they were from the first day. And it's
a big success story, right, if you look
into the 90s or so when these support
vector machines and these alternative
models came up, but none of them have
outlived the neuromorphic approaches.
So it's actually very nice. But still
there is this community that thinks that
there is more features from the brain
that you need to put in to get to
the real thing. So I think this is a bit
of a it's not a very well defined term,
actually, and I think with. Your
research, yours is almost like the
smallest level that I've seen people
look at it on. I don't know if you've
seen anything else, but we're not just
talking about a cell level of free
energy and active inference. We're
actually talking about a cell structure.
So then you think, well, how small does
it go? Are we going to talk about cell
subcellular structures eventually, like
Mitochondria using free energy in a
similar way with compartments, I guess
actually it'd be interesting to get your
thoughts, david on, you talked at the
start about how synapses are
compartmentalized. Do you see different
sort of instantiations of this in
different compartments just within one
synapse, almost like are you wanting to
sort of look at that granular level or
is it more now taking what you've
learned from this and putting it back
into how can we sort of make the AI more
efficient? Yeah, we are going much more
in this direction now that we see how we
can build this back into AI models.
One has to be a bit careful when using
the free energy principle because it's
such a powerful general framework that
you can apply it to basically anything
and it's not necessarily you will come
up with a useful result in the end.
Just putting this this
started actually as a side project.
This was my kind of COVID pandemic
lockdown project. And I was just curious
about this and whether you can actually
solve this, because I thought the
synopsis is maybe simple enough.
Because when you go into the papers,
they have at some point to go into some
approximations. They do some mean field,
usually, so they go for first modes,
and then you can solve these guys for
more complex, even for neurons, it's
hard, actually, if you go to the neuron
or network level, it's hard. It's very
involved math, but for a sinus is simple
enough, actually. So you can actually do
this and spell everything out if you
make the right assumptions and really
just derive these things. And that was
kind of just kind of
a game I went into and
then it turned out to work quite nicely,
I think, in the end. Yeah.
I'm not sure if you like Mitochondria or
so I'm sure you could apply the same
principles but I'm not sure if the
results you get would be any meaningful
or would help you in any way.
That's always the risk. You invest so
much time and then in the end you get
some results and you don't know. That
was also something that I thought was
quite interesting, which was the synapse
was the agent. It's really easy to
think, oh, we'll make an agent based
model of a neural system. First off,
that tends to not include Glia or non
neural cell types, but it's almost like
a doubly unquestioned assumption that
the cell would be the agent.
But then it was a great transition from
the person throwing the ball over the
wall. That's an action centric approach
where you only have partial visibility
of the consequences and then that
is the exact scenario that the synapse
finds itself in in a different way.
Or it could have been set up so that a
neuron is the agent. We're building
maps, not territories. And so then,
just like you said, free energy
principle, it's a principle for
everything. And so just
making principled statements about
things is table stakes.
And then I guess my question for you is
then what does make it useful or in your
learning and tinkering around with these
models? What differentiated situations
where you applied free energy principle
or active inference and you felt like it
was providing a contribution to your
research direction versus where you
played around and it was like, well,
that was tautological. I think the free
energy principle makes sense in a
context where you have incomplete
information.
So for example, in the synapse case,
right, the question we started with was
this problem that the synapse has to
solve, that it has incomplete
information about the state in the cell
body because it only sees this
kind of or that's the assumption, at
least of the model. And also what we get
from the experimentalists, that it
essentially only sees this back
propagating action potential. So it sees
a single binary variable about the
state of the soma.
So essentially this is a problem of
incomplete information and also the
second ingredient that
you need some form of agency. I think if
you apply the free energy principle to a
system without agency, so if something
is not interacting with an environment
in a closed loop, then it becomes really
sketchy. And I think already this model
is on the edge when it comes because
these models don't really have an
agency, but they at least produce an
output, right? So you can still think of
this as an interaction with an
environment. But as soon as you lose
that, I think then there would be
simpler models that can just give you
the same.
Actually, in the synapse case, the
agency is only this adding noise
actually in the model because the
synapse is triggered presynaptically and
then it uses its internal
state to add the right amount of noise,
which is probably already the minimal
agency you could imagine.
Sir, you want to ask a question or I can
ask a question? Yeah, it was more just a
comment. I think it's quite interesting
people talk about biology. Some people
say it's not a real science because it's
all messy and noisy. But I think it
works really interesting because it's
like you say, the synaptic noise is
actually a reporting of uncertainty. So
in that essence, it's actually probably
quite accurately reporting the messy
world rather than the biology itself
just being all messy. But that's just
what I was thinking about. Yeah, I think
I was curious as well. Like you said,
this was like your Lockdown project,
but I'm just interested in how you sort
of came to use the free energy
principle, how you came across it. Was
it something you were quite familiar
with already or some of your network or
peers were talking about it? Or did you
just stumble across it in a.
Was during my PhD, I was interested in
variational methods and probabilistic
methods. And then I started reading
about this. And so I read a bunch of
Karl Friston's papers and I found this
interesting. And actually,
my PhD supervisor always encouraged
me not to go in that direction.
And then after I finished my PhD and
thought, okay, now I can do what I want,
I try it out.
And then, I guess, do you think it would
be worthwhile, like, next steps for you
or for the field actually trying to
implement this on maybe some of the more
analog chips that are being built in the
space? Like the analog neuromorphic
chips, which I know you can have some
dynamic synapses and things like do you
think it would be worthwhile trying to
implement it on hardware? Or what are
your thoughts on that? I mean, the
triplet rule that comes out from this
first work I showed, I think that would
be interesting to implement it.
The nice feature is that it should, in
principle, should have this self
stabilizing feature because it's really
mimicking the dynamics of
the membrane, of the cell membrane. So
if the neuromorphic hardware would so
if the model in the synapse and the
neuron model match up very well, the
model should give you this nice self
stabilizing feature so that neurons
really not go into some epileptic states
or so. And you get this for free from
this model. That's what we saw in the
simulations, at least. But in
the simulations, of course, we had full
control over this dynamics matching up
in the right way. So that is
probably a bit more tricky for hardware,
but it's probably solvable. So it would
be interesting. What you get for it is
that you have these purely event based
tools which only use pre post spikes,
which is nice. Very cool. Thank you.
Yeah. Daniel, if you had a question?
Well, that's a great principle there,
which is like, if you can design the
neuromorphic algorithm so that it
harnesses a material feature like the
actual leaky permeability of a membrane
or actual spatial proximity, if you can
leverage a material feature,
analog feature that isn't virtualized,
then it's already an adjacency into
future hardware. So that's one great
point. And then to Sarah's point about
almost biology not being a science,
which there is a famous quotation,
there will never be a Newton for a blade
of grass. Because some people say,
yeah, it's a different biology is more
like history. Because whether you
approach this from a development or
ecology or evolution perspective,
biology is a historical science. It's
not like a real science. And then that
reminded me of the cross country shirt
that says, our sport is your punishment.
So it's like, well, no, your noise
is biology's signal. And that's how
it happens. My question was
about this tension between,
I guess, neural and computational ways
of looking at the resources associated
with computation. So from the von
Neumann paradigm. We have a
lot of shared reference points, CPU
cycles, Ram capacity, and all
these kinds of and like, even in your
introductions, you conveyed like, well,
this is how many CPU cycles it's going
through, or this is how many parameters
would have to be stored, or something
like that. However, that's referencing
another paradigm. So what do resource
descriptors or capacity descriptors
look like when we're outside the
space of okay, yeah, power consumption.
That's something that you can put into a
box and just use a bomb calorimeter
that's kind of like a low hanging fruit.
But now okay, beyond just the sheer
energy or caloric requirements, what can
we say that is, like, analogous to the
way that we talk about the processor or
the Ram or the hard drive on a computer?
Yeah, I'd have to think about that one
some more. I do think there was some
interesting comments in the paper on
that slide I showed that talks about the
brain and energy. There was a paper I
linked to. I'll have to get the
reference and let you know what it is
because QR code is gone now. But that
had some interesting ideas, I think, on
what you're getting at there. But I'd
have to defer to the paper.
How do they describe what is being
designed? So they say it has this many
of this type of component, and then that
might do nothing though. So how do they
describe or evaluate these different
designs or algorithms?
I think it's all different depending on
the use case. That's what I've found.
Really? Like, the language is different
depending on if it's written by someone
maybe with more of a neuroscience
background or an engineering background.
And then you kind of get used to some
terms that are more interchangeable than
others. But I do think the terminology
is something which needs to be looked at
a lot more closely in this space,
because then I think that will help
everybody working in it to be on the
same page a little bit closer.
Cool. Well, any other thoughts
or questions? David first and then
Sarah. Also, I'm very curious, what
direction will this series go? But
first, David, what are any other kind of
closing comments or directions you want
to.
Really? I mean, I would say thanks for
having me today. It was really a
pleasure to discuss with you.
Thank you. David, it was amazing to have
you on. I think your work is absolutely
fascinating, and I think it's going to
have lots of benefits in the future for
implementation, which is always nice to
see as well. Yeah. So what was the
question? Where do I see the series
going? Hopefully we can have a new
guest each month. I think it'd be kind
of cool maybe next month to have someone
who's building hardware, so, like,
maybe someone from the BrainScaleS team
or spinnaker team or something like that
would be. Pretty cool, but yeah,
really, I just want to have a space for
people who are interested in this
intersection to meet people and see
talks and reach out to people who are
also working in the space, because it's
pretty niche, but I think it's pretty
important, actually. Having said that,
David, could you let everybody know if
they wanted to reach out to you, what's
the best way for them to do that?
I'm not very active on this discord
channel, so maybe email is still the
best to reach out to me, I guess.
Cool. Do you want to give your oh.
I think my email should be easy
enough to find. But you can also give
the email out there. Sure. Cool. People
can check the papers, and then in the
active inference institute discord,
there's the neuromorphic channel.
All right. Thank you, David and Sarah.
Really cool to see morphstream kick off
its developmental trajectory this way.
So till next time. Thank you.