Daniel: All right, the next session is
going
to be the final session of this symposium.
.
It's been a really incredible journey,
and I think this final session is going
to be great as well.
So we have a whole panel here, and people
can use their cameras (even though I'm
not), if they want to, Welcome, everyone!
I'll just introduce the facilitator, Curt
Jaimungal.
So Curt is a legend in the ActInf
ecosystem and has done incredible work
with a variety of researchers and curious
individuals in the space, so we could
think of no one better to host this
conversation and bring it all together.
So, Curt, I'll pass it to you.
You'll keep an eye on the live chat.
Anyone can call it if they need any
supports.
Otherwise, thanks, everybody, for joining.
.
And we don't see you yet, Curt.
Curt: But yeah, it would it be all right
if I left and then came right back?
For whatever reason, my camera is not
working.
Daniel: Sounds good.
Sounds good.
Curt: Okay, I'll be right back in about
25 seconds.
Daniel: Well, welcome, everyone.
We will get started in just a second.
Curt: It's so odd.
I apologize for that.
Okay, well, you can hear my voice, at
least.
Yes, just give me a moment.
Boy.
Okay, well, we'll do what we can.
Okay, so you all can't see me, but that's
all right.
So we have this all-star panel here today,
, which to me means my invitation must
have been a mistake, but I'll take it.
Thank you to the Active Inference
Institutes!
And I'll go around this virtual zoom
table and introduce everyone briefly.
Karl Friston is the Wellcome Principal
Research Fellow and Scientific Director
at the Wellcome Trust Center for
Neuroimaging and professor of Neurology
at University College London.
He's also the chief scientist at VERSES.
Anna Lembke is chief of the Stanford
Addiction Medical… (Sorry.)
Medicine Dual Diagnosis Clinic at
Stanford University.
Her popular books include “Drug Dealer,
MD” and “Dopamine Nation.”
Rafael Kaufmann is CTO of Digital Gaia
and the onboard… (sorry.)
And is on the board of directors of the
Active Inference Institute.
Bert de Vries is a professor at Eindhoven
University of Technology, where he
directs the BIASlab research team and
also works with industry.
Guillaume Dumas is an associate professor
in computational psychiatry of the
Faculty of Medicine at the University of
Montreal and the Director of the
Precision Psychiatry and Social
Physiology Laboratory in CHU Saint
(Sorry.)
In the CHU
Sainte-Justine Research Center.
He's also affiliated with Mila (or Mila),
which is Quebec's Artificial Intelligence
Institute; and other art, science, and
consciousness service initiatives.
My name is Curt Jaimungal, and I use my
background in mathematical physics to
analyze various Theories of Everything
that are proposed.
These include both the theoretical
physics side of Grand Unification with
gravity, and dualities, other schemes; as
well as attempting to understand what
constitutes consciousness.
You can find the podcast by typing in
“Theories of Everything” onto YouTube or
whatever podcast catcher you have.
So my question to everyone,
the initial question, is: What have you
been working on in the past few months,
and what excites you about it?
We'll start with Bert.
You seem to be smiling; and your name
sounds like mine.
Bert: [Bert is accidentally muted.]
Okay.
All right, so my name is Bert de Vries.
And, yeah,
I lead a lab in an electrical engineering
department.
And so our lab is called BIASlab, as you
mentioned.
So we are interested in Bayesian
inference in general, but more
specifically in doing it as fast as
possible.
That has lots of applications outside
active inference, also for signal
processing and other control systems, but
definitely, of course, also for active
inference.
So half our work over the past few months,
, but even over the past few years, has
been on developing a toolbox to support
or to get as far as we can go with trying
to do real time Bayesian inference or
real time free energy minimization and
trying it in applications.
So that's the work – that I try to lead a
team of PhD students who do the real work,
,
of course. I walk around with a cup of
coffee, but that's what they've been
working on.
Curt: Great!
And Professor Lembke, please.
Anna: Yeah, well, what I've been working
on in the last, I don't know, year or so,
is spending a lot of time thinking about
how it is that a faith framework - in
particular, surrender to a higher power -
improves people's lives.
And I've been really struggling to come
up with a way of talking about this that
is inclusive.
Thinking about it, talking about it.  It
gets to a kind of core piece of it that I'
'm interested in, which is not so much
whether or not God exists and what the
proof is or not of whether God exists.
But really, what is it that changes in
people's lives when they undergo a
spiritual transformation, when they
surrender to a higher power?
Why do their lives get better, when they
DO get better?
And I'm really new to the active
inference world.
Daniel Friedman is the one who's
introduced me to these ideas.
I'm really excited about the ways in
which the whole active inference model
might help me (at least) think about what'
's going on there.
And that's what I'm working on.
It's a little weird, but that's what I'm
interested in.
Curt: Great.
Professor Friston. (You're muted.)
Karl: Yes, that's going to be the title
of my next book:
“Karl, You're on Mute!” Retro from the...
possibly the future.
I generally work on what I'm told to work
on, so I'm just trying to list what I've
been working on in the past few months.
Interestingly,
it actually starts with Daniel Friedman
and his fascination, along with Axel
Constant, for evolutionary explanations
that speak to many of the scale free
issues that we've been hearing about in
the prior session.
So that's what I was working on, really,
a scale free approach to understanding
temporally nested processes as free
energy minimizing processes as a kind of
active inference, and how that would lead
to a variational synthesis of evolution.
And then I was told to work on belief
sharing by Mahault and colleagues at
VERSES, and worked on that in the context
of synthetic language and tried to
establish a really simple proof of
principle that communication was an
emergent property of any free ensemble,
free energy minimizing system.
And just to open brackets, just to make
the observation, it struck me time and
time again during the session today how
important communication is, whether we're
talking about Bert's passing messages or
responding to "you've got a new posterior,
," or we're talking about the kind of
communication that Mahault was talking
about.
Well, everybody's been talking about.
It does seem to be really, indeed, the
Gaia notion of overconnectivity and too
much communication or the wrong kind of
communication.
It does strike me that's quite central to
both the theme of the workshop and the
specific presentations that we've heard.
And then in the past few weeks, working
on stuff I think that Bert would be more
interested in, which is fast and frugal
message passing schemes that enable the
evaluation of the expected free energy,
not to suffer from the limitations
imposed by deep tree searches.
So possibly Ashwin has spoken about this
earlier on, but you're using ideas from
dynamic programming, backwards induction,
to try and take the pressure off the
message passing to get fast and efficient
evaluations of the expected free energy
in sort of single unit, single agent
active inference.
What have I been doing this week?
Can't remember.
That's what I've been doing.
Curt: Great.
Rafael Kaufmann, please.
Just a moment.
Can everyone else hear?
Okay.
Rafael: What about now?
Curt: Yeah, great.
Rafael: Yeah, thanks.
It's contagious, I think.
So I've also been drinking a lot of
coffee as I've been caring for my now
nine month old daughter.
Curt: Congratulations.
Rafael: Thank you.
So aside from sleep deprivation, what I'
've been doing is (I told you guys about
this in the session earlier today) but in
a nutshell, we've been working on what we
call the Gaia Protocol, or the Gaia
network, which is this open approach for
building a common engine.
You can think of it as a common runtime
and a common language with the building
blocks of shared decision making in the
context of the Med [?] crisis, and
getting to a set of building blocks for
decision making that don't kill us all.
Bert: So that's kind of it.
Curt: Rafael, how much coffee is a lot of
coffee?
Rafael: Well, it's espresso, so I don't
think it's quite comparable to American
coffee.
Curt: All right.
And Guillaume Dumas, please.
Guillaume: Yes, sure.
Can you hear me?
Curt: Yes.
Guillaume: Okay.
So in the context of active inference, I
have mostly focused on, well, the two big
topics of my lab.
So precision psychiatry and social
physiology.
So.
On the precision psychiatry side, Nynke
Boiten presented earlier in this
symposium our work on trying to model
theory of mind to being able to evaluate,
through digital phenotyping, the level of
sophistication of interaction in patients
with neurodevelopmental disorders.
And that connects with also our interest
in the social mind and how we can connect
our understanding of how we deal with
other people but with also ourselves.
And so that connects with other work at
the Mila, with deep learning architecture,
, with higher order function in humans,
where we're trying to combine different
theories of consciousness, such as global
neural workspace and attention schema
theory.
And in the context of attention schema
theory, there is this kind of recycling
of self and other mechanisms.
So that's one big work.
And on the other side, I'm very
interested also in multi agent systems.
And so with Natalie Castell, who's going
to join us soon, we've been working on
creativity and the emergence of cultural
norms in multi agent systems with the
idea of applying that to climate action.
And also a new project that is starting
here with NFRF [[New Frontiers in
Research Fund]] of a big Canadian project
on Indigenous knowledge and how we can
think about new narrative around AI and
typically a less solipsistic and
individualistic way of dealing with AI.
So that's the two main fields of research.
.
Curt: Can you explain what you mean by
less solidistic, less solipsistic when it
comes to AI.
Guillaume: The Californian view of AI,
because the narrative is mainly driven by
U.S. and California right now, tends to
circle around optimization, profits...
I mean, even OpenAI states that AGI is
about optimizing profitable human tasks.
They put like profitable in their
definition.
In the case of Indigenous systems of
knowledge, we are more talking about
community sustainability;
and the view already only in the
application is less individualistic.
But also in the cognitive science point
of view, we have the outcore
computationalism that could say the brain
is just like a computer in a very
restrictive sense.
And so AI, like, typically those
transformers that are massively used
right now, are kind of like "brain in a
vat" in a very silicon sense, while we
are embodied systems that are constituted
by our interaction with others.
And so, in a way, how we can think about
artificial intelligence in this kind of
more co-constitutive way and through a
developmental and cultural lens.
Curt: Mm-hmm! Okay, now, speaking of the
brain as a computer, we frequently hear
in these circles "the brain as a
predictive machine."
So where does this, the (quote unquote) "
"brain as a predictive machine," have its
limits?
And also, is that to be interpreted as
implying conscious experience is a
predictive machine as well?
And if not, why not?
So I think, Karl, you'd be a great person
to start this off, and then we'll go
around the table again.
Karl: Yeah, I was mindful of Mahault's
presentation the past half hour and the
notion of temporal thickness.
I'm sure that's got a lot to do with the
necessary conditions for the kind of
consciousness
(I'm guessing) you're referring to - that
freedom from the moment.
And if one reads prediction in its sort
of psychological or protension nature in
terms of being able to predict what will
happen in the future,
I think that's going to be sort of a key
bright line between things that do not
possess certain kind of sentience and
things that do.
And that bright line just rests basically
upon - well, from perspective of active
inference - having a generative model
that includes the consequences of your
own actions in the future.
So just by having consequences you're now
talking about the future. And the
consequences in the future now become
random variables.
Therefore you have to infer them.
Which leads you directly to the notion of
planning as inference, which means that
bright line is just a difference between
things that plan and do not plan.
And I would guess that that's where you
probably want to start in terms of
foregrounding the role of prediction as
being an aspect of self organization and
its sort of reading under active
inference that characterizes conscious
things from non conscious things, namely
the ability to plan.
Does that make sense?
Curt: I have follow up questions;
we'll get to them at some point. But for
now, Anna, do you have any comments on
that, and Bert as well afterward?
Anna: Well, I'm new to this field so I'm
just familiarizing myself even with the
language.
But I can respond to the question.
The brain is a predictive machine in
terms of the work that I do clinically
and the kind of psychopathology that I
see when I'm working with patients, I
work primarily with narrative, the
stories that they tell about their lives.
.
And one of the recurring themes I've seen
through my work is that when patients
tell stories in which they are
perpetually the victims of other people's
actions or the world, that tends to be a
predictive model for them so that they
will then go out into the world and
unconsciously create scenarios which will
perpetuate their victimhood.
And that part of getting into wellness is
to stop seeing themselves as entirely the
victim of other people or circumstance,
instead begin to appreciate what they
contribute to their life problems.
So I guess when I think of the limits of
the brain as a predictive machine, I
think in some ways one of the big limits
is that it's a very powerful predictive
machine that actually allows us to
subsequently shape what actually happens
to us and or our perceptions of what
happens to us, which then can perpetuate
a false narrative.
And I'll just give one small example from
my own life.
I've had my conflicts with my mother and
one of my beefs about her is that she's a
very poor communicator and that whenever
I email her I either get a cryptic
response or no response at all and it
drives me crazy.
And about five years ago she sent an
email, asked me some questions, I wrote
her back and responded and it was clear
to me that that required yet a response
from her which I never got.
And that then perpetuated my narrative
about her as a very poor communicator and
many other negative things.
And then about three months after I sent
that email, I found the email in my draft
box.
So I had never actually responded to my
mother's email.
I hadn't actually sent the email.
And that was, for me, just a personal,
wonderful example of the ways in which
our actions can actually be manipulated
to support our models and perpetuate
falsehoods about the world that we live
in.
Curt: Right.
And I have a quick question, Bert, just
for Anna before we get to you.
So you use the word narrative there.
How are you defining the word narrative?
Is it the same as model?
Is it a sequence of events?
Like, what is the specific definition of
narrative?
Anna: I never really thought about it in
those terms.
But when I talk about narrative, I'm
talking about the stories that people
tell about their lives, because that's
sort of my data and also about models,
because what I've discovered about self
narrative is it's not just a way to
organize the past.
It also becomes a roadmap for the future.
.
That's the language that I use, but I see
it maps very nicely onto Ural's language
of modeling the world.
Curt: I see.
Professor DeVries, please.
Bert: Yeah, it's clear that the ability
to predict is the essence of intelligent
decision making.
Yeah, I have a different background.
Right.
I'm not a psychiatrist, so I think about
these things in different way.
The thing that I think about when I think
about prediction is I would assume that
brain predicts far ahead, that things get
less accurate.
Right.
If I predict that I want to go three
quarters around a roundabout.
I don't care about the centimeter where
my car goes when I'm around there, I just
want to get in the right lane.
And I would assume that the brain doesn't
takes less computations if you care about
things less precisely.
But that's very hard in a computer.
This is what kind of kills us, I think,
in our current way of implementing active
inference.
When we want to predict a deep hat, we
don't care about the accuracy, but we don'
't know how to do it much cheaper when
things are less accurate.
And so that's a problem that we need to
be working on.
It might be a key to building or to
scaling up active entrance agents if we
can actually compute messages that we
want to know that we don't care about, if
they are less precise, that we also spend
much less computation on them.
Curt: Thank you.
Now, Professor Kaufman.
Rafael: I am not a professor, but I'll
answer anyway.
Can just call me Rafa.
Karl: Rafa.
Rafael: Yeah.
So there's so many really interesting
avenues here, and it's not often that I
get the pleasure of discussing this kind
of stuff with this kind of diverse crowd.
.
But I've been interested in these
questions for a pretty long time.
And I think what comes to mind is how
active inference at the lens, for
instance, it enables us to get another
sense of what nondualist views on
consciousness are saying when they get us
experientially to notice the difference.
Between what we actually perceive and
between the different various different
processes or things that are going on in
our head and our tendency to lump them
all together into the same okay.
This is my experience that I'm immersed
in.
So noticing being able to notice the
difference between the process of
perceiving and acting and to an extent,
it's automated, and the narrative or the
various narratives that are going on in
parallel in my head, whether I'm aware of
them or not.
And our ability to just put kind of
seemingly arbitrary manner levels on top
of it, to try to make sense of it all and
to force that experience of having
multiple narratives and multiple framings
going on at the same time make sense of
that experience.
Curt: In a.
Rafael: Way that aligns with our
presuppositions about how things are.
So I think that's super interesting.
I also want to highlight that this view
of consciousness as being kind of defined
by having a narrative or an internal
model that's about self or that at least
is about self.
And that leads, as Karl said, to planning
this inference that's actually, like,
super deflationary in a way that people
are not used to thinking about exciting.
It's opening the doors to all sorts of
exciting interdisciplinary conversations
to be had on the basis of at least, I
feel like, better, less talking past each
other than we've ever had.
So I'm excited about that.
Curt: And how is it that you're using the
word deflationary there, Karl?
I remember I asked you about that when we
had our podcast together.
But Rafael, similar question.
So you said deflationary view.
When we have narratives of self, do you
mean us to something that consciousness
is much more than sorry.
Rafael: Much, yeah.
It's not necessarily much less than in
the subjective sense, but it's perhaps
much less than in the scientific sense.
So one example of not saying exactly that,
, but maybe something close to what
Daniel Dennett calls hetero phenomenology,
, which is basically the statement that
the sum of what one can say
scientifically about consciousness is is
equal to what?
Can be studied and modeled and theorized
and communicated and learned and agreed
upon on the basis of objective data about
what people, including you, but also
other people say about their experience
and, of course, what can be measured.
Up neuro, correlates and whatever.
Which is not the same as not necessarily
the same as our experience of what we
think is our direct experience of being
conscious.
Curt: Right.
Rafael: So one way to look at it is that
the science of consciousness doesn't
necessarily have to put the primacy on
people.
For instance, people saying they have
qualia, that we thought in that sense it'
's deflationary.
Right.
You have to explain why people believe
they have qualia, not why people have
qualia because it's not necessarily a
scientific truth that people have.
Curt: Right, Professor Dumas.
Guillaume: Yes.
Well, on the limits of brain as
predictive machine, well, we should be
always careful to not move from one map
territory fallacy to another one for sure.
.
So we need to be skeptics and avoid to
refine the methods.
And well, this World symposium show how
this metaphor is super useful and
fruitful, but I can see like two main
limits or at least things where we should
be careful.
So following what Professor Lembke said
in psychiatry, I think the looping
effects and the way people picture
themselves can be very unpredictable.
And so the way we think about the brain
as a predictive machine think prediction
for patients would have different
signification of what we mean by
predictive machines in the context of
active inference and in general.
Also, I can see that certain
psychologists or anthropologists would
have a big appeal all of a sudden for
active inference and free energy
principles, but taking the words as
directly what they think the word mean,
where we need to be careful in the way to
communicate it.
And typically following also what
Professor Debris said about prediction as
being super important for decision making,
, I think we should be careful about the
weirdness of cognitive science and how it
doesn't necessarily expand to non Western
educated industrialized country, where
maybe the cultural value is not about
optimization of your decision making or
your profit.
And so that's the first thing where I
think we should be careful.
It's more like a matter of how to
communicate the theory in that case, not
necessarily a limit of the theory itself,
but the second one is about the
equivalents or not with other.
Like, I can see we had Mahault Albarracin
talking about category theory.
And I'm very curious about right now
among the different frameworks that are
out there, how can we define what is
equivalent or not with active inference
to be able to see those limits?
Maybe we are leaving what happened with
quantum mechanics in the early 20th
century with different interpretation,
with different tools to model quantum
mechanics, and here with artificial
intelligence and cognitive neuroscience,
we have also all those frameworks.
And I think the limitation would be then
to not take this interpretation as the
only one, but try to have a cross talk
and a differential diagnosis of which one
is the best for explaining what.
Curt: Okay, now my role is the moderator,
but I would like you all to speak to one
another.
So I'm going to ask a question that will
serve as well.
You each will speak on it, but as the
other person is speaking sorry, as the
other people are speaking, just think,
okay, is there a question that I have or
is there a comment that I have?
So the question is what are some of the
recent advancements or breakthroughs in
your respective fields that you find
particularly promising and well recent,
let's say 2020 till now so we'll start
off with Rafael you're smiling and you
look like.
Rafael: You'Re champion I was thinking
what is my field?
Bert: Right?
Karl: Because.
Rafael: We'Re very much in the last mile
of applying the wonderful stuff that y'
'all come up with and making it useful on
the so I'm extraordinarily excited about
research like what Bird is doing.
And I feel like, as Gion was saying, we'
're also starting to see some convergence
on different ways to get.
Curt: At.
Rafael: Least the same shape of answers
and in some cases, even to the same
result.
So one example of this is work that Chris
Fields, Karl and others have been doing
on the quantum basically explaining
quantum information theory and how it
relates to the free energy principle.
Looking at the free energy principle as
the classical limit of quantum
information theory and I don't pretend to
understand all of it, but as somebody who
is coming from a quantum physics
background just being alive to see this
kind of conversions happening which as I
mean, as Guillaume said, we've been at
this business of post classical what the
hell is going on for over a century now
and it's nice to be at a time where again
we're starting to talk less past each
other and that's from a theoretical
perspective, from a practical perspective,
, I think just finding that we have all
the building blocks to create fast,
interpretable, reliable and aligned
decision making systems which includes AI
systems, autonomous systems that have all
those characteristics and that it turns
out that all the things that the
reinforcement learning and deep net
neural networks people talk were very
hard or impossible are sort of in the
realm of what we can do looking at things
from an active inference lens and vice
versa.
A lot of things that active inference
models have incorporated so far, it turns
out if you toss in a neural network
approximator here and borrow some other
massively parallel computation techniques,
, it also becomes feasible.
So it's converging.
Karl: Yeah.
Curt: For me, what's remarkable is that
there's so many domains of what we
thought was exclusively human or would be
exclusively human for decades that in
just the past couple years robots or
computers seem to be just as good, if not
exceeding us.
And I don't know if that's promising or
worrisome, but anyhow Karl, please, if
you don't mind answering the question.
And then we'll go.
Anna then Bert and then Dumas.
Karl: Actually, just reflecting upon one
of your observations I think it's very
difficult to identify one thing.
In a sense, what is impressive is the
diversity of advances and applications.
And I just say that because that's what I
was thinking over the past 6 hours, just
listening to your amazing presentation
after presentation and just noting how
diverse and yet there's this common
thread, this common commitment, basically
stating our curiosity and using the tools
that naturalize, that kind of sense
making, curious behavior and
communication that inherit from sort of
either maths or category theory or as
Ralph notes now, quantum information
theory.
But just to pick up on a couple of things
which are relevant to this conversation.
So the work with Chris Fields, it sounds
lovely and exciting to bring quantum
mechanics into active inference, but that'
's not the move that I think Chris is
really wanting to champion.
The move, I think, is something that we'
've all been addressing in one way or
another, which is leveraging the scale
free aspects of this principled approach
to self organization and hopefully self
organization to some kind of generalized
synchrony.
So that's where the quantum information
theory gets into the game.
It is scale free.
And indeed, he will go further and say it'
's completely background free and
everything is constructed.
So I think that's a lovely move, because
once you've gone scale free, you then
start to ask deep questions about how you
couple one scale to another scale.
And in a sense, ecosystems is just that.
How do the denizens of an ecosystem, how
is it constituted?
How is it co constructed?
What is the structure of it?
These are all questions about how one
scale links to another scale.
So I think there have been lots of
advances in that direction in many, many
different fronts.
And you can read that either in terms of
coupling, difference of spatial or
spatial scales, but probably more
importantly, sort of temporal scales.
And you see that wherever you look, you'
'll just come back to what do you mean by
a narrative?
It is exactly I think, as I said, it's
just a plan.
It's just a story.
But notice the story has a temporal
aspect to it.
I have narratives about being a good
person, being a good father, being a good
scientist.
I also have narratives about I want my
cup of coffee, or I have to go look after
the I don't, but Ralph has to go look
after the child.
So we've all got narratives at very, very
different timescales.
And of course, if you're I just came back
to Bert's example of I'm an autonomous
vehicle and I'm sentient and we're five
years into the future, and I have to
drive around the roundabout.
What temporal scale and what kind of
temporal course grading to define the
narratives necessary with narratives
would be appropriate for that kind of
situation and the ensuing planning.
Short answer to your question.
I think there have been many, many
advances.
I think what they've had in common is
basically transcending either different
domains, but in particular different
scales of application.
I also agree with the notion.
Well, another I think, important and
pragmatic advance is something that Bert
mentioned, which is democratization of
this technology.
I think Ralph also hinted at this is the
time you start using this for the common
good.
So.
I think things like RX infer and PMDP.
And I didn't know about the Gaia project,
but it sounds as though there's been
great advances there as well.
So this kind of democratization, I think,
is really important, this sort of
socialization where everybody can play
and start to sort of not talk past each
other.
I think that's a very important advance.
Curt: And did you say the word scale
invariance or scale independence?
Karl: I said scale invariant.
I actually said scale free, and I shouldn'
't have done that.
I said scale free.
So the idea that you can apply exactly
the same mechanics and literally, for
example, say, from Bert's perspective,
the same kind of message passing at
different space time scales or at
different levels in a hierarchical model.
.
So I've actually got a question for Bert
in terms of reactive message passing,
because reactive means that you don't
have to prescribe the scheduling, but in
addressing the problems or the issues
that entailed, by having to specify the
scheduling of talking or of message
passing, you're bound to deal with time.
And in a scale invariant context, or
nested with nested scales, for example,
you have to deal with the separation of
temporal scales.
So I think there's going to be a very
important generic question, which
technically Bert will have been thinking
about furiously for the past few years,
but I think implicitly, we're all going
to have to be addressing soon, which is,
how do you put the timing of your
messages when you make a move or when you
listen to a patient, or when you actually
pass a message on a Factograph?
How are we going to be able to put the
separation of timescales into the
architecture in a way that speaks to this
scale
invariance. The Gear project, for example,
, how do you integrate live feed from
traffic flow sensors with fluctuations in
the climate?
This kind of data comes at very, very
different temporal scales and yet has to
be assimilated and modeled in a way that
also, I think, has to know due courtesy
to that separation of temporal scales.
Curt: Bert, could you please recapitulate
the question for the audience and then
begin to answer it?
Bert: Okay, yeah.
The issue is active instance agents are
nested agents, and the higher levels
supposed to operate on a larger temporal
scale, but they are also working at a
lower resolution.
If you look far ahead, you don't care as
much about precision, not at a centimeter
level.
When I go around a roundabout, I don't
care at the centimeter where I land, but
for the next few milliseconds, I do care
because it may mean the difference
between getting in the ditch or not.
So the higher level, I want to look very
deep ahead, but I don't want to send
every millisecond a message to go to look,
, let's say, a minute ahead.
So I need to space it out a lot, but then
I may miss things.
So preferably you would just send
inaccurate messages.
But that only works if you actually have
a method to also, let's say, use less
computational power to compute a less
accurate message.
And we're not good at that yet.
What we are thinking about is there's a
new field or a new field, but there's a
field called probabilistic numerics where.
... We are used in math to just compute
everything very precisely or as precise
as possible and do not care about how
much computation we spend on it.
So in probabilistic numerics, I hope we
can leverage this for message
computations.
I would like to spend, let's say,
proportionally less computational power
on the accuracy of a message.
One way possibly would be to consider a
message a latent variable that has
uncertainty by itself.
But I don't have a totally clear answer
for Karl because we haven't solved that
either.
But there is a problem in, let's say,
what we do on... Our computers were so
completely different from computers, let'
's say, from the from the from the brain,
that, yeah, we are spending we're
spending just too many computations on
messages that in the end are very
inaccurate.
And that's a problem in what we do on our
computers currently.
Yeah.
So I don't know how we go what you want
to do with this on the higher level.
If you want to look maybe ten times
farther ahead and spend about the same
amount of computation on the lower level,
that's sort of our goal.
But we don't have an answer for that
either at the moment.
Curt: And, Anna, so please feel free to
comment on or ask a question to anyone.
Anna: I don't I don't have anything to
contribute, unfortunately, to how
computers work.
But I can tell you that this idea of
temporal scales is something that we face
often in our work with patients.
For example, addicted patients are very
focused on short term rewards and, in
fact, their ability to control how they
feel in the moment, that is partially
what drives the addiction.
So when I try to adopt Ural's language of
minimizing surprise or minimizing free
entropy, that's one of the things that
people are trying to do on a short term
time scale when they become addicted.
So I have a young woman who's addicted to
nitrous oxide, which has a very fast
onset of intoxication over the order of
seconds and a very fast offset, and she
says that that's exactly what she likes
about it, because she's controlling it
second by second.
So when we work with patients to get them
out of that short temporal horizon, we
actually rely more and more on action and
having them change something in their
lives, namely abstain from their drug of
choice for long
enough to kind of completely reset their
brains and to allow them to see this
longer temporal. Because when they're
chasing this short control, they're
actually not able to see themselves in
the longer narrative arc of their lives.
So that's what comes to mind for me.
I don't think it's going to be helpful to
people who are trying to build computers,
but that's the kinds of interventions
that I make with humans.
Curt: I have a question about that.
So you mentioned control in the short
term, and you've also mentioned that you
study the positive effects of having a
higher power in your life or surrender.
Okay.
I kind of gave the punchline away by
saying surrendering to the higher power.
Where I was going was, okay -
What's the association between seeing
yourself in the largest time frame and a
higher power?
And then also is there something that is
akin to giving up control when you look
farther and farther into the future?
Anna: Yeah! Such a great - yeah, that's
at the heart of what I'm very interested
in, because it's a real paradox, right?
It's this kind of locus of control within
ourselves that really, in modern culture,
we think is a great thing.
But when that's taken to an extreme and
one example of that is addictive
behaviors,
it's very bad for people and for
communities.
And so what can pull people out of that
is this kind of surrender to a higher
power, giving up that locus of control,
locating that locus of control outside
themselves, not necessarily like in a
theistic sense. One of the things that
they talk about in Alcoholics Anonymous,
for example, is you don't have to believe
in God.
It's just not you.
You're not driving it.
And so I would be very curious, from the
perspective of your-all's [?]
understanding of active inference and the
free energy principle and how the brain
works, why is it that sort of embracing
our inability to control what happens in
our lives can actually be the very source
of healing, especially embedded in this
really kind of over controlled,
I would even go so far as to say
endemically narcissistic culture.
I'm really curious.
I don't want to take the conversation in
a direction...
Curt: Please! That's a fantastic question.
.
So if anyone has a comment on that,
please.
Rafael: I have some thoughts, and I think
this applies both at the personal level
and at the global level.
And I think it has to do with my quote
from earlier by Edward Fulbrook that if
you're falling from a plane, yes, maybe
an altimeter and some instruments might
be useful, but what you really need is a
parachute.
Right?
So we have this presupposition that
whatever framing we have operating in our
day to day is going to be, okay:
This is the right framing.
And it tends to be this rational,
scientific framing of very linear cause
and consequence for most stuff.
And it turns out that even if you inspect
our day to day behavior, bigger, more
complicated models are not necessarily
better, which is where we get the success
of heuristics under bounded computation,
bounded rationality.
And if you scale it up to 8 billion
humans interacted in resource constrained
planet, a world of possibilities, but
also of challenges,
then we have to drastically lower
Guillaume: our
Rafael: bar for, yes, how much macro we
have.
But also even where does information
gathering reach diminishing returns?
Where does modeling reach diminishing
returns?
There's a whole literature in the
business world about the expected value
of information, how much you should
actually invest.
Also in science is also known as optimal
experiment design, where basically
acknowledging that you have limited
budget in terms of how much you can act
and how much you can probe and how much
time you can spend thinking about stuff.
And I think what we're doing when we feel
like, burned out or exhausted from
overthinking, we're innately feeling that,
, okay, we've gone too high and we need
to give ourselves a vacation, give
ourselves some free time here.
I think that doing this principle in a
principled way, we're just not just like,
taking the heuristics and the signals
that we inherit from evolution, but
actually being able to figure out
collaboratively and with some rigor.
Okay, we don't need to know exactly how
many degrees the world is going to warm
by 2000 and 2100.
In order to know that maybe it's a good
idea to start doing something about the
amount of carbon in the atmosphere or
whatever.
Right?
And so I think this leads to this idea of
a real knowledge economy and of things
like abstraction as a service.
How can you actually build in these kind
of sophisticated, sophisticated
translation layers that take some of this
burden from ourselves as individuals and
even as organizations, right?
And just put it out in the world as value
added services, which is what they are.
Curt: And Guillaume, if you have any
statements or questions or retorts, then
please feel free.
Guillaume: Yeah, thanks.
Now, I was still also thinking about the
recent breakthrough post 2020 in Action
France.
To me, there were theoretical progress
that were very interesting.
We heard already about the formalism
maturity at the mathematical level
between multiscale and scale free aspects.
.
I really liked also the development of a
more multi agent perspective of active
insurance.
It's very interesting, especially like,
for instance, seeing multi agent systems.
.
We just heard about even society as a
wall, like as many as one system or many
as many subsystems, and how we can use
maybe those formalisms to also deal with
policy making.
That's very interesting venue and the
emergence of norms, culture and ideas
also.
Because one thing that I'm still
struggling with in the case of active
insurance models is like how to get
outside the checkerboard.
You can put a lot in the model, a priory,
and how you make the model, creating new
stuff that is not becked inside.
At the first and on that one very
interesting breakthrough was the
application of active inference to
morphogenesis.
I really like the work that has been done
on that and on the technical aspects.
I think the two main focus that I love
are all the deep active inference and how
to scale up active inference because it's
a strong limitation for the adoption of
the formalism if it's not scaled enough
compared to other framework like deep
learning and then the link with empirical
data.
I really like, for instance, the work of
Ryan Smith and how to connect with
electrophysiology and clinical data.
And I think it's also something very
important to anchor the theory in the
real world and have falsifiability and
empirical validation of those models.
Curt: And what are some of the
applications of active inference to.
Guillaume: So?
Well, I'm not the expert here.
Karl would be the best to answer that.
But I was referring to the work with
Michael Levin and how a model can help to
create a sort of embryogenesis.
So maybe, Karl, you can explain better
than me, please.
Karl: I don't have a reputation for
explaining things very clearly, but yeah,
that's absolutely right.
It was just at work with Michael Evan and
colleagues showing that you can get quite
expressive and bimimetic pattern
formation and movement of different cells
into an organization often described in
terms of morphogenesis simply by
communicating your beliefs.
So I'm coming back to this sort of cross
cutting theme of communication.
So if you just broadcast your beliefs and
you're a little cell and there are a
little ensemble of cells, and they all
have the shared generative model that
includes if I was in this position, I
would sense that.
Now, they all have exactly the same
generative model, the same predictions,
the same expectations, and they're all
broadcasting their beliefs about where
they are.
And the free energy minimizing solution
is just when they're all in a place such
that they receive signals that they would
expect to receive when they're in this
place.
And of course, if that is the same for
everybody, there's only one arrangement
where each cell finds its place.
So basically, knowing your place is an
emergent property of making the world
mutually predictable through, yeah, a
deflationary account of morphogenesis.
But Gim, I thought one of your units is
precision psychiatry.
So I thought you're going to talk about
precision, so I'm going to do a Guillem.
Now, he talked about morphogenesis, I'm
going to talk about precision.
Now.
I think that's a really nice way just to
pick up on themes which everybody's just
mentioned, in particular the pathology of
precision.
And by precision you can read precision
in the sense that Bert was talking about
in terms of do you use an unsigned
integer or a double?
How much can I coarse grain to my numeric
representation?
Or you can use it in terms of coarse
grading in the sense of the
renormalization group chunking things in
hours or years as opposed to milliseconds
and minutes.
Or you can look at it in terms of a
statistician describing the reliability
or the inverse variance of a signal.
And of course we have to estimate that
when I say we I mean your agents and
statisticians and act accordingly.
And certainly in the work of Ryan Smith
on addiction, much of the sort of
mathematical explanation for these
addictive locked in OCD like phenomena
rests upon a failure to get that course
grading that precision estimation right.
The reason I wonder whether it be just
worthwhile revisiting addiction and
psychopathology or certainly pathology of
behavior from the point of view of
getting precision wrong and certainly
assigning too much precision to low level
processing, which is what Bert wants to
avoid doing.
It just strikes me that that kind of
story also has mileage in terms of why we
are in a state of paralysis when it comes
to climate change because I also noticed,
Guillermo, that you talked about climate
action.
I've never heard that before, but that
seems to me to be the important thing.
Why isn't there any climate, Anna?
You know, it'll be like you going to the
clinic and finding someone with Parkinson'
's disease.
Why isn't this person moving?
And interestingly, the computational
explanation for Parkinson's disease is
assigning too much precision to the
evidence that you're not moving before
you move.
So if you can't ignore the fact that
nothing is changing, all your prior
beliefs, your predictions that I am going
to stand up or going to initiate walking,
don't get a looking because they are
immediately cancelled because you've
assigned too much precision to the lower
level processing.
And I'm just wondering whether that kind
of pathology is exactly what Ralph is
trying to reverse by having models at
hand, recommendations at hand that
provide a more coarse grained view of
things, a deeper view.
Curt: Anna, would you like to comment
on?
Anna: I love this idea of the pathology
of precision because I think it manifests
in so many different ways not just among
my patient population but I think it's
almost like a cultural sickness, in a way.
.
The ways in which we seem, like obsessed
with certain types of data and we're
missing the big picture.
So I'm going to think more about that.
I'm going to read more about it.
I really appreciate the discussion.
It's interesting for me and Adam when.
Curt: You'Re referring to the pathology
of precision, do you mean so in a more
conscious sense that we're over
evaluating something that we don't need
to?
Whereas, Karl, you're referring to it in
an unconscious sense like the brain is
putting too much precision on something
because in Parkinson's it's not like you
consciously are putting precision in a
place.
Anna: Well, I think you could look at it
sort of like in both cases.
When I think about addiction, people aren'
't doing it consciously.
It's that they really do see this as
adaptive and healthy and also even on
some level that they can't do otherwise.
And they're not able to see the true
impact of their drug use on their lives.
They're genuinely not able to see the
negative consequences.
And that's what contributes to getting
caught in that vortex.
But I mean, you could also see it as part
of what's happened culturally.
Like, for example, the whole wellness
industrial complex, the way that we now
count ourselves through all these
different devices.
And if we could just count our breathing
and count our heart rate and take
supplements, then we would somehow reach
some levitating state of precise wellness.
.
I don't know, this is all kind of new
ideas for me.
Curt: That's interesting.
So you believe that we can be inundated
with health data and that's detrimental
to us?
Anna: Oh, absolutely.
I see that all the time.
Curt: So for me, I used to have maybe I'
'll take this out of the well, this is
going out live.
Okay, let me figure out how to say this
diplomatically.
I used to have a device that would
measure my heart rate, let's say that and
my sleep.
And instead of improving my sleep, it led
to me becoming obsessed with it and then
noticing, oh, I didn't sleep well.
I must not be feeling good today as well
because apparently there's a high
connection between how your sleep quality
and.
Anna: How well you plus added to that the
other layer that I should be able to
control it.
Right.
So with all of this data and information,
I should be able to, I don't know, reduce
free entropy or whatever, reduce surprise,
, as you guys talk about.
And I think that's obviously that only
goes so far and then can actually
contribute to our misery because why aren'
't we all levitating like the Buddha or
whatever when we have all these tools and
we can pay attention to all this data?
Curt: I see this also with people who
have productivity tools.
Not only that, but mechanical keyboards.
Let's say the reason why I don't have a
mechanical keyboard, even though I think
I'd love it, is because I know that why
the heck do I care about the clicking
sound of a keyboard?
But if I got one, then I'd be like, well,
what's the difference between clicking
sound A versus clicking sound B versus
clicking sound C?
And I'd become obsessed with the
trappings of productivity that is
sharpening, so called sharpening the axe
rather than cutting down the tree.
There's this phrase that is apocryphal.
And it said it's attributed to, I think,
Lincoln, which is that he'd spend 80% of
his time or half the time sharpening the
knife than cutting the tree.
And then this is just echoed in
productivity circles, but it can't be the
case.
Why would you spend so much time
sharpening your axe?
Like, look at anyone who cuts down a tree
with an axe.
Most of the time they're not doing that
anyhow.
So if anyone has any comments on what was
just said, please can I.
Bert: Just talk what I find exciting in
my field about access?
Sure, yes, I read it's a long time ago,
but there was a paper and it's about that
it says, well, active inference is not
really a scientific loop because it's
biased.
And I read that, and the sound of the
paper was kind of so it's not good.
But I think active inference is maybe not
a science loop.
It's an engineering loop because there's
bias, and we need bias in engineering.
We need to make stuff.
We need to build stuff.
We need to have a bias.
So it's an engineering design cycle.
I see that everywhere around me.
And active inference could be a complete
breakthrough in in engineering.
Right.
The fields around me are signal
processing.
I am myself in a signal processing
department or group, and everybody builds
algorithms.
For us.
In active inference agents, it's
inference over states.
Then the floor below me, they build
control systems.
Well, it's inference over actions.
Then other people are working on machine
learning.
It's inference over parameters.
Active inference could be and you like
this, Curt.
It's a very deflationary view on
engineering, because everything is just
inference.
And so rather than building algorithms
everywhere, if we become really good at
implementing minimization, we will be
able to build a great engineering design
cycles, and we'll be engineering better
machines for medical procedures or for
other things that are important.
So it has a tremendous application
potential in engineering.
In engineering, and I think in many
fields, people have sort of drifted in
different directions.
Control theorists have.
I mean, they do almost the same thing as
signal processing people, but they speak
a different language.
Karl: Now.
Bert: Signal processing people, it's a
completely different group for the
machine learning people, but it's all
information processing, and this field
can bring it together.
But the thing is that in order to make it
successful in engineering, we need to
build an application that impresses.
Right?
It's not like a TicTacToe thing.
It really needs to impress people, needs
to be better than some other control
systems.
But once we do that, I think there is
tremendous application potential because
there haven't been enormous breakthroughs
in signal processing and control.
The last big breakthrough, I think, was
Kalmont filtering, and this was 1960s.
It's kind of funny that the essence of
what we do in active influence is also
carbon filtering.
I think there's tremendous opportunities
for what we do here for engineering.
That's why it's exciting to me.
Curt: Anna, do you mind expanding on what
you said about acting?
And therapists should be helping their
patients with that.
Anna: Oh, sure.
Just so.
I mean, one of my critiques of mental
health treatment today is that there's
not enough encouragement of patients to
actually go and act differently in the
world as a way of gathering data.
Instead, it often ends up being kind of
this world building between therapists
and patients, not necessarily ultimately
adaptive in the world.
So I was really just kind of responding
to what Raft was saying, that we need to
act in the world.
I think that's more true now in modern
rich nations than ever before because we
are so incredibly sedentary and
interacting.
Of course we're interacting with a
virtual world, and that's good and bad.
But I think we need to be actually acting
in the world.
Curt: And so there's different forms of
therapy.
As you know, there's talk therapy, and
then there's also cognitive behavioral
therapy or psychotherapy and sort of talk
therapy.
But cognitive behavioral therapy, as far
as I understand, focuses on the actions.
Is that incorrect?
It also focuses on model buildings.
Anna: On the cognition, again, treating
addiction.
You're not going to really get that far
with cognitive behavioral therapy or
anything that's focused on just emotions
and cognitions.
People have to go out and actually try
stop using their stopping their substance
or their addictive behaviors and gather
data from that experience and then come
back and process it.
Curt: So, Anna, in your field and this
question will go to everyone, but in your
field and what you study, where is the
largest gap that you would like to see
closed?
Anna: Well, I mean, we're facing a huge
mental health crisis now.
We have more and more young people coming
in with depression, anxiety, suicidality,
addictions of all sorts.
And these are not necessarily people who
are struggling by virtue of trauma or
socioeconomic disparity.
These are people who have really
privileged lives in many instances.
So it's really a puzzle what is going on
for people.
And I think a big part of it is the fact
that people are not having embodied
experiences.
They're not having experiences in the
world.
And also the experiences that they are
having are these kinds of very quick
fixes and fast pleasures.
Curt: Are you noticing?
Anna: I think the co created sort of
models through healthier communication
that allow people to feel part of a
community and also to have truthful co
created narratives.
Trying to use the language here, I think
that's really important.
So, for example, one of the things Bert
mentioned, what he's excited about?
One of the things I'm excited about in
the field of addiction medicine is mutual
support and the proliferation of things
like Alcoholics Anonymous, but also other
mutual help groups, a lot of them
existing now online.
And the way that people are together
creating healthier narratives and acted
together to counteract a lot of the
unhealthy narratives that I think are
driving a lot of decision making today.
Curt: I wanted to know, is there a
correlation between the rise in mental
health or, sorry, mental illness or
mental health issues, whatever we want to
call it, and a certain trait of people?
Is it affecting the population the same?
So the whole population is raised 20% in
terms of how many mental health issues
they have per year?
Or is it affecting people who deal with
abstractions more and more?
So, for instance, we're talking over zoom
and some people study abstractions just
like us.
And then there are some people whose work
it is to do something physical like
running or swim?
Is it affecting everyone equally or are
you noticing that there's some broad
trend?
Anna: Well, the broad trends that are out
there are just correlational, but the
more time that people spend in the
virtual world, the more likely they are
to suffer from depression, anxiety and
other mental health problems.
People haven't really been able to narrow
that down to specific content, but they
have been able to save just the sheer
amount of time that spending that you're
spending online increases your risk for
certain poor mental health outcomes.
Curt: Okay.
Now, Karl well, again, if anyone has any
comments or questions, please just raise
your physical hand.
I can see raph ralph Rafael sorry.
Rafael: I was just going to say that I
think another notable trend is, and I
just saw somebody say this on YouTube
just yesterday, that young people are
disproportionately affected by things
like climate grief because they're the
ones that are going to be alive to deal
with it.
And I think that applies more generally
that Peter Sanghi already like 30 years
or something ago, wrote about the
Inescapable Network of neutrality, the
reality that what we do affects each
other.
Right?
And we took advantage of this huge
resource buffer that's called the
biosphere.
Curt: And.
Rafael: Earth to pretend that it didn't
for quite a long time and got a lot of
mileage out of it.
But now we're at a point where there's a
whole generation of people that are
coming to grips with the fact that I'm
going to stop myself from saying a square
word, but oh my God, we actually need to
change everything about everything that
we do and we need to do it fast.
By the way.
It's not just what we do out there, it's
also what we do inside, how we get ready
for how to show up for life internally.
Karl: Right?
Rafael: So no wonder that it has that
impact.
Like myself, I've dealt with anxiety and
a lot of other things.
We've had conversations about what are we
doing bringing a daughter into this world
and all these kinds of things.
And I think it's only natural that it's
coming to a head in this way right now.
Curt: Naom you have your hand up and I
can't see yes.
Guillaume: Yeah, it's connect with what
has just been so and your initial
question about the gaps that needs to be
closed, I think like a scale free model
of health and mental health particularly
would be great.
We are in silos, in biomedical research
and the fact that someone is having
depression can come from interacting
genes as much as interacting people and
also is related to climate change and so
on.
So how we can have a new health systems
that doesn't deal with those silos and
integrate those different scales, to me
it's like really a big challenge, but a
challenge that current models and work
that we can see going that direction.
And I'm very enthusiastic.
Bert: About that?
Curt: Bert.
Bert: Yeah.
In my field in engineering, active
inference is not understood because
almost all papers are written by
neuroscientists and they're hard to read.
.
So I was really happy to hear today that.
And I think it's Sanjeev Namjoshi who is
writing an engineering book on active
inference.
So I think that will really help.
That, together with the availability of
good toolboxes for implementing active
inference, should make a lot of engineers
much more enthusiastic about active
inference because it's not something that
is not understood at the moment in
engineering circles.
So I hope that the book will be good.
I'm enthusiastic about that.
Curt: And Karl, where are some gaps in
your research that you'd like to see?
Karl: More than gaps?
There's a whole empty space out there yet
to be explored.
But in terms of what seems to be emerging
from the session and specifically the
past few answers, it does seem to be
important to have this very generic just
to take Bert's sort of line that this is
just one deflationary simple and probably
the right way to understand stuff and to
make recommendations or to describe
people's actions, possibly to themselves
in a therapeutic context.
And as such, it should be push button
technology and it should be democratized
and socialized.
And I think that's the challenge,
practically.
And 1 may ask, why would you want to do
that?
For me, there are two clear imperatives.
One is very abstract, and it's not really
within my comfort zone, and the other one
is in my comfort zone.
But the one that's outside my comfort
zone is this notion of interactivity and
hyperconnectivity and the metacrisis that
we heard about.
And Aguim also referred to this in terms
of what he was trying to distinguish
between a Californian notion of
optimality and another kind, another way
forward.
And to me, it's a stark contrast with
growth is good versus sustainability.
And of course, the math of the free
energy principle is just about
sustainability.
It's just a description of the physics of
systems, random, dynamical systems that
self organize to some non equilibrium
steady state.
That is what we are.
So for me, there's something deeply, if
you like, apt about the free energy
principle and its chronologies, such as
active inference in application to
ecosystems and lived ecosystems and
realized ecosystems.
So if those basic principles can be
brought back into globalization, into the
market, into fintech, into social media,
into politics, into climate action, I
think that would be a good thing.
I'm just mindful this struck me in a
number of the presentations today.
You remember before, Bert was saying, if
you look at the brain, which is a really
lovely example of a self organizing
system to a non equilibrium steady state,
then it's empty.
And what did he mean by that?
What he didn't mean you were empty headed.
.
What he meant was it's incredibly
sparsely connected.
Now, that tells you immediately that a
pathology of connectivity is
hyperconnectivity overconnectivity, which
immediately, well, it made me very alert
to the presentation of the metacrisis.
That one of the first three things that
was underwrote the metacrisis or the
current crisis we're tending with is a
destruction of that sparse, delicate
connectivity that defines thingness and
defines ensembles of things technically
in terms of Markov blankets.
So if we want a world in which lots of
different things can coexist in some kind
of generalized synchrony in a sustainable
way, you need fast connectivity.
And the pathology, the thing that will
destroy that, is overconnectivity.
So it seems to be very important that we
get that into play in terms of machine
learning, artificial intelligence,
politics, fintech, climate change.
And the only way it's going to get there
is epistemically by equipping people to
actually build their own little models
and ask their own questions.
You can't tell people this they've got to
learn they've got to learn it for
themselves.
Just very quickly, I'm sure we've only
got a couple of minutes left.
The other agenda, which I'm more familiar
with is exactly Anna's and Guillaume's
agenda, which is making this work in the
context of neurology and psychiatry.
So if you can democratize and socialize
this way of describing things so that
people can now build models of their
particular patient in the other use of
precision psychiatry, I suspect that
Guillum's unit was called after.
So it's a personalized medicine that is
really personalized in the sense that you
actually have your digital twin of your
behavior.
And then you've got that.
You optimize your digital twin to become
a model of your patient, and then you can
start to do experiments on that model,
behavioral interventions, or even share
that model very much in the spirit of CBT
with the patient and say, look, this is
you.
This is what would happen if you went out
and did this.
And this is what would happen if you went
out and did that.
To my mind.
And indeed, that was the initial
motivation for much of this work, was
actually to build observation models of
psychiatric conditions, to work out both
the pharmacological and physiological
basis and the disruption of the pathology
of precision and message.
Passing on the factographs that are our
brain even though they are very empty on
the one hand, but also get that behavior,
that key thing that Anna was talking
about the active engagement with the
lived world into that model and hence
active inference.
And just to conclude that that activity,
that sort of physical engagement, that
embodiment, that sort of for ease and
everything else, I think it's really
coming to a head now in terms of people
after, the large language model, after
the Chat GPT moment, the bounce back has
been what's missing?
What's not there?
And of course, what is not there is
agency and embodied engagement with the
world.
And that's why I think there's still a
lot of work to be done in bringing
artificial intelligence read as active
inference in a way that matters to people
who people who can make a difference,
which is basically everybody, but
specifically politicians and doctors and
engineers and the like.
Curt: So you all now have 30 seconds to
60 seconds to speak directly to the
audience.
What is the message that you what closing
message do you have?
You're speaking directly to someone who's
listening.
They're a curious person.
They're interested in active inference.
They also want to lead better lives,
hopefully, and do something propitious.
So what message do you have for them?
Anna, we'll start with you.
Anna: Gosh.
I'm just going to say what pops into my
mind right now is that one of the things
I have learned from my patients who are
trying to get into recovery from severe
addictions is something that they call
the set aside prayer where they set aside
all of the notions that they have about
how the world works and try to be
completely open and receptive to
information coming into their minds.
And I think that's just a wonderful frame
or concept for all of us living in the
world to periodically just take a moment
and take these models and just say
everything I think I know about the world,
, I'm going to temporarily suspend it,
and I'm just going to be open.
And when that happens, we can be present
and learn in a way that it's not possible
when we're just trying to reinforce our
models.
Curt: Great.
Fantastic.
And Bert.
And then we'll go.
Karl.
And then Raph and then Guillaume.
Bert: Well, I just enjoyed today very
much.
I thought there was a lot of material,
both for people from, let's say,
psychology, neuroscience, but also for
engineers.
So if you haven't watched some of the
talks, go look through the schedule,
because some of the talks were really
good, I think.
So I really enjoyed that.
And then, yeah, what should I tell
people?
Go work out.
Do a lot of sports.
It's good for you.
Karl: Yeah.
Sorry, I was going to make a joke, but I
can't because it wouldn't be.
So I'm going to use my 30 seconds just to
thank Daniel and his team for this.
If you want something to do, you should
go and watch the live streams and get
involved with this ecosystem.
I hadn't seen that paper being presented
before, but I was really impressed with
the Active Institute and its openness and
its welcoming attitude and vision, like
the Smithsonian.
So if you want to pursue these ideas, get
involved.
And if you haven't got time, just make
sure you attend next year's Active
Inference Institute celebration.
But thank you, Daniel.
Curt: Rafael yeah.
Rafael: So I'll second what Karl said and
follow on with it's.
An invitation not just to participate in
the Active Defense Institute, but also
the invitation to participate in building
this Gaia tractor, this new way of doing
things that acknowledges the value of
growth, and also the value of
sustainability, joins it all together in
this thing called regeneration.
And it really is a collective effort.
It's a collective learning effort.
And this also, by the way, also applies
to the panelists as well.
I think.
Obviously, what Bert and Karl are doing,
it has immediate things that have to do
with what we're after.
But one of the main things that we keep
discussing is also like this the inter
subjectivity and the importance of being
able to operate well as humans together.
And that connects directly to cognitive
science in psychiatry.
And so everybody that wants to be engaged
and be a part of building a better world
should be thinking about what am I doing
as an individual or as employee of
organization or as a researcher or as a
leader or as a family member, what am I
doing?
How does it contribute to this new non
equilibrium set of state?
So, yeah, that's kind of it.
I probably blew through the 60 seconds,
but here it is.
Curt: And Guillaume,
Guillaume: Well, I would thanks also, all
of you for the discussion and the
organizer for what they are doing.
Indeed, the work of the Active Inference
Institute is very laudable and
interesting from an open science
perspective.
They are really embodying
that. So big kudos to them.
And well, the Frieze was saying to do
sport is good for you.
I'm not very good at sports, but some say
that science is a team sport.
So at least have a good team perspective
when doing science.
And being kind to each other would be the
best advice to everyone.
Curt: Well, thank you.
Daniel: You get yours too.
Somebody else has to come in from outside
the Markov blanket, though.
Curt: Well, I wanted to just thank you,
Daniel.
Thank you, Daniel.
And Rafael and also Karl and Anna and
Bert and Guillaume.
This was tremendous amount of fun.
And well, I hope I get to speak to you
all individually.
And as usual, I have way more questions
than we were able to get to.
Thank you all.
Rafael: Thanks.
Thank you.
Daniel: Thanks everyone.
Farewell to the panelists.
Karl: You're all.
Daniel: Welcome back anytime.
Thanks everybody, for watching.
Be watching.
Right now we're about to head over to the
discord and hang out and talk a little
more if you want to, and then stay
involved, get involved.
So till next time.
Curt: Bye.