all right
the next session is going to be the
final session of
this symposium
it's been a really
Incredible Journey
and I think this final session is going
to be great as well
so
we have a whole panel here
and
people can use their cameras even though
I'm not if they want to
um
welcome everyone
all just introduce the facilitator Kurt
Jai mungle so Kurt is a a legend in the
active ecosystem and has done incredible
work with a variety of researchers and
curious individuals in the space so we
could think of no one better
to host this conversation
and
bring it all together so Kurt I'll pass
it to you
you'll keep an eye on the live chat
anyone can call it if they need any
supports otherwise thanks everybody for
joining and uh
we don't see you yet Kurt but yeah I it
would it be all right if I left and then
came right back for whatever reason my
camera is not working sounds good sounds
good okay I'll be right back in about 25
seconds
well welcome everyone
um
we will get started in just a second
[Music]
so odd I apologize for that okay well
you can hear my voice at least
yep
just give me a moment let me apologize
boy okay
well
well we'll do what we can okay
so you all can't see me but
that's all right so we have this
All-Star panel here today which to me
means my invitation must have been a
mistake but I'll take it thank you to
the active inference Institute and I'll
go around this virtual Zoom table and
introduce everyone briefly
Carl friston is the welcome from
Principal research fellow and scientific
director at the welcome trust Center for
neuroimaging and professor of Neurology
at University College London he's also
the chief scientist at versus
and a lamp key is chief of the Stanford
addiction medical sorry medicine dual
diagnosis clinic at Stanford University
her popular books include drug dealer MD
and dopamine Nation
Rafael Kaufman is CTO of digital Gaia
and the onboard sorry and is on the
board of directors of the active insta
active inference Institute
Bert DeVries is a professor
at Eindhoven University of Technology
where he directs the bias lab research
team and also works with industry
is an associate professor in
computational Psycho Psychiatry of the
faculty of medicine at the University of
Montreal and the director
of the Precision Psychiatry and social
physiology laboratory in Chu Saint sorry
in the chu Saint Justine Research Center
he's also affiliated with Mila or Mila
which is Quebec's artificial
intelligence Institute and other art
science and Consciousness service
initiatives my name is and I use them I
use my background in mathematical
physics to analyze various theories of
everything that are proposed these
include both a theoretical physics side
of grand unification with gravity and
dualities other schemes as well as
attempting to understand what
constitutes Consciousness you can find
the podcast by typing in theories of
everything onto YouTube or whatever
podcast catcher you have
so my question to everyone the initial
question is what have you been working
on in the past few months and what
excites you about it
we'll start with
Bert you seem to be smiling
and your name sounds like mine
okay so
um all right so my name is and uh yeah I
lead a lab in in an electrical
engineering department
and so our lab is called by slot as you
as you mentioned so we are interested in
Bayesian influence in in general but
more specifically in doing it as fast as
possible that that has lots of
applications outside active inference
also in yeah for Signal processing and
other control systems but definitely of
course also for active inference so have
our work over the past few months but
even over the past few years has been on
developing a toolbox
to support or to get as far as we can go
with trying to do real-time Beijing
inference or real time for energy
minimization and and trying it in
applications
um so that's that's the work that I I
try to lead a team of PhD students who
would do the real work of course I walk
around with a cup of coffee but uh
that's what they've been working on
great and Professor Lemke please
yeah well what I've been working on in
the last
um I don't know a year or so is spending
a lot of time thinking about
how it is that a faith framework in
particular surrendered to a higher power
improves people's lives
and I've been really struggling to come
up with a way of talking about this that
is inclusive thinking about it talking
about it it gets to a kind of core piece
of it that I'm interested in which is
not so much whether or not God exists
and what the proof is or not of whether
God exists but really what what is it
that changes in people's lives when they
undergo a spiritual transformation when
they surrender to a higher power
why why do their lives get better when
they do get better
and um I'm really new to the active
inference World Daniel Friedman is the
one who's introduced me to these ideas
I'm really excited about the ways in
which the whole active inference model
might help me at least think about
what's going on there and um so so
that's what I'm that's what I'm working
on it's a little weird but uh that's
what I'm interested in
great professor friston
you're muted
yes that's going to be the title of my
next book Carl you're on mute
a retro from here
possibly the future
um I I generally work on what I'm told
to work on so I'm just been trying to
list what I've been working on
um in the past few months interestingly
um it actually starts with um Daniel
Friedman and his um fascination with um
along with Axel constant for
evolutionary explanations and specimen
in the scale of three issues that we've
been hearing about
um in the prior session and so that's
what I was working on really a
scale-free approach to understanding
temporary nested processes as free
energy minimizing processes as a kind of
active inference and how that would lead
to a variational synthesis of evolution
and then I was told to work on belief
sharing by Mao and colleagues versus
um and um
worked on that in the context of
synthetic language and try to
um
establish a really simple proof of
principle that communication was an
emerging property of any free Ensemble
free energy minimizing system
[Music]
um and the just to Open brackets is to
make the observation it struck me time
and time again uh during the session
today how important communication is
um you know whether we're talking about
birds passing messages or responding to
uh you know you've got a new posterior
or we're talking about the kind of
communication
um that Mal was talking about Well
everybody's been talking about it
doesn't seem to be a really uh and
indeed the guy the guy
um notion of over connectivity and too
much communication or the wrong kind of
communication
um it does strike me that's quite
Central uh to a lot to the both the
theme of the um the workshop
um and
um the specific presentations that we've
heard
um and then uh in the past few weeks
working on stuff I think that Bert would
be
um more interested in which is
um fast and Frugal
um message passing schemes that
um enable the evaluation the expected
free energy not to suffer from uh the
limitations imposed by Deep tree
searches so
um possibly uh Ashwin has spoke about
this earlier on but um you're using
ideas from dynamic programming backwards
induction to try and
um take the pressure off the message
passing to get fast and efficient uh
evaluations of the expected free energy
in sort of um sort of single unit uh
sort of single agent active inference
what have I been doing this week
can't remember no that's what I've been
doing
great Raphael Kaufman please
just a moment
and can everyone else hear
okay
what about now yeah great yeah thanks uh
and it's contagious I think uh I know so
I've also been drinking a lot of coffee
as I've been caring for my now nine
month old daughter
so uh congratulations thank you so aside
from sleep deprivation what I've been
doing is
um uh I told you guys about this in the
in the session earlier today but uh in a
nutshell been working on what we call
the the the guy protocol uh or the guy
Network which is this uh this
um open approach for for building a uh
common uh common engine you can think of
it as a common runtime and uh in a
common uh language for with the building
blocks of of shared decision making
um and um in the context of on the Mad
crisis and getting to getting to a set
of of
building blocks for decision making that
don't kill us all so that's that's kind
of it
and then Raphael how many how much
coffee is a lot of coffee
well it's espresso so I don't think it's
quite comparable to like American coffee
all right
and Guillaume Dumas please
yes sure can you hear me
yes
okay uh so in the context of action
inference uh I have mostly focused on uh
well the two big topic of my lab so uh
Precision Psychiatry and social
physiology so on the Precision
Psychiatry side
presented earlier in this Symposium uh
work on trying to model theory of mind
to it being able to evaluate uh through
digital phenotyping the level of
sophistication of interaction in
patients with neurodevelopmental
disorders
and that connect with also our interest
in the social mind and how we can
connect our understanding of
how we deal with other people but with
also ourselves and so that connect with
other work at the Mila with the Deep
learning architecture with ir order
functioning humans where we're trying to
combine different theories of
Consciousness such as Global artwork
space and attention schema Theory and in
the context of attention schema Theory
there is this kind of recycling of self
and other mechanisms so that's one
big work and on the other side I'm very
interested also in a military agent
systems and so with the Natalie Castle
we're going to join us uh soon we've
been working on creativity and the
emergence of cultural norms in
meditation systems with the idea of
applying that to climate action and also
a new project that is starting here with
the an frf of a big Canadian project on
indigenous knowledge and how we can
think about new narrative around AI
typically a less solipsistic and
realistic way of dealing with AI
so that's the two main field of research
can you explain what you mean by less
solipsistic less solips oh geez Louise
the the Californian view of AI because
uh the narrative is mainly driven by uh
us and California right now tends to
circle around optimization profits I
mean even open AI states that uh AGI is
about optimizing profitable human tasks
they they put like a profitable in their
definitions uh in the case of indigenous
systems of knowledge we are more talking
about Community
sustainability
and the view already only in the
application is less individualistic but
also in the cognitive science point of
view we we have like the the outcore
computationalism that would say the
brain is just like a computer in a very
restrictive sense and so AI like
typically the those Transformers that
are massively used right now are kind of
like bringing that in a very silicon
sense while we are an embodied systems
that are
constituted by our interaction with
others and so like in a way how we can
think about artificial intelligence in
this kind of more co-constitutive way
and through a Developmental and cultural
lens
mm-hmm
okay now speaking of the brand as a
computer we frequently frequently hear
in these circles the brain as a
predictive machine
so where does this the quote-unquote
brain as a predictive machine have its
limits and also is that
to be interpreted as implying conscious
experience is a predictive machine as
well okay and if not why not so
I think Carl you'd be a great person to
start this off and then we'll go around
the table again
yeah I'm just mindful of Mao's
presentation the past half hour
um and a notion of temporal thickness
um and I'm sure that's got a lot to do
with the necessary conditions for the
kind of Consciousness and guessing
you're referring to you know that
freedom from the moment
um and if one reads prediction in its
sort of psychological or pretensive or
pretension
um
nature in terms of being able to predict
what will happen in the future I think
that the um
that's that that's going to be a sort of
uh a key bright line between things that
um do not possess
certain kind of um bentians and things
that do
um and that bright line just rests
basically upon
um well from perspective of active
infants having a generative model that
includes the consequences of your own
actions in the future so just by having
consequences you're now talking about
um the future and the cause the
consequences
um in the future now become random
variables therefore you have to infer
them which leads you directly to the
notion of planning as inference which
means that bright lie is just the
difference between things that plan and
do not plan
um and
um I would guess that that's where you
probably want to start in terms of
foregrounding the role of prediction
um as being
an aspect of self-organization and its
sort of reading under active inference
that characterizes just things from
non-conscious things namely the ability
to plan does that make sense
I have follow-up questions we'll get to
them at some point but for now Anna Do
you have do you have any comments on
that and and Bert as well afterward
um well you know I'm I'm new to this
field so I'm just familiarizing myself
even with the language but I I can
respond to of the question the brain is
a predictive machine in terms of
the work that I do clinically in the
kind of Psychopathology that I see when
I'm working with patients
um you know we I work primarily with
narrative the stories that they tell
about their lives and one of the
recurring themes I've seen through my
work is that when patients tell stories
in which they are perpetually the
victims of other people's actions of the
world they tend to then that tends to be
a predictive model for them so that they
will then go out into the world and
unconsciously create scenarios which
will perpetuate their victimhood and
that part of getting into Wellness is to
stop seeing themselves as entirely the
victim of other people or circumstance
instead begin to appreciate what they
contribute to their life problems so I
guess when I think of the limits of the
brain as a predictive machine I think in
some ways one of the big limits is that
it's a very powerful predictive machine
that actually allows us to subsequently
shape what actually happens to us and or
our perceptions of what happens to us
which then can perpetuate
a false narrative and I I'll just give
one small example from my own life I've
had um you know my conflicts with my
mother and one of my beefs about her is
that she's a very poor communicator and
that whenever I email her I either get a
cryptic response or no response at all
and it drives me crazy and about five
years ago she sent an email asked me
some questions I wrote her back and
responded and it was clear to me
um that that required yet a response
from her which I never got and that then
perpetuated my narrative about her as a
very poor communicator and many other
negative things and then about three
months after I sent that email I found
the email in my draft inbox in my draft
box so I had never actually responded to
there's email I hadn't actually sent the
email and that was for me um just a you
know a personal uh wonderful example of
the ways in which we can our actions can
actually
um
be manipulated to support our models and
perpetuate falsehoods about the world
that we live in
right and I I have a quick question Bert
just for Anna before we get to you so
use the word narrative there how are you
defining the word narrative is it the
same as model is it a sequence of events
like what is the specific definition of
narrative
you know I never really thought about it
in those terms but when I talk about
narrative I'm talking about
um
the stories that people tell about their
lives because that's sort of my data
um and and also about models because
what I've discovered about
self-narrative is it's not just a way to
organize the past it also becomes a road
map for the future that's the language
that I use but I see it Maps very nicely
onto urals a language of modeling the
world
I see Professor DeVries please
um yeah it's it's clear that uh
the ability to predict is is the essence
of intelligent decision making
um yeah I have a different background
right I'm not a psychiatrist so I think
about these things in different really
the thing that that I think about when I
think about prediction is I I would
assume that it brain predicts far ahead
but things get less accurate right if I
predict that I want to go three quarters
around around about I don't care about
the centimeter where my car goes when
I'm around here I just want to get in in
the right lane
um and I would assume that the brain
doesn't take much it takes less
computations if you care about things
less precisely but that's very hard in a
computer we have this is what uh kind of
kills Us in uh in in I think in our
current uh way of implementing active
inference when we want to predict a deep
hat we don't care about the accuracy but
we don't know how to do it much cheaper
when things are less accurate and so
that's still a that's a problem that we
need to be working on
um it might be in
it might be a key to building or to
scaling up active Entrance Agency if we
can actually
compute messages that we want to know
that we don't care about if they are
less precise that we also spend much
less computation on there
thank you now Professor Kaufman
uh I am not a professor but I'll answer
anyway
um can you just call me Rafa uh yeah so
uh there's uh so many really interesting
Avenues here and it's not often that I
get the the the pleasure of discussing
this kind of stuff
with this uh kind of diverse crowd but I
do I mean I've been interested in uh in
these questions uh for for a pretty long
time and I I think what comes to mind is
like how
how active inference has a lens uh for
instance it enables us to to to to
get another sense of what non-dualist
views on Consciousness uh are saying
when they when they uh get us
experientially to to notice the
difference between what we actually
perceive and what
between the different various different
uh uh processes or things that are going
on in our in our head in our tendency to
like want them all together into the
same okay this is this is my this is my
experience that that I'm immersed in
um so noticing being able to to to uh
notice the difference between the the
the the the the process of proceeding
and act and and acting and it's
automated and the narrative where the
various narratives that are going on uh
uh in parallel to my head whether I'm
aware of them or not and uh and our
ability to to to just put kind of
seemingly arbitrary Mana levels on top
of it to to try to make sense of it all
into to force uh for static experience
of having multiple Americans and
multiple framings going on at the same
time makes uh make sense of that
experience in a in a
um in a way that aligns with the
presuppositions about about how things
are so
um I I think that's super interesting
and also I also I like that uh like this
this view of Consciousness as being kind
of uh defined by having a narrative or
an internal model that's about self or
that at least uh it's about self and
that leads us as Carl said to the
blindness influence uh that's actually
like super deflationary in a way that
that people are not uh not used to
thinking about it and uh and so it's an
exciting it's opening the doors all sort
of exciting interdisciplinary
conversations we had on the basis of at
least I feel like better uh less talking
past each other than we've ever had so
I'm excited about that
Aaron how is it that you're using the
word deflationary there Carl I remember
I asked you about that when we had our
podcast together but Raphael a similar
question so you said deflationary view
when we have narratives of self do you
mean it leads us to something that
Consciousness is much more than
sorry much yeah yeah I mean it's uh not
necessarily much less than in the in the
uh subjective sense but it's uh perhaps
much much less than in the in the
scientific sense so uh one example of
like one not saying exactly that but but
maybe something close to what uh Daniel
Bennett calls heterophenology which is
basically the the statement that the the
sum of what one can say scientifically
about Consciousness is is
um is equal to what can be can be uh
what can be studied and uh and modeled
and theorized and communicated and
learned and uh agreed upon on the basis
of objective data about what people
including you but they're also other
people say uh about their experience
which and of course like what can be
measured up neural correlates and
whatever which is not the same as or not
necessarily the same as our experience
so our direct what we think is our
direct experience of being conscious
conscious right so one way to look at it
is that uh uh is that the science of
Consciousness doesn't necessarily have
to put the privacy on on people the
purpose people think they have quality
uh that that we thought and that sense
this deflationary right it's
um yeah you have to explain why people
believe they have quality or not white
people have quality because it's not
it's not necessarily a scientific truth
that people have value right
Professor Dumas
uh yeah so well on the limits of brain
experiment well which we should be
always careful to not move from uh one
uh
map territory fallacy to another one for
sure so we need to be uh Skeptics and
avoid to refi the methods and well the
this world Symposium I'm sure this
metaphor is super useful and and
fruitful but I can see like two main uh
limits or at least things where we
should be careful so uh following what
uh Professor Lemke said like in
Psychiatry I think the the looping
effects and the way people picture
themselves uh can be uh very
unpredictable and so the way uh we think
about the brain as a predictive machine
think prediction for patients would have
different signification of what we mean
by predictive machines in the context of
factory inference and in general also
like uh the I I can see that certain uh
psychologists or anthropologists would
have a big appeal or a sudden for uh
active inference and prenergic
principles but taking the the words uh
as uh directly what they think the word
mean where it needs to be we need to be
careful the way to communicate it and
typically Following also what Professor
debris said about uh predict prediction
as being super important for decision
making I think like uh
we should be careful about the the
weirdness of uh cognitive science and
how it doesn't necessarily expand to uh
non-western educated industrialized
country where maybe the cultural value
is not about optimization of your
decision making or your profit and so
that's the first thing where I think we
should be careful it's more like a
matter of how to communicate the theory
in that case not necessarily a limit of
the theory itself but the the second one
is
that the the equivalence or not
with other Frameworks so like uh
I can see uh we are the Mao uh al-basa
talking about category Theory and I'm
very curious about right now among the
different Frameworks that are out there
how can we Define what is equivalent or
not with actually inference to be able
to to see those limits uh maybe we are
leaving what happened with quantum
mechanics in the in the early uh 20th
century with different interpretation
with different tools to model quantum
mechanics and air with artificial
intelligence and cognitive Neuroscience
we have also all those Frameworks and I
think the limitation would be then to
not take this interpretation as the only
one but uh try to have a crosstalk and a
differential diagnosis of which one is
the best for explaining what
okay now my role is the moderator but I
would like you all to to speak to one
another so I'm going to ask a question
that will serve us well you each will
speak on it but as the other person is
speaking as sorry as the other people
are speaking just think okay is there a
question that I have or is there a
comment that I have so the question is
what are some of the recent advancements
or breakthroughs in your respective
fields that you find particularly
promising
and well recent let's say
2020 until now
so we'll start off with Raphael you're
smiling and you look back to Champion oh
I was thinking what is my field right
because
uh we're very much in the in the
um in the last mile of applying the the
wonderful stuff that y'all come up with
and uh and uh making it uh useful on the
ground but
so I'm I'm extraordinarily excited about
research like what uh what Bert is doing
and uh uh I feel like as uh as you
almost saying we're also starting to see
some some conversions on uh on different
um different ways to get to to the same
uh at least the same shape of answers
and in some cases even to the same
um
the same uh results so one example of
this is uh work that uh
um Chris Chris Fields call and others
have been doing on uh on the the quantum
uh
basically explaining Quantum information
Theory uh and uh and how it relates to
to the free energy principle looking at
the free energy Principle as the as the
classical limit of of quantum
information Theory and I don't pretend
to to understand all of it but as
somebody who has school is coming from a
quantum physics background uh just uh uh
being alive to see this this kind of
conversions happening which as I mean as
as uh as kyom said you know we've been
at this at this business of like both
classical what's what the hell is going
on for over a century now and it's nice
to to be at a time where again we're
we're starting to talk less about each
other
and that's that's from up here
perspective from a practical perspective
I think just uh just finding that we
have all the building blocks to to
uh create
uh fast interpretable
um
um reliable and aligned
um decision making systems which
includes uh AI systems autonomous
systems that have all those
characteristics and that it turns out
that all the things that the
reinforcement learning and uh and the
neural networks people thought were very
hard or impossible are sort of in the
realm of what we can do uh looking at
things from an active inference lens and
vice versa a lot of things that that
that active influence models have
Incorporated so far so it turns out if
you if you toss in a neural network
approximator here
um and uh you know some borrow some
other you know massively parallel
computation techniques uh it also
becomes feasible so it's it's converging
yeah for me it's
what's remarkable is that there's so
many domains of of what we thought was
exclusively human or would be
exclusively human for decades that in
just the past couple years
robots or computers seem to be
just as good if not exceeding us
and I don't know if that's promising or
worrisome but anyhow Carl please if you
don't mind answering the question and
then we'll go Anna then Bert and then
Dumas
well actually just reflecting upon your
um
one of your observations I think it's
very difficult to identify one thing uh
you know in a sense
um
what is impressive is the diversity of
advances and applications
um and I just say that because that's
what I was thinking you know over the
past six hours is listening to your
amazing presentation after the
presentation and just you're noting how
diverse yeah and yet there's this Common
Thread this common commitment uh
basically say to your curiosity and and
using the the tools that naturalize that
kind of sense making curious behavior
and communication
um that inherit from sort of either
maths or category Theory or as rough
notes now Quantum information Theory but
just to pick up on a couple of things
which arrive into this conversation so
they work with Chris Fields
um you know it sounds um lovely and
exciting to bring quantum mechanics into
um active inference but that's not the
move that I think Chris has um really
wanting to Champion the move I think is
something that we've all been addressing
in one way or another which is
um leveraging the scale-free aspects of
these this principled
approach to
self-organization and hopefully
self-organization to some kind of
generalized synchrony
um so that that's where the quantum
information Theory gets into the game it
is scale free and indeed he will go
further and say it's completely
background for free and everything is
constructed it's just uh so I think that
that's a lovely move
um because once you've gone skill free
you then start to ask deep questions
about how you couple one scale to
another scale and in a sense ecosystems
is just that how do the your the
denizens of an ecosystem
um How is does it constitute how is it
co-constructed what is the structure of
it these are all questions about how one
scale links to another skill so I think
there have been lots of advances in that
direction in many many different fronts
um and you can read that either in terms
of coupling different sort of spatial or
um yeah spatial scales but probably more
importantly sort of temporal scales and
you see that yeah wherever you look
um you'll just come back to what do you
mean by a narrative it is exactly I
think Anna says it it it's just a a plan
is this a story but notice the story has
a temporal aspect to it you know I have
narratives about being a good person
being a good father being a good
scientist I also have narratives about
you know I want my cup of coffee or I
have to go look after the if I don't but
Ralph has to go look after the child
um so yeah we've all got narratives at
very very different time scales and if
you're
um you know I just came back to Bert's
example of you know I'm an autonomous
vehicle and I'm sentient and we're five
years into the future and I have to
drive around the roundabout you know
what Temple scale and what kind of
Temple course cleaning to define the
narrative in narratives would be
appropriate for that kind of situation
um and um
the you know the the ensuing planning so
um so to my uh so a short answer to your
question I think there have been many
many advances
um they have um I think what they've had
in common is basically transcending
either different domains but in
particular different scales of
application I also agree um with the
notion well another I think important
and pragmatic Advance
um is something that Bert mentioned
which is democratization of this
technology and I think Ralph also into
that you know this is the time you start
using this for the for the common good
um
so I think you know things like um RX
infer and pi mdp and I didn't know about
the the Gaia project uh but it sounds as
though there's been great advances there
as well so this kind of democratization
I think is really important this sort of
socialization everybody can play and
start to sort of um not to talk past
each other I think that that's a that's
a very important uh a very important
advance
and did you say the word scale and
variance or scale Independence
I say scaling variant
um I actually said scale free and I
shouldn't have done that
um I meant
um I I said scale uh scale free so the
the idea that you can apply exactly the
same mechanics and literally for example
say from birth perspective the same kind
of message passing at different space
time scales or
um at different levels in a hierarchical
model so I've actually got a question
for bird
um in terms of reactive message passing
because
reactive means that you don't have to
um prescribe the scheduling but you in
in addressing the problems or the issues
that are entailed by
um having to specify the scheduling of
talking or of message passing
um you your
um you're bound to deal with time and in
a scale invariant context or nested with
nested scales for example you have to
deal with the temp uh the separation of
temporal scales so I I think there's
going to be a very important generic
question which technically but will have
been thinking about furiously for the
past few years and I think implicitly
we're all going to have to be addressing
soon which is the um how do you put that
the timing of your messages when you
make a move or when you listen to a
patient or
um
when you actually pass a message in on a
photograph
um how does how are you gonna how are we
going to be able to put the separation
of time scales
into the architecture in a way that
speaks to this this scale invariance you
know the gear project for example how do
you integrate
um live feed from traffic flow
um sensors with fluctuations in the
climate you know these kinds of this
kind of data comes a very very different
uh Temple scales and yet has to be
assimilated and modeled
um you know
in a way that is also I think has to pay
take you know due courtesy to that
separation of temporal scales
Bert could you please recapitulate the
question for the audience and then begin
to answer it
okay
um
yeah the issue is if you if I mean
active for instance agents are nested
agents and the higher levels
supposed to operate on a larger temporal
scale
but they should they're also working at
a lower resolution right if you if you
look far ahead you don't care as much
about Precision not that the centimeter
level when I go around to around about I
don't care the centimeter where I land
but if I'm but for the next few
milliseconds I do care about because it
may mean the difference between getting
in the ditch or not
so
um I don't want to send so the higher
level I want to look very deep ahead but
I don't want to send every millisecond
message to go to to look let's say
um a minute ahead because so I need to
space it out a lot but then I may miss
things
um so preferably you would just send
inaccurate messages but that only works
if you actually have a method
to Also let's say use less computational
power to compute a less accurate message
and we're not good at that yet
um there there I think I mean what we
are thinking about is there's an infield
or a new field but there's a
a field called probabilistic numerics
where
um we are used in in math to just
compute everything very precisely or as
precise as possible
and and and and do not care about how
much computation we spent on it
um so in probabilistic numerics
um I I hope we can leverage this for uh
for message computations
um I would like to spend let's say
proportionally less
computational power on on the accuracy
of a message One Way possibly would be
to consider a message a latent variable
that has an uncertainty by itself
um but
I I don't have a a totally clear answer
for for Carl because we haven't solved
that either
um but there
there is a problem in let's say what we
do on our I mean our computers
were so completely different from
computers that from let's say from the
um from the from the brain
that uh yeah we're spending
you're spending just too many
computations on messages that in the end
are very very inaccurate and that's a
problem in what we do on our computers
currently
um
yeah so I don't know
how we go I mean what you want to do
with this on the higher level if you you
want to look maybe
um 10 times farther ahead and spent
about the same amount of computation on
the lower level that's sort of the uh
our goal
and uh but but we don't have an answer
for that either at the moment
[Music]
and and Anna so please feel free to
comment on or ask a question to anyone
yeah well I mean I you know I don't I
don't have uh anything to contribute
unfortunately to how computers work but
I can tell you that this idea of
temporal scales is something that we
Face often in our work with patients
um for example addicted patients are
very focused on short-term rewards and
it's it's a fact in fact their ability
to control how they feel in the moment
that is partially what drives the
addiction so when when I try to adopt
url's language of minimizing surprise or
minimizing free entropy
that's one of the things that people are
trying to do on a short-term time scale
when they become addicted so I have a
young woman who's addicted to nitrous
oxide which has a very fast onset of
intoxication over the order of seconds
and a very fast offset and she says that
that's exactly what she likes about it
because she's controlling it second by
second
so when we work with patients to get
them out of that short temporal Horizon
we actually rely more and more on action
and having them change something in
their lives namely abstain from their
drug of choice for long enough to kind
of completely reset their brains and to
allow them to see this longer temporal
because when they're chasing this short
control they're actually not able to see
themselves in the longer narrative Arc
of their lives so that's that was that's
what comes to mind for me I don't think
it's going to be helpful to people who
are trying to build computers but that's
that's the kinds of interventions that I
make with humans
I have a question about that so you
mentioned control in the short term and
you've also mentioned that you study the
positive effects of having a higher
power in your life or or Surrender okay
I kind of give the punch line Away by
saying surrendering to the higher power
where I was going was okay what's the
association between seeing yourself in
the largest time frame and a higher
power and then also is there something
that is akin to giving up control
when you yeah look farther and farther
into the future such a great yeah that's
right like at the heart of what I'm very
interested in because it's a real
Paradox right it's this kind of locus of
control within ourselves that really in
modern culture we think is a great thing
but when that's taken to an extreme and
one example of that is addictive
behaviors it's very bad for people and
for communities and so what can be what
can pull people out of that is this kind
of surrender to a to a higher power
giving up that locus of control locating
that locus of control outside themselves
not not necessarily like in a theistic
sense
um one of the things you know that they
talk about an alcoholic synonymous for
example is
um you know you don't have to believe in
God it just doesn't it's just not you
you're not you know you're not driving
it and so I would be very curious from
the perspective of ural's understanding
of active inference and the free energy
principle and how the brain works why is
it that um sort of embracing our
inability to control what happens in our
lives can actually be the very source of
healing especially embedded in this
really kind of over controlled yeah I
would even go so far as to say
endemically narcissistic culture like
I'm really curious I I don't want to
take the conversation you know in a
Direction please please that's a
fantastic question so if anyone has a
comment on that please
oh I have some thought
uh and I think this applies
um supplies both at the personal level
and at the at the global level and I
think it has to do with the the my quote
from earlier uh brought by Edward
Fullbrook that uh if you're falling from
a plane yes maybe an altimeter and some
instruments uh might be useful but what
you really need is a parachute right so
we have this
um uh we have this uh presupposition
that that are whatever like framing we
have we have operating in our day-to-day
is going to be okay this this is the
right Framing and it's gonna it tends to
be the this uh this rational scientific
uh framing of of okay very very linear
uh consequence for for for most stuff
and it turns out that even like if you
inspect or or day-to-day Behavior you
know bigger more complicated models are
not necessarily better which is where we
get uh the success of heuristics under a
bounded computation boundary rationality
uh and uh if you scale it up to to uh a
billion humans interacted in a in a
resources Planet you know a world of
possibilities but also of challenges
then you just you have to we have to
like drastically lower our our uh our
bar for
yes how much Metro we have but also even
like how much was where does uh
information gathering which diminishing
returns where does modeling reach uh
diminishing returns uh there's a whole
literature on uh in the business World
about the expected value of information
how much you should actually invest but
also in science is also uh known as uh
optimal experiment design where
basically you know acknowledging that uh
that you have a limited budget in terms
of how much you can act and how much you
can probe and how much you can how much
time you can spend thinking about stuff
and uh I think what we're doing when we
feel like burned out or or exhausted
from from overthinking uh or in Italy
feeling that that okay we've gone too
high and we need uh we need to to uh
give ourselves education give ourselves
some uh some uh some free time here I
think that doing this on a principle in
a principled way we're just not not just
like taking the heuristics and the
signals that are that we inherit from
from Evolution but actually being able
to figure out uh collaboratively and uh
and with with some rigor okay this is uh
we don't need to know exactly how much
how many degrees the world is going to
warm uh by 2000 2100 in order to know
that maybe it's a good idea to to start
doing something about the amount of of
carbon in the atmosphere or whatever
right uh and so I think this leads to
this this this no knowledge this idea of
a real knowledge economy and of things
like abstraction as a service how can
you actually
um how can you actually build in
um
building this this kind of like
sophisticated and uh and
um sophisticated translation layers that
take some of this burden from from
ourselves as individuals and even as
organizations right uh and just put it
out in the world as as value-added
Services which is what they are
in Guillaume if you have any statements
or questions or retorts then please feel
free uh yeah thanks uh now I was still
uh also uh thinking about the recent
breakthrough post 2020 in actually
inference uh to to me like they were
like theoretical uh progress that were
very interesting uh we heard already
about the the formalism majority of the
mathematical level between military
scale and scale free aspect
um I I really liked or so the the
development of a more multi-agent
perspective of active insurance it's
very interesting like uh especially like
for instance the
seeing military agent systems we just
heard about like even society as well
like as many as one of a system or many
as many subsystems and how we can uh use
maybe those formalisms to also deal with
policy making that's very interesting
venue and uh the emergence of norms
culture and ideas or so on because
um one thing that I'm still struggling
with in in the case of active inference
models is like how to get outside the
checkerboard uh you you can put a lot in
the in the model a priori and uh how you
make the model creating new stuff that
is not backed inside at the first and I
on that like one very uh interesting
breakthrough was the application of
active inference to morphogenesis I
really like the the work that has been
done on that
and on the technical aspects I think the
the two main uh Focus that I love are uh
all the Deep active inference and how to
scale up uh actually in front because
it's a strong limitation for the
adoption of the the formation uh if it's
not scale enough compared to other
framework like deep learning and then
um the the link with empirical data I
really like for instance the the work of
uh Ryan Smith and how to connect with uh
electrophysiology and clinical data and
I think it's also something very
important to Anchor
uh the theory in in the real world and
have like a fancifiability and empirical
validation of those models
and what are some of the applications of
active inference to morphogenesis
so well I'm not the expert Erica would
be the the best to answer that but uh I
was referring to the the work with
Michael Levin and how a mother can uh
help to create a sort of embryogenesis
uh
so maybe Carl you can explain better
than me
please yeah I don't have a reputation
for explaining things very clearly
but yeah that's absolutely right
um it was just at work with Michael Evan
and colleagues
um uh showing that um you can get quite
expressive and bimetic out in the
formation and movement of different
cells into an organization
um often described in terms of
morphogenesis
um simply by
communicating your beliefs
um so I'm coming back to this sort of
cross-cutting theme of communication so
if you just broadcast
your beliefs and you're a little fell
and you have um there are a little
ensemblance of cells and they all have
the shared charity model that includes
if I was in this position I would sense
that now they all have exactly the same
generative model the same predictions
the same expectations
um and they're all
um broadcasting their beliefs about
where they are and the free energy
minimizing solution is just when they're
all in a place that they except that
they
um receive signals that they would
expect to to
um receive when they're in this place
and of course if that is the same for
everybody there's only one Arrangement
where each cell Finds Its place so
basically it's just knowing your place
is is an immersion property of making
the world mutually predictable through
communication so
you know a deflationary account of
morphogenesis
um but the game I thought you know one
of your units is precision Psychiatry so
I thought you're going to talk about
Precision so I'm going to do a game now
he talked about morphogenesis I'm going
to talk about Precision now but I think
there's there's a that's a really nice
way just to pick up on themes which uh
everybody's just mentioned and in
particular the pathology of precision uh
and by Precision you can reposition in
the sense that Bert was talking about in
terms of do you use an unsigned integer
or a double you know how much can my
course grain to my numeric
representation or you can use it in
terms of course grading in the sense of
the renormalization group you know it's
just chunking things in hours or years
as opposed to milliseconds and minutes
or you can look at it in terms of a
statistician and describing the
reliability or the inverse variance of a
signal because we have to estimate that
um when I say we I mean uh your agents
and statisticians and and act
accordingly and certainly
um in the active in the work of Ryan
Smith uh on addiction much of the sort
of mathematical explanation for these
addictive locked in OCD like a phenomena
rests upon a failure to get that coarse
grading that Precision estimation right
um
the reason I I I wonder whether it be
just worthwhile revisiting
um
um addiction and psychopathology of its
only pathology of Behavior Uh from the
point of view of getting Precision wrong
and certainly assigning too much
Precision to low level processing which
is what Bert wants to avoid doing
um It just strikes me that that kind of
story also has mileage in terms of why
we are in a state of paralysis when it
comes to climate change because I also
notice gear that you talked about
climate action I've never heard that
before but that seems to me to be the
important thing why isn't there any
climate action and Anna you know what it
would be like you going to the clinic
and finding some of the Parkinson's
disease why isn't this person moving you
know
and interestingly the the computational
explanation for Parkinson's Disease is
assigning too much Precision to the
evidence that you're not moving before
you move so you know if you don't if you
can't ignore the fact that nothing is
changing or your pride beliefs your
predictions that I'm going to stand up
are going to initiate walking
don't get a look at because they are
immediately canceled because they've
assigned too much Precision to the lower
level processing and I'm just wondering
whether that that's something that that
kind of pathology is exactly what the
the you know what what Ralph is Ralph is
trying to reverse by having you know uh
morals that have recommendations at hand
that provide a more coarse grained view
of things a deeper view
um
Anna would you like to comment on that
yeah well I just I love I love this idea
of the pathology of precision because I
think it it manifests in so many
different ways
um you know not just among my patient
population but I think it's almost like
a like a cultural sickness in a way
um you know the ways in which we we seem
like obsessed with certain types of data
and we're missing the big picture so I'm
gonna I'm gonna think more about that
I'm gonna read more about it I really
appreciate the discussions interesting
for me
and Anna when you're referring to the
Pathology of precision do you mean so in
a more conscious sense that we're over
evaluating something that we don't need
to whereas Carl you're referring to it
in an unconscious sense like the brain
is
putting too much Precision on something
because in Parkinson's it's it's not
like you consciously are putting
Precision in a place
well I think you could look at it sort
of like in both cases when I think about
addiction
um you know people aren't doing it
consciously it's that they really do
um see this as adaptive and healthy and
also even on some level they can't do
otherwise and they're not able to see
the true impact of their drug use on
their lives they're genuinely not able
to see the negative consequences I mean
that's that's what contributes to
getting caught in that vortex
but I mean you could also see it as part
of
what's happened culturally like for
example like the whole Wellness
industrial complex the way that we now
count ourselves
um you know through all these different
devices and if we could just count our
breathing and count our heart rate and
take supplements you know then we would
somehow reach some levitating state of
precise wellness and I don't know I mean
you know just kind of visit all this is
all kind of new new ideas for me
that's interesting so you believe that
we can be inundated with Health Data and
that that's detrimental to us oh
absolutely I see that all the time
uh-huh so for me I used to have uh okay
maybe I'll take this out of the well
this is going out live
okay let me be
let me figure out how to say this
diplomatic diplomatically I used to have
a device that would measure my heart
rate let's say that and and my sleep and
instead of improving my sleep it led to
me becoming obsessed with it and then
noticing oh I didn't sleep well I must
not be feeling good today as well
because apparently there's a high
connection between how your Sleep
Quality that's exactly it plus added to
that the other layer that
I should be able to control it right so
with all of this data and information I
should be able to I don't know reduce
free entropy or whatever how to produce
surprise as you guys talk about
um you know and I think that's obviously
that only goes so far and then can
actually contribute to our misery
because we're why aren't we all you know
levitating like the Buddha or whatever
um you know when we have all these tools
and we can pay attention to all this
data so
I see this also with people who have
productivity tools so and not only that
but mechanical keyboards let's say
some the reason why I don't have a
mechanical keyboard even though I think
I'd love it is because I know that why
the heck do I care about the clicking
sound of a keyboard but if I got one
then I'd be like well what's the
difference between clicking sound a
versus clicking sound B versus clicking
sound C and I become obsessed with the
trappings of productivity that is
sharpening so-called sharpening the ax
rather than cutting down the tree
there's this phrase that is apocryphal
and it said it's attributed to I think
yeah
Lincoln
which is that he'd spend 80 of his time
or half the time sharpening the knife
than cutting the tree and when you just
if you just think and then this is just
echoed in productivity circles but it
just it can't be the case why would you
spend so much time sharpening your ex
like look at anyone who cuts down a tree
with an X most of the time they're not
doing that
anyhow
so if anyone has any comments on on what
was just said please
can can I uh just talk about what I find
an exciting in my Fields about access
sure sure yes
um I read it was a long time ago but
there was a paper
um and it it's about that it says well
active inference is not really a
scientific Loop because it's biased and
um and I read that and the the
sound of the paper was kind of sort of
just so it's not good
but I think you know active influence is
is maybe not a science book it's an
engineering Loop because there's bias
and we need buyers in engineering we
need to make stuff we need to build
stuff we need to have a biased so it's
an engineering design cycle I see that
everywhere around me
um and active inference could be
um a complete breakthrough in in
engineering right
um the fields around me are signal
processing I myself in a signal
processing uh
department or group and everybody builds
algorithms
for us I mean elective interest agents
it's influence of States then the floor
below me they build Control Systems well
it's influence over actions
then other people are working on machine
learning influence over parameters
active infants could be and you'll like
this curve it's a very deflationary view
on uh on engineering because everything
is just inference and so rather than
building
algorithms everywhere if we become
really good at implementing
minimization we will we will be able to
build a great engineering design cycles
and and we'll be engineering better
machines for us or yeah
you know for medical procedures or for
other things that are important so it
has a tremendous uh application
potential in engineering
um in in engineering I think in most
many fields
people have sort of drifted in different
directions control theorists have I mean
they do almost the same thing as signal
processing people but they speak a
different language now
and you know so uh and everybody and and
Signal processing people
it's a completely different group from
the machine learning people but it's all
information processing and this brings
it uh this field can bring it together
uh so I think it's the
if but the thing is that in order to
to make it successful in engineering we
need to build an application that uh
well that impresses right that it's not
like a tic-tac-toe thing that it really
needs to impress people it's to be
better than
you know there's some other control
systems but once we do that I think
there's tremendous uh application
potential because there haven't been
enormous breakthroughs in Signal
processing and control the last big
breakthrough
I think it was common filtering and this
was 1960s and and I mean it's it's kind
of uh it's kind of funny that the
essence of what we do in active interest
is also carbon filtering so
um that's uh yeah I think there's
tremendous opportunities for for what we
do here for uh for engineering
so that's why that's why it's exciting
to me
and do you mind expanding on what you
said about acting and therapists should
be helping their patients with that
oh uh sure just so I mean one of my
critiques of uh you know mental health
treatment today is that there's not
enough
um
there's not enough encouragement of
patients to actually go and act
differently in the world as a way of
gathering data instead of it often ends
up being kind of this
World building between therapists and
patients not not necessarily ultimately
adaptive in the world so I was really
just kind of responding to what rap was
saying that we need to act in the world
I think that's
more true now
um in you know modern Rich Nations than
ever before because we are so incredibly
sedentary and interactive of course
we're interacting with a virtual world
and that's
you know good and bad but I mean I think
we need to be actually acting in the
world
hmm
and so there's there's different forms
of therapy as you as you know there's
talk therapy and then there's also
cognitive behavioral therapy or
Psychotherapy and top therapy but but
cognitive behavioral therapy as far as I
understand focuses on on the actions is
that incorrect or
[Music]
um
I mean for you know again treating
addiction like you're you're not going
to really get that far with cognitive
behavioral therapy or anything that's
focused on just emotions and cognitions
people have to go out and actually
um try stop using their stopping their
substance or their addictive behaviors
and gather data from that experience and
then come back and process it
mm-hmm
so Anna in your field and this question
will go to everyone but in in your field
in what you study where is the largest
gap that you would like to see closed
well I mean we're facing a huge Mental
Health crisis now we have more and more
young people coming in with depression
anxiety suicidality addictions of all
sorts and these are not necessarily
people who are struggling by virtue of
trauma or socioeconomic disparity these
are people who have really privileged
lives in many instances so it's uh it's
really a puzzle you know what what is
going on for people and I think a big
part of it is
the fact that people are not having
embodied experiences they're not having
experiences in the world
um and and also the experiences that
they are having are
you know these kinds of very quick fixes
and
um fast Pleasures so
I think noticing I think you know the
the co-created sort of models through
healthier communication that allow
people to feel part of a community and
also to have like truthful co-created
narratives trying to use the language
here
um I think that's really important
so for example one of the things
mentioned once he's excited about one of
the things I'm excited about in the
field of addiction medicine is mutual
support and the proliferation of things
like Alcoholics Anonymous but also other
mutual help help groups a lot of them
existing now online and the way that
people are together creating healthier
narratives enacted together to
counteract a lot of the unhealthy
narratives that I think are driving a
lot of decision making today
I wanted to know is there a correlation
between the rise in mental health or
sorry mental illness or mental health
issues whatever we want to call it and
at a certain trait of people like is it
affecting every is it affecting the
population
the same so the whole population has
raised 20 in terms of how many mental
health issues they have per year or is
it affecting people who deal with
abstractions more and more so for
instance we're talking over zoom and
some people study abstractions just like
us and then there's some people who
whose work it is to to do something
physical like running or or swim like is
it affecting everyone equally or are you
noticing that there's some broad trend
well the broad trends that are out there
are just correlational but the more time
that people will spend in the virtual
world the more likely they are to suffer
from depression anxiety and other mental
health problems
um you know people haven't really been
able to narrow that down to specific
content but they have been able to save
just the sheer amount of time that
spending that you're spending online
increases your risk for certain mental
health you know poor mental health
outcomes
[Music]
um
okay now Carl well again if anyone has
any comments or questions please just
raise your physical hand I can see that
and okay Raph Ralph Raphael sorry no I
was just gonna say that uh I think
another uh notable trend is that and I
just saw somebody see this on YouTube
yet just yesterday that uh uh young
people or this proportionately affected
by things like climate grief because
they're the ones that are going to be
alive to deal with it
um and uh I think that applies more
generally that you know Peter Sandy
already like 30 years or something ago
uh wrote about the inescapable network
of neutrality the reality that that uh
that what what we do affects each other
right and we built we we took advantage
of this huge resource buffer that's
called uh the biosphere and uh and uh
and and Earth to to pretend that it
didn't for
um for quite a long time and you know
got got a lot of mileage out of it but
it's uh now we're at a point where we
know that there's there's a uh a whole
generation of people that are coming to
grip so the fact that
um I'm gonna stop myself from seeing a
swear word but oh my God we need to uh
we actually need to change everything
about
everything about everything that we do
and and we need to do it fast and uh and
by the way that it's not just uh what we
do in uh
it's not just what we do out there it's
also what we do inside our get ready for
for how to show up for Life internally
right so no wonder that that it has that
impacts like my myself I've dealt with
anxiety and uh and uh and a lot of of
other things we've had conversations
about what what are we doing bringing a
daughter into this world and all these
kinds of things I think it's it's only
natural that that it's it's coming to a
head in this way right now
Neil you have your hand up and I can't
see you
yes
um yeah it's connect with the what has
just been said uh so and your initial
question of that the the gaps that needs
to be closed I think like uh the scale
spree model of health and mental health
particularly would be great like uh we
are in silos in biomedical research and
uh the fact that someone is
uh having depression can come from uh
interacting genes as much as interacting
people and uh also is related to climate
change and so on so how we can have a
new health systems that doesn't deal
with those silos and integrate those
different skills to me it's like really
a big challenge but a challenge that uh
current models and work that we can see
going that direction and I'm very
enthusiastic about that
Bert
um
yeah the um
well I in in my field in engineering
active inference is not understood
because almost all papers are written by
neuroscientists and they're hard to read
so I was really happy to hear today that
I think it's Sanjeev namjoshi who who is
writing an engineering book on active
inference so that I think it will really
help
um that together with the availability
of good toolboxes for implementing
active inference should make a lot of
Engineers uh much more enthusiastic
about active influence because that's uh
it's not something that is
and it's not understood at the moment in
engineering circles so I hope that the
book will be good because that I'm
enthusiastic about that
and Carl
where where are some
gaps in the in your research that you'd
like to see addressed
um
oh empty space out there yet to be um
explored
um but in terms of
um
in in terms of what seems to be emerging
from um the session and specifically the
past few
um answers it it does seem to be um
important to have
um this very generic just to take births
um sort of line that this is just one
deflationary simple and probably the
right way to understand stuff and to
make recommendations or to
um describe people's actions possibly to
themselves in a therapeutic uh context
um and as such it should be push button
technology and it should be democratized
and socialized and
um I I think that's the challenge
practically
um and what one may ask why would you
want to do that
um for me that there are two
um clear imperatives
um one is
um very abstract and it's not really my
uh um within my comfort zone and the
other one is in my cumbersome another
one that's outside my comfort zone as
um is um this notion of
um
interactivity and Hyper connectivity in
them and and The Meta crisis that we we
heard about
um and um and our game also refer to
this in terms of what he was trying he
was trying to distinguish between a
Californian notion of optimality and
another kind another way forward
um and to me it's it's it's you know a
stark contrast with growth is good
versus sustainability and of course the
maths of the free energy principle is
just about sustainability it's just a
description of the physics of systems
random dynamical systems that
self-organized to some non-equilibrium
steady state and that is what we are
um so you know for me there's something
deeply if you like apt about the free
energy principle and its coronal risk
such as active inference in application
to ecosystems and lived ecosystems and
realized ecosystems so if that if those
basic principles can be brought back
um into globalization uh into the you
know into the market into fintech into
um social media into politics into your
climate action I think that would be a
good thing
um I'm just mindful of you know this
struck me in a number of the
presentations today
um you remember before Bert was saying
if you look at the brain which is a
really lovely example of a
self-organizing system to a
non-equilibrium steady state
um then it's empty and what did he mean
by that it didn't mean you were
empty-headed what he meant was it's
incredibly sparsely connected
now that tells you immediately that a
pathology of connectivity is hyper
connective to overconnectivity which
immediately
um well it made me very alert to
um the presentation of the meta crisis
that one of the first three things that
was uh and underwrote them the the
metacris or you know the current crisis
were kind of intending with is a
destruction of that sparse Delica
connectivity that defines thingness and
defines ensembles of things technically
in terms of Markov blankets so if we
want a world in which lots of different
things can coexist in some kind of
generalized synchrony in a sustainable
way
new deep sparse connectivity and the
pathology the thing that will destroy
that is over connectivity
um so it seems to be very important that
we get that into uh into play in terms
of uh machine learning
um artificial intelligence politics
fintech climate change and the only way
it's going to get there is is
epistemically by uh equipping people to
actually
um build their own little models and ask
their own questions you can't tell
people this they're going to learn and
they're going to learn it for themselves
uh just very quickly because I'm sure
yeah we've only got a couple of minutes
left um the the the
um the other agenda which I'm more
familiar with is exactly Anderson and
guillaume's agenda which is uh making
this work in the context of uh
um of Neurology and Psychiatry
um so if you can democratize
um and socialize this way of describing
things so that people can now build
models of their particular patient in
the other use of precision Psychiatry
um that are suspended games unit was
called after
um so to personalized medicine that is
really personalized in the sense that it
yo you actually have your digital twin
of the of your behavior and then you've
got that you know you optimize your
digital twin to become a model of your
patient and then you can start to do
experiments on that on that model
behavioral interventions or even share
that model very much in the spirit of
CBT with the patient and say look this
is you this is what would happen if you
went out and did this and this is what
would happen if you went out and did
that
um you know that that to to my mind and
indeed that was the initial motivation
for much of this work was actually to
build
um observation models of psychiatric
conditions to work out both the
um the the pharmacological and
physiological basis on the disruption of
the overly the pathology of precision
and message passing on the factor graphs
that are our brain even though they are
very empty and on the one hand but also
get that behavior that that key thing
that Anna was talking about the active
engagement with the lived world uh into
into that model and hence active
inference and just to conclude you know
um that that that activity that sort of
physical engagement that embodiment that
sort of um fouries and everything else
um I think it's really coming to a head
now in terms of people's um you know
after the large language model after the
chat GPT moment people the bounce back
uh has been What's missing
you know what's not there and of course
what is not there is agency and embodied
engagement with the world
um and that's why I think Mr whole
there's still a lot of work to be done
you know in bringing artificial
intelligence red as active inference to
in a way that matters to people who you
know your the people who can make a
difference which is basically everybody
but specifically politicians and doctors
and the engineers and the like
hmm
so you all now have 30 seconds to 60
seconds to speak directly to the
audience what is the message that you
what closing message do you have you're
speaking directly to someone who's
listening they're a curious person
they're interested in active inference
they also want to lead Better Lives
hopefully and and and do something
propitious so what message do you have
for them
Anna we'll start with you
gosh
um I'm just gonna say what pops into my
mind right now is that one of the things
I have learned from my patients who are
trying to get into recovery from severe
addictions is something that they call
the set aside prayer where they set
aside all of the Notions that they have
about how the world works and try to be
completely open and receptive to
information coming into their minds and
I think that's just a wonderful
um
a wonderful frame or concept for all of
us uh living in the world to
periodically just take a moment and take
these models and just say you know
everything I think I know about the
world I'm going to temporarily suspend
it and I'm just going to be open and
when that happens we can be present and
learn in a way that it's not possible
when we're just trying to reinforce our
models
great fantastic and Bert and then we'll
go Carl and then Rapha and then
Guillaume
um well I I just enjoyed today very much
I thought there was a
there was a little material boost for
people from let's say psychology
Neuroscience but also from for engineers
so if you haven't watched some of the
talks go go look through the schedule
because some of the talks were really
good I think so I really enjoyed that
um and then yeah what should I tell
people um go work out do do a lot of
sports it's good for you
[Music]
oh
yeah sorry I was going to make a joke
but I called because
[Music]
um so I'm going to use my 32nd uh just
to thank uh Daniel and his team for for
this um you know so if you want
something to do
um you should go and watch the live
streams
um and
um get involved with this ecosystem I
hadn't seen that paper be presented
before but I was really impressed with
you know with the sort of the active
Institute and its openness and it's your
welcoming
um
um attitude and vision like the
Smithsonian
um so if you want to pursue these ideas
get involved and if you uh haven't got
time just make sure you attend next
year's active inference Institute a
celebration but thank you Daniel
Raphael
yeah so I'll second what uh what Carl
said and follow along with uh it's it's
an invitation not just uh to participate
in the in the active Advanced Institute
but also an invitations participate in
uh building this uh this Gaia tractor
this uh this new way of of doing things
that acknowledges the value of growth uh
and also the value of sustainability
joins it all together in this thing
called regeneration and uh it really is
uh it really is a collective effort it's
a collective learning effort so
um so and this also by the way also
applies to to the the panelists as well
and I think uh obviously what uh board
and Carl are doing it has immediate uh
things having that have to do with with
uh what we're after but one of the main
things that we discussed that we keep
discussing is also like this uh the
inter intersubjectivity and the The
Importance of Being able to operate well
as humans together and that connects
directly to cognitive science Psychiatry
uh and so
and uh and yeah so everybody that wants
to to to be engaged and and be a part of
building a better world should be
thinking about how do I how what am I
doing with my as an individual or as a
as an employee organization or a
researcher or as a leader uh or the
family member what am I doing how does
it contribute to to this uh this new
this new non-steady non non equilibrium
set of state so yeah that's that's kind
of it I probably blew through the 60
seconds but here it is
and Guillaume
well uh I would thanks also all of you
for the discussion and the the organizer
for what they are doing indeed like the
the work of the actual Insurance
Institute is very uh lovable and
interesting from open science
perspective they are really uh embodying
that so big kudos to them and uh well uh
where the fridge was saying like to do
sport is good for you I'm not very good
at sports but uh some say that science
is a team sport so at least uh I have a
good team perspective when doing science
and being kind to each other would be
the best advice to to everyone
well thank you I also would like to you
get you get yours too somebody else has
to come in from outside the Markov
blanket though
right well I wanted to just thank you
Daniel thank you Daniel and and Raphael
and well and also Carl and Anna and Bert
and Yom this was a tremendous amount of
fun and well I hope I get to speak to
you all individually and for I as usual
I have way more questions than we were
able to get to
thank you all
right
thank you thanks everyone
farewell panelists you're all welcome
back anytime
um thanks everybody for watching or
re-watching
right now we're about to head over to
the Discord and hang out and talk a
little more if you want to and then stay
involved get involved so until next time
bye bye-bye bye bye