You. Hello everyone. It's october 14,
2022. We're in meeting
20. We're in our second discussion of
chapter eight. We have a few topics
and points in chapter eight and then
maybe we can preview some
chapter nine and have a lot of
space for any other foster questions
people are having so we can jump
to the questions and look at the written
chapter eight questions. Or does anyone
want to suggest a point for us
to go to last
time? We know that some of the areas we
wanted to pick up on involved
learning and hierarchical modeling and
hybrid modeling.
One question that came up, I think here,
but maybe we can revisit is the birdsong
model is widely
pointed at as an example of how
communication is modeled in active
inference or for active inference
entities. However, it's quite literally
singing from the same hymn sheet. And
the turn taking is based upon a
joint expectation of that song
being sung that way.
And then the actions that the birds can
take, the kind of turn taking that they
enact is again
related to whether it's like, well,
somebody has to say it is it going to be
me or is it going to be them? So how do
you think we would broaden that scope
of communication to account for
situations where there
isn't a prescripted song?
How do other frameworks for
communication cybernetic
ish or otherwise deal with
the semantics of conversation,
improvisation,
open endedness in conversation?
Actually, I had somewhat
more general question about the bird
songs and its relation to these
particular systems that they've
developed in the textbook. You see,
some researchers believe that I'm sure
you're much qualified to
talk about this than me, but there
are lots of research going around about
the territorialization function of
birdsong. So if
we take a bird song as its
territorializing mechanism,
at least one of its territorializing
mechanism, can we somehow
put the dynamic I mean,
the dynamic boundary of the markup
blanket, I think would be affected from
this point of view. And then I'm not
sure how that would translate into this
specific model if we take that dynamic
nature of the markup blanket boundary.
Yeah, I guess I would just build on that
and say that communication serves a
purpose. And so I think a
model should incorporate what that
purpose is and how it's served by the
communication. And then whether it
happens to be syncing up with some
predefined pattern or whatever is a
follow on consideration.
The generative model in the singing from
the same hymn sheet is very much
like the sheet music example provided
in the textbook.
There's a known sheet music script
such that even when there's like an
error in the playing of the music,
still the sheet music can be heard.
So just coarsely
what generative models?
I think it's pretty straightforward to
see how a generative model could have
the notation or the sheet music and then
use the sheet music as its prior to kind
of converge reality.
To what extent is communication that
way? Is it totally
disparate and differently structured?
Or is it a little bit like a hybrid?
Like you're doing inference on the sheet
music that they're about to say and then
you use your inference about what
they're about to say to converge what
they do say?
Well, you asked a good question, which
is, well, what are some alternative
frameworks? And I
know, I know some or should know some,
and they're not clean to mind. What
comes to mind most immediately in this
example is a phase lock loop in
electronics which is simply a way of
synchronizing one circuit's oscillation
with another. And this is like a phase
lock loop with a bigger vocabulary. So
figure out where we are in the pattern
and then synchronize with it.
But the question of what other
frameworks?
I mean, there's this whole field of
conversation analysis.
Which. The field is actually called
CA conversation analysis. And they have
identified patterns of how
people communicate through certain
structure of I guess we call them
rhetorical devices for achieving the
purpose of the conversation. So the
purpose of the communication is kind of
bedrock. And there are multiple
purposes, some of which are
instrumental, some are which are social.
And then they have identified patterns
for the way human conversation tends to
proceed which are culturally influenced.
There's some cross cultural aspects,
but then there are certain different
cultures that have different takes on
it. So they identify things like, okay,
now we're in the conversation opening
phase. Now we're in a phase of where
we're exchanging information and we have
turntaking. Now we have notions of
epistemic leadership or epistemic
authority. Who's the person who's
asking? Who's the person who's answering
or taking those roles in the
conversation? And there are certain
rhetorical stances that are taken.
That's a pretty well worked out,
I guess, even formalized system because
there are well identified patterns.
It's not strictly worked out because it
seems like every domain a conversation
analyst goes to and every every group
has their own kind of flavor of it. But
it does have this aspect of
synchronizing with respect to the
underlying known patterns of each of the
parties in the conversation.
Bird Song is also ollie, please.
Sorry. Adding to what Eric just
mentioned that reminded me of
a mechanism on a much smaller scale,
namely the scale of cells and so on,
and particularly the model proposed
by Stuart Kaufman because he
talks about the pluripotent,
potent nature of cells and how they
communicate with each other in the
context of phenomena of induction,
biological induction.
I mean, in the embryological development
stage of the cells, almost all cells are
pluripotent and they're capable of
becoming any of the different types of
cells which characterize the adult
individual. So that also,
from Kaufman's model perspective,
these kind of inductive signals,
or so to speak, communicative signals
between cells can act as a kind of
nonspecific stimulus which switch a cell
among a variety of internally available
stable states.
Or let's put it this way the
basic idea in this model is that the
regulatory genes within a cell form a
complex network in which genes
interacting by their products can turn
one another on or off.
These patterns exhibit the kind of
homeostatic stability associated with
attractors of the systems.
So I think that translates
perfectly into this scale as well. This
is small.
Yeah. The mapping
of communication as generalized
synchrony may be compatible with a
variety of communication mechanisms.
And so it abstracts us from the
media of communication per se
because we can talk about the
informational synchronizations between,
for example, the two internal states of
the two entities or multilateral
synchronizations with environmental
states or so on. Um,
like thinking about the Bayesian
mechanics, Bayesian physics,
the synchronizing metronomes.
They don't have a hymn sheet, they don't
have sheet music. Their embodiment
and coupling enables
synchronization.
One thing I might note, I think you
asked a good question here, which is how
would you translate something like
conversation analysis or human
conversation into an active inference
model? That kind
of reminds me that the continuous valued
models because they're limited
by what you can do in these differential
equations, they seem to be fairly
simple. Whereas if I were to do
something like thinking about human
conversation in terms of active
inference, I would want something more a
very highly high dimensional or
multistate type of system where I can
have more complex patterns
and they may not make these loops,
these voltera loops. Is that what they
call voltera? Is that right? Or is this
Lawrence something? That dynamics and
the Lawrence yeah, so they may
not make those continuous loops, but
you'd still get good structured patterns
out of discrete systems.
So I'd kind of be curious and I think
this chapter would be cool if it had
something about communication and
synchrony, pattern synchrony, but in
terms of discrete valued active
inference models instead of the
continuous valued ones. Yeah,
very interesting. That's what I was
wondering. Which is why is communication
continuous time models are argued to be
a natural fit for motor control? Are
communication situations naturally
fit for one or the other? Seems like no,
you could imagine it either way. And
then also the synchronization means
the internal state of one creature
should come to resolve the resemble
internal state of another. A primitive
kind of theory of mind, I think. Not as
a fatal
critique, but these examples put
the rabbit in the hat a little bit too
keenly. Like the planning example we
explored wasn't truly planning. It was
like a parameterized subspace where
single step optimization emulated
planning. Now, one could argue that they
believe that that's actually like a
better approach than true explicit
planning, but that's not what was on the
COVID And then similarly, theory of
mind, though qualitatively, may be a
framing for communication. We're talking
still about the birdsong where they have
the same shared a prior regenerative
model. So this doesn't in
other words, theory of mind is
axiomatically and implicitly embedded
within this model, rather than active
inference being used as in a priori
first principles to generate some
realized computational theory of mind.
I feel like, yeah, it's like another
aspect of the continuous valued
formulations is there's really not that
many degrees of freedom, but when you're
communicating anything other than a
fixed song, there's a lot of degrees of
freedom. And that's why we have symbol
systems. But symbol systems is where you
would use a discrete model framework for
not a continuous value to win.
Okay, let's talk about hybrid
models, discrete and continuous models
and learning and updating. So these are
two features. Chapter eight is
within a continuous time framework,
just like chapter seven, layered in
these kind of patterns or archetypes of
discrete time models in chapter
eight, analogously, the most
kernel continuous time formalism is
introduced with movement control and
then we're going to see some kind of
extensions or patterns
like design patterns that include
continuous time.
This is the message passing.
Okay, so missing line here, but we
have here, this top
half is like the bottom of figure 4.3,
or the top, I guess, discrete time. So
we have B matrix as a transition matrix.
We have discrete time and we have
discrete time. T plus one, t minus one.
But within each time point we
see the continuous time e whatever
we want to call this motif where
the B transition matrix in discrete time
is functionally substituted
with a derivative map such
that rather than actually retro
or forecasting state values through
time. This is much more like a Taylor
Series approximation, where
extrapolation from the present,
under the auspices of slower changing
causes v, which play a functional role
of policies, higher derivatives
capture more and more variance further
and further from the origin.
What is the Ita doing?
It's playing some functional role to g
again, allowing for a line here in the
sense that it is selecting
policy, but it's not policy that's being
selected or discussed this way, but
these slower changing factors that
influence how the derivatives are made.
But is EDA a free energy variable?
Let's just ask,
okay, what do people
think about this type of hybrid
modeling? How does
this align with
the previous decades of analog digital
signals engineering and the interfaces,
the digitalization of analog noise and
signals and so on?
Well, I'll lay off one thought,
if it's all right.
So one
of the things that active inference lets
you do is look at a past trajectory
and figure out how to interpret it in
terms of your variable, your state
variables. So essentially,
you look for the probability
distribution over variables
that optimizes the free energy and that
allows you to look back in time and
reinterpret evidence because
you get something new. And in light of
new evidence and in some of the earlier
chapters, they had this kind of example
and they had the example of a
dynamic programming kind of a model for
this. So I would expect that to be the
case also in communication systems.
And I guess I'm going back again to
communication where to some extent
you're able to reinterpret what you
thought you heard before. It's kind
of rare in language, but it happens.
There are garden path sentences,
but usually most communication
systems try to be relatively
hierarchical in that once you interpret
your continuous value signal, then you
don't leave a lot of ambiguity. You kind
of fix on that and then you have to deal
with it later and sometimes you go back
and do repair. So I'm wondering if this
figure 8.6, if that allows that kind of
dynamics where you're
kind of tracking something at the
continuous value level, you're tracking
a signal. Why? Effectively by making
predictions of what you're going to
hear, what you observe and then
is that able in this framework to go and
influence the symbol level,
the S variables above
and how far back in time is it able to
do that? Nice.
That makes me think about phonemes down
here and audio.
And then here are the spellings.
So in a language or someone is speaking
unclearly or you're not super familiar
with a language,
then you really are like doing inference
on the whole time series. It's like
that kind of retrocasting
which can include even revisionism and
delusions and false memories and all of
that. Now casting including the tension
between representing things quote as
they are versus like having
delusions in the presence and then
anticipation, which of course hasn't
even happened unless you have a vision
of time as something
that always was or however. So it's
really interesting that although this
time T is an index, we are doing
inference across these and maybe it
would speak to some measure of
information processing and
memory and anticipation.
The extent to which meaning
is able to be the
closer meaning is to a critical point.
Like the more this graph structure if
someone says but I was just kidding,
you would want that to apply to
be like oh, I didn't know I was in
Apprentices. And now that they were just
kidding about that.
So it's actually like delineating those
structural markers and then
reinterpreting meaning is
perhaps moving towards the kind of
linguistic modeling.
So yeah, to come back to it.
So this could be a waveform. The
observables down here could be just a
Fourier analysis or a pure auditory
waveform.
Yeah, I think phonemes is that's what
comes to mind? Also.
Okay. Ocular motor tasks.
So selecting a target location and using
motor behavior functionally eyes to fove
eight the target.
Figure 87. Okay, so figure eight seven
is a hybrid or mixed generative model.
Higher level is this is kind of like the
decision making motor active inference
fusion.
Here we have a little bit of the italics
and bold,
which we could dive into, but don't need
to do so at this moment.
So my recollection for last week was
that that corresponded to generative
model versus process model. You think
that might map again here? I know you
didn't want to dive into it.
I believe it does. Let's just remind
ourselves where it came up earlier in
the chapter. Yeah, it was always the
very beginning right here with
italics versus process in bold
model in italics.
So 87. So now
here the discrete
model is on a time period of 200
milliseconds. Continuous model operates
continuously. I think this speaks
to how biological knowledge
can be encoded in the model
structure. I mean, a more comprehensive
approach would have done parameter
sweeps for what the optimal number of
milliseconds is to do a discrete model
on. However, one could say,
like, well, the physiology that we're
interested in is accomplished with a
gamma EEG cycle. The gamma EEG
cycle is this many milliseconds. So
we're just going to treat that
as like a discrete rhythm. Like, one can
imagine if the discrete time were one
millisecond here, you would be losing
computational advantage and you'd be
kind of like overslicing. Because if
eye movement does happen on a timescale
of hundreds of milliseconds,
discretizing to one millisecond is going
to be too fine, and discretizing to 1
second is not going to enable multiple
actions to be taken within that frame.
So timescale and spatial scale of a
system might be able to be encoded
at the phase of its construction or
structure learning more generally.
Okay,
doubtsian mixture model and
the hierarchical. Yeah, sorry, before we
move on, just about the isochods,
I don't understand what is gained by an
active inference model for this. I mean,
why not just say you got a controller
and it's a control loop and that's good
enough?
Yes. In live
stream number 50, which we're just
preparing for, it's like very classical
cybernetic control loop,
homeostatic dynamics. And it's
interesting to ask
again, what makes the model active
inference? One could
say that there's a Markov blanket, but
between every one of these variables,
it is a model of action and perception,
like so many other models of action and
perception. So what is being shown
here is it that the
single imperative that energy based
imperatives just
speaking narrowly here, energy based
imperatives can mediate decision
making in discrete continuous hybrid
models,
and that it's possible to have a
categorical decision making model in
feedback with a continuous ocular motor
model.
At the very least, it places this type
of model within
the domain and grammar of active
inference modeling.
Data clustering. We may have touched
upon also hierarchical Gaussian filter
that I know some people have worked
on.
Okay, let's look at some of the summary
advances in continuous time models.
Synthetic birdsong. We talked about
this.
Ocular motor delays conditioned
reflex. Okay, so this is in the chapter.
This is in the chapter. I don't know
about this exact paper, perhaps, but
Ocular motor is in the chapter and
smooth eye pursuits, conditioned
reflexes, that is in this chapter. The
blank, the conditioned and the
unconditioned stimuli building
on the songbird model. But the songbird
model was in 2015.
False inference from suboptimal prior
beliefs. Can prior beliefs
be suboptimal?
Sorry. Actually, Friston has talked
about bird songs before 2015 in
one of his papers, I think from 2013 or
twelve. Yeah, it's from 2013,
which is co authored with his son,
I guess. Dominic A. Friston 2015
paper was not the first paper.
The name of the paper is the Free Energy
Formulation of Music Generation and
Perception. Thank you. Thank you. Yeah.
Wow. Yeah, good find reminder.
Interesting.
Looks very much like the textbook, you
know, opening quotes. I can
see how this is related to your
researching too.
Okay. Maybe even 2009.
Birdsong chaotic Attractors. Wow.
It's ten plus years on the
birdsong paradigm.
Okay, so deviations
in perception,
more eye movement. It's kind of fun.
Like how we've talked about babbling and
that across different domains like
cicading. Now there's the Ocular motor
cicade, but are there other kinds of
cicadings?
For example, I think that knowledge
management niches facilitate semantic
cicading. Yes. Enabled by visual
cicading as well because you have to be
like looking around on the page, but
it's just like what was chapter four?
Okay, that's what we were talking about,
chapter four. What's notation? I think
it's just sort of like the analog to
scanning around a little. Bit,
but just have in conversational analysis
that's a very important topic is topic
control.
If you look at any, most conversations
have multiple threads going. So it's
like a fugue in Bach. Okay, which voice
is this? Every note is in a voice and
the voice has got some topic and they
intertwine.
In Godel, usherbach,
prelude, ant fugue.
Nice. This is very interesting and I
think it starts to plant
some seeds towards, again,
semantic circading, computational
conversation analysis and generation
adaptive knowledge environments like
visual accessibility is one topic.
If somebody has a visual difference,
then making sure that they can see it is
the enabling system. But let's just
assume that we're within a space where
we can talk about what is being seen.
So then how does someone get a
clear picture of what we're talking
about? That would be through some sort
of circade where you would recognize
more uncertainty at the periphery and
the phobia in this case is paying
attention to the conversation. And
that's why with a language we're
unfamiliar with, we get a little bit
lost because our cicade, we're too slow,
we don't have the fluency to circade.
And so the video is moving too fast to
track. So we're just kind of like
randomly listening and trying to
compute. But what if
somebody were on a guided cicade journey
through their semantic landscape. I
mean, just to take this a little bit
further, this is also maybe
it's a critical element of cognitive
architecture, which is the ability to
topic switch. And in psychology and
cognitive science, there's this notion
of executive control. And one of the
fundamentals of executive control is to
be able to topic switch. So you're on
some task, you get an interrupt, you
have to put that on a stack, deal with
your interrupt. Then when you're done,
maybe the interrupt is a goal, it could
be a sub goal, it could be some other
topic that comes in, something you have
to deal with. Then when you're done,
you have to be able to pull that back,
push that back off the stack and get
back to where you were. So all that
context switching is really I mean,
there's measures of how people do this
and there's debates about whether people
can multitask or not, whether they're
actually really multitasking or they're
just multithreading, but they're
dividing the amount of computational
process by the number of processes you
have going. So you're actually not doing
multiple things at once as effectively
as if you just stuck with one.
And then it's like, do we have that
intel hyperthreading capacity?
Is it a virtualized hyper thread?
On one thread? Are there actually
different threads?
Yeah, I mean the conversation analysis,
other than us being right in the thick
of it and it being highly engaging,
support an area. Let's just continue
through this cases here. Action
observation. Okay. Mirror neurons.
This may be very much related to the
birdsong singing from the same hymn
sheet or whatever and then doing the
same dance. Attention.
This is a super fascinating area and
I think a lot of notebooks and
applications like just taking
a trace of somebody's browsing on
Wikipedia or across websites and
then reconstructing components of their
generative model based upon their
salience revealed choice is a huge area.
And then doing again, that with Ocular
motor, with Webcams,
and doing it with semantic landscapes,
hybrid modeling, self organization,
arguably with some pretty interesting
advances in the last several months and
days from Fields, Levin and others on
the And Forestaged earlier,
but on the morphogenesis as Bayesian
inference.
Okay, in our last few
minutes here, let's just look ahead to
nine because I think this is setting us
up well.
Okay,
model based data analysis or databased
modeling, or however we want to say this
is about parameterizing structured
models with observations.
So rather than just by fiat dictate
saying this is the structure of the
model and it spits out observations like
so and so. We want to be able to
actually run it backwards, not as a
generative model, but as a recognition
model, so to speak, in this expectation
maximization framework and parameterize
our generative model from sparse or
dense observations. And that's also
called parametric empirical base because
you're parameterizing the prior based
upon the mean invariance and patterns of
some empirical data.
Okay? The metabasian approach,
base theorem.
This may even be something that could be
introduced earlier, even though it's
also meta.
This is like the map territory fallacy,
fallacy graphical abstract,
which is we're making a map here's us in
the bigger box, even though there's a
dashed box even beyond us. We're making
a map of a cognitive entity
in its map making of its generative
process. And that was the subject also
of some very rich discussion several
days ago with Yaakov and Dali and Dalton
Ali, anything to add on this?
No, nothing much. But.
One general comment I wanted to make
about chapter nine is that,
you see, because of my project
that I've been working on for the past
several months, this chapter nine has
been quite helpful in developing some of
my ideas around how
to exactly model my music
emotional recognition system that I've
been working on. But I wanted to point
out one small caveat here,
which is that you see, at least
in my opinion, chapter nine, or this
so called model based data analysis,
is not conducive to generate
on every model that's been described
throughout the book. It's just focused
on some specific kinds of models. So it
might not be generalizable to every
kind of model that we've seen throughout
all the previous chapters.
Good point. Some models
might be just plug and play, so to
speak, and other ones might take a
little bit more work to get to use
empirically.
Okay, let's just continued in our last
minutes to scan through so metabasian
process. We're drawing inferences about
an inferential process.
It's a key point. And that's
the two levels of mapping. It's like the
map of the map variational,
LaPlace variational, bayes factorized
models for computational simplicity
and interpretability based upon the
sparsity of coupling of variables in a
Bayes graph. And LaPlace using
a parabolic approximator of
the mode and a variance to ensure
a simple optimizable heuristic.
Not that it perfectly recapitulates
capitulates the shape of the posterior,
which doesn't have to be inverted
quadratic, but the LaPlace approximation
is smoothly optimizable for both the
mode and the variance. And here's where
they mentioned that's the parametric
empirical Bayesian approach and
basically LaPlace approximation can be
thought of as making a commitment to the
quadratic form. So choosing the family
that your prior is going to be of and
then bootstrapping your initial prior
with your observed data bootstrapping
not in the resampling sense, but in the
starting oneself out sense.
This was explored more in
other works,
but you have some likelihood function of
all the parameters l of data and
optimizing action involves
computing beliefs about policy such
that policies are proportionally taking
up slices of the pie monotonically
with respect to their free energy. And
then there's a precision on action
parameter where you can turn it all the
way down to sort of like don't know,
don't care, where even large differences
in free energy between policies get
equilibrated out. That's like hot
decision making. And then absolute zero
decision making would be a policy that's
even 51% more likely would
be always selected. So the
variation of free energy, expected free
energy, it's a bound on surprise due to
Jensen's inequality and evidence lower
bound. And all this other work in
variational inference. And then that pi
slicing can be tuned up or down with
a shaky hand parameter. Soft max
temperature parameter.
If the soft max is one, the pie is
undistorted. If the soft max
is large, you have a relentless
bias for better policies.
Or it can be less than one.
Here's some technical details of the
LaPlace approximation.
Parametric empirical base,
generalized linear modeling,
hashtag SPM.
Here's recipe. So this is kind of like
chapter six, but now it's model based
data analysis. Collect behavioral data.
Maybe the data has already been
collected. Maybe there's some data sets
that we already can use. Formulate a
POMDP. I wonder if this is as chapter
six, not as chapter seven. It could be
chapter seven as well. If it's discrete
time,
specify likelihood, perhaps we can,
in the coming weeks, check out SPM
Mdpvx,
and they mention the scripts,
data. This is nice. This will
be fun. Chapter seven. I mean, it is the
correct if they're using this type four.
Chapter seven. Chapter four.
So this looks pretty
cool, pretty interesting. We could walk
through some examples.
False inference,
computational pathology.
So it kind of ends like chapter eight
with a table of references and a
summary. So it's a pretty short chapter
and has
some formalisms, but it's only
from page 179 of the PDF to
196, so it's less than 20 pages.
The next chapter, I think, is the
longest chapter in the book. Which one
is chapter ten? Chapter ten, 197.
Yeah. That one's over 30 pages.
Yeah,
but it ends on a high note.
All right, well,
interesting conversations.
Thanks for this. We will come
back to chapter nine,
look through it, and then peep into ten,
go through ten, and really solidify our
understanding of the map
and I guess indirectly of the territory.
And then for those who want to join,
we'll probably continue the discussion
and especially start looking towards
those project ideas again. Like we
talked just a little earlier about
making a dot
zero sessions for the textbook.
It so I have to apologize.
I'm traveling for a few weeks, so I'm
going to miss the next several sessions.
It's all good. Thank you, Eric. Any
other comments people want to make or
I'll close the recording.
Okay, thank you.