You.
Hello. Welcome, everyone. It is October
25, 2023. We're in active inference for
the social sciences, and today we're in
a discussion section. It is Avel and I,
and we'll start off by just saying hello
and kind of reflecting on where we're at
with the course. Then in
we have the questions form that is on
the course website. It's in the video
description. Feel free to submit
questions via this form. And then today
we're going to look at the questions
that have been submitted and not
answered yet, and we'll just give some
thoughts on them. Also look for more
questions to arise in the live chat.
So with that, what do you want
to begin with, Avel? Feel free to give
any kind of overview or statement,
and then we'll jump to the specific
questions that have been submitted
before today and during today.
The only statement that I want to make
is the last presentation I did. So
prediction cause constraints to exist
would be our wealth summary of that.
But really, I don't have anything to say
that is more specific right now.
All right, well, this should be pretty
fun. Let's jump into some questions.
Okay.
What are the challenges and potential
solutions in using active inference to
model collective behaviors with various
environmental constraints?
Um, so the
challenges first is that in any model,
you have to pick what you include and
what you did not include. So when you
talk about boundary conditions, when you
talk about what's including the model,
you have to make hypothesis. Like, if I
tell you model another country that is
under sanctions, like North Korea or
Russia. Okay, how do you model that? Do
you make a set pace for every possible
product? Like, every dimension
accounts for a specific product or type
of product, and you have a zero if you
have access to sorry, a zero if you
don't have access to it, and one if you
have access to it. Okay, but what if we
have new things that happen that is not
very useful if you're interested in
innovation or something? So you will
have to make specific policies that will
produce specific questions that you want
to ask to the model. And using active
inference does
not change anything to that. And where
it is relevant is that you can
have endogenous evolution of constraints
using act inference, I think,
in a more meaningful sense than you'd
have with a pure, let us say, Hebian or
non representational framework
or a framework that is representational,
but where the space presentation is
like, hard coded. So there is a space
of models, let us say, of evolution of
social norms, where I think active
inference would have an edge
because active inference is built to
represent normativity and
intentionality, and it is not the case,
to my knowledge, of other, like, either
dynamicist or cognitiveist frameworks
for modeling.
Could you maybe restate and go into a
little more detail? Was it non
representational or indirect
specification of what?
Of the beliefs of the system.
So what's being directly specified?
What's directly specified? And then what
is being indirectly specified? In active
inference? Yeah, in active inference,
you have, at least in a sense,
correspondence between dynamical
constraints like information over where
the system is and belief that the system
holds that are akin to norms or
internal states. So beliefs or
intentions are things that are going
on inside. And to my knowledge, there is
no framework that makes an explicit
formal connection between the two.
You'd have dynamic framework where you
have stuff that happens and there is no
presentation or intentional states. And
you have things like utility theory
where you have to specify preemptively
what are the intentional states of the
agents, which are not
very relevant to represent the
endogenous evolution of social
constraints within a collective system.
So situation
where active inference would be useful
is to model.
I will try to remember the term Stuart
Kauffman used. Kaufmane fillin and
fillin in.
So I will share the can we both share
the screen? No, we can't. You can add it
directly in this coda
page.
Probably a little easier than just go to
the back end course code of page and
then follow the token. Yes. And then go
to the questions table and pop it out.
I don't have the questions that is on
your screen.
Just click on the little challenges
and potential solutions and then pop it
out.
It pop out what?
Just like next to the row. See this
expand row? And then you'll be in the
same place. What is the row?
C. There is no letters.
No. Just look visually at the expand
row. Look visually
at the expand row. Just click the expand
row on
the question that we're addressing and
you'll pop into this campus. The
question that we are addressing is not
on the page, at least on my terminal.
Are you looking at the public front end
or at the course back end? I'm looking
at the back end. Okay. And I do not have
a question. What are blah, blah, blah?
Oh, it is sub question.
What are the challenges? Okay, cool.
All right. Fun.
You were talking about Kaufman, though.
What was it? Yes, it's a paper
that he co signed whose manator is
Tepophilin critique of economic,
like I say rationality, but now they say
it's born in rationality. So the
Dictionary of Cognitive Biases approach
to modeling human behavior. And
basically the point of the paper, as I
understand it, is that you have an
evolution of the goals and norms that
shape a social ecology. And this kind
of open ended evolution of the
intentional states of the agent, I
think, can be addressed in a more
meaningful way with active inference
than with any other formal
framework I know.
There are several other aspects, I
think. So first to kind of restate
the challenges and then go to the
potential solutions and the advantages.
Like the advantages in principle and in
practice you started with identifying
the major any kind of modeling
challenges. So active inherits from all
of these modeling challenges or areas
that are difficult to step aside from
and then depending on the resources of
the group and whether it's 2023
or 2000 future time when there's
different tooling. So that is just about
the challenge of active inference
sometimes compared today with more off
the shelf approaches which also may or
may not work. But in an active you'll be
spending your time making something that
may or may not work, may or may not be
orders of magnitude more just
sophistication of a modeling setting
then the team is ready to again, that's
a general modeling point. But it's also
very easy to get into with activ and to
jump the gap between something that is
pedagogical and helps show something
like intuitive or cool and making
something, for example, that can be used
in high reliability settings. And that's
a jump that hasn't been necessarily
conveyed in the open source setting. So
it's difficult to see examples of
whereas there's kind of like production
type machine learning algorithms that
can at least be no, that's just a little
general point. So what are some
advantages precisely?
There's some really interesting concepts
related to this like indirect
specification. So like let's just say
that we were talking about the mountain
car example or a social variable
that seemed to be moving within a
certain range. Then the direct encoding
of that constraint would be
basically made outdated. Okay, now the
landscape changes and then all of a
sudden the mountain car can go twice as
far to a different direction. So if that
constraint had been explicitly encoded
about cognitive variables or about the
exposition of the mountain car, then the
model goes stale. But if what's encoded
is somehow a relation with an agent in
the environment so the mountain car has
10 can go left or right as
its affordances and everything that
builds from there. And then here's the
laws of physics or mechanics, such that
here's the weight of the car. And then
if the landscape changes or is modeled
as changing, then you get, oh, yeah,
now it can go further or shorter. In
this direction, but that's like an
outcome of the relationship between the
agent and the environment explicitly
represented as such versus
just looking at the outcome and then
putting constraints on the outcome.
Yes, to say we have historically
the concept of explanation that we have
inherited from the 19th 20th century is
that we explain by having a lawful
relationship between variables. And to
do that we have to press specify what
are the relevant variables. And this is
not a thing that exists with open ended
evolutionary dynamics. This is all in
the genital cognitive agency something
paper.
And so when we ask questions to a model
we don't want to have the answer. Yeah,
it will evolve anxiously. We don't
really know. This is not what is
expected basically so we tend not to
look at operanded evolutionary dynamics.
I would say that active inference has
some leverage to represent that that
other framework could not have because
of the relationship between constraints
as a clinical thing and beliefs as an
intentional statement.
Yeah. One thing that makes me think of
so when we're doing modeling based,
outcome based modeling whether for hobby
or for grad school, for job,
we're often in a setting that
either expects or rewards or accepts
only a converging answer.
Because it's being does insulin
in drosophila change their circadian
this or that? It's very converged
of a question already and it's something
where we're looking to reduce our
uncertainty about. So then that
closes off to the extent that it
converges it closes off divergent routes
not just of like doing and addressing
that question. That's more of a
methodological point. But then we don't
make models that can see
a more open ended horizon of what could
actually happen in the system because
that always adds more state
spaces that can be broken and unfolded.
So I guess again to the kind of kernel
of the question you've written these
very interesting sequence of papers
about symmetry breaking and all
of this. So how do you use that in
a way that goes beyond just stating
larger and larger state spaces or
feeling less and less confident when
it seems like a large piece of this is
that certain aspects of systems are
unprestatable.
Sorry, confident. But what precisely
unprestatable?
Unprestatable? Yes, I'm confident that
you cannot prestate the space of
possibilities or space of belief that an
agent can have and model upon an
evolution. Something that could like
that is by definition of the terms
something that could be argued is that
there is no such thing as a plane
devolution. But that
would be a very bold thing to claim and
most people would not say that
explicitly ever because it's
kind of obviously not the case. If there
is argument for it, I'd like to hear it.
But the argument that are
stated against the upper ended evolution
thing are basically,
you have, I would say, all rely on a
confusion between the fact that the law
of physics work, which they do, and the
idea that the specific language that
physics talks is a full and objective
representation of everything there is or
could be, which is like it's a
possibility we can discuss about it.
But this is a distinct possibility.
That the statement that the law of
physics work, which again they do.
Okay, cool. Well then just to sort
of close on this octave advantages many
interesting conceptual advantages, we
hope analytical and more
transdisciplinary or more holistically.
And also another huge piece is it's
connected to an always improving open
source computational environment? We
expect and prefer but in that case
linking a system in year X social
system or model. It's kind of like using
a Linux system that there could be some
developments like in message passing
algorithms or interoperability of
different generative models or category
theoretic augmentation of models
that are connected to the active
inference ontology all these different
kinds of synthetic technologies which we
can basically already imagine and to
some extent already have. It becomes
a way to map systems to a
lot. And that is not, as far as I
understand, possible without
kind of a first principles and
ecosystems of shared intelligence and
all these other kind of memes and themes
that we talk about all the time,
surprise, minimization things, doing as
most likely for them to do, paths of
least action, Bayesian mechanics.
Then there's a continuity of explanation
with the rock just being there and the
investor trading with this strategy, an
instrumental unifying account that
makes relatively minimal claims
about the territory that includes the
rock and the investing activity.
What did you add in.
What you said about message passing is
interesting to me because you have a
broad coalition of physicists,
mathematicians, social scientists,
people in academia who basically think
there is one language to nature and what
we do as scientists is to discover it.
And I do not think that holds water.
Not only because open evolution is a
thing which is a sufficient element
actually. But if you look at Mr.
Spacing, if you look at Quantum
Basinism, if you look at category
theory, open formally and conceptually
the possibilities that there are
different languages in the world and
they may be more or less interoperable
and they may be non reducible to each
other and then you start to ask
collision questions. I'd say especially
when implicitly or explicitly you are
interested in what determines the fact
that a specific language works in a
specific context. Why is not
going to go further down the math road.
But.
You have important compatibility,
interoperability result between major
fields of physics.
I will give a reference by John Bayes.
I don't know you pronounce it. I never
said this.
So we have important interoperability
results in fields of physics and
formal science and we
don't have a proof, however, that all
possible presentation of physics are
interoperable.
How do you say that? Interoperable,
interoperable, interoperable. Okay,
so they said it's wrong. No,
it's a great point. And what's really
interesting is like the relationship
between Bayes graphs.
First off, Bayes graphs being
analytically described and then
computationally implementable is on the
order of decades old. And then as we
kind of explored just yesterday in Live
Stream 55.0, the relationship
between the Bayes graph and forney
graphs which enabled message passing to
be done procedurally to optimize a Bayes
graph which just brings all of these
computational, all these analytical
connections. But that wasn't understood
until it was and that was only slightly
over two decades ago. So then
in fact, those kinds of results and
developments reflect the
changing social and scientific niche.
So I don't know, maybe this is a
different question, but science as a
social activity and then I
don't know, how does that ground our
work or give us more? What.
So about
the whole language thing, I don't know
where it's at now, but at least ten
years ago it seemed that
you can have message passing.
You can have bias and coherence of state
of observable that does not rely
explicitly on the probabilities as
in a dispersion that is embedded in a
specific set space. You can have bias
and coherence that preexist to the
representation in which probability is
embedded. And if there was a way to
cross this and message passing, you'd
have a pretty straightforward
road to straighter
account of contextuality and social
construction. I said this with scare
quotes. Great note.
Exciting for quantum context and quantum
social and scripts and constraints and
norms. Let's close that question for
now, though. Nice. Okay.
How can yeah, great question. Thank you
to whoever asked. And again, video
description. You can ask it'll appear
and we'll see if anyone writes more
questions during the stream.
How can or does a framework theory,
principle of everything articulate with
moral, normative, ethical,
deontic considerations?
So I think it is addressed in a
good amount of detail by an activist.
How you relate a theory of biological
individuation to a theory of ethics.
I do not have a good grip on this
literature, so I have high
level intuitive opinion on that.
But this is not like state of the art.
And okay,
basically I'd say this flows well
with stoic virtue etics.
Things act according to the nature. So
you may as well work so that your nature
is good. And then you have recursivity
in accounting what is good and what is
not. And I do not see straightforward
analytical way to resolve this
ambiguity. I said circularity or
ambiguity. Both apply.
Yeah. So I think Evan Thompson has
worked nuts and may have a
much better answer to how
we relate theories of being and theories
of physics. Oh, Varila did actually.
Yeah, I guess my sort of
short answer would there would be first
just we would have to hear a lot more
even possible perspectives, but without
even hearing them can at least maybe say
that there is an articulation and a
meter stick as an instrument. And this
kind of goes actually to that question
about the Bayes spaces and what
is preconditioned. So in what ways is
the meter stick articulate
with downstream ethical
frameworks? What ought to be done? Or
just normative more broadly,
there's downstream decisions that the
meter stick is agnostic too, and then
the meter stick is also a social result
that is itself downstream of other norms
and constraints, biotic abiotic
constraints, regularities of
space time.
I would say what
we can do with theory of sense making,
be it active inference or inactivism,
is to just describe
what we mean by normativity analytics?
What are the underlying natural
processes? When I say natural, I do not
mean by opposition to social. Those
processes are biological and social at
the same time. And that
may bring reflexivity or distance to
account of normativity. That may prove
some of them incoherent or ill advised.
That will not give you a solution to
what is ethical and what is not,
notably. Because the most natural way
to derive ethics
from something like an activism or
something like active inference is that
both those framework are centered around
biological individuation. So we may say
that biological individuation is good.
Actually, that sounds sensible, but then
the question is biological individuation
for whom? Because you have a right, I
guess, or desire will at least to exist.
But soros cancer cells within your body,
who trumps who? I don't know. Not from a
purely sweetie account.
There is no way you can
straightforwardly, ambiguously derive a
prescriptive notion of good from any
physics, any descriptive account of the
world you will love
when you do, when you make nomadic
claims, you have goals because you are
linking and because of active inference
enactivists. We know that cognition is
embedded in no activity, in the
autonomy, in the biological activity of
the agent. So the theory that you are
framing is in some way motivated, even
if you don't know how or admit that it
is. And then I'd say from there
it does not quite destroy the project of
an objective system of ethics, but it
makes it much harder to refund.
So yeah, I'd say you can derive a lot of
negative results from descriptive theory
of like, I wouldn't say ethics because
ethics are non descriptive, but
descriptive theory of how ethics come to
be. I would say that it is hard,
if not impossible, to derive positive
results if someone tried to do it.
I'd like to see what this is.
Wow. Thank you. Avil. That last piece
was very interesting. Many results,
many ant
colonies with their behavior to model
many real situations, to understand
social constraints and norms in
instrumentally with descriptions
that are then in the discussion section
of the paper. And the data are the
data and those are the descriptive
aspects. It's a different kind of data
in a slight way, but there's already
enough to describe and interpret from
what would be merely described. And it
is very hard to derive positive results
first. It's a hard domain to make
positive results in not just ones that
make people feel good, but by positive,
like positivism, like justified,
true assertions about a metaphysical
space. So it's hard to derive positive
results about normativity and the kind
of areas that this person asked. These
are all areas that are and
it's hard to use a quantitative theory,
which is almost it's an abstraction or
it's just one language. It's hard to use
that to make positive results
external to the system, harder to make
external to the system. Positive results
internal to the system are dime a dozen.
But then to really make that reflexive
loop that you described between
what is and what we expect and prefer,
which is actually woven up in an
interesting way in act INF rather
than two kind of diverge timelines like,
what we quote, expect to happen, like a
prediction of the, likeliest, future and
then a second timeline that's like,
well, what I would really prefer to be
doing in Actimp, the agent just has
one expectation preference which
loads up on the pragmatic value.
But that gives a unified approach
towards one's expectations of how things
will be and what they expect prefer them
to be.
I would say that at Vibe check level
active inference flows well with the
idea that empowerment is good actually
but make it a formal
relation would be quite hard.
You could say that inference vibes well
with the notion that everyone knowing
their place is good, which is quite the
opposite. So I don't
see an amigos relation between active
inference and any ethical
framework I can think of.
I would say again that it flows
well with virtue ethics framework
because of the relation between one's
action and one's nature. According to
axio inference, nature being here in
Australia term, that is maybe not the
best term, but I'm literally using
production of before Christ text.
So yeah, nature is not that bad,
just not what we mean in
the context of 19th 20th discussions.
Yeah, that's a very complex topic with
definitely a lot of rich work on our
cities and people nature, our humans,
animals and that sort of
homo sapiens type discourse. And then
how does active inference frame the
relationship with the niche in
terms of entanglement or communication
or co action, intra action,
communication and influence through the
blanket? Where does that go beyond just
describing? It doesn't have to.
I think a sort of base level in what you
referred to here is like that artifact.
The product of the work, which is what
the work is about, can be a jumping
off point for other directions.
And so the work of active inference
modeling can be in what it leads to.
It's not always internal
to the model that the improved
awareness or better decision is
realized.
I can see one quite straightforward and
I don't think it is entirely broken
way to relate ethics to active inference
is ethics like
not ethics normativity as a social
feminine is a collective phenomenon.
It's about social relationships. And you
could apply descriptive theory
of human behavior and like human social
aggregated collective behavior to
find out what traits in Australia are
prone to survival or adaptivity and
you could say that those traits are good
actually by construction of what we
mean by ethics. That could be Bayes
Coherence claim and then you could be
interested in what traits make
organization durable.
This is the only logically,
straightforward way I see. But that
would tend to identify
as good things that I would not see as
good. Like feudalism. It lived quite
a long time. Well, feudalism, let us say
old school empires with no claimed
representations or power by the,
how do you say populace.
And you
could basically renormalize this theory
not around clock time but around.
I. Don'T know, metric of lifetime, how
much things happen within organization.
And then you'd start having something
that is less obviously wrong. And you
could have basically ethics be about
optimization of specific parameters that
can be addressed by descriptive
framework, but you'd have to make a lot
of jumps to get there. And while
I do not see an obvious problem to that,
it is very possible that we
would not like the conclusion of such
optimization thing. And again,
if you want to model something, you have
to decide what are the parameters of
interest and you can be wrong about
that. So here again, you do not have an
ambiguous even at a purely descriptive
level, you do not have an ambiguous
application of anything to anything.
Would say that more empowerment is good,
actually.
And I would say this goes at many nested
scales of organization and
I would say it has somehow something to
do to the physics of electrical
integration, but only
in a vibe check way.
Nothing wrong with that.
Yeah, especially with some of the recent
work like the variational synthesis with
eco evo devo and the connections between
the statistical concepts of persistence
or thinkness from free energy principle
related to remeasurement of the observer
or the organism of themselves. That
concept of repeated measurement being
compatible in our work and in other
related works. Basically with fitness,
if there's a height distribution of
trees in the forest and then a certain
time point later, the height
distribution is the same. That was
stabilizing dynamics.
We could say stabilizing evolution or
stabilizing selection. If it moved, it
moved. And so
how do since there is such a coupling
between things being as they are and
basically what the distribution
of what is there is described both this
stoic way but also this kind of
evolutionary biology way. So does active
inference offer any other
or complementary perspective other than
just the kind of strengths and
weaknesses of
using fitness,
phenotypic fitness or memetic fitness as
its own justification?
To say that is to say that something is
good because it exists. This is not a
strong position to take. So this is why
you'd have quite
high level of difficulty to derive
anything prescriptive from anything
descriptive. The function is not the
same. You can make relation between the
two. No, ethics is purely blind about
nature, of nature is purely
ethically unmotivated.
But to have formulation between the two
is probably not possible, at least
highly nontrivial.
Okay, so to kind of close on this
question how does a free energy
principle as a principle for everything
and active inference as an implementable
framework for applying free energy
principle systems. How does that
articulate with these broader, very deep
and fundamental human social contexts?
Short answer seems to be it's
a lot like other scientific ideas,
inherits a lot of their challenges and
frictions and situations. Also there
appear to be some interesting promising
routes or themes to weave in.
However, even with a very charitable or
optimistic interpretation, there seems
some in principle challenges with
these areas that make
certain kinds of claims, perhaps not
even within the proximate understanding
we have of active inference, but people
should totally write in the live chat or
add comments and stuff. I mean it's just
interesting question. Okay,
how are higher order beliefs about doing
better than expected at PEM? Probably
prediction error minimization integrated
into the architecture of the agent's
internal model of external dynamics and
itself in those dynamics. My thought
here is that we have prior beliefs to
fulfill certain self evidencing
expectations, e. G homeostatic
predictions. But how do those interact
with these higher order predictions
which appear to my mind to deny or
negate the fundamental priors insofar as
they predict the agent to go over and
above the levels of prediction error
minimization which otherwise might be
achieved by fulfilling those fundamental
priors they
gave their thought? Let's return to the
original question.
I do not know like I know that
comparison to a baseline homeostatic
level of prediction arm innovation is
quite important thing in the shop
psychiatry, possibly in the work of
park's homes. I do not know how that's
implemented actually in computational
models. So I'd rather not
answer progressively. Ben White
should be more informed about these
things. Yeah. Or maybe you Daniel.
Well,
I mean the word that seems to be doing
the work is integrated.
So higher beliefs about doing better
than expected, prediction error
minimization or we can just say free
energy minimization. So this was
explored in the active inference work.
So if the free energy
was decreasing as expected,
it was associated with neutral valence.
If things were improving better than
expected it was associated with positive
valence and if things were doing
worse than expected, it was negative
valence. So because of the
ability to make hierarchical active
models and just hierarchical
bayesian models in general, it is
possible to talk about these beliefs,
about beliefs, metacognitive beliefs.
So it is possible to make models
that have expectations about
how well even an optimization process is
going to go and then a computational
psychiatrist or whatever may associate
that with the affect.
How is that integrated into the
agent's internal model of external
dynamics? Well, shortest answer is to
sketch it out how one sees it and then
it becomes either there or not. But just
in general, if the internal model
includes these higher order beliefs
about doing better than expected,
then that's the agent's generative model
that then interfaces or articulates with
external dynamics.
So you could have some environment that
has environmental regularity or
dynamics. Or that are influenceable or
not. And then you could deploy two
agents. One of them that has the
baseline generative model and the other
one has this doing better than expected
layer that the questioner is asking
about. And then they can do parameter
sweeps and maybe adding this higher
order belief increases the state space a
lot and so it increases the
computational costs a lot, but some
interesting pockets of behavior are
found, or the behavior in that setting
ends up looking the exact same, but in
another setting it would have been
different. A lot of these questions
point towards very important modeling
questions which can basically only be
pointed at because so much is going to
depend on what the actual model goal is.
Okay,
where can I find the recommended reading
list mentioned in the lectures?
You it's.
So where we have
the slides from the
lecture, they're in live streams.
Just go to the big table and find the
slides. If you find a lecture that
doesn't have slides, just let us know
and we'll add it.
Where things were just mentioned
in the lectures? That's a great
question. And our goal at the active
inference journal, beyond just
transcribing and publishing and adding
captions and translating and everything
of these live streams, we would like to
also do more bibliographic work
so that the books that people mention we
can also have in that open source
versioned journal. So we
generate the first version of the
transcript, people update it and improve
it. Oh, what was the name of that
author? What book are they talking about
here? And then we can actually have a
unified bibliography section for the
stream. So if that sounds interesting to
you and you'd benefit from it, then
surely many, many others will too. So if
you're excited to see that kind of
active inference journal work, I highly
encourage recommend it.
Abel, what else will you add?
Same I can have nothing to add.
Yeah.
Okay, well,
we can look at some of the other
questions that were added that others
wrote. People in live chat can add
question or they can go to the course
website and ask
a new question.
Do you want to look
at one of the previous ones or do
you have any other just thoughts you
want to bring up? Not really.
The first ones were answered.
They were asked weeks ago. So there is a
relatively low likelihood that going
over them again would be very helpful.
I think we can cut the discussion.
Cool. But the important things that are
not treated now can be treated in
conclusion anyway. Okay, so what are the
next steps then for the course?
Next step is, did a lot of people
register for the presenting in the
conclusion session?
I haven't gotten any specific responses
or like titles yet. Okay,
so we see if people do that.
Yeah, we can write another message,
including even a short video message or
just a written one. And then also ask
specific people also if anyone
is interested to present something, but
they're not really sure the format or
they want pre recorded.
We're just kind of exploring and seeing
what the people who are following along
live want to do and also trying out
things that we think futures will want
to do too. So if someone
has an idea on that, we're definitely
open to it. It any
last thoughts?
No, I am good. Cool. All right.
Thank you, then. See you, AVO.
Ciao.