You.
Hello and welcome, everybody. This is
physics as information processing.
It's October 28, 2023,
and we're in discussion
six, so we'll see where and how
and when we go. But to begin with,
thank you for watching. If you're
watching live, please feel free to write
any questions or comments in the live
chat. As this is our last discussion,
we're going to be probably ranging
broadly, so looking forward to
people's comments there. Otherwise,
perhaps we can all go around first and
say hello or just give any thoughts or
reflections to get things going.
And then we'll jump into some of the
questions and answers and look at some
of these great thoughts that have been
sent and responded to. So perhaps
Dean and then Harrison. David,
any just overall thoughts or comments
to get us going?
Thanks. Daniel. I guess my overall
impression was that I think that the way
that the entire series was organized
and structured allowed for these kinds
of conversations that we're having
today, which I think are really
valuable. As you can see on the slide
here, I think a lot of question
and answer tends to be focused around
what is,
whereas the conversations that we've
had, we can sort of tease that apart a
little bit and ask questions around what
if? And get into the counterfactual
piece of it and interact around that.
And I've really, really appreciated
that. So that's my overall sense that
we haven't left it sort of on the page.
We've actually been able to sort of
breathe some life into it through these
conversations.
Cool. Haris?
Yeah, I just wanted to say that it was a
great series. We all learned a lot, and
we got the opportunity to even ask
questions to Chris and
get back some very insightful answers
that they are very helpful in order to,
let's say, push the envelope forward.
Overall, this has been a great series.
I've enjoyed it a lot. And while
conversing with some of my colleagues,
they also enjoyed it. So the feedback is
great. And thanks to active Inference
Institute for facilitating this, and to
you guys. Thank you. ThanK you
and welcome. David, if you want to just
begin with, any thoughts or what brought
you into the game in the bottom of the
9th?
Well, in school,
I was actually trying to use free
energy to develop some sort of a network
of agents that were deciding what
information to send and what states to
be in based on each other's
approximation of each other's states.
So I registered at the beginning, but
then I guess life happened and I didn't
really cross the page.
Now I'm just kind of opening up to
things and participating more in the
world that I exist in. And this is a
natural. This is really tied to
the work that I was doing in school. I
don't know if this is a place to ask a
question, so I'm. Not going to ask any
questions. But that's like the urgent.
Let's begin with that. Okay. Yeah, so I
was thinking about. I'm still confused
about like Markov Blanket and non
localism.
How would those two. What about work
together? Well, like, non localism,
seems to me that an entity could be
distributed arbitrarily in
whatever is. I don't know if the
universe is like Spacetime is what is,
or if that's just a construction that we
create through the information
processing and putting relation,
enunciating or rendering the
information in a way where it's like all
the related components can be mutually
distinguished. But the Markov blanket
seems to be highly local. I don't know,
maybe this is what, like, I'm confused
about this. It seems to be highly local,
and it seems like everything is
connected with everything. So I'm kind
of confused about how an entity could be
defined with a Markov blanket while at
the same time what seems to be
completely intertwined. Non local,
mutually defined.
Yes, Dean, please. So can I just.
David, just clarification. Are you
thinking that local and non local is
somehow similar to maybe arbitrary?
I'm thinking local is within a volume
and non local is distributed like
a sphere, like a small sphere, where all
the information is within a sphere and
everything within that sphere is
causally relevant and Everything without
is causally irrelevant. But then I'm
thinking of a Markov blanket as a sphere
and everything on the inside is like
independent statistically from
everything on the outside. I guess I'm
asking around, where do you see that
being placed? Do you see that being
placed arbitrarily?
When you set that up, whenever you
decide where that boundary exists,
are you asking because it's local or
it's non local because it's wherever
inside and outside is present?
Is the. What's the word I'm looking for?
Are you wondering about how that doesn't
seem to be consistent, that 1 minute it
can be here and then the next minute it
can change and arbitrarily end up being
in a different place?
It doesn't seem to me that that's the
confusion. It's more like,
you know, David Bohm's implicate and
explicated order and the idea that the
explicated order is like one hologram.
There's like the hollow movement where
each layer affects each layer and the
explicated is all at once explicate
order, mutual relatedness. I don't know.
I don't know if these words are
incoherent completely,
like, and then,
but then the Markov blanket, like, I'm
I'm taking the example of my skin. I
don't know if that's even good example,
but my skin is like a Markov blanket.
But then if everything is mutually
related and explicated order, this whole
body is submerged in the same field that
everything else is submerged in. And in
that sense, everything is linked to
everything. There's no. I don't know.
Like.
Let me try adding a few pieces.
So welcome.
Andrew and Chris will hopefully join,
too. Here we go.
Okay, opening act.
Just to catch up, Chris and Ander
David asked about the Markov blanket
and about if how everything
is connected to everything and how we
associate Markov Blanket or the
holographic screen with localism and non
locality. Do you want to give any quick
thoughts on this, or are you asking. Me
if you want to? Either of you could. I
don't know. Let's wait a minute for
Chris to show up.
Yeah, I'm here now. Yeah,
I'm glad you found the way.
Question. Did you guys go through the
slides of last time, the lecture on.
No, no. We just began and started with a
Markov blanket question. Yeah,
I think you wouldn't hurt to talk about
that, because a big part of that last
lecture was the copy and diversify
notion as a universal feature in
mean, naively, I think know the creation
of new boundaries is implicit in there.
So maybe Chris can comment, but I
also thought it was very worthy of
mentioning today. Know, the cycle of
error correction, memory and so on. So
those would be my only two comments in
the agenda for today. Maybe Chris can
say a few words, but I didn't mean to
interrupt. So, Markov Blanket, we can
pivot it to, I'm sure.
Okay, I think I'm seeing this question.
Is this a question about the definition
of Markov Blanket?
There's something about I can't actually
see the entire. No, it's not a
question on my screen. Oh, it's not a
question on your. Question on your
screen. Right.
But could you tell me what the question
is again? Yeah, David, just restate it
how you see it.
Well, the question was if
everything is mutually connected and
mutually defined and interconnected,
and there's non localism in the sense
that everything is mutually connected
and mutually defined. And I'm kind of
implicitly working with the
assumption that the implicit explicit
order makes sense. And the explicit is,
like one hologram. And it's lost audio
altogether now.
Oh, I still hear him. Oh, the audio.
Chris?
Chris. Yeah,
I lost at least half of that audio.
Just dropped out.
Try to. Sorry about that.
If everything is kind of explicated,
like, if it's information in the brain
is kind of rendering it all at once
together, I'm just confused. And the
whole body is submerged the
whole body is submerged in it. If I look
in the mirror, the whole body is
submerged in it, and it's all non local.
By that, I mean it's all connected
together and mutually defined and
mutually necessary to even make sense of
any piece of it, if there is even such a
thing as a piece. And I'm wondering.
So thaT's one way of looking at it. And
then the other way is, like, the local
to me, it seems like there's, like, the
skin Markov blanket, and it's kind of
local. And I'm kind of confused
as to how those things kind of worked.
Like, how those things.
It seems like all the information in a
sphere, a sphere could be a Markov
blanket. And then on the inside and the
outside, they're statistically
independent, is that the whole movement
on the inside and the outside, because
of the Markov blanket, separates those.
But then if this whole body is submerged
in this thing that's mutually related.
I'm just confused as to how.
I don't know. I'm confused as to how
those things work together.
I'm not sure I understand your question,
but I suspect the answer has to do with
whose point of view we're talking about.
So, if you
are the system that's in. So let's fix a
Markov blanket someplace.
If you're the system on the inside,
then all you can see is what's encoded
on the blanket, and you have
no independent access to what the
dynamic says on the outside. So you
don't actually know what the dynamics is
on the outside. And similarly,
if you're on the outside now, if you're
somehow able to view the whole system,
you can see the whole system as having
some joint dynamics.
But if the whole system is
isolated, then there isn't anybody on
the outside, kind of by definition. So
the idea of a whole dynamics is just a
theoretical postulate that we make to
make the mathematics make sense. Now,
if you move to from
the classical formulation to the quantum
formulation, then it's possible to
prove a very nice theorem, which is that
if you're inside a
holographic screen,
you can't measure the entanglement
entropy across the screen.
What that means is that you can't know
that your state is conditionally
independent of what's going on outside.
So if you're inside a holographic
screen, you can't know that you're not
entangled with whatever's outside.
So you can't even know whether you have
a well defined state in a sense.
And sort of,
I think the same thing would probably
hold true from the point of view inside
a Markov blanket, that you
wouldn't be able to know whether your
Markov blanket had holes in it or
something like that. The problem is, in
the classical formulation, you assume
there's no analog of entanglement.
So there's no analog of entanglement
entropy. So I think the strongest thing
you can say is you don't actually know
your statistical relationship to what's
going on outside, but you still can only
see what's encoded on the blanket.
Thank you, Chris. If I could add a few
more pieces. So, David, you described
everything connected to everything. For
a system with that kind of a base graph,
there aren't Markov blankets, because a
Markov blanket is the set of nodes that
make two other sets of nodes
conditionally independent. So in a fully
connected setting, again leading
to the question, what is outside of
that? But in a fully connected setting,
you don't have a blanket as such.
In fact, the Bayesian Graph describes
the factorization, or the articulation
and the sparsity of the system. So it is
a connectedness that is usually much,
much sparser than everything connected
to everything. But that's not to say
that differences can't make a difference
at a distance. It's just that they
propagate through a local causal
structure. And then Spacetime is
constructed by certain kinds of
cognitive agents. That was one of the
key aspects of this course.
And so we can take as primary
the topology of the active inference
agent environment relation.
And then Markov
Blanket is just the sensorium on
the inbound and the action capacity on
the outbound. One question, though, I do
have to that is, what about the non zero
gravitational effect, for example, of
something that's distant in space and
time? Of course, Markov Blanket
don't have to be spatial temporal. They
can be in arbitrary state spaces. But
how do we deal with those kinds of long
range influences?
That's my question. Yeah. Well,
here I think it's useful to contrast
Newtonian gravity with Einsteinian
gravity. Newtonian gravity
is infinite range and instantaneously
acting, whereas Einsteinian
gravity is infinite range, but it's
locally encoded. So the
Einsteinian gravity that you feel is
your local measurement of the
curvature of your local bit of
Spacetime. So that is very much
happening on your Markov blanket,
right? It's a local measurement, local
in Spacetime. So let's assume there's a
Spacetime that's objective and
characterizes everything,
then you're locally measuring it on your
blanket, and that's what you feel as
gravitational attraction or your mass.
Whereas in Newtonian or Laplacian
gravity,
you don't have that sense of locality,
right. As soon as something changes
anywhere in the universe, it affects
you. So Einstein
was struggling, of course, to make
gravity consistent with
electromagnetism, where it was clear
that forces are transmitted at finite
speed, the speed of light. And he didn't
have the idea of a graviton moving at
the speed of light, but he did have this
idea of local measurement. So non
locality was anathema to Einstein, and
that's basically why he spent so much
trouble removing it from physics. And
that's why he hated the idea of
entanglement so much, because it seemed
to him that from a Spacetime point of
view, it had to be non local.
Daniel, can I bring up a point at this
point? So I think this is somewhat
relevant to a question I really wanted
to ask Chris, which is in lecture six.
I remember minute 23. I wish I had
written it down, but I can roughly
remember there was that
phylogenetic graph, and you see life
growing in a self similar way,
just like the genealogical tree
of species, same thing happens at the
individual level with growth and so on.
Anyways, I found that fascinated in the
sense that the degrees of freedom, of
life as a whole grow. Right. And around
that minute 23, you made a comment,
well, then the environment must be
shrinking. And you tie this with
Spacetime. And something about Spacetime
from the physics side, we also have that
we have cosmological inflation and
Whatnot. Are any of those things
related? That remark, I feel like, was
made in passing, and I think there's a
lot there to be said. It also maybe
shed some light on the
emergent Spacetime issue. If it does
emerge from a more basic ontological
object, like the Tensor network and the
degrees of freedom in the tensor
network, is it fair to say that life,
as it grows, gets more of those degrees
of freedom, but then somehow anything
that happens to Spacetime is an
illusion? In that sense, I don't even
know if I'm familiar in that question.
Right. But I think Chris knows what I'm
talking about. Yeah,
the comment makes the most sense in the
context of the state space itself,
leaving aside Spacetime. So if you
think of a Hilbert space and draw
a boundary someplace that separates
what we're going to call life from what
we're going to call non life. And
essentially, what life has done over the
past 3 billion years is incorporate
bits of the non life part of the state
space into life. Right?
Total biomass is increasing,
so more and more of the available mass
is getting incorporated into living
things. And so if we can
kind of heuristically fold Spacetime in
and say.
You. Know, in the, in the, in the
locality, in the locale of Earth, and
over this fairly short time period,
the expansion of Spacetime is more or
less negligible. So life
is actually taking up more space now
than it did certainly
at the time of LUCA, when all of us
weren't around. But there is just one
probably population of cells that we're
descendants of.
But the point about the Hilbert space
is just the point that if
you've divided it in two and you move
the boundary, then one system gets
bigger at the expense of the other
system, which now has less of the
Hilbert space.
So that's all that remark really is,
right? As the system,
in a sense, takes over degrees of
freedom of the.
That's. In that case, it becomes a
different system at every time step from
the point of view of it has now a
different Hilbert space and different
internal dynamics. So physically it's a
different thing. But when we
look at it, we say, oh, this thing is
continuous through time. It is
expanding, it's growing, it's
developing, evolving, whatever.
Right? So then, I guess,
comment, just a question that just
occurred as you were talking, that begs
the question, does that biomass come to
dominate all the degrees of freedom in
the universe? Is that presumably there's
a tension with the rate at which those
degrees of freedom are growing and the
rate at which Spacetime is growing,
does the growth of Spacetime, in terms
of those degrees of freedom that may be
more fundamental, amount to loss in
error correction capacity?
And maybe more speculatively, how you
reconcile this with loss of
thermodynamics.
Are you implying that life is going to
come to dominate everything and fill up
the entirety of the known universe?
Yeah, I think that's a stretch.
But I
would say at this point that until we
have a mature theory of quantum gravity
that makes enough empirical predictions
to be testable. It's not
clear, at least to me, how the
whole emergent Spacetime picture fits
together with the inflationary
picture or the expanding Spacetime
picture,
in some sense, taking a strict Hilbert
space view. If the universe is
an isolated system, then its Hilbert
space is fixed.
And so your question,
in a sense, becomes, what's the
relationship between Spacetime and this
silver space? Are what we
think of as Spacetime degrees of
freedom, real degrees of freedom, or
not? And seems
to me that question really isn't
resolved, and I'm not sure at this point
how to resolve it.
HArris yeah, just have
something small to add.
Overall, this is very interesting, and
these questions are very deep.
What I wanted to add is that I was
thinking the initial question regarding
Markov Blanket, and I also have some
question that it's related with it. But
I will ask Chris later. What I
wanted to add now is that basically,
Markov Blanket are a way of describing
the boundaries of a system in terms of
statistical mechanics or statistics,
let's say. And essentially,
from what I understand, they are
paramount in order to define observers
and also the systems under observation.
So any physical system that can be seen
as an observer with a Markov
blanket, let's say, so now, trying to
tie it all up with active inference.
Well, active inference, as I understand
it, it implies that the system is
actively referring to its external
states from its internal states in an
effort to both learn, let's say,
and adapt to the environment.
So this goes
back and ties with this metaphorical
link, let's say, with the skin. This is
how I understand it. And it
actually means that a system with a
Markov blanket can actually be seen as
performing physics as information
processing, which is the back of this
series that Haris is offering to us.
And a final comment. In terms of non
locality. Non locality can actually be
seen as a form of information
processing. So this is what I wanted to
add.
Did you say how non locality is a form
of information processing? Yes,
this is how I understand it.
What do you think about that, Chris?
If we put it in
terms of entanglement,
entanglement is a useful
resource for information processing,
but it's only a usable resource if
it's combined with classical
communication, either across time or
across space.
So entanglement
is only useful as a resource if
different observers can act locally,
I. E. Without interfering with each
other on the
quantum resource.
So if
you think of entanglement as non
locality, if you embed it in Spacetime
in that way, then it
is useful as a computational
resource. But the observers also
have to transmit
classical communications in
a way that fully complies
with locality. So in a Bell EPR
type experiment. For example, if you
have Alice in one lab and Bob in the
other lab making measurements of some
entangled state, then at some point to
know that the state is entangled, they
have to send their classical records to
each other as classical communication
and then deal with those records
locally.
So in a sense,
non locality in that sense is useful for
computation, but it's only useful if you
also have locality.
Great. Thank you.
Actually, I'm working on
a novel notion. Let's say.
That is something like, takes the notion
of entanglement and transform it in the
following sense. I'm actually thinking
of maximum tacklement as
a resource for classical computation.
So that's something I am actually
exploring. I find it to be a
nice concept.
Did you say maximum unentanglement?
Yes. Maximum separability? Yeah.
Okay, that makes sense. I mean, we need
maximum separability.
We need to be able to factor a state
space to talk about two different
observers. So to talk about conditional
independence.
Yeah. In my head, this maximum
entanglement as a resource can actually
be expended to perform classical
computation or even to increase the
coherence of a quantum system.
So I'm playing with that notion a bit.
Thank you.
Can I ask one thing really quick about.
Yeah, okay.
So apparently, from what I don't
understand very much, but from Bohr,
apparently. The. Whole experimental
setup was one entity
that couldn't be broken down into
constituent pieces that are interacting,
but had to be taken as one entity, from
what I understand, and apparently
Einstein's view was. Well, I really
don't know what his view was, but
apparently it's not one entity. It can
be broken down into localized pieces
that are interacting. And apparently
they couldn't get along. Like Warren
Einstein. Apparently there was like a
party or something, and then they all
congregate to separate parts of the room
and didn't really interact. And
apparently it was because they had these
opposing views on the same thing of
breaking down the interconnectedness
into separate constituent subsystems.
And even like taking the partial trace,
there was one universal function taking
the partial trace, which Puzzley defined
the subsystems. Whenever perfectly,
it's all tied together. But I can't
really explicit. I'm trying to say.
Everyone.
These seem like two very opposed view.
They seem like very alternative views.
Like on one side you have kind
of like an indivisible whole. On the
other side you have locality where it's
almost like there's like a sequence of
measurements leading up to an ego, an
eye that then measures as like a real
entity, as another one is like the
observer and the observed are one thing,
they cannot be meaningfully separated.
Maybe functionally they can be
separated, but as actually existing
subcomponents, they cannot be defined
strictly. From what I understand. One of
them is saying, yes, you can define
these subsystems and they really do
exist as separate entities. The other
one is saying, that's just kind of like
a useful way to organize information as
to operate on that information, deposit
a subject and an object, and to have the
subject operate on the object is a
useful way for thinking to separate
itself. And it seems like this is closer
to Bohr than the other one is closer.
Well, apparently that's a distinction
of, like, Boer and Einstein, from what I
understand. From what I understand,
which is, please correct me if it's.
Yeah, I just wanted to put that out
there. And I don't know what that's
going to spawn in terms of responses,
but yes. Well, I think that's a fair
characterization of the Bohr Einstein
debate, actually,
to. Add a response there,
whether it actually exists. It seems
like in one of those framings, you had
an observer looking at something, and if
we define actually existing in a
relational observed setting, then to
the observer the measurement actually
exists. Prepare, measure, prepare,
measure. And then from another
perspective, viewing that setup,
then it's the observer of a setup.
And so it's just, again, to Chris's
first point about what perspective, and
this is one of the most essential pieces
that the blanket screen relationality
brings into play, is there isn't a view
from nowhere, but there is a perspective
that may have a definite answer,
and yet there are multiple perspectives
that have complementary answers in our
scenario. Daniel, can I speak for a
minute? Oh, yeah. I was muted earlier.
I didn't realize. I meant to ask.
David, I don't have an answer to your
question, but I was wondering if you
could reformulate. Would it be fair to
reformulate your question as saying,
are blankets objective or not? Is the
Bohr Einstein debate equivalent to that?
And then second, and I guess this may be
for Chris, I was skimming through the
answers, and one of them was talking
about how one of the big tensions
between general relativity and quantum
theory is the idea of object
persistence. And I don't know how to
articulate it either, but I feel like it
was more or less what you were getting
at, David, is that correct?
Yeah, I think that's another way to put
it. And also the thing you said about
the third person looking at those
systems, if there's multi agent
communication,
that's kind of the thing that I'm kind
of stuck on in terms of trying to
understand this. Because if there's a
third agent looking okay, those two are
subsumed in the information on the
holographic screen.
I don't know. Anyways, so that's where
I'm kind of.
I think a delightful thing to read here
is Gene Wigner's paper
where he introduces the Wigner's friend
thought experiment. And I think it's
from. There's a
book called the Scientist Speculates.
The editor is someone named Good,
good.
And Wigner has a paper in this book. I
think it's 1961. And it's
also the paper where Wigner
talks about consciousness
being an essential concept in quantum
theory. But the thought experiment is
that Wigner's friend is doing an
experiment in his laboratory and making
observations. And Wigner is
outside the laboratory.
And Wigner has
to regard his friend as in some sort of
superposition with his instrument. He
has to regard his friend as entangled
with his friend's instruments.
Until Vignner can actually interact
locally with the friend. And make a
measurement of the friend's state.
And so it makes Wigner's
friend and his apparatus look like an
entangled pair. And Wigner now
looks like an experimenter who's
operating on just one part of an
entangled pair.
But Wigner himself tells the story very
nicely. And that
sort of historical text,
I think, is always useful to have a look
at and see how the people themselves
were responding to this idea.
And Wigner is quite perplexed by this
thought experiment.
And I think all of those people,
they were quite honestly mystified with
what observation actually is and what
consciousness is. And all of these other
questions that people are a little bit
scared to talk about in the ensuing
several decades.
Self reference.
Yeah, you can go ahead. Self reference
seems to be like there's this ancient
symbol of the uroboros. The output is
the input. It feeds on itself. Even like
consciousness. I have to contextualize,
to contextualize, like it's self
referential. Everything refers to
itself. And then at the end, self
reference is where all the paradoxes are
like, this sentence is false. Or all I
know is that I know nothing. These are
all paradoxical statements. So there's
some sort of mystery cell division of
self reference. That ancient view is
that it's like embryogenesis,
cosmogenesis, same thing.
I don't know. It seems to me that
there's some sort of mystery that's so.
It's like the mind. It just eludes I
don't know. Thinking tries to make these
thought systems, but it just slips out.
I can't grasp it. I don't mean,
but that's already a conclusion, which I
don't necessarily want to even make,
because if it's self referenced, that is
thinking, OK, then maybe it goes all the
way to the bottom. But I don't know.
Daniel, can I ask you a question before
we run out of time? Actually, I have
two. Maybe one is a bit longer. The
second one. So the
first one, Chris, I was very
intrigued and looking forward to hear
you talk a little bit about that cycle
of error correction and memory and
persistence and so on. And in
particular, I was wondering if it
relates at all to the main other thing
you talked about in that lecture, six,
the copy and diversify business.
Because intuitively, if that cycle is
something that an organism has to
implement, I'm talking about that slide
with the error correction and whatnot,
then it pays the thermodynamic price for
it. So presumably
there is an anabolic process of trying
to grow so you can feed degrees of
freedom into this error correcting
scheme, thinking like a physicist.
Something like that might be happening.
So is the copy and diversify feature
a necessity of having to run this cycle?
That's my first question.
That's a good question. I don't know
whether it's necessary.
I think one could think of a
fairly small scale heat engine or
metabolic system that can pull
just enough free energy out of its
environment to store a
one bit memory.
And you can think of something like a
flip flop, right? These things aren't
alive. So it's not quite as
complex as an organism, but it
is using energy to maintain a memory,
and its memory does influence its
behavior. So I think we have
these limiting cases like this that
don't have to grow.
But when
you think about organisms,
organisms have the
problem of being made out of very
delicate parts that need to be replaced.
And it's that degradation
that I think is driving
this need for constant copying.
And from
a physics point of view, I think
what that boils down to is that
the organisms living right at the edge
of an interaction with its environment
that's too strong to maintain.
So the environmental
interaction is constantly
at risk of spinning out of control and
having too large an energy transfer,
which basically tears the Markov blanket
apart and exposes too many of
the internal degrees of freedom to the
outside.
So this may be
one way of saying what characterizes
life, that it's interacting with its
environment right on the edge of an
interaction that's too strong.
And it's great to have a strong
interaction because then you have big
eigenvalues and so you have large
bandwidth,
but the risk is that the environment
tears you apart.
Close to the fire, but don't get burnt.
Become the fire and then control the
redox balance and
gain that autopoietic regulative
capacity,
which works when it works. Yeah. Until
something comes along with bigger teeth.
Another comment, if I may, is,
as the course comes to an end, two
things I realized associated to
classicality that we've talked a lot
about in this class are object
persistence and boundaries. Right? So
classicality being a feature,
intrinsically boundary related, and
having a lot to do with object
persistence. So artists just
think completely dual from an FEP point
of view, because you want to maintain
the integrity of the boundary.
You want to preserve that classical
information, presumably. I'm not sure.
I guess my question to everyone is, are
object persistence in
the topic of classicality, object
persistence and boundaries,
are these basically completely dual
pictures? That's my question.
Yeah, I wouldn't be surprised.
And we also need object persistence to
define space.
So this
idea of object persistence is a
very key idea that has to be dealt with.
And physics has largely ignored this
idea, which is kind of objects are taken
for granted.
But I think what Carl says in that 2019
free energy principle for a particular
physics paper is fairly clear on this.
He basically says the free energy
principle tells systems to persist.
That's basically what a system has to do
by maintaining the integrity of its
Markov blanket. I think that's very
insightful.
If it doesn't, it's not.
Yeah, it's not a system anymore.
Well, as we somewhat
glide towards a local closure,
of course anyone is welcome to bring
up any reflections.
And also, I'd love to hear about where
we go from this now measured
outcome. How do we prepare
individually at the Institute scale,
ecosystem scale, and what are we
going to do coming out of this?
Are we talking about that right now.
Or any thoughts? Yeah,
keep learning, bro. What do you
mean by the ecosystem scale? Like the
active inference ecosystem and our own
ecosystems going on our
own scale. I guess the only thing I can
comment on this is I echo the view that,
or not view, or rather remark that Chris
made in the lecture about quantum
biology as a field. It's in a nascent
stage, right? Mean, I think, you know,
there will be a non trivial interaction
between the active inference community
and quantum biology. I'm making that
surmise right now.
So let's talk about quantum biology for
a second,
I'll open up the Pandora's box here.
Let's think of it as a parable as
opposed, or maybe even fan fiction.
Because Chris has shared so much with
us, I want to kind of build off of it.
If you will indulge me for a second,
I'll read you a little story. Just hear
the story out. Quantum biology sounds
like more than up or down without saying
that it is more up or down as
what information can be counterfactually
is looking at carrying capacity as in
quotes can be. And from that carrying
capacity comes orientation. Things like
direction and scale, things like the
ability to plan appear to fit better in
the orientation category relative
to the carrying capacity category,
which is noncommunativity in action.
This is a big if we agree that
orientation is to follow should
our recognizing of planning affordances
follow as well. So from the session
slide, there was a quote. Living systems
are genetic quantum systems that the FEP
has driven to a high level of
computational complexity. And here the
in quotes computation is baked in as
something planable with this as a
reference frame. To make plans, we need
carrying capacity. Check.
Agreed. But in order to learn where
does the carrying capacity plus
orientation relationship insist that we
start with a received plan? This
perspective is compared to, say,
actively inferring our way to the
plan falls out of carrying capacity.
Just making this explicit, we can then
ask should we first apply a received
plan or apply active inference that
helps clarify when the strategy is one
more based on exploitation versus a
strategy more based and biased to
exploration. In summary, when did
information delivery things like product
or package packaging begin to
Trump information carrying capacity,
which is essentially information
processing rather than we need this
paired relationship, the carrying
capacity plus the orientation as a
minimum of two so that we can compare,
identify change and know change model
patterns, et cetera. This is another way
of asking when did subject matter
expertise come to be seen as more
valuable than prediction matter
expertise? When it seems like we need
both capacities if we want independency.
And here's the kicker. If not given time
to reflect on what's being asked here,
and I know Chris oftentimes has a nice
long pause to reflect. But if not given
the time to reflect, people will take
their subject matter expertise strategy,
which clearly is a next move perspective
over one that holds up next move plus
all moves, meaning that they bring
prediction matter expertise in to
follow, to parameterize, to unlock,
to unring, to unbound what's
in and what's out. Of course, without
prediction matter expertise, what is
quantum biology?
Wow. Can you just post that someplace so
we can think about. I'll just email it
to you, Chris. Cool.
That was great.
Yeah. I think you're asking about the
fundamental question of what does Carl
call it? Epistemic value and
the role of curiosity and that whole
cluster of issues.
Well, I think I need to give you the
credit that you deserve on this. I think
it's the fact that you have allowed us
to interact with you that's given us
that kind of courage and confidence to
be able to put things out there. I don't
know how much of it sticks or how much
of it. I'm not sure that it requires
disciples, but I do think it provides.
What you've done is provided that
medium. So again, I guess that's my way
of saying thank you. Well, thank.
That's.
Yeah. Thank you, Chris. I have learned
so much this year, more than ever
before.
Okay, well, great. This has been a great
class, and hopefully
various things will come out of mean.
Certainly just from looking at the
questions that have been in the question
forum. Lots of people are thinking about
these issues, and that's
what I think AI needs going forward, is
people thinking and talking about stuff.
Thank you, Chris. Yeah. A few outcomes
that we know will transcribe the
lectures, the discussions, add in
screenshots, add in the Q and A, and
publish those proceedings as a book.
We will pick back up in 2024
with potentially having the recorded
and written contents as part
of a curriculum. So not just
replicating, but now continuing on
with another quantum flow across this
now classical artifact, because it's
quantum in the moment, and then once
it's communicated, it becomes a classic.
And we have months to prepare that
state. All right,
great. I'm going to have to sign off,
but thank you very much. Thank you,
Chris. Thank you. Thank you, Chris.
Ciao. Bye. Does anyone else,
does anyone else want to make any
reflection or comment?
I just thank everybody that's helped
organize, participated in all of the
discussions, even the people who showed
up at the very end of the discussions,
because I really appreciate that.
Again, I cannot emphasize enough, when
we get a chance to interact with this
stuff, when we get to manipulate it,
when we're able to ask questions, even
though we feel vulnerable, I think that
that's when a lot of the really good
stuff tends to get consolidated.
So thank you to all of you.
I'll read some fun comments from the
live chat, just the last several,
just to recognize some of our great
colleagues. Lucrative leadership wrote,
yes. More on affordances. Ian wrote,
would love for this series to continue.
Joanne wrote, thank you. This was a
wonderful learning experience. Mills 81
Two wrote the probable and the possible.
There are some emojis. Pablo sent a
heart pow wow dao. I don't speak
this language, but I can definitely
hear, understand, and feel it. So thank
you, everybody who's watching along.
These were all great, and we
prepare and measure every day at the
institute. So I really do hope that
people from all backgrounds, all
vectors, all preference and prior sets
come engage and not presuppose
too much about us or themselves
or what can happen when we really do
interact and when we take it into the
kinds of spaces and timelines that we
know we want to be on.
All right, thank you. Bye.
Thank you, everyone.